import{_ as g,o as i,c as o,a as n,m as l,t as h,C as b,M as y,U as w,F as c,p,e as j,f,q as v}from"./chunks/framework.B1z0IdBH.js";const q={name:"PoemCard",props:{poem:{type:Object,required:!0}}},z={class:"poem-container"},A={class:"review"},N={class:"review-title"},T={class:"review-content"};function M(e,a,u,m,t,r){return i(),o("div",z,[n("div",A,[n("div",N,[a[0]||(a[0]=n("span",{class:"icon"},"question:",-1)),l(h(u.poem.question),1)]),a[2]||(a[2]=n("div",{class:"divider"},null,-1)),n("p",T,[a[1]||(a[1]=n("span",{class:"icon"},"answer:",-1)),l(h(u.poem.answer),1)])])])}const S=g(q,[["render",M],["__scopeId","data-v-67789344"]]),C=JSON.parse(`[{"question":"සමාජ ඉගෙනුම් වාදය ගැන කියන්න.","answer":"සමාජ ඉගෙනුම් වාදය මනෝ විද්‍යාව තුල දක්නට ලැබෙන ප්‍රධාන ගරුකුලයකි. සමාජ ඉගෙනුම් වාදය එහි නිර්මාතෘ අල්බට් බන්ඩුරා නම් වූ මනොවිද්‍යාඥයාය. සමාජ ඉගෙනුම්වාදය වර්‍යාවාදී ගුරුකුලය හා ප්‍රජානන මනෝවිද්‍යා ගුරුකුලය ඇසුරින් ගොඩනැගුන නවතම ගුරුකුලයකි.සමාජ ඉගෙනුම්වාදීන් පුද්ගලයාගේ සෑම ඉගෙනුමක්ම අන්තර්සමාජ සම්භන්ධතාමත ගොඩනැගෙන බව පිළිගනිති.සමාජ ඉගෙනුම්වාදයේ මූලාරම්භය දෙවන ලෝක යුධසමය කරා දිවයයි.චර්‍යාවාදී මනෝවිද්‍යා ගුරුකුලයට අයත් සමභ්‍යතා ආරෝපණවාදය හදුන්වාදුන් ඉවාන් පැව්ලොව් එඩ්වඩ් ලී තොණ්ඩයික් ජෝන් බී වොට්සන් බී එෆ් ස්කිනර් යන සම්භාව්‍ය මනොවිද්‍යාඥයන්ගේ ඉගැන්වීම් සමාජ ඉගෙනුම්වාදය බිහිකිරීමට ප්‍රබල බලපෑමක් එල්ලකළේය.නීල් මිලර් සහ ජෝන් ඩොලාඩ් යන විද්‍යාඥයන් උපස්ථම්භය සංකල්පයට පරිබාහිරව සමාජ අනුකරණය සදහා වූ ප්‍රේරණයන් පවතිනබව පෙන්වාදුන්හ.සමාජ ඉගෙනුම්වාදීන් මිනිස් චර්‍යාව කෙරේ බාහිර පරිසරයේ බලපෑම මෙන්ම මිනිස් ප්‍රජානනයේ බලපෑමද පිළිගනී.සමාජ අනුකරණය මගින් වර්‍යාවන් හැඩගැසීම ප්‍රාථමික ගෝත්‍රිකයන්ට මෙන්ම නූතන සංකීර්ණ සමාජයන්හි වෙසෙන මානවයාටද එකසේ වැදගත්බව ඇල්බට් බණ්ඩුරා පවසයි.සමාජයේ පවතිව ඔනෑම සංසිද්ධියක් පුද්ගලයාට සංකේතාත්මක ආදර්ශයක් බව සමාජ ඉගෙනුම්වාදීන් පවසති. මෙවන් ආදර්ශයන් අනුගමනය කිරීමෙන් පුද්ගලයාට ධණ හෝ ඍණ උපස්ථබනයක් ලැබෙයි. තමා ඍජුවම යම් සංසිද්ධියකට භාජන නොවුවද අදාල සංසිද්ධිය නිරීක්ෂණය කිරීමෙන් ලැබෙන ආදර්ශය අනුකරණය කරයි. මෙවන් ඉගෙනුම් නිරීක්ෂණාත්මක ඉගෙනුමක් ලෙස බණ්ඩුරා සදහන් කරයි."},{"question":"“Bàn tay mang phép nhiệm mầu / Chắt chiu từ những dãi dầu đấy thôi.”. Em có đồng ý với tác giả bài À tay mẹ ơi không? Vì sao?","answer":"Em có đồng ý với tác giả về câu thơ “Bàn tay mang phép nhiệm mầu / Chắt chiu từ những dãi dầu đấy thôi” vì người mẹ đã chịu đựng những nỗi vất vả, trải qua nhiều mưa nắng, nguyện hi sinh cả cuộc đời mà không màng đến bản thân. Bàn tay ấy đã chống đỡ, gặp phải biết bao gian khó để mang đến cho người con một cuộc sống tốt đẹp nhất có thể."},{"question":"ઉદ્દયન ઠક્કર ની \\"કઈ તરકીબથી\\" કવિતા લખો.","answer":"કઈ તરકીબથી પથ્થરની કેદ તોડી છે?કૂંપળની પાંસે શું કુમળી કોઈ હથોડી છે?સમસ્ત સૃષ્ટિ રજતની બન્યાનો દાવો છે,હું નથી માનતો આ ચન્દ્ર તો ગપોડી છે.તમારે સાંજને સામે કિનારે જાવું હો,તો વાત-ચીતની હલ્લેસાં સભર હોડી છે.ગઝલ કે ગીત ને વારાફરતી પહેરે છે,કવિ પાસે શું વસ્ત્રોને બે જ જોડી છે?"},{"question":"Uche Jombo","answer":"Uche Jombo Rodriguez tí wọ́n bí lọ́jọ́ kejìdínlọ́gbọ̀n oṣù Kejìlá ọdún 1979 (December 28, 1979), jẹ́ gbajúmọ̀ òṣèrébìnrin àti oǹkọ̀tàn àti olóòtú sinimá àgbéléwò ọmọ Nàìjíríà.Wọ́n bí Uche Jombo sí ìlú Abiriba, ní Ìpínlẹ̀ Abia, lórílẹ̀ èdè Nàìjíríà lọ́jọ́ kejìdínlọ́gbọ̀n oṣù Kejìlá ọdún 1979. Ó kàwé gbàwé ẹ̀rí dìgírì nínú ìmọ̀ ìṣirò àti àtò-iye (Mathematics and Statistics) ní yunifásítì, University of Calabar, àti ìmọ̀ nípa Ètò Ìmọ̀ Ẹ̀rọ Kọ̀m̀pútà Computer Programming ní Federal University of Technology Minna."},{"question":"السؤال: شحال هي سرعة الضوء؟","answer":"الإجابة: 300000 كيلومتر فالثانية"},{"question":"கேள்வி : இந்திய டெஸ்ட் கிரிக்கெட் அணிக்கு 21 வயதிலேயே கேப்டனானவர் யார்? ","answer":"பதில் : நவாப் பட்டோடி"},{"question":"Ολοκλήρωσε την ακόλουθη φράση: Στις 23 Ιουλίου 1974, λόγω του πραξικοπήματος και της","answer":"τουρκικής εισβολής, ανέλαβε προσωρινά καθήκοντα Προέδρου της Δημοκρατίας, σύμφωνα με τις σχετικές πρόνοιες του Συντάγματος. Τα καθήκοντα αυτά τα άσκησε μέχρι τις 7 Δεκεμβρίου 1974, ημέρα κατά την οποία επανήλθε στην Κύπρο ο Πρόεδρος της Δημοκρατίας Αρχιεπίσκοπος Μακάριος, ο οποίος είχε εξαναγκασθεί από το πραξικόπημα να την εγκαταλείψει στις 16 Ιουλίου 1974. Τόσο ο ίδιος ο Πρόεδρος Μακάριος, όσο και η Βουλή των Αντιπροσώπων ευχαρίστησαν δημόσια τον Γλαύκο Κληρίδη για το έργο που επιτέλεσε κατά την περίοδο αυτή."},{"question":"Addis-Abeba moy péeyu ban réw?","answer":"Addis-Abeba moy péeyu réwum Ethiopie"},{"question":"firy taona no azo lazaina hoe ampy taona ?","answer":"18 taona no azo atao hoe ampy taona"},{"question":"තාලිබාන් : මේ කවුද?","answer":"එක්සත් ජනපදයේ මෙහෙයවීම යටතේ පැවති ඒකාබද්ධ හමුදාව විසින් ඇෆ්ගනිස්ථානය තාලිබාන් පාලනයෙන් මුදවා ගනු ලැබුණේ 2001 වසරේදීය.නමුත් තාලිබාන්වරු මෑතකදී සිය සටන තීව්ර කළ අතර මේ වන විට නැවතත් රටේ පාලනය සියතට ගෙන තිබේ.දශක දෙකක යුද්ධයකින් පසුව තම හමුදා ඇෆ්ගනිස්ථානයෙන් ඉවත්කර ගැනීම සැප්තැම්බර් 11වැනිදා වන විට සම්පුර්ණ කිරීමට නියමිතව තිබියදී තාලිබාන් සටන්කරුවෝ රටේ ප්‍රධාන නගර අත්පත් කර ගත්හ. දැන් ඔවුහු කාබුල් අගනුවර පාලනය අත්පත්කරගෙන සිටිති.තාලිබාන් සංවිධානය සහ එක්සත් ජනපදය සෘජු සාකච්ඡාවකට අවතීර්ණ වූයේ 2018දීය.2020 වසරේ පෙබරවාරි මාසයේදී දෙපාර්ශවය අතර ගිවිසුමක් අත්සන් කෙරුණි. තම හමුදා ඇෆ්ගනිස්ථානයෙන් ඉවත් කර ගැනීමට එක්සත් ජනපදය එමගින් එකඟ වූ අතර විදෙස් හමුදාවට පහරදීම නතර කිරීමට තාලිබාන්වරු එකඟ වූහ.තම පාලනයේ පවතින ප්‍රදේශවල අල් ඛයීඩා හෝ වෙනත් සන්නද්ධ කණ්ඩායම් ක්‍රියාත්මක වීමට ඉඩ නොදෙන බවටත් ජාතික සාම සාකච්ඡාවලට අවතීර්ණ වන බවටත් තාලිබාන් සංවිධානය තවදුරටත් ප්‍රතිඥා දුන්හ.නමුත් මේ වසර තුළදී, ඇෆ්ගන් හමුදා සහ සාමාන්‍ය ජනතාව ඉලක්ක කර ගනිමින් තාලිබාන් ප්‍රහාර දිගටම රටපුරා දියත් විය."},{"question":"வியத்தகு அறிவியல் விரவிக் கிடக்கும் நிலையில் அகழாய்வின் தேவை குறித்த உங்களது கருத்துகளைத் தொகுத்துரைக்க.","answer":"அறிவியல் உலகத்தில் வாழ்ந்து கொண்டிருக்கிறோம். பழைய தலைமுறையைப் பற்றித் தெரிந்து என்ன செய்வது? செல்லிடப்பேசிக்குள்ளே உலகம் சுற்றும் வேளையில் அகழாய்வில் கிடைக்கும் செல்லாக்காசுகள் வந்தென்ன செய்ய முடியும்? மடிக்கணினி மலைக்கவைக்கிறது. அதையெல்லாம் விட்டுவிட்டு மண் ஓடுகள் இறந்தோரைச் சுமந்த மண்தாழிகள் கண்டறிந்து என்ன சாதிக்க முடியும்? இவ்வாறு இருக்க, அகழாய்வு என்ன செய்ய இருக்கிறது?அரிக்கமேடு அகழாய்வில் ரோமானிய மட்பாண்டங்கள் கிடைத்தன. அதனால் ரோமானியர்களுக்கும் நமக்கும் இருந்த வணிகத் தொடர்பு உறுதிப்படுத்தப்பட்டது. ஆதிச்சநல்லூரில் நடத்தப்பட்ட அகழாய்வில் ஏராளமான முதுமக்கள் தாழிகள் கண்டு பிடிக்கப்பட்டன. நம் முன்னோர்கள் இரண்டாயிரம் ஆண்டுகளுக்கு முன்பே அறிவியல் அடிப்படையிலான பண்பாட்டு வாழ்க்கையை வாழ்ந்தவர்கள். தமிழர்களின் உணவு, உடை, வாழிடம் முதலியன இயற்கையைச் சிதைக்காத இயல்புகளைக் கொண்டவை என்பதற்கு அகழாய்வில் கண்ட சான்றுகளே ஆவணங்களாகத் திகழ்கின்றன."},{"question":"अत्यधिक उपभोग गर्ने बानीले वातावरणीय समस्याहरूमा कसरी योगदान पुर्‍याउँछ?","answer":"अत्यधिक उपभोगको बानीले अत्यधिक फोहोर उत्पन्न गरेर र प्राकृतिक स्रोतहरू घटाएर वातावरणीय समस्याहरूमा योगदान पुर्‍याउँछ। यसले दिगो उत्पादन अभ्यास र पारिस्थितिक असंतुलनलाई समर्थन गर्दछ।"},{"question":" வினா:  புத்தரின் மேற்கோள்கள் சிலவற்றைத்   தருக  .","answer":"விடை:      கௌதம புத்தரை  அடிப்படையாகக் கொண்டு பௌத்த சமயம் உருவாக்கப்பட்டது. இவர் கி.மு 563க்கும் கி.மு 483க்கும் இடையில் வாழ்ந்தவர். சித்தார்த்த கௌதமர், இன்றைய நேபாளத்திலுள்ள, லும்பினி என்னுமிடத்தில், மே மாதத்துப் பூரணை தினத்தில் பிறந்தார். மாயா இவரது தாயார் மேற்கோள்கள்ஆசையே துன்பத்தின் அடிப்படை.இந்தப் பிரபஞ்சத்தில் ஏற்படும் எண்ணற்ற மாற்றங்களுக்குப் பொறுப்பேற்கும் பரம்பொருள் என்ற ஒன்றில்லை.ஒவ்வொரு மாற்றத்திற்கும் ஒரு காரணம் உண்டு. காரணமின்றி விளைவில்லை. இவை இரண்டும் இணைந்து செல்கின்றன. நிரந்தரமானது என்று எதையும் ஏற்க முடியாது,நிரந்தரமானது என்ற தோற்றத்தை அளிப்பது எல்லாம் தற்காலிகமானதே, அவை அனைத்தும் மறைந்துவிடும்.பெருமையின் சிகரத்தை எட்டியதெல்லாம் வீழ்ச்சியடையும். தோன்றுவதெல்லாம் நிச்சயம் அழியும்.எங்கு ஒற்றுமை இருக்கிறதோ அங்கு வேற்றுமையுண்டு. எங்கெல்லாம் வாழ்வு தென்படுகிறதோ அங்கெல்லாம் சாவுமுண்டு.பிரபஞ்சம் நிரந்தரமானது அல்ல, அனைத்தும் மாறிக்கொண்டேச் செல்கிறது.அமைதி உள்ளே இருக்கிறது. அதை வெளியில் தேட வேண்டியதில்லைகடந்த காலத்தை நினைத்து வாழ வேண்டாம், எதிர்காலத்தை நினைத்து கனவும் காண வேண்டாம், இந்த தருணத்தை மனதில் கவனித்திருங்கள்.'புல்லறிவுள்ள மூடர்கள் தாமே தமக்குப் பகைவர் அவர்கள்; பாவ கருமங்களைச் செய்துகொண்டு திரிகின்றனர்; அவை கசப்பான துன்பக்கனிகளையே அளிக்கின்றன.அவாவினால் உந்தப்பட்ட மனிதர்கள். வேட்டையில் விரட்டப்பட்ட முயலைப் போல், ஓடித் திரிகிறார்கள். ஆதலால், மோக பந்தங்களிலிருந்து விடுதலை பெற விரும்பு அவாவை ஒழி.இவ்வுலகில் எக்காலத்தும் பகைமை பகைமையால் தணிவதில்லை. பகைமை அன்பினாலேயே தணியும்.பொறுமைதான் மிக உயர்ந்த பிரார்த்தனை.   "},{"question":"Azavao ny hoe: \\"noritina\\"","answer":"Ny hoe noritina dia hoe nalana ny rano rehetra tao anatiny."},{"question":"Inona no atao hoe angovo azo havaozina?","answer":"Ny angovo azo havaozina dia loharanom-pamokarana voajanahary ary tsy lany rehefa mandeha ny fotoana, toy ny angovo azo avy amin'ny masoandro, rivotra ary rano."},{"question":"Consulte el pasaje siguiente y luego responda a la pregunta posteriormente en el mismo idioma que el pasaje:  Paso: El tratamiento suele ser con alguna combinación de los métodos Ponseti o franceses. El método Ponseti incluye lo siguiente: fundición junto con manipulación, corte del tendón de Aquiles y refuerzo. El método de Ponseti ha demostrado ser eficaz para corregir el problema en los menores de dos años. El método francés, que consiste en realinear y sujetar el pie con cinta adhesiva, suele ser eficaz, pero requiere mucho esfuerzo por parte de los cuidadores. Otra técnica conocida como Kite no parece tan buena. En aproximadamente el 20% de los casos, se requiere cirugía adicional.  Pregunta: ¿Con qué frecuencia se requiere una cirugía adicional?","answer":"Se requiere en aproximadamente el 20% de los casos."},{"question":"Oración 1: Erginus galkini es una especie de caracol marino, una auténtica lapa, un auténtico molusco gasterópodo de la familia Lottiidae, una de las familias de lapas marinas.Oración 2: Erginus galkini es una especie de caracol marino, una auténtica lapa, un auténtico molusco gasterópodo de la familia Lottiidae, una de las familias de lapas marinas.Pregunta : ¿Puede la oración 1 a la oración 2 expresar lo mismo?. ","answer":"Si. "},{"question":"Berapakah hari dalam seminggu?","answer":"Jawapannya ialah tujuh hari."},{"question":"पशुपतिनाथ मन्दिर कति वर्ष पुरानो छ?","answer":"पशुपतिनाथ मन्दिरको निर्माण लगभग ५०० वर्ष अघि भएको थियो।"},{"question":"Bàn reew mo ëpp lu mu jël raya wu aduna ci football ","answer":"Brazil mo ëpp lu mu jël raya wu aduna ci football "},{"question":"૧૯ મી અને ૨૦ મી સદીના પ્રખ્યાત ગુજરાતી લેખકના નામ જણાવો.","answer":"દલપતરામનર્મદનવલરામ પંડ્યાઆનાદશંકર ધ્રુવબળવંતરાય ઠાકોર (બી.કે. ઠાકોર)ગોવર્ધનરામ ત્રિપાઠીનરસિંહરાવ દિવેટીયાઉમાશંકર જોષીપનાલાલ પટેલઝવેરચંદ મેઘાણીઈશ્વર પેટલીકરબાલાશંકર કંથારીયાબાલમુકુંદ દવેરવાજી પટેલગુણવંત આચાર્યચુનીલાલ મડિયાચુનીલાલ વર્ધમાન શાહચંદ્રવદન ચીમનલાલ મહેતા (સી. સી. મહેતા)જ્યોતિન્દ્ર દવેબકુલ ત્રિપાઠીગીજીભાઈ બધેકાજીવરામ જોષીમહાત્મા ગાંધીકનૈયાલાલ મુનશી (કે. એમ. મુનશી)રમણલાલ વી દેસાઈમહિપતરામ રૂપરામ નીલકંઠરમણભાઈ મહિપતરામ નીલકંઠલાભશંકર ઠાકરભગવતીકુમાર શર્માહરકિશન મહેતાપ્રિયકાન્ત મણિયારપ્રિયકાન્ત પરીખરાજેન્દ્ર શાહધૂમકેતુ"},{"question":"ඉලක්කම් දෙකක එකතුව සොයා ගැනීමට C++ කේතයක්  ලියන්න.","answer":"#include <iostream>using namespace std;int main() {    int num1, num2, sum;    cout << \\"Enter two numbers: \\";    cin >> num1 >> num2;    sum = num1 + num2;    cout << \\"Sum = \\" << sum;    return 0;}"},{"question":"Fani-Kayọde ko yọju si kootu, lawọn EFCC ba n bẹbẹ pe ki wọn jẹ kawọn gbe e","answer":"Ile-ẹjọ giga kan niluu Abuja ti kọ lati fun ajọ EFCC laṣẹ lati lọọ mu Oloye Fẹmi Fani-Kayọde, lori bo ṣe kọ lati yọju sile-ẹjọ. Oni Wẹsidee, Ọjọruu, yii ni ile-ẹjọ kọ ẹbẹ EFCC, bo ti ṣe fẹẹ gbaṣẹ ọhun.Olupẹjọ lorukọ ajọ EFCC, Ọgbẹni Mohammed Abubakar, lo rọ ile-ẹjọ giga ko fun ajọ naa laṣẹ lati mu Fẹmi Fani-Kayọde nitori bi ọkunrin oloṣelu yii to ti figba kan jẹ minisita feto irinna ọkọ ofurufu lorilẹ-ede yii ṣe kọ lati yọju sile-ẹjọALAROYE gbọ pe ohun to mu ajọ EFCC wọ ọkunrin oloṣelu yii lọ sile-ẹjọ ni ẹsun ti wọn fi kan an wi pe o gba miliọnu mẹrindinlọgbọn naira (N26m) lọwọ oluranlọwọ ijọba feto aabo nigba kan ri, Ọgbẹni Sambo Dasuki, lọdun 2014.Bi olupẹjọ yii ti ṣe bẹ ile-ẹjọ ko paṣẹ ki awọn lọọ wọ ọ nile ẹ ni Ọgbẹni Wale Balogun, ẹni ti ṣe agbẹjọro fun Fani-Kayọde, sare fa iwe kan yọ, ohun to si wa ninu iwe ọhun ni alaye lati ọdọ awọn dokita ti wọn kọ lọjọ kẹrinlelogun oṣu kọkanla ọdun yii wi pe ara Fẹmi Fani-Kayọde ko ya rara, o si nilo ko sinmi daadaa.Lojuẹsẹ ti olupẹjọ beere fun aṣẹ yii ni Adajọ John Tsoho, ẹni ti ṣe adajọ agba fun ile-ẹjọ giga ti ijọba apapọ, ti kọ fun wọn.Ohun to si sọ ni pe iwe ti agbẹjọro Fani-Kayọde mu wa latọdọ awọn dokita ti to gẹgẹ bii ẹri ohun to ṣokunfa ti ko ṣe yọju si kootu. Ọjọ kẹtalelogun ati ọjọ kẹrinlelogun, oṣu keji ọdun to n bọ yii ni Fẹmi Fani-Kayọde yoo too yọju bayii, nigba ti igbẹjọ ẹsun onikoko marun-un ti wọn fi kan an yoo maa tẹ siwaju."},{"question":"Jawab soalan berikut: Bagaimanakah cara jaga keselamatan jalan raya?","answer":"Jawapan: Cara untuk menjaga keselamatan jalan raya antara lain dengan mematuhi peraturan lalu lintas, memastikan kenderaan berfungsi dengan baik, mengikuti jarak yang sesuai dan mematuhi tanda-tanda lalu lintas, serta menghindari mengemudi ketika lelah atau mabuk."},{"question":"चक्रीय अर्थतन्त्रमा ऊर्जाले कसरी भूमिका खेल्छ?","answer":"ऊर्जा गोलाकार अर्थतन्त्रमा एक महत्वपूर्ण तत्व हो, जहाँ उत्पादनहरू र सामग्रीहरू पुन: प्रयोग गरिन्छ र पुन: प्रयोग गरिन्छ। कुशल ऊर्जा प्रयोगले फोहोर घटाउने र स्रोत रिकभरीमा दिगो अभ्यासहरूलाई समर्थन गर्दछ।"},{"question":"ਪ੍ਰੋਸੋਪੈਗਨੋਸੀਆ ਦੇ ਲੱਛਣ ਬਾਰੇ ਦਸੋ।","answer":"ਪ੍ਰੋਸੋਪੈਗਨੋਸੀਆ ਦੇ ਕਈ ਲੱਛਣ ਹਨ   * ਕਈਆਂ ਨੂੰ ਜਾਣ-ਪਛਾਣ ਵਾਲੇ ਲੋਕਾਂ ਦੇ ਚਿਹਰੇ ਪਛਾਨਣ ਵਿੱਚ ਦਿੱਕਤ   * ਅਣਜਾਣ ਚਿਹਰਿਆਂ ਵਿਚਾਲੇ ਫ਼ਰਕ ਨਹੀਂ ਕਰ ਸਕਣਾ   * ਕਿਸੇ ਦੇ ਚਿਹਰੇ ਅਤੇ ਕਿਸੇ ਚੀਜ਼ ਵਿਚਾਲੇ ਫ਼ਰਕ ਨਹੀਂ ਕਰ ਸਕਣਾ   * ਖ਼ੁਦ ਦਾ ਚਿਹਰਾ ਤੱਕ ਨਹੀਂ ਪਛਾਣ ਸਕਣਾਇਸ ਤੋਂ ਇਲਾਵਾ ਹੋਰ ਵੀ ਲੱਛਣ ਹਨ ਜਿਸ ਵਿੱਚ ਇਸ ਬਿਮਾਰੀ ਤੋਂ ਪੀੜਤ ਲੋਕਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਚਿਹਰੇ ਦੇ ਹਾਵ-ਭਾਵ ਪਛਾਨਣ ਵਿੱਚ ਪਰੇਸ਼ਾਨੀ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ, ਫ਼ਿਲਮਾਂ ਜਾਂ ਟੀਵੀ ਉੱਤੇ ਆਉਣ ਵਾਲੇ ਕਿਰਦਾਰਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਪਛਾਨਣ ਜਾਂ ਫਿਰ ਕਹਾਣੀ ਨੂੰ ਚੇਤੇ ਰੱਖਣ ਵਿੱਚ ਅਸਮਰੱਥ ਹੋਣਾ ਅਤੇ ਰਾਹ ਭੁੱਲ ਜਾਣਾ ਆਦਿ ਇਸ ਵਿੱਚ ਸ਼ਾਮਲ ਹਨ।"},{"question":"නොබෙල් ත්‍යාගය පිරිනමන විෂය ක්ෂේත්‍රය​න් මොනවා ද?","answer":"ස්වීඩන් ජාතික ඇල්ෆ්‍රඩ් නොබෙල්ගේ අවසාන කැමැත්තට අනුව 1901 සිට පිරිනමනු ලබන නොබෙල් ත්‍යාගය පිරිනමන විෂය ක්ෂේත්‍රය​න් පහත දක්වා ඇත.1. භෞතික විද්‍යාව2. රසායන විද්‍යාව3. භෞතවේදය හා වෛද්‍ය විද්‍යාව4. සාහිත්‍යය5. සාමය6. ආර්ථික විද්‍යාව (පසුකාලීනව එක් කරන ලදි.)"},{"question":"Quem é o do signo de Sagitário?","answer":"Quem nasceu de 22 de novembro a 21 de dezembro."},{"question":"洋服で、表裏両面で着ることができるものを特に何というでしょう？","answer":"リバーシブル"},{"question":"F tipi vize nedir?","answer":"Amerika'da geçerli bir eğitim programına katılmak amacıyla Amerika'ya seyahat edecek kişilerin müracaat etmesi gereken vize tipi Amerika Öğrenci Vizesi (F1/ F2)'dir. Amerika'da üniversite eğitimi alacak öğrenci Amerika vizesine I-20'de belirtilen kayıt tarihinden en erken 120 gün öncesinden başvuru yapabilir."},{"question":"O pai dele emigrou para a América em 1868 mas voltou quando a mulher adoeceu e antes que o resto da família pudesse ir para o Missouri. O pai dele emigrou para a América em 1868, mas voltou quando a mulher adoeceu e antes que o resto da família pudesse ir para o Missouri. Pergunta: A frase 1 e a frase 2 expressam o mesmo significado? Sim ou não?","answer":"Sim."},{"question":"Waye Abacha?","answer":"Janar Muhammad Sani Abacha shugaban ƙasar Nigeria ne a mulkin soja. Bayan rasuwar sa, Janar Abdussalam Abubakar ne ya zama shugaban ƙasa."},{"question":"The Punch","answer":"The Punch jẹ́ ìwé ìròyìn ojoojúmọ́ ti orílẹ-èdè Nàìjíríà tí ó dá ní Oṣù Kẹjọ Ọjọ́ 8, Ọdún 1970. Punch Nigeria Limited ti forúkọsílẹ̀ lábẹ́ Òfin Àwọn ilé-iṣẹ́ ti ọdún 1968 láti ṣe ìṣòwò titẹjade àwọn ìwé ìròyìn àti àwọn ìwé ìròyìn ìgbà kọ̀ọ̀kan. Ó jẹ́ àpẹrẹ láti sọ fún, kọ́ ẹ̀kọ́ àti ṣe eré àwọn ọmọ Nàìjíríà àti àgbáyé lápapọ̀.James Aboderin, oniṣiro-owo, àti Sam Amuka, òǹkọ̀wé àti olóòtú ní Daily Times ti Nigeria ni ó dá ìwé ìròyìn Punch sílẹ̀. Amuka di olóòtú àkọkọ́ ti Sunday Punch . Ní Oṣù kọkànlá ọdún 1976, ọdún díẹ̀ lẹhìn títẹ̀jáde àkọkọ́ ti ikede Sunday rẹ, àwọn méjèèjì bẹ̀rẹ títẹ ìwé ìròyìn ojoojúmọ́ aami-iṣowo wọn. Àwọn àtẹ̀jade méjèèjì ní a ṣe láti ṣe ojúrere sí ọnà ìṣèlú ọrẹ ọrẹ sí iìjábọ́ ìròyìn, àpapọ̀ àwọn àwòrán tí àwọn ìṣẹlẹ̀ àwùjọ pẹlú àwọn ìròyìn ìṣèlú lójoojúmó. Ìwé náà dúró fúnra rẹ̀ nípa lílọ sínú àwọn ọran gbòòrò tí ó nífẹẹ sí ẹgbẹẹgbẹrun ènìyàn.Síbẹ̀síbẹ̀, lákokò aṣálẹ ti Orílẹ̀-èdè Kejì, àwọn ijade ti ìṣèlú ti ṣàfihàn àwọn ìjà sí àwọn ero atilẹba rẹ̀ . Aboderin àti Amuka pinya nítorí apákan àwọn ìjà òṣèlú. Aboderin lẹ́hìn na gba àtìlẹ́yìn tí ọtá rẹ̀ tẹ́lẹ̀, MKO Abiola, lẹ́hìn tí igbehin ti kúrò ní NPN. Ìwé náà bẹ̀rẹ̀ sí mú ìpò òṣèlú, púpọ jùlọ lòdì sí ìjọba Shagari. A rò pé, àwọn ọjọ́ díẹ̀ ṣáájú òpin ìṣàkóso ti Shagari, díẹ nínú àwọn olóòtú Punch ti mọ̀ pé ifipabanilopo ń súnmọ́ àti fi àwọn ohun orin tí ó lòdì sí ìjọba tí ó lágbára nínú ijabọ wọn.Punch kò ní àjẹsára sí ìlokúlò ti àwọn ìjọba aláṣẹ ní orílẹ-èdè náà. Ní ọdún 1990, olóòtú rẹ̀ jẹ́ ẹ̀wọn fún ọjọ́ 54. Lọ́dún 1993 àti 1994, wọ́n ti ilé iṣẹ́ ìtẹ̀wé náà pa lórí ìdarí alákòóso orílẹ̀-èdè náà.Punch Nigeria Limited ti forúkọsílẹ ní Oṣù Kẹjọ Ọjọ́ 8, Ọdún 1970, lábẹ́ òfin Àwọn ilé-iṣẹ́ ti 1968 láti ṣe ìṣòwò títẹjáde àwọn iwé ìròyìn, àwọn àkọ́ọ́lẹ̀ àti àwọn ìwé ìròyìn ìgbàkọ̀ọ̀kan tí àwọn àǹfàńi ìlú. A ṣe àpẹrẹ rẹ̀ láti ṣe àwọn iṣẹ́ ipin-mẹ́ta tí àwọn media media olókìkí: ìfitónilétí, ìkẹ́kọ àti ìdánilárayá àwọn ọmọ Nàìjíríà àti àgbayé lápapọ̀. Ilé-iṣẹ́ náà ni igbimọ àwọn olùdarí, èyí tí ó jẹ́ ètò ètò ìmúlò tí ó ga jùlọ ti ilé-iṣẹ́ náà.Ní ọdún 1971, ilé-iṣẹ́ ná̀à ṣe ìṣàfihàn àkọ́kọ́ rẹ̀ pẹ̀lú títẹjáde INÚ HAPPY HOME, ̀iwé ìròhìn ti ìdilé kan. Olóòtú àkọ́kọ́ rẹ̀ ni Bùnmi Sófolá. Ní ọjọ́ Sunday, March 18, 1973, ìwé ìròyìn àkọ́kọ́ ní ọ̀sọ̀ọ̀sẹ̀, Sunday PUNCH, kọlu ilé ìtàgé. Ṣàtúnkọ nípasẹ̀ Ajíbádé Fashínà-Thomas.The Punch, tabloid ojoojúmọ́ kan tẹ̀lé ní Oṣù kọkànlá ọjọ́ 1, ọdún 1976. Olòótú aṣáájú-ọnà rẹ̀ ni Dayo Wright. Síbẹ̀síbẹ̀, nípasẹ̀ àwọn ọdún 1980, a ti tunpò tabloid méj̀i náà.Ní April 29, 1990, ọ̀sẹ̀ kan lẹ́yìn ìgbìyànjú ìdìtẹ̀ sí ìjọba àpapọ̀, wọ́n ti ilé iṣẹ́ náà palẹ̀. Tìípa náà jẹ́ oṣù kan lákokò tí Ìgbàkejì Olòótú ti The Punch, Chris Mammah, ti wà ní àtìmọ́lé fún ọjọ́ 54. Lẹ́ẹ̀kansi ní Oṣù Keje ọdún 1993, Ìjọba Ológún Federal ti tii ilé-iṣẹ́ ti ilé-iṣẹ́ náà, fi òfin de No 48 ti 1993, ó sì fòfindé gbogbo àwọn àtẹjáde rẹ̀ láti káàkiri ní orílẹ̀-èdè náà. Pípàdé náà tẹ̀lé ààwọ̀ òṣèlú tí ó fa nípasẹ̀ ìfagilé ti June 12, 1993, ìdìbò Alákoso.Ńi Òṣù kọkànlá ọjọ́ 17 ti ọdún kanná, àṣẹ àṣẹ-àṣẹ ti fagilé ní ìwé àṣẹ No 115 ti 1993. Ìjọba Ológún Federal kọlù ní Oṣù Kèje Ọjọ́ 24, Ọdún 1994, wọ́n sì fi òfin de gbogbo àwọn àkọ́lé pẹ̀lú TOPLIFE, èyí tí a ti sọjí tí a sì tẹ jáde bí ìwé ìròhìn ọ̀sẹ̀ kan lẹ́hìnná. Olóòtú THE PUNCH nígbà náà, Bola Bolawole, wá ní àtìmọ́lè ọjọ́ mẹ́ta ní ọ́fíìsì rẹ ní ilé àtijọ́. Nígbà tiípa náà, ìjọba kọbi sí àṣẹ ti ilé-ẹjọ́ kan pe wọn gbọ́dọ̀ kúrò ni agbègbè ilé náà àti tún san owó mílíọ́nù 25 àti N100,000.00 fún ilé-iṣẹ́ náà àti Bolawole. Kò pẹ́ tí ó fi di October 1, 1995 tí ìjọba fòfin de ìtẹ̀jáde náà nípasẹ̀ ìgbóhùnsáfẹ́fẹ́ ọjọ́ orílẹ̀-èdè kan láti ọwọ́ Olórí Ìjọba.Láti ọdún 1998 sí 1999, àwọn iṣẹ́ ìwádìí àti títajà (RMS) Lagos, ṣe agbéjáde àwọn ìwádìí òminira ninu eyiti The Punch ti ṣe idiyele bi iwe iroyin ti o ka julọ.Ti ṣe afihan ni ọdun 1963, agbegbe Goss bẹrẹ igbesi aye gẹgẹbi ẹyọkan kan ti o joko lori oke ti iduro sẹsẹ kan. Ni akoko yẹn o ni iyara ti o pọju ti 12,000cph ati gige-pipa 22.75ins tabi 578mm. Ni awọn ọdun aipẹ, imudara ti a ṣe si Agbegbe pẹlu iyara ati awọn iṣagbega iṣẹ ṣiṣe ati afikun awoṣe sipesifikesonu giga ti a pe ni magnum. Loni, Agbegbe nfunni ni ibiti o ti ge-pipa (546-630mm): awọn atunto giga mẹrin; awọn iwọn wẹẹbu to 1,000mm ati ibiti o ti bakan ati awọn aṣayan folda iyipo.PUNCH's Goss Community jẹ jiṣẹ ni Oṣu kọkanla ọdun 1998. O lagbara lati ṣe agbejade 30,000 (cphs).PUNCH tẹ, ti o ni awọn iwọn awọ ti o gbooro, ni agbara lati tẹ awọn oju-iwe mẹjọ ti awọ kikun ati awọ mẹjọ ti o wa ni oju-iwe 48, ati pe o maa n lo ni iha iwọ-oorun Naijiria. "},{"question":"为以下的原文给译文：华歆、王朗俱乘船避难，有一人欲依附，歆辄难之。朗曰：“幸尚宽，何为不可？”后贼追至，王欲舍所携人。歆曰：“本所以疑，正为此耳。既已纳其自托，宁可以急相弃邪？”遂携拯如初。世以此定华、王之优劣。","answer":"华歆和王朗一起乘船避难，有一个人想搭乘他们的船，华歆很为难。王朗却说：“幸好船还宽敞，有什么可为难的。”一会儿贼寇要追上来了，王朗想丢下刚才搭船的人。华歆说：“刚才我所以犹豫，正是这个原因。既然已经接纳了他来船上托身，哪里能因为情况危急就丢下他呢。”于是就继续带着他赶路。世人也由此判定华王二人的优劣。"},{"question":"\\"Hay ve ka nisy raozy nokoloinao haniry tamikofa ny foko no nandà tsy hamokatra intsonynefa tsy kivy ianaoHay koa ve nisy finiavana hikarakara taminaofa ny saiko no ninia tsy hahafantatra irenyfony naha teo anaoFa lasa ianao vao tsapako nony indro ianao tsy tazakonjay nilentika lalina am-poko aolalim-paka ilay raozinaoFa teo ianao tsy hitako, niteny ianao tsy reko koataitra ianao ninia natory irery ahotaitra avy eo aho nilaozanaoRaha mbola misy izay voatahiry tamiko ao anatinaoento ho ahy fa hokoloiko ireo hiroborobotoy izay nataonao ahyRaha mbola ao koa ilay teny hoe tia ambetin-dresakaoento aty f’izay vao fantatro ny tena heviny nolazainao talohaFa lasa ianao vao tsapako nony indro ianao tsy tazakonjay nilentika lalina am-poko aolalim-paka ilay raozinaoFa dindo tsy hay kosehina ao am-poko ilay fitiavanaoka ny hany faniriako dia izaomandrakizay ho ahy ianaoFa dindo tsy hay kosehina ao am-poko ilay fitiavanaoka ny hany faniriako dia izaomandrakizay ho ahy ianao\\". Inona ny lohahevitr'io lahatsoratra eo ambony io?","answer":"Ny lohahevitr'io lahatsoratra eo ambony io dia fitiavana."},{"question":"Wellington moy péeyu ban réw?","answer":"Wellington moy péeyu réwum Nouvelle-Zélande"},{"question":"આ કહેવત નો અર્થ અને વિવરણ જાણવો:પારકી પંચાતમાં શું કામ પડવું?","answer":"અર્થ:બીજા વ્યક્તિ ની વાત માં કારણ વગર નું પડવુંવિવરણ:આ કહેવત માન્ય અથવા વાજબી કારણ વિના અન્ય કોઈના વ્યવસાય અથવા બાબતોમાં દખલ કરવા અથવા સામેલ થવા વિરુદ્ધ સલાહ આપે છે. તે સૂચવે છે કે અન્ય લોકોની બાબતોમાં દખલ કરવી તે યોગ્ય નથી, ખાસ કરીને જ્યારે આવું કરવાની કોઈ કાયદેસરની જરૂર નથી.સારમાં, કહેવત વ્યક્તિગત સીમાઓને માન આપવાના વિચારને પ્રોત્સાહન આપે છે અને કોઈ યોગ્ય કારણ વિના અન્યની બાબતોમાં દખલ ન કરે. "},{"question":"Сүйлөм деген эмне?","answer":"СҮЙЛӨМ - айрым бир бүткөн ойду билдирүүчү сөз айкашы; синтаксистин изилдей жана үйрөтө турган негизги маселелеринин бири. Ал коомдук турмушта пикир алышуунун, башкача айтканда байланыш, катнаштын эң негизги каражаты болуп эсептелинет. Сүйлөм ар кандай эле сөздөрдүн жыйындысынан курала бербей, лексикалык-семантикалык маанилери боюнча жакындыгы  бар, ошонун негизинде грамматикалык жактан байланышкан сөз айкашынан түзүлөт. Сүйлөм айтылыш максатына карай: жай, суроолуу жана илептүү болуп үчкө бөлүнөт."},{"question":"Quels sont les enjeux éthiques liés à la recherche en intelligence artificielle, notamment en ce qui concerne la vie privée, la discrimination et la prise de décision automatisée ?","answer":"Les enjeux éthiques de la recherche en intelligence artificielle incluent la protection de la vie privée des individus, la prévention de la discrimination algorithmique, la transparence des décisions automatisées et la responsabilité en cas de défaillance des systèmes d'IA. Il est essentiel de promouvoir des normes éthiques dans le développement et l'utilisation de l'IA."},{"question":"Sheeg Ubadka Aan Aabe Mooyee Awoow Laheyn?","answer":"Waa Ilma Aadan Cs"},{"question":"螃蟹為什麼會吐泡泡？","answer":"螃蟹是用鰓呼吸的，它的鰓長在身體背部兩側，並且由許多像海綿一樣的鰓片組成，能吸進很多水，當它離開水時，在一定時間內，還可靠鰓中的水呼吸，當鰓中的水和空氣大量接觸，並且一起被吐出鰓外時，就形成了無數的氣泡。"},{"question":"Tôi đang cải tạo căn nhà phố 3 tầng. Ngân sách không có nhiều nên muốn tìm các phương án thi công hợp lý, độ bền cao, ít hỏng hóc hay cần bảo dưỡng liên tục.Cầu thang nhà tôi đặt ở dưới giếng trời, có mái kính che chắn và vẫn có ánh nắng chiếu xuống vào buổi trưa. Vậy tôi nên làm tay vịn bằng chất liệu gì cho phù hợp? Xin chuyên gia tư vấn giúp!","answer":"Tay vịn cầu thang không chỉ giúp đảm bảo an toàn cho các thành viên trong gia đình khi lên xuống, mà còn đáp ứng yếu tố thẩm mỹ cho ngôi nhà. Trên thị trường hiện nay có nhiều loại chất liệu tay vịn khác nhau như: gỗ, sắt, inox, kính... với mẫu mã và chi phí đa dạng.Trường hợp của bạn, nếu cầu thang đặt dưới khu vực giếng trời thì nên chọn tay vịn bằng sắt hoặc inox vì chất liệu này có thể thích nghi tốt với điều kiện ánh sáng mặt trời chiếu trực tiếp, đồng thời có độ chắc chắn cao, đảm bảo an toàn khi sử dụng. Nên chọn loại thép có lớp mạ kẽm, độ dày tối thiểu từ 1,4 mm để tăng độ bền, tránh han gỉ.Về kích thước, tay vịn cần có đường kính khoảng 6 cm, thiết kế hình tròn hay oval để dễ cầm, nắm. Khoảng cách của lan can và tay vịn cần bố trí từ 0,9-1 m so với bề mặt bậc thang, để giữ an toàn cho người đi lại. Giá thành của tay vịn và lan can bằng chất liệu sắt, inox thường dao động từ 900.000 đồng đến 1,2 triệu đồng một mét dài."},{"question":"ما هو العنصر ذو الفاعلية في الالبان؟","answer":"هو عنصر الكالسيوم."},{"question":"menene ma'anar soja?","answer":"kalmar soja na nufin mayaki mai kare kasar sa"},{"question":"ዳግማዊ ሚኒሊክ ኢትዮጵያን በሚያስተዳድሩበት ወቅት ከሰሩት አንዱ ተግባር ምን ነበር?","answer":"የአውሮፖ ሀይሎችን ጥቃት በመከላከል"},{"question":"Su’aal: Sheeg Sanadkii ey Xurnimada qaadatay dalka Baxreyn?","answer":"Jawaab: Wadanka Baxreyn wuxu Xurnimada qaatay Sanadkii 1977."},{"question":"මගධ රාජ්‍යයේ බලය ලබාගැනීම සඳහා මෞර්‍ය චන්ද්‍රගුප්ත රජුට උදව් උපකාර කල බ්‍රාහ්මණ පඬිවරයා කවුද?","answer":"මගධ රාජ්‍යයේ බලය ලබාගැනීම සඳහා මෞර්‍ය චන්ද්‍රගුප්ත රජුට උදව් උපකාර කල බ්‍රාහ්මණ පඬිවරයා චානක්‍ය හෙවත් කෞටිල්‍යයි."},{"question":"रॉलेट एक्ट के विरोध में लोगों की प्रतिक्रियाओं का वर्णन कीजिए? ","answer":"जीवन के सभी क्षेत्रों के लोगों द्वारा अलोकतांत्रिक और सत्तावादी कानून की निंदा की गई। गांधीजी ने रौलट सत्याग्रह को कानून की अहिंसक सविनय अवज्ञा का आह्वान किया। गांधीजी के नेतृत्व में यह पहला राष्ट्रव्यापी आंदोलन था। 6 अप्रैल को प्रस्तावित रॉलेट एक्ट क खिलाफ एक शक्तिशाली हड़ताल का प्रस्ताव रखा गया था। विभिन्न शहरों में रैलियों का आयोजन किया गया, सभी दुकानें बंद कर दी गई। रेलवे वर्कशॉप में कर्मचारी पर हड़ताल चले गए।"},{"question":"\\"Arrancar os cabelos.\\" O que significa esta expressão?","answer":"Bom, a expressão \\"arrancar os cabelos\\" é uma daquelas expressões que a gente usa quando a coisa está feia, quando a gente está naquela situação de desespero, entende? É como se fosse uma imagem bem vívida da frustração, daquela vontade de puxar os próprios cabelos da cabeça. Por exemplo, imagine você tentando resolver um problema super complicado, as coisas não dando certo de jeito nenhum, e aí, você fica com vontade de arrancar os cabelos, como se isso fosse resolver alguma coisa, certo? É uma expressão que mostra o quanto a gente fica estressado, agoniado, quando as coisas não vão do jeito que a gente quer. É como se fosse um jeito de dizer: \\"Nossa, isso tá me tirando do sério!\\"."},{"question":"පහත මාතෘකා ව ඇති කතාව ලියා  දක්වන්න. (ඉඟිය: මෙය රසවාහිනීයේ එන කතාවකි)මුව වැද්දාගේ කථාව","answer":"මෙයට තිස්එක්වැනි කපට පෙරාතුව සිඛී සම්බුදුරජාණන් වහන්සේ බුද්ධත්වයට පැමිණි එක් සමයක විවේක සැපය විඳිමින් එක් වන සෙනසුනක සඟල සිවුර එලා වැඩහුන් සේක. දෙව් බඹ ආදීහු එහි රැස්ව උන්වහන්සේට පුදමින් වඳිමින් සිටියහ. ඔවුනට බුදුහු චතුරාර්ය සත්‍යය දේශනා කළහ. එක් මුව වැද්දෙක් දඩයමට ගොස් මෙසේ වැඩ සිටි බුදුරජාණන් වහන්සේ දැක එකත් පස්ව සිට බණ අසා සිත පහදා එයින් මියගොස් දෙව්ලොව ඉපිද නැවත නැවතත් සදෙව්ලොවම ඉපිද මේ බුද්‍ධොත්පාදයෙහි සැවැත්නුවර කුලගෙයක ඉපිද නුවණ ඇතිව බුදු සසුනෙහි මහණව ගෙණ, දිනක් බුදුරජාණන් වහන්සේ දේශනා කොට වදාළ ධර්මය අසා සිව්පිළිසිඹියාපත්ව සංඝයා මැද දී තමා විසින් කරන ලද පින්කම පිළිබඳ උදානය මෙසේ පැවැසීය.සිඛී බුදුරජාණන් වහන්සේ මිනිසුන්ට ධර්ම දේශනා කරමින් ජීවත් වූහ. එ සමයෙහි මම මුව වැද්දෙක් වී දඩයමට කැලයට ගියෙමි. දෙව් බඹුන්ට දේශනා කළ චතුරාර්ය සත්‍යය මම ද ඇසීමි. එම පින නිසා දෙව්ලොව ඉපදුනෙමි. නැවත නැවතත් සදෙව්ලොව ඉපිද දෙව් සැපත් වින්දෙමි. ඒ මම දැන් මහ ධනවත් කුලයක ඉපිද වැඩිවියට පත්ව ගිය කල්හි දිනක් දෙව්රම් වෙහෙරට ගියෙමි. එහිදී ශිෂ්‍යයන්ට ධර්මය දේශනා කළ බුදුරජුන් දැක මම ද බණ ඇසීමි. පසුව මහණ වීමි. දැන් නිවන් පසක්කර ගත්තෙක් වෙමි. එබැවින් මම එක වචනයක් කියමි. එනම්, “මනාකොට ධර්මය අසව්” යන වචනයයි."},{"question":"Түркмөнстан өлкөсү жөнүндө маалымат бере аласыңбы?","answer":"Түркмөнстан Республикасы (түркмөнчө: Türkmenistan Respublikasy, орусча: Туркменистан же Туркмения) – Орто Азияда жайгашкан түрк мамлекеттердин бири. 1991 жылга чейин Советтер Союзунун мүчөсү болгон жана Түркмөн Советтик Социалистик Республикасы деп аталып жүргөн. Ал түштүк-чыгыш тарабында Ооганстан менен чектешет, түштүк жана түштүк-батыш тарабында Иран менен, Өзбекстан менен чыгышта жана түндүк-чыгышта, Казакстан менен түндүктө жана түндүк-батышта жана батышта Каспий деңиз менен. Деңизде ал Азербайджан, Армения, Грузия жана Орусия менен чектешет.Совет доорунан кийин көп убакыттан бери – 15 жыл – мамлекетте бир партиялык система болду[1] жана анын өзгөрбөгөн башчысы Сапармурат Ниязов болду. Ал өзүн өмүргө калган президент кылып, Сапармурат Түркмөнбашы (түркмөндөрдүн атасы) деп атап койгон. Сапармурат Ниязов 21 декабрьдын 2006 жылында кызыктай бир себептерден каза болгон. Расмий түрдө ал жүрөктүн жетишсиздигинен өлдү деген маалымат таратылган.Ал өлгөндөн кийин, президенттин милдетин аткаруучусу вице-премьер-министр, Сапармурат Ниязовдун тиш доктуру Гурбангулы Бердымухамедов болду.2007 жылдын 11 февралында эгемендик Түркмөнстан тарыхында экинчи гана президенттик шайлоо болду. Анда президенттин милдетин аткаруучу Гурбангулы Бердимухамедов болду."},{"question":"Mitovy hevitra sa mifanipa-kevitra sa tsy misy ifandraisany ireto fehezanteny roa ireto?Fehezanteny A: Tsara ery izany akanjonao izany!Fehezanteny B: Tsy manendrika anao mihitsy ilay akanjo.","answer":"Mifanipa-kevitra ireo fehezanteny roa ireo."},{"question":"Millaisia väärinkäsityksiä ylinopeuteen liittyy?","answer":"Ylinopeuteen liittyy erilaisia väärinkäsityksiä”Pahinta, mitä voi tapahtua, on se, että menetän ajokorttini.”Väärin. Ajokortin menettäminen on vähäistä siihen verrattuna, että itse tai joku toinen menehtyy. Ylinopeus lisää sekä liikenneonnettomuuksien riskiä että pahentaa niiden seurauksia.”Autoni on turvallinen ja olen hyvä kuski, joten voin ajaa lujaa.”Väärin. Edes maailman turvallisin auto ei selviä ehjänä suurella nopeudella tapahtuneesta törmäyksestä. Edes maailman turvallisin auto ei selviä ehjänä sivutörmäyksestä nopeuden ollessa yli 50 km/h ja nokkakolarista nopeuden ollessa 80 km/h. Jos ajat suojattoman tienkäyttäjän päälle, hänellä on vain pieni mahdollisuus selvitä hengissä, jos nopeutesi on törmäyshetkellä yli 30 km/h. Koska liikenne on yhteispeliä, ei riitä, että sinä olet taitava. Jos ajat lujaa, et ehdi reagoida, kun joku vähemmän taitava kuski ajautuu väärälle kaistalle tai kun hirvi tai lapsi juoksee tielle. Et ole liikenteessä yksin.”Ajan ylinopeutta säästääkseni aikaa – minulla on kiire.”Väärin. Kiire on yksi tavallisimmista syistä, jonka vuoksi ajetaan ylinopeutta. Tämä koskee sekä ammattiautoilijoita että stressaantuneita yksityishenkilöitä. Totuus on, että ajansäästö on hyvin vähäistä. On vaikea ylläpitää samaa nopeutta, koska ennen ohituksia joutuu usein jarruttamaan.”Ylinopeuden ajaminen ei ole yhtä vaarallista kuin humalassa ajaminen, eli se on ihan ok.”Väärin. Ei ole ok tehdä jotakin vaarallista, typerää ja laitonta sillä perusteella, että on olemassa vielä vaarallisempia, typerämpiä ja laittomampia asioita. Kuten rattijuoppouskin, ylinopeuden ajaminen vaikuttaa siten, että kuljettajalla on huomattavan paljon vähemmän aikaa reagoida yllättäviin tilanteisiin, mikä lisää sekä onnettomuusriskiä että huonontaa kuljettajan (tai uhrin) henkiinjäämismahdollisuuksia.”Minun on seurattava liikenteen rytmiä, vaikka kaikki muut ajavatkin ylinopeutta.”Väärin. Olet aina vastuussa omasta toiminnastasi etkä voi vedota siihen, mitä kaikki muut tekevät. Liikenneturvallisuus perustuu tietysti osittain siihen, että mukautuu liikenteen rytmiin – edellyttäen, että kyse on normaalista liikenteen rytmistä. On siis tärkeää näyttää hyvää esimerkkiä, kun kaikki muut ajavat liian lujaa. Silloin tilanne on kaikkien kannalta turvallisempi.”Minähän ajan niin lujaa kuin haluan.”Väärin. Ajokortti on sinun ja yhteiskunnan välinen sopimus. Sinun autonkuljettajan oikeuksien vastapainona ovat velvollisuudet, joihin kuuluu nopeusrajoituksien noudattaminen teillä, joilla ajat. Rajoitukset on asetettu sinun ja muiden turvallisuuden takaamiseksi.Liikenteen ympäristövaikutuksiin liittyviä väärinkäsityksiä”On pakko ajaa vähän lujempaa, jotta palaminen olisi optimaalista. Liian hitaasti ajaminen on vähintään yhtä haitallista ympäristölle.”Väärin. Mitä lujempaa ajat, sitä enemmän polttoainetta moottorin on poltettava. Mitä enemmän polttoainetta palaa, sitä enemmän hiilidioksidia syntyy ja hiilidioksidi edistää kasvihuoneilmiötä.”Pakokaasut vähenevät sitä mukaa kun markkinoille tulee uusia, vielä parempia autoja.”Väärin. Tosiasia on, että hiilidioksidipäästöt kasvavat kasvamistaan: tällä hetkellä niitä on 15 % enemmän kuin vuonna 1990. Vaikka suurin osa nykyisistä uusista autoista säästää huomattavan paljon enemmän energiaa kuin vanhemmat mallit, ympäristötavoitteiden saavuttamisessa menee vielä pitkään.”Kokonaisuuden kannalta minä ja autoni olemme kuin pisara meressä, joten sillä ei ole väliä.”Väärin. Jokainen suomalainen henkilöauto päästää keskimäärin kolme tonnia hiilidioksidia vuodessa (15 000 kilometrillä), eikä sinun autosi ole poikkeus.”Pakokaasujen määrä ei kasva, kun ajaa nopeammin – päinvastoin, saastuttaminen kestää lyhyemmän aikaa.”Väärin. Tosiasia on, että jos kaikki suomalaiset noudattaisivat nopeusrajoituksia, hiilidioksidipäästöt vähenisivät vuosittain 350 000 tonnia. Määrä vastaa runsaan 100 000 auton päästöjä normaaliajossa samalla aikavälillä."},{"question":"第一句: 怀特出生在皮埃尔岛, 在哈利法克斯接受教育, 她从达尔豪西大学获得英语学士学位. 她出生在皮埃尔岛, 在哈利法克斯学习, 住在多伦多, 问题:第一句和第二句表达相同的意义吗? 相同还是不同?","answer":"相同"},{"question":"گا وشەیەکی کوردیە؟ ","answer":"ڕاستە "},{"question":"ஏறு தழுவுதல் குறித்துக் கூறும் ஒரே சங்க நூல் எது?","answer":"ஏறு தழுவுதல் குறித்துக் கூறும் ஒரே சங்க நூல் கலித்தொகை ஆகும் "},{"question":"ਸੋਹਣੀ ਮਹੀਵਾਲ : ਲੋਕ ਕਹਾਣੀ","answer":"ਝਨਾਅ ਦੇ ਪਾਣੀਆਂ ਨੇ ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਮੁਹੱਬਤੀ ਰੂਹਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਜਨਮ ਦਿੱਤਾ ਹੈ ਉਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਵਿਚ ‘ਸੋਹਣੀ’ ਇਕ ਅਜਿਹਾ ਅਮਰ ਨਾਂ ਹੈ ਜਿਸ ਨੇ ਪੰਜਾਬੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਮਨਾਂ ‘ਤੇ ਅਮਿੱਟ ਛਾਪ ਛੱਡੀ ਹੈ। ਸਦੀਆਂ ਬੀਤਣ ਬਾਅਦ ਵੀ ਲੋਕ ਉਸ ਦੀਆਂ ਬਾਤਾਂ ਬੜੇ ਚਾਵਾਂ ਨਾਲ ਪਾਉਂਦੇ ਹਨ।ਬਾਤ ਸਦੀਆਂ ਪੁਰਾਣੀ ਹੈ। ਬਲਖ਼ ਬੁਖਾਰੇ ਦੇ ਸੌਦਾਗਾਰ ਅਲੀ ਬੇਗ ਦਾ ਨੌਜਵਾਨ ਪੁੱਤਰ ਇੱਜ਼ਤ ਬੇਗ ਅਜੋਕੇ ਪਾਕਿਸਤਾਨ ਦੇ ਸ਼ਹਿਰ ਗੁਜਰਾਤ ਵਿਚ ਭਾਂਡਿਆਂ ਦਾ ਵਪਾਰ ਕਰਨ ਲਈ ਆਇਆ। ਇਕ ਦਿਨ ਉਹ ਆਪਣੇ ਨੌਕਰ ਨਾਲ ਗੁਜਰਾਤ ਦੀਆਂ ਹੱਟੀਆਂ ਵੇਖਦਾ-ਵੇਖਦਾ ਤੁੱਲੇ ਦੀ ਭਾਂਡਿਆਂ ਦੀ ਦੁਕਾਨ ‘ਤੇ ਪੁੱਜ ਗਿਆ। ਦੁਕਾਨ ‘ਤੇ ਭਾਂਡੇ ਖਰੀਦਣ ਵਾਲਿਆਂ ਦੀ ਬੜੀ ਭੀੜ ਸੀ। ਦੁਕਾਨ ਵਿਚ ਕੂਜੇ, ਬਾਦੀਏ, ਸੁਰਾਹੀਆਂ, ਘੜੇ, ਮਟਕੇ ਆਦਿ ਇਸ ਸਲੀਕੇ ਨਾਲ ਟਿਕਾਏ ਹੋਏ ਸਨ ਜਿਵੇਂ ਕਿਸੇ ਚਿੱਤਰਕਾਰ ਨੇ ਆਪਣੇ ਚਿੱਤਰਾਂ ਦੀ ਪ੍ਰਦਰਸ਼ਨੀ ਲਾਈ ਹੋਵੇ।ਇੱਜਤ ਬੇਗ ਬਾਹਰ ਖੜ੍ਹਾ ਸਜੀਲੀ ਦੁਕਾਨ ਵੱਲ ਪ੍ਰਸੰਸਾ ਭਰੀਆਂ ਤੱਕਣੀਆਂ ਨਾਲ ਤੱਕਦਾ ਰਿਹਾ। ਗਾਹਕਾਂ ਦੀ ਕੁਝ ਭੀੜ ਘਟੀ। ਤੁੱਲੇ ਦੀ ਨਿਗਾਹ ਨੌਜਵਾਨ ਸੌਦਾਗਰ ‘ਤੇ ਜਾ ਪਈ।”ਹੁਕਮ ਕਰੋ ਸਭ ਕੁਝ ਹਾਜ਼ਰ ਹੈ, ਜਲ ਪਾਣੀ ਦੀ ਆਗਿਆ ਦਿਓ।” ਤੁੱਲੇ ਨੇ ਨੌਜਵਾਨ ਸੌਦਾਗਰ ਅੱਗੇ ਦੋਨੋਂ ਹੱਥ ਜੋੜੇ ਅਤੇ ਕਾਹੀ ਦਾ ਬਣਿਆ ਰਾਂਗਲਾ ਮੂਹੜਾ ਅੱਗ ਵਧਾ ਦਿੱਤਾ।”ਜਲ ਪਾਣੀ ਲਈ ਮਿਹਰਬਾਨੀ, ਸਾਨੂੰ ਕੁਝ ਭਾਂਡਿਆਂ ਦੀ ਲੋੜ ਏ, ਅਸੀਂ ਆਪਣੇ ਦੇਸ਼ ਨੂੰ ਤੁਹਾਡੇ ਦੇਸ਼ ਦੀ ਸੁਗਾਤ ਲਿਜਾਣਾ ਚਾਹੁੰਦੇ ਹਾਂ, ਕੁਝ ਨਮੂਨੇ ਵਿਖਾਓ।” ਮੂਹੜੇ ‘ਤੇ ਬੈਠਦਿਆਂ ਇੱਜ਼ਤ ਬੇਗ ਨੇ ਉੱਤਰ ਦਿੱਤਾ।ਤੁੱਲਾ ਘੁਮਿਆਰ ਦੁਕਾਨ ਅੰਦਰੋਂ ਭਾਂਡੇ ਲੈਣ ਲਈ ਚਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ. ਇੱਜ਼ਤ ਬੇਗ ਸੋਚ ਰਿਹਾ ਸੀ ਕਿ ਉਹ ਖੂਬਸੂਰਤ ਭਾਂਡਿਆਂ ਦੇ ਰਚਣਹਾਰੇ ਦੀ ਸਿਫਤ ਕਰੇ ਤਾਂ ਕਿਵੇਂ ਕਰੇ।ਤੁੱਲਾ ਅੰਦਰੋਂ ਕਈ ਨਮੂਨੇ ਲੈ ਆਇਆ. ਨਮੂਨੇ ਕੀ ਸਨ- ਕਿਸੇ ਕਰਾਮਾਤੀ ਹੱਥਾਂ ਦਾ ਕਮਾਲ ਸਨ- ਤੱਕਿਆ ਭੁੱਖ ਲਹਿੰਦੀ ਸੀ।”ਇਹ ਬਹੁਤ ਸੁੰਦਰ ਹਨ- ਅਤੀ ਸੁੰਦਰ। ਕੋਈ ਕਦਰਦਾਨ ਦਿਲ ਹੀ ਇਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਦਾ ਮੁੱਲ ਤਾਰ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ। ਤੁਸੀਂ ਏਡੇ ਮਨਮੋਹਣੇ ਭਾਂਡੇ ਕਿਵੇਂ ਬਣਾ ਲੈਂਦੇ ਹੋ?” ਇੱਜ਼ਤ ਬੇਗ ਦੀਆਂ ਪ੍ਰਸੰਸਾ ਭਰੀਆਂ ਤੱਕਣੀਆਂ ਜਾਣਕਾਰੀ ਲੋੜਦੀਆਂ ਸਨ। ਪ੍ਰਸੰਸਾ ਦੇ ਸ਼ਬਦ ਸੁਣ ਕੇ ਤੁੱਲੇ ਦੀਆਂ ਅੱਖਾਂ ਚਮਕ ਉਠੀਆਂ। ਉਹ ਇੱਜ਼ਤ ਬੇਗ ਨੂੰ ਆਪਣੇ ਅੰਦਰ-ਬਾਰ ਲੈ ਗਿਆ ਜਿਥੇ ਭਾਂਡੇ ਬਣ ਰਹੇ ਸਨ। ਚੱਕ ਬੜੀ ਤੇਜ਼ੀ ਨਾਲ ਘੁੰਮ ਰਿਹਾ ਸੀ ਤੇ ਤੁੱਲੇ ਦੀ ਮੁਟਿਆਰ ਧੀ ਆਪਣੀਆਂ ਕੋਮਲ ਉਂਗਲਾਂ ਨਾਲ ਗੁੰਨ੍ਹੀ ਹੋਈ ਮਿੱਟੀ ਨੂੰ ਜਾਦੂ ਭਰੀਆਂ ਛੂਹਾਂ ਦੇ ਰਹੀ ਸੀ।”ਇਹ ਹੈ ਮੇਰੀ ਧੀ ਸੋਹਣੀ, ਇਹ ਸਾਰੇ ਭਾਂਡੇ ਏਸੇ ਦੇ ਬਣਾਏ ਹੋਏ ਹਨ।” ਤੁੱਲੇ ਨੇ ਆਪਣੀ ਧੀ ਵੱਲ ਇਸ਼ਾਰਾ ਕੀਤਾ।ਘੁੰਮਦਾ ਚੱਕ ਹੌਲੀ ਹੋ ਗਿਆ. ਮੁਟਿਆਰ ਚੱਕ ਉਤੇ ਜਨਮ ਲੈ ਰਹੇ ਸ਼ਾਹਕਾਰ ਵਿਚ ਮਗਨ ਸੀ, ਉਸ ਜ਼ਰਾ ਕੁ ਪਿੱਛੇ ਮੁੜ ਕੇ ਤੱਕਿਆ- ਕਾਲੀਆਂ ਘਟਾਵਾਂ ਪਿੱਛੋਂ ਚੰਦ ਦੀ ਪਿਆਰੀ ਟੁਕੜੀ ਟਹਿਕ ਪਈ।ਇੱਜ਼ਤ ਬੇਗ ਨੇ ਧੁੱਪ ਵਿਚ ਸੁਕਾਏ ਜਾ ਰਹੇ ਭਾਂਡੇ ਤੱਕੇ ਅਤੇ ਆਵੇ ਵਿਚ ਪਕਾਏ ਜਾ ਰਹੇ ਭਾਂਡਿਆਂ ਬਾਰੇ ਜਾਣਕਾਰੀ ਪ੍ਰਾਪਤ ਕੀਤੀ। ਜਿੰਨੀ ਦੇਰ ਉਹ ਇਸ ਬਾੜੇ ਵਿਚ ਰਿਹਾ ਸੋਹਣੀ ਦੀ ਪਿਆਰੀ ਸੂਰਤ ਉਹਨੂੰ ਨਜ਼ਰੀਂ ਆਂਦੀ ਰਹੀ ਸੀ। ਉਸ ਨੂੰ ਭਾਂਡਿਆਂ ਦੀ ਖੂਬਸੂਰਤੀ ਦਾ ਭੇਤ ਸਮਝ ਪੈ ਗਿਆ, ”ਸੋਹਣੀ ਦਾ ਆਪਣਾ ਰੂਪ ਹੀ ਤਾਂ ਇਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਭਾਂਡਿਆਂ ਵਿਚ ਸਮਾਇਆ ਹੋਇਆ ਹੈ ਜਿਸ ਕਰਕੇ ਉਹ ਐਨੇ ਖੂਬਸੂਰਤ ਲਗਦੇ ਨੇ।”ਇੱਜ਼ਤ ਬੇਗ ਨੇ ਬਹੁਤ ਸਾਰੇ ਭਾਂਡੇ ਖਰੀਦ ਲਏ; ਜੋ ਮੁੱਲ ਤੁੱਲੇ ਨੇ ਮੰਗਿਆ ਉਹਨੇ ਤਾਰ ਦਿੱਤਾ।ਤੁੱਲੇ ਦੀ ਦੁਕਾਨ ਵਿਚੋਂ ਨਿਕਲਦਿਆਂ ਇੱਜ਼ਤ ਬੇਗ ਨੇ ਇਸ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ ਮਹਿਸੂਸ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਿਵੇਂ ਉਹ ਕਿਸੇ ਮੰਦਰ ਦੀ ਜ਼ਿਆਰਤ ਕਰਕੇ ਆ ਰਿਹਾ ਹੋਵੇ।ਹੁਣ ਤੁੱਲੇ ਦੀ ਹੁਸ਼ਨਾਨ ਧੀ, ਸੋਹਣੀ ਇੱਜ਼ਤ ਬੇਗ ਦੇ ਖਿਆਲਾਂ ‘ਤੇ ਛਾ ਚੁੱਕੀ ਸੀ।ਇੱਜ਼ਤ ਬੇਗ ਨੇ ਖੂਬਸੂਰਤ ਭਾਂਡੇ ਆਪਣੇ ਤੰਬੂ ਵਿਚ ਸਜਾ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਜਿਸ ਭਾਂਡੇ ਵਲ ਉਹ ਤੱਕਦਾ, ਚੰਨ ਨਾਲੋਂ ਪਿਆਰੀ ਸੂਰਤ ਉਹਨੂੰ ਨਜ਼ਰ ਆਈ। ਹਰ ਪਾਸੇ ਸੋਹਣੀ, ਜਿਧਰ ਵੀ ਤੱਕਦਾ ਮੁਸਕਰਾਉਂਦੀ ਸੋਹਣੀ ਵਿਖਾਈ ਦਿੰਦੀ। ਸਾਰੀ ਰਾਤ ਉਹ ਸੋਹਣੀ ਦੇ ਖਿਆਲਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਖੋਇਆ ਰਿਹਾ, ਇਕ ਪਲ ਲਈ ਵੀ ਉਹਨੂੰ ਨੀਂਦ ਨਾ ਆਈ। ਪੈਸੇ ਦਾ ਵਣਜ ਕਰਨ ਆਇਆ ਸੌਦਾਗਰ ਇਸ਼ਕ ਦਾ ਵਣਜ ਕਰਨ ਲਈ ਉਤਾਵਲਾ ਹੋ ਉਠਿਆ। ਉਹਨੇ ਆਪਣਾ ਨੌਕਰ ਆਪਣੇ ਦੇਸ਼ ਪਰਤਾ ਦਿੱਤਾ ਤੇ ਆਪ ਗੁਜਰਾਤ ਵਿਚ ਹੀ ਭਾਂਡਿਆਂ ਦੀ ਹੱਟੀ ਪਾ ਲਈ। ਉਹ ਭਾਂਡੇ ਖਰੀਦਣ ਦੇ ਪੱਜ ਹਰ ਰੋਜ਼ ਸੋਹਣੀ ਦਾ ਪਿਆਰਾ ਮੁਖੜਾ ਤੱਕਣ ਆਉਂਦਾ। ਭਾਂਡਿਆਂ ਦਾ ਵਪਾਰੀ ਉਹ ਕਿਧਰੋਂ ਸੀ, ਉਹ ਤਾਂ ਨੈਣਾਂ ਦਾ ਵਣਜਾਰਾ ਸੀ, ਹੁਸਨ ਦੀ ਹੱਟੀ ਦਾ ਸੌਦਾ ਖਰੀਦਣ ਵਾਲਾ। ਦੁਕਾਨ ਵਿਚ ਘਾਟੇ ‘ਤੇ ਘਾਟਾ ਪੈਂਦਾ ਗਿਆ। ਇਕ ਵਰ੍ਹੇ ਵਿਚ ਹੀ ਉਹਨੇ ਆਪਣੀ ਸਾਰੀ ਪੂੰਜੀ ਮੁਕਾ ਦਿੱਤੀ। ਤੁੱਲੇ ਦਾ ਸੈਂਕੜੇ ਰੁਪਏ ਦਾ ਕਰਜ਼ਾ ਉਦੇ ਸਿਰ ਹੋ ਗਿਆ। ਹਾਲਤ ਇਥੋਂ ਤੱਕ ਪੁੱਜ ਗਈ ਕਿ ਉਹ ਰੋਟੀ ਤੋਂ ਵੀ ਆਤੁਰ ਹੋ ਗਿਆ।ਅਜੇ ਤੀਕਰ ਇੱਜ਼ਤ ਬੇਗ ਨੇ ਸੋਹਣੀ ਨਾਲ ਦੋ ਪਿਆਰ ਭਰੀਆਂ ਗੱਲੜੀਆਂ ਨਹੀਂ ਸਨ ਕੀਤੀਆਂ, ਸੋਹਣੀ ਦੀਆਂ ਅੱਖਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਅੱਖਾਂ ਪਾ ਕੇ ਮੁਸਕਰਾਇਆ ਤਕ ਨਹੀਂ ਸੀ।ਹਾਰ ਕੇ ਇੱਜ਼ਤ ਬੇਗ ਨੇ ਤੁੱਲੇ ਦੇ ਪੈਰ ਜਾ ਫੜੇ।”ਮਾਪਿਆ ਮੈਨੂੰ ਬਚਾ ਲੈ। ਮੇਰੇ ਪਾਸ ਫੁੱਟੀ ਕੌਡੀ ਵੀ ਨਹੀਂ ਜੀਹਦੇ ਨਾਲ ਤੇਰਾ ਕਰਜ਼ਾ ਮੋੜ ਸਕਾਂ। ਇਸ ਪ੍ਰਦੇਸ਼ ਵਿਚ ਮੇਰਾ ਕੋਈ ਨਹੀਂ। ਹੇ ਨੇਕ ਦਿਲ ਬੰਦੇ ਮੇਰੇ ‘ਤੇ ਤਰਸ ਕਰ। ਮੈਨੂੰ ਆਪਣੇ ਕੋਲ ਨੌਕਰ ਰੱਖ ਲੈ। ਮੈਂ ਸਿਰਫ ਦੋ ਟੁਕੜੇ ਰੋਟੀ ਦੇ ਖਾ ਕੇ ਗੁਜ਼ਾਰਾ ਕਰ ਲਵਾਂਗਾ, ਮੇਰੀ ਨੌਕਰੀ ਵਿਚੋਂ ਆਪਣਾ ਕਰਜ਼ਾ ਕੱਟ ਲੈਣਾ।” ਇੱਜ਼ਤ ਬੇਗ ਨੇ ਲੇਲੜ੍ਹੀਆਂ ਕੱਢਦਿਆਂ ਆਖਿਆ। ਉਹਦੇ ਨੈਣ ਭਰ ਆਏ।ਤੁੱਲਾ ਸੋਚੀਂ ਪੈ ਗਿਆ। ਕੁਝ ਚਿਰ ਸੋਚ ਕੇ ਤੁੱਲੇ ਨੇ ਹੁੰਗਾਰਾ ਭਰਿਆ, ‘ਬੇਟਾ ਘਾਬਰਨ ਦੀ ਲੋੜ ਨਹੀਂ। ਵਣਜਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਘਾਟੇ-ਵਾਧੇ ਬਣੇ ਹੀ ਹੋਏ ਨੇ। ਇਹ ਮੈਂ ਜਾਣਦਾਂ ਕਿ ਤੂੰ ਪ੍ਰਦੇਸੀ ਏਂ, ਤੇਰਾ ਏਥੇ ਕੋਈ ਮਦਦਗਾਰ ਨਹੀਂ। ਤੂੰ ਮੇਰੇ ਕੋਲ ਨੌਕਰ ਰਹਿਣ ਦਾ ਸਵਾਲ ਪਾਇਆ ਏ, ਮੈਂ ਸਵਾਲੀ ਕਦੇ ਦਰੋਂ ਮੋੜਿਆ ਨਹੀਂ। ਮੈਂ ਤੈਨੂੰ ਆਪਣੇ ਕੋਲ ਨੌਕਰ ਰੱਖਣ ਲਈ ਤਿਆਰ ਹਾਂ ਪਰ ਇਕ ਸ਼ਰਤ ਏ…””ਹਾਂ ਦੱਸ ਬਾਬਾ…।” ਇੱਜ਼ਤ ਬੇਗ ਕਾਹਲੀ ਨਾਲ ਬੋਲਿਆ। ਉਸ ਨੂੰ ਆਸ ਦਾ ਟਹਿਟਹਾਣਾ ਜਗਮਗਾਂਦੇ ਵਿਖਾਈ ਦੇ ਰਿਹਾ ਸੀ।”ਤੈਨੂੰ ਮੱਝਾਂ ਚਾਰਨ ‘ਤੇ ਨੌਕਰ ਰਹਿਣਾ ਪਵੇਗਾ, ਸੋਚ ਲੈ।” ਤੁੱਲੇ ਨੇ ਗੰਭੀਰਤਾਪੂਰਬਕ ਆਖਿਆ।”ਮੈਨੂੰ ਮਨਜ਼ੂਰ ਏ, ਮੈਂ ਖਿੜੇ ਮੱਥੇ ਇਹ ਨੌਕਰੀ ਕਰਾਂਗਾ।”ਇੱਜ਼ਤ ਬੇਗ ਲਈ ਜਿਵੇਂ ਸਵਰਗ ਦੀ ਖਿੜਕੀ ਖੁੱਲ੍ਹ ਗਈ ਹੋਵੇ। ਆਪਣੇ ਪਿਆਰੇ ਨਾਲ ਨੇੜਤਾ ਪ੍ਰਾਪਤ ਕਰਨ ਦੀ ਸੱਧਰ ਉਹਨੂੰ ਹੁਣ ਪੂਰੀ ਹੁੰਦੀ ਜਾਪਦੀ ਸੀ। ਇੱਜ਼ਤ ਬੇਗ ਮੂੰਹ ਝਾਖਰੇ ਹੀ ਮੱਝਾਂ ਖੋਲ੍ਹਦਾ, ਆਪਣੇ ਸਾਥੀਆਂ ਸਮੇਤ ਝਨਾਅ ਦੇ ਬੇਲੇ ਵਿਚ ਪੁੱਜ ਜਾਂਦਾ। ਇੱਜ਼ਤ ਬੇਗ ਤੋਂ ਉਹ ਹੁਣ ਮਹੀਂਵਾਲ ਬਣ ਚੁੱਕਾ ਸੀ, ਉਹਨੂੰ ਇਸੇ ਨਾਂ ਨਾਲ ਸੱਦਦੇ ਸਨ। ਕੋਈ ਡੇਢ ਵਰ੍ਹਾ ਇਸੇ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ ਲੰਘ ਗਿਆ. ਸੋਹਣੀ ਦੀ ਰਾਂਗਲੀ ਨੁਹਾਰ ਉਹਨੂੰ ਜ਼ਿੰਦਗੀ ਜੀਣ ਦਾ ਲਾਰਾ ਦਈ ਜਾ ਰਹੀ ਸੀ। ਉਹ ਕਲਪਨਾ ਵਿਚ ਹੀ ਕਈ ਵਾਰ ਸੋਹਣੀ ਨਾਲ ਸ਼ਹਿਦ ਭਰੀਆਂ ਗੱਲਾਂ ਕਰਦਾ, ਰੁੱਸਦਾ, ਹੱਸਦਾ ਅਤੇ ਮਨਮਨਾਈ ਕਰਦਾ। ਪਰੰਤੂ ਸੋਹਣੀ ਉਹਦੇ ਪਾਸੋਂ ਬਹੁਤ ਦੂਰ ਸੀ- ਅਸਮਾਨੀ ਤਾਰਿਆਂ ਨਾਲੋਂ ਵੀਦੂਰ। ਸੋਹਣੀ ਤਾਂ ਉਹਦੇ ਲਈ ਲਾਜਵੰਤੀ ਦਾ ਬੂਟਾ ਸੀ, ਜਿਹੜਾ ਹੱਥ ਲਾਇਆ ਕੁਮਲਾ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਏ।ਇਕ ਦਿਨ ਸੋਹਣੀ ਮਹੀਂਵਾਲ ਲਈ ਭੱਤਾ ਲੈ ਕੇ ਆ ਗਈ। ਉਹਦਾ ਚੋ ਚੋ ਪੈਂਦਾ ਰੂਪ ਮਹੀਂਵਾਲ ਨੂੰ ਤੜਪਾ ਗਿਆ। ਉਸ ਆਪਣੀ ਦਿਲ ਸੋਹਣੀ ਅੱਗੇ ਫੋਲ ਸੁੱਟਿਆ।”ਸੋਹਣੀਏ! ਮੈਂ ਤੇਰੇ ਪਿੱਛੇ ਆਪਣੇ ਮਾਂ ਬਾਪ ਅਤੇ ਪਿਆਰਾ ਦੇਸ ਛੱਡ ਦਿੱਤੇ। ਪਰ ਤੂੰ ਏਂ ਜੀਹਨੇ ਮੇਰੇ ਨਾਲ ਸਿੱਧੇ ਮੂੰਹ ਗੱਲ ਵੀ ਨਹੀਂ ਕੀਤੀ। ਹਜ਼ਾਰਾਂ ਲੱਖਾਂ ਦੀ ਦੌਲਤ ਨੂੰ ਲੱਤ ਮਾਰ ਕੇ ਮੈਂ ਤੇਰੀਆਂ ਮੱਝਾਂ ਚਾਰ ਰਿਹਾ। ਕੁਝ ਰਹਿਮ ਕਰ ਸੋਹਣੀ ਏਂ। ਕੁਝ ਤਰਸ ਕਰ ਹੁਸਨ ਪਰੀਏ।”ਸੋਹਣੀ ਦੇ ਹੁਸ਼ਨਾਕ ਚਿਹਰੇ ‘ਤੇ ਲਾਲੀ ਦੀ ਲਹਿਰ ਦੌੜ ਗਈ। ਉਹਨੇ ਮਹੀਂਵਾਲ ਨੂੰ ਆਪਣੀ ਮੁਹੱਬਤ ਇਸ਼ਕ ਦੀ ਦਹਿਲੀਜ ਚੜ੍ਹਾ ਦਿੱਤੀ।”ਸੋਹਣੀਏਂ ਦੁਨੀਆਂ ਦੀਸਾਰੀ ਦੌਲਤ ਅੱਜ ਮੇਰੀ ਝੋਲੀ ਵਿਚ ਏ. ਮੇਰੇ ਨਾਲੋਂ ਅਮੀਰ ਹੁਣ ਦੁਨੀਆਂ ਵਿਚ ਦੂਜਾ ਕੋਈ ਨਹੀਂ।””ਮਹੀਂਵਾਲਾ ਮੈਂ ਆਪਣੀ ਪਾਕ ਮੁਹੱਬਤ ਤੇਰੇ ਹਵਾਲੇ ਕਰ ਦਿੱਤੀ ਐ, ਮੈਂ ਵਫਾ ਨਿਭਾਵਾਂਗੀ ਇਸ਼ਕ ਨੂੰ ਦਾਗ ਨਹੀਂ ਲੱਗਣ ਦਿਆਂਗੀ…।”ਸੋਹਣੀ ਮਹੀਂਵਾਲ ਹਰ ਰੋਜ਼ ਬੇਲੇ ਵਿਚ ਪਿਆਰ ਮਿਲਣੀਆਂ ਮਾਣਦੇ ਰਹੇ।ਬੇਲੇ ਵਿਚ ਸੋਹਣੀ ਦਾ ਰੋਜ਼ ਮਹੀਂਵਾਲ ਪਾਸ ਜਾਣਾ ਕਈ ਖਚਰੀਆਂ ਨਜ਼ਰਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਖੁੜਕ ਗਿਆ। ਉਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਦੇ ਇਸ਼ਕ ਦੀ ਚਰਚਾ ਸ਼ੁਰੂ ਹੋ ਗਈ:ਤੂੰ ਹੱਸਦੀ ਦਿਲ ਰਾਜ਼ੀ ਮੇਰਾਲਗਦੇ ਨੇ ਬੋਲ ਪਿਆਰੇਚੱਲ ਕਿਧਰੇ ਦੋ ਗੱਲਾਂ ਕਰੀਏਬਹਿ ਕੇ ਨਦੀ ਕਿਨਾਰੇਲੁਕ ਲੁਕ ਲਾਈਆਂ ਪ੍ਰਗਟ ਹੋਈਆਂਵਜ ਗਏ ਢੋਲ ਨਿਗਾਰੇਸੋਹਣੀਏਂ ਆ ਜਾ ਨੀਡੁੱਬਦਿਆਂ ਨੂੰ ਰੱਬ ਤਾਰੇਤੁੱਲੇ ਨੂੰ ਵੀ ਸੋਹਣੀ ਮਹੀਂਵਾਲ ਦੇ ਪ੍ਰੇਮ ਬਾਰੇ ਸੂਹ ਮਿਲ ਗਈ. ਦੋ ਜਵਾਨੀਆਂ ਦੀ ਪਾਕ ਮੁਹੱਬਤ ਨੂੰ ਉਨ੍ਹਆਂ ਪ੍ਰਵਾਨ ਨਾ ਕੀਤਾ। ਮਹੀਂਵਾਲ ਨੂੰ ਚਾਕਓਂ ਜਵਾਬ ਮਿਲ ਗਿਆ ਤੇ ਸੋਹਣੀ ਨੂੰ ਉਨਾਂ ਗੁਜਰਾਤ ਦੇ ਇਕ ਹੋਰ ਘੁਮਾਰਾਂ ਦੇ ਮੁੰਡੇ ਨਾਲ ਵਿਆਹ ਦਿੱਤਾ।ਸੋਹਣੀ ਮਹੀਂਵਾਲ ਲਈ ਤੜਫਦੀ ਰਹੀ, ਮਹੀਂਵਾਲ ਸੋਹਣੀ ਦੇ ਵੈਰਾਗ ਵਿਚ ਹੰਝੂ ਕੇਰਦਾ ਰਿਹਾ। ਝੂਠੀ ਲੋਕ ਲਾਜ ਨੇ ਦੋ ਪਿਆਰੇ ਵਿਛੋੜ ਦਿੱਤੇ, ਦੋ ਰੂਹਾਂ ਘਾਇਲ ਕਰ ਦਿੱਤੀਆਂ।ਇੱਜ਼ਤ ਬੇਗੋਂ ਮਹੀਂਵਾਲ ਬਣਿਆ ਮਹੀਂਵਾਲ ਮਹੀਂਵਾਲੋਂ ਫਕੀਰ ਬਣ ਗਿਆ ਤੇ ਗੁਜਰਾਤ ਤੋਂ ਵਜ਼ੀਰਾਬਾਦ ਦੇ ਪਾਸੇ ਇਕ ਮੀਲ ਦੀ ਦੂਰੀ ‘ਤੇ ਝਨਾਅ ਦਰਿਆ ਦੇ ਪਾਰਲੇ ਕੰਢੇ ਝੁੱਗੀ ਜਾ ਪਾਈ।ਸੋਹਣੀ ਹੁਣ ਆਪਣੇ ਸਹੁਰੇ ਘਰ ਰਹਿ ਰਹੀ ਸੀ। ਇਕ ਦਿਨ ਫਕੀਰ ਬਣਿਆ ਮਹੀਂਵਾਲ ਸੋਹਣੀ ਨੂੰ ਜਾ ਮਿਲਿਆ ਤੇ ਉਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਹਰ ਰੋਜ਼ ਅੱਧੀ ਰਾਤ ਮਗਰੋਂ ਝਨਾਅ ਦੇ ਕੰਢੇ ਮਿਲਣਾ ਨੀਯਤ ਕਰ ਲਿਆ।ਅੱਧੀ ਰਾਤ ਗੁਜ਼ਰਦੀ, ਸੋਹਣੀ ਆਪਣੇ ਘਰਦਿਆਂ ਤੋਂ ਚੋਰੀ ਉਠਦੀ ਤੇ ਇਕ ਮੀਲ ਬੇਲੇ ਦੇ ਤਰਾਹ-ਤਰਾਹ ਕਰ ਰਹੇ ਸੁੰਨਸਾਨ ਰਾਹਾਂ ਵਿਚੋਂ ਲੰਘਦੀ ਹੋਈ ਆਪਣੇ ਮਹੀਂਵਾਲ ਨੂੰ ਜਾ ਮਿਲਦੀ। ਮਹੀਂਵਾਲ ਪਾਰੋਂ ਕਾਲੀ ਬੋਲ੍ਹੀ ਰਾਤ ਵਿਚ ਝਨਾਅ ਪਾਰ ਕਰਕੇ ਆਉਂਦਾ। ਸਤਾਰਿਆਂ ਜੜੇ ਚੰਦੋਏ ਦੀ ਛਾਂ ਥੱਲੇ ਦੋ ਘਾਇਲ ਰੂਹਾਂ ਮਿਲਦੀਆਂ, ਪਿਆਰੀਆਂ, ਰਸ ਭਰੀਆਂ ਤੇ ਨਾ ਮੁੱਕਣ ਵਾਲੀਆਂ ਗੱਲਾਂ ਕਰਦੀਆਂ।ਇਕ ਰਾਤ ਝਨਾਅ ਪਾਰ ਕਰੇਂਦੇ ਮਹੀਂਵਾਲ ਦੇ ਕਿਸੇ ਜਾਨਵਰ ਨੇ ਚੱਕ ਮਾਰਿਆ ਤੇ ਉਹਦਾ ਪੱਟ ਚੀਰ ਸੁੱਟਿਆ। ਹੁਣ ਉਹਦੇ ਲਈ ਤੈਰਨਾ ਮੁਸ਼ਕਲ ਹੋ ਗਿਆ ਸੀ।ਅਗਲੀ ਰਾਤ ਸੋਹਣੀ ਆਪਣੇ ਨਾਲ ਮਿੱਟੀ ਦਾ ਪੱਕਾ ਘੜਾ ਲੈ ਗਈ। ਘੜੇ ਦੀ ਮਦਦ ਨਾਲ ਉਹਨੇ ਝਨਾਅ ਪਾਰ ਕੀਤਾ ਤੇ ਮਹੀਂਵਾਲ ਦੀ ਝੁੱਗੀ ਵਿਚ ਜਾ ਪੁੱਜੀ। ਮਹੀਂਵਾਲ ਸੋਹਣੀ ਨੂੰ ਮਿਲ ਕੇ ਆਪਣੀ ਪੀੜ ਭੁੱਲ ਗਿਆ, ”ਤੈਨੂੰ ਪਾ ਕੇ, ਸੋਹਣੀਏਂ ਮੇਰਾ ਦੁੱਖ ਅੱਧਾ ਰਹਿ ਗਿਐ। ਤੂੰ ਤਾਂ ਮਰਦਾਂ ਨਾਲੋਂ ਵੀ ਤਕੜੀ ਨਿਕਲੀ ਏਂ, ਐਡੀ ਕਾਲੀ ਬੋਲ੍ਹੀ ਰਾਤ ਵਿਚ ਐਡੇ ਵੱਡੇ ਦਰਿਆ ਨੂੰ ਪਾਰ ਕਰਨਾ ਇਕ ਔਰਤ ਲਈ ਬਹੁਤ ਵੱਡੀ ਗੱਲ ਏ।” ਉਹ ਹਰ ਰੋਜ਼ ਦਰਿਆ ਪਾਰ ਕਰਕੇ ਮਹੀਂਵਾਲ ਪਾਸ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਅਤੇ ਆਉਂਦੀ ਹੋਈ ਘੜੇ ਨੂੰ ਸਰਕੜੇ ਦੇ ਬੂਝੇ ਵਿਚ ਲੁਕੋ ਦੇਂਦੀ।ਸੋਹਣੀ ਦੇ ਹਰ ਰੋਜ਼ ਅੱਧੀ ਰਾਤੋਂ ਬਾਹਰ ਜਾਣ ਤੇ ਉਹਦੀ ਨਨਾਣ ਨੂੰ ਸ਼ੱਕ ਹੋ ਗਿਆ। ਇਕ ਦਿਨ ਉਹ ਵੀ ਸੋਹਣੀ ਦੇ ਮਗਰ ਤੁਰ ਪਈ। ਸੋਹਣੀ ਨੂੰ ਆਪਣੇ ਮਗਰ ਆਉਂਦੀ ਕਦਮਾਂ ਦੀ ਵਾਜ਼ ਵੀ ਸੁਣਾਈ ਦਿੱਤੀ ਪਰੰਤੂ ਉਹਨੇ ਆਪਣੇ ਹੀ ਕਦਮਾਂ ਦੀ ਆਵਾਜ਼ ਦਾ ਭੁਲੇਖਾ ਜਾਣ ਕੇ ਗੱਲ ਆਈ ਗਈ ਕਰ ਛੱਡੀ। ਸੋਹਣੀ ਦਰਿਆ ‘ਤੇ ਪੁੱਜੀ, ਸਰਕੜੇ ਦੇ ਬੂਝੇ ਵਿਚੋਂ ਘੜਾ ਚੁੱਕਿਆ ਤੇ ਦਰਿਆ ਵਿਚ ਠਿੱਲ੍ਹ ਪਈ. ਉਹਦੀ ਨਨਾਣ ਦੂਰ ਖੜ੍ਹੀ ਸਭ ਕੁਝ ਤੱਕਦੀ ਰਹੀ। ਸੋਹਣੀ ਕੁਝ ਸਮੇਂ ਮਗਰੋਂ ਵਾਪਸ ਪਰਤੀ ਤੇ ਘੜਾ ਉਸੇ ਥਾਂ ‘ਤੇ ਲੁਕੋ ਦਿੱਤਾ। ਉਹਦੀ ਨਨਾਣ ਛੋਪਲੇ-ਛੋਪਲੇ ਕਦਮੀਂ ਸੋਹਣੀ ਤੋਂ ਪਹਿਲੋਂ ਘਰ ਪੁੱਜ ਗਈ।ਦਿਨੇ ਨਨਾਣ ਨੇ, ਆਪਣੀ ਮਾਂ ਨੂੰ, ਸੋਹਣੀ ਦੇ ਦਰਿਆ ਪਾਰ ਕਰਕੇ ਮਹੀਂਵਾਲ ਨੂੰ ਮਿਲਣ ਜਾਣ ਦੀ ਸਾਰੀ ਵਾਰਤਾ ਜਾ ਸੁਣਾਈ।ਅੱਧੀ ਰਾਤ ਲੰਘੀ, ਸੋਹਣੀ ਉੱਠੀ। ਬਾਹਰ ਘੁੱਪ ਹਨੇਰਾ ਪਸਰਿਆ ਹੋਇਆ ਸੀ। ਸਾਰੇ ਅਸਮਾਨ ‘ਤੇ ਬੱਦਲ ਛਾਏ ਹੋਏ ਸਨ। ਸੋਹਣੀ ਨੇ ਦਰੋਂ ਬਾਹਰ ਪੈਰ ਰੱਖਿਆ ਹੀ ਸੀ ਕਿ ਬਿਜਲੀ ਕੜਕੜਾਈ। ਉਹਦਾ ਦਿਲ ਕੰਬ ਗਿਆ ਪਰੰਤੂ ਉਸ ਪੈਰ ਪਿੱਛੇ ਨਾ ਮੋੜੇ। ਉਹਦਾ ਮਹੀਂਵਾਲ ਉਹਨੂੰ ਉਡੀਕਦਾ ਪਿਆ ਸੀ… ਦੂਰ ਪਾਰਲੇ ਕੰਢੇ ਉਹਦਾ ਇੰਤਜ਼ਾਰ ਕਰ ਰਿਹਾ ਸੀ। ਉਹ ਆਪਣਾ ਦਿਲ ਤਕੜਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਤੁਰ ਪਈ। ਰਾਹ ਨਜ਼ਰੀਂ ਨਹੀਂ ਸੀ ਪੈਂਦਾ। ਰਾਹ ਵਿਚ ਅਨੇਕਾਂ ਕੰਡੇ ਤੇ ਝਾੜੀਆਂ ਖਿੰਡੀਆਂ ਪਈਆਂ ਸਨ। ਉਹ ਡਿਗਦੀ ਢਹਿੰਦੀ, ਝਾੜੀਆਂ, ਝਾਫਿਆਂ ਵਿਚ ਫਸਦੀ ਲਹੂ ਲੁਹਾਣ ਹੋਈ ਝਨਾਅ ਦੇ ਕੰਢੇ ‘ਤੇ ਪੁੱਜ ਗਈ। ਉਸ ਸਰਕੜੇ ਦੇ ਬੂਝੇ ਵਿਚੋਂ ਘੜਾ ਚੁੱਕ ਲਿਆ। ਘੜੇ ਨੂੰ ਉਸ ਆਪਣੀ ਆਦਤ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਟੁਣਕਾ ਕੇ ਵੇਖਿਆ, ਪਹਿਲਾਂ ਵਰਗੀ ਟੁਣਕਾਰ ਨਹੀਂ ਸੀ। ਆਹ! ਕਿਸੇ ਪਾਪੀ ਨੇ ਪੱਕੇ ਦੀ ਥਾਂ ਕੱਚਾ ਰੱਖ ਦਿੱਤਾ ਸੀ। ਮੁਹੱਬਤ ਨਵੇਂ ਇਮਤਿਹਾਨ ਵਿਚ ਪਾ ਦਿੱਤੀ ਸੀ।ਪਾਰਲੇ ਕੰਢੇ ਮਹੀਂਵਾਲ ਦੀ ਝੁੱਗੀ ਵਿਚ ਦੀਵਾ ਟਿਮਟਮਾ ਰਿਹਾ ਸੀ ਤੇ ਮਹੀਂਵਾਲ ਸੁਰੀਲੀ ਬੰਸਰੀ ਦੀਂ ਤਾਲਾਂ ਤੇ ਪਿਆਰੇ ਬੋਲ ਗਾਉਂਦਾ ਪਿਆ ਸੀ। ਉਰਲੇ ਕੰਢੇ ਸੋਹਣੀ ਕੱਚਾ ਘੜਾ ਚੁੱਕੀ ਸੋਚਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਡੁੱਬੀ ਖੜ੍ਹੀ ਸੀ। ਵਿਚਕਾਰ ਦਰਿਆ ਪੂਰੇ ਸਿਖਰ ‘ਤੇ ਸੀ। ਅਸਮਾਨਾਂ ‘ਤੇ ਕਹਿਰਾਂ ਦੀ ਬਿਜਲੀ ਲਿਸ਼ਕ ਰਹੀ ਸੀ।”ਕੀ ਹੋਇਆ ਘੜਿਆ ਤੂੰ ਪੱਕਿਓਂ ਕੱਚਾ ਬਣ ਗਿਓਂ। ਮੈਂ ਪਿੱਛੇ ਨਹੀਂ ਪਰਤਾਂਗੀ, ਆਪਣਾ ਕੌਲ ਪੂਰਾ ਕਰਾਂਗੀ। ਮੈਂ ਮਰਦ ਜਾਤ ਪਾਸੋਂ ਇਹ ਉਲਾਂਭਾ ਨਹੀਂ ਖੱਟਾਂਗੀ। ਆਪਣੀ ਵਫ਼ਾ ਨਿਭਾਵਾਂਗੀ, ਚਾਹੇ ਮੈਨੂੰ ਆਪਣੀ ਜਿੰਦ ਵੀ ਕਿਉਂ ਨਾ ਵਾਰਨੀ ਪੈ ਜਾਵੇ…”ਸੋਹਣੀ ਨੇ ਸੱਚੇ ਰੱਬ ਅੱਗੇ ਦੋਨੋਂ ਹੱਥ ਜੋੜੇ ਤੇ ਕੱਚੇ ਘੜੇ ਨਾਲ ਦਰਿਆ ਵਿਚ ਠਿੱਲ੍ਹ ਪਈ:ਰਾਤ ਹਨੇਰੀ ਲਿਸ਼ਕਣ ਤਾਰੇਕੱਚੇ ਘੜੇ ‘ਤੇ ਮੈਂ ਤਰਦੀਵੇਖੀਂ ਰੱਬਾ ਖੈਰ ਕਰੀਂਤੇਰੀ ਆਸ ਤੇ ਮੂਲ ਨਾ ਡਰਦੀਮੂੰਹ ਜ਼ੋਰ ਪਾਣੀਆਂ ਅੱਗੇ ਕੱਚਿਆਂ ਨੇ ਕਿੱਥੋਂ ਠਹਿਰਨਾ ਹੋਇਆ। ਸੋਹਣੀ ਅਜੇ ਥੋੜ੍ਹੀ ਦੂਰ ਹੀ ਗਈ ਸੀ ਕਿ ਘੜਾ ਖੁਰ ਗਿਆ। ਉਹ ਆਪਣੇ ਹੱਥ ਪੈਰ ਮਾਰਨ ਲੱਗੀ… ਹੋਰ ਕੁਝ ਗਜ਼ ਵਧੀ… ਕਹਿਰਾਂ ਦਾ ਪਾਣੀ ਵਗ ਰਿਹਾ ਸੀ। ਉਹਦਾ ਸਾਹ ਟੁੱਟਣ ਲੱਗਾ…।”ਮਹੀਂਵਾਲਾ… ਮਹੀਂਵਾਲਾ…. ਆ ਮਿਲ ਲੈ ਮਹੀਂਵਾਲਾ… ‘ਤੇ ਸੋਹਣੀ ਦੀ ਆਵਾਜ਼ ਗੁਆਚ ਗਈ। ਪਾਣੀ ਦੀ ਇਕ ਤੇਜ਼ ਲਹਿਰ ਉਹਨੂੰ ਆਪਣੇ ਨਾਲ ਵਹਾ ਕੇ ਲੈ ਗਈ।ਬੜੇ ਜ਼ੋਰਾਂ ਦੀ ਬਿਜਲੀ ਕੜਕੀ। ਬਿਜਲੀ ਦੇ ਲਿਸ਼ਕਾਰੇ ਵਿਚ ਮਹੀਂਵਾਲ ਨੂੰ ਪਾਣੀਆਂ ਨਾਲ ਘੋਲ ਕਰੇਂਦੀ ਸੋਹਣੀ ਵਖਾਈ ਦਿੱਤੀ।”ਸੋਹਣੀਏਂ ਦਿਲ ਨਾ ਛੱਡੀਂ, ਮੈਂ ਆਇਆ।” ਮਹੀਂਵਾਲ ਨੇ ਆਪਣੇ ਪੂਰੇ ਜ਼ੋਰ ਨਾਲ ਆਵਾਜ਼ ਮਾਰੀ ਅਤੇ ਦਰਿਆ ਵਿਚ ਛਾਲ ਮਾਰ ਦਿੱਤੀ।ਉਹ ਮੁਸ਼ਕਿਲ ਨਾਲ ਝਨਾਂ ਦੇ ਅੱਧ ਵਿਚਕਾਰ ਪੁੱਜਿਆ ਹੀ ਸੀ ਕਿ ਉਹਨੇ ਬਿਜਲੀ ਦੇ ਲਿਸ਼ਕਾਰੇ ਵਿਚ ਆਪਣੇ ਤੋਂ ਚੰਦ ਕਦਮਾਂ ਦੀ ਦੂਰੀ ‘ਤੇ ਰੁੜ੍ਹੀ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਸੋਹਣੀ ਤੱਕੀ। ਉਹਨੇ ਬੜੇ ਜ਼ੋਰ ਨਾਲ ਹੱਥ ਮਾਰੇ ਤੇ ਬੇਸੁਰਤ ਸੋਹਣੀ ਨੂੰ ਫੜ ਲਿਆ ਅਤੇ ਕੰਢੇ ਵੱਲ ਨੂੰ ਵਧਣ ਲੱਗਾ। ਦਰਿਆ ਅੱਜ ਪੂਰਾ ਚੜ੍ਹਿਆ ਹੋਇਆ ਸੀ। ਉਹਦੀ ਕੋਈ ਪੇਸ਼ ਨਹੀਂ ਸੀ ਜਾ ਰਹੀ। ਪੂਰਾ ਅੱਧਾ ਦਰਿਆ ਅਜੇ ਉਸ ਪਾਰ ਕਰਨਾ ਸੀ। ਉਸ ਬੜੀ ਕੋਸ਼ਿਸ਼ ਕੀਤੀ ਪਰੰਤੂ ਉਹਦਾ ਸਾਹ ਅਧ-ਵਿਚਕਾਰ ਹੀ ਟੁੱਟ ਗਿਆ। ਪਾਣੀ ਦੀ ਇਕ ਕਹਿਰਾਂ ਭਰੀ ਲਹਿਰ ਉਹਨੂੰ ਸੋਹਣੀ ਸਮੇਤ ਵਹਾਅ ਕੇ ਲੈ ਗਈ।ਮਹੀਂਵਾਲ ਦੀ ਝੁੱਗੀ ਵਿਚ ਟਿਮਟਮਾਉਂਦਾ ਦੀਵਾ ਚਿਰੋਕਣਾ ਬੁੱਝ ਚੁੱਕਾ ਸੀ।ਜਿਸ ਸਿਦਕ ਦਿਲੀ ਨਾਲ ਸੋਹਣੀ ਨੇ ਆਪਣੀ ਪ੍ਰੀਤ ਨਿਭਾਈ ਹੈ ਉਸ ਸਦਕਾ ਪੰਜਾਬ ਦਾ ਲੋਕ ਮਾਨਸ ਅੱਜ ਵੀ ਉਸ ਦੇ ਸਿਦਕ ਨੂੰ ਵਾਰ-ਵਾਰ ਪ੍ਰਣਾਮ ਕਰਦਾ ਹੈ:-ਸੋਹਣੀ ਜਹੀ ਕਿਸੇ ਪ੍ਰੀਤ ਕੀ ਕਰਨੀਉਹਦੀ ਪ੍ਰੀਤ ਵੀ ਪਾਣੀ ਭਰਦੀਵਿਚ ਝਨਾਵਾਂ ਦੇਸੋਹਣੀ ਆਪ ਡੁੱਬੀ ਰੂਹ ਤਰਦੀ।"},{"question":"Apakah maksud \\"bagai apa sakit berbini janda, anak tiri boleh disuruh\\"?","answer":"Kahwin dengan janda banyak untungnya"},{"question":"キングオブコント2020で3位に入賞した鈴木もぐらと水川かたまりからなるお笑いコンビは何？","answer":"空気階段です。"},{"question":"Wanene mafi arziki a Najeriya a 2021?","answer":"Attajirin da ya fi kowa kudi a Afirka, Aliko Dangote, ya kafa kuma ya jagoranci kamfanin siminti na Dangote, wanda shi ne babban mai samar da siminti a nahiyar. Ya mallaki kashi 85% na simintin Dangote da ake sayar da shi a bainar jama'a ta hannun wani kamfani. Dangote Cement na da karfin samar da metrik ton miliyan 48.6 a duk shekara kuma yana aiki a kasashe 10 na Afirka. Ya kuma samar da kamfanin taki na Dangote a Najeriya wanda ya fara aiki a watan Maris na 2022. Tun shekarar 2016 ake gina matatar mai na Dangote wacce aka kammala a 2023. Dangote dan asalin jihar Kano ne."},{"question":"දරු නැළවිලි කවියක් කියන්න ","answer":" අඩන බිළිඳු දරුවන්නේ තුඩකින් වද? ඇද බොන්නේ දසෙකඩ වන් මසකින්නේ බඩේ අඩාලද? උන්නේ"},{"question":"Que língua é falada no país Butão?","answer":"butanês"},{"question":"Nunmehr hält er Rückblick auf die zwischenzeitliche Entwicklung, wobei er sich selbst dabei gerne in Pose setzt. Highlight ist diesmal sein Erfolg, bei der Klimakonferenz in Paris 2015 das Land Indien zum Einlenken bewegt zu haben. Eine Rolle spielte dabei auch das kalifornische Unternehmen SolarCit. Minutiös wird dargestellt, wie Al Gore mit einigen international maßgebenden Politikern persönlich verhandelt. Der Film zeigt Katastrophenszenarien aus den USA, wo der neue Präsident Donald Trump das mühsam verhandelte Klimaschutzabkommen wieder aufkündigen will. Al Gore, der außerdem 2007 den Friedensnobelpreis erhielt, kritisiert aber auch das politische System seines Landes.Verfasse eine passende Überschrift für den vorangehenden Artikel.","answer":"Ein passender Titel für den Artikel wäre \\"Neuer Film von Al Gore in den deutschen Kinos\\"."},{"question":"Apakah maksud \\"ada umur ada rezeki\\"?","answer":"Asal masih hidup, tentu akan beroleh rezeki"},{"question":"Kung aduna ka 40 ka patatas ug gikuhaan ka og 16, pila ang nabilin?","answer":"Ang nabilin nlang kay 24 ka patatas."},{"question":"தர்க்க நடையில் உரை கண்டவர் யார்?","answer":"தர்க்க நடையில் உரை கண்டவர் சேனாவரையர்.சேனாவரையர், தொல்காப்பியத்துக்கு உரை எழுதிய இடைக்காலத் தமிழ் மொழி உரையாசிரியர்களில் ஒருவர். சேனை அரையர் என்னும் சொற்கள் புணரும்போது சேனாவரையர் என வரும்.[1] எனவே இவரது பெயர் சேனைத் தலைவரைக் குறிக்கும்.பொ.ஊ. 13 ஆம் நூற்றாண்டு கல்வெட்டுகளில் வரும் சில தொடர்கள் இவரைக் குறிக்கும் என்பது அறிஞர்கள் கருத்து.கல்வெட்டு ஆற்றூர் சோமநாத சாமிக்குச் சேனாவரையர் நிலம் அளித்த செய்தியைக் கூறுகிறது. இதனால் இவரது ஊர் மிழலை ஆற்றூர் எனத் தெரிகிறது.நன்னூலை இவர் மேற்கோள் காட்டுவதால் இவரது காலம் அதற்குப் பிந்தியது. சேனாவரையர் நிலம் அளித்த சேய்தியைக் கூறும் கல்வெட்டு மாறவர்மன் குலசேகர பாண்டியன் காலத்தது. எனவே சேனாவரையர் 13 ஆம் நூற்றாண்டின் பிற்பகுதியில் வாழ்ந்தவர் என்பது தெளிவாகிறது.இவர் தொல்காப்பியத்தின் சொல்லதிகாரத்துக்கு மட்டுமே உரை எழுதினார். எனினும் இவ்வதிகாரத்துக்கு எழுதப்பட்ட எல்லா உரைகளிலும் சிறந்த உரை இவர் எழுதிய உரையே என்று கருதப்படுகிறது. "},{"question":"Completa la siguiente frase :  Maxence Idesheim (Quimper, 7 de agosto de 1974) es un deportista francésa que compitió en \\"snowboard\\" y ganó una medalla de plata en el... ","answer":"Campeonato Mundial de Snowboard del año 1999, en la prueba de eslalon gigante."},{"question":"கேள்வி:   உலக போதை மருந்து எதிர்ப்பு நாள் எப்போது அனுசரிக்கப்படுகிறது?","answer":"பதில்:  உலக போதை மருந்து எதிர்ப்பு நாள் ஜூன் 26  அன்று  அனுசரிக்கப்படுகிறது.          மனித மனத்தை சிதைத்து மனித இனத்தை அழிக்கும் பேரபாயமான வேலையை சுலபமாக செய்வது போதைப் பொருள்கள் தான். மனித ஆற்றலை உருக்குலைத்து, அந்த மனித சக்தியை ஒன்றுக்கும் உதவாததாக மாற்றும் சக்தி படைத்தவை போதைப் பொருட்கள். போதைப் பொருள் பயன்படுத்தும் ஒருவர் தனது சுயக் கட்டுப்பாட்டில் இருப்பதே கிடையாது. அதனால் அவரால் சுயமாக சிந்திக்கவும் முடியாது. மனச்சிதைவு, உடல் நலக் கோளாறு, நாள்பட்ட நோய்கள், தீராத வலி இவை தான் போதைப் பொருள் பயன்பாடு நமக்கு தரும் பரிசுகள்.         அதனால் தான் சர்வதேச அளவில் போதைப் பொருள் தொடர்பான விவகாரம் மிகவும் முக்கியமானதாக பார்க்கப்படுகிறது. போதைப் பொருள் கடத்தல் மற்றும் உபயோகம் உள்ளிட்டவற்றை தடுக்க சர்வதேச நாடுகள் பெரும் முயற்சிகள் எடுத்து வருகின்றன.சர்வதேச ஆய்வுகளின் படி உலகம் முழுவதும் கிட்டத்தட்ட 30 கோடிக்கும் அதிகமானோர் போதைப் பொருட்களுக்கு அடிமையாகி உள்ளதாக கூறப்படுகிறது. மது, சிகரெட் ஆகியவை முதலில் வழி கொடுத்து பிறகு அதையும் தாண்டி கஞ்சா, கொகைன், பிரவுன் சுகர், ஹெராயின், அபின், புகையிலை, ஒயிட்னர் போன்ற மனிதனை அழிக்கும் போதைப்பொருள்கள் இளைஞர்களின் வாழ்வைச் சீரழிக்கிறது.         போதைப்பொருள் பயன்படுத்துபவர் மட்டுமன்றி அவரை சுற்றியுள்ள அனைவரையும் அது பாதிக்கிறது. தனிமனித ஒழுக்கம் சீர்கெட்டு நாட்டின் முன்னேற்றப் பாதைக்கே போதை தடையாக இருக்கிறது. உலக வர்த்தகத்தில் பெட்ரோல், இராணுவத் தளவாடங்களுக்கு அடுத்து மூன்றாவது இடத்தில் சட்டவிரோதமாக போதைப்பொருள் கடத்தல் வியாபாரம் கொடிகெட்டிப் பறக்கிறது. அதை தடுப்பதற்கான முன்னெடுப்பாகத் தான் ஒவ்வொரு ஆண்டும் ஜூன் 26 ஆம் நாள் சர்வதேச போதைப் பொருள் ஒழிப்பு தினம் மற்றும் சித்ரவதைக்கு ஆளானவர்களுக்கான ஆதரவு தினம் அனுசரிக்கப்படுகிறது.       மனித சமூகத்திற்கு போதை பொருள் பயன்பாட்டால் ஏற்படும் பாதிப்புகளை பற்றிய விழிப்புணர்வை ஏற்படுத்தவே இந்த நாள் அனுசரிக்கப்படுகிறது. ஐ.நா சபை 1987 ஆம் ஆண்டு முதல் ஜூன் 26-ம் தேதியை சர்வதேச போதைப் பொருள் ஒழிப்பு தினமாக அங்கீகரித்தது. அப்போது முதல் ஒவ்வொரு ஆண்டும் ஜூன் 26 ஆம் தேதி போதைப் பொருள் ஒழிப்பு தினமாக கடைப்பிடிக்கப்படுகிறது. இந்த ஆண்டிற்கான கருப்பொருளாக மக்களே முக்கியம் என அறிவிக்கப்பட்டிருக்கிறது.      அதாவது போதைப் பொருட்களால் ஏற்பட்டிருக்கும் களங்கத்தை துடைப்போம் என்றும் பாகுபாடு காட்டாமல் போதைப் பொருளை தடுப்போம் என்றும் வலியுறுத்தியுள்ளது ஐக்கிய நாடுகள் சபை.சந்தோசத்திற்காகவும், துக்கத்தை மறக்கவும், சமூக அந்தஸ்திற்காகவும், கெட்-டு-கெதருக்காவும், கெஸ்ட் மேனஸ்-க்காகவும் என போதையில் உழல்வதற்கான காரணம் சொல்வதை நிறுத்திக் கொண்டாலே போதையின் பாதையில் நாம் தொடர்ந்து செல்ல வேண்டியதில்லை."},{"question":"ਮਹਾਂਸਾਗਰਾਂ ਤੋਂ ਪ੍ਰਾਪਤ ਹੋ ਸਕਣ ਵਾਲੀ ਊਰਜਾ ਦੀਆਂ ਕੀ ਕਮੀਆਂ ਹਨ ?","answer":"ਮਹਾਂਸਾਗਰਾਂ ਤੋਂ ਬਹੁਤ ਜ਼ਿਆਦਾ ਮਾਤਰਾ ਵਿੱਚ ਊਰਜਾ ਦੀ ਪ੍ਰਾਪਤੀ ਹੋ ਸਕਦੀ ਹੈ । ਅਜਿਹਾ ਹਮੇਸ਼ਾ ਸੰਭਵ ਨਹੀਂ ਹੋ ਸਕਦਾ ਕਿਉਂਕਿ ਮਹਾਂਸਾਗਰਾਂ ਤੋਂ ਉਰਜਾ ਰੁਪਾਂਤਰਨ ਦੀਆਂ ਤਿੰਨ ਵਿਧੀਆਂ-ਜਵਾਰ ਉਰਜਾ, ਤਰੰਗ ਉਰਜਾ ਅਤੇ ਸਮੁੰਦਰੀ ਤਾਪ ਊਰਜਾ ਦੀਆਂ ਆਪਣੀਆਂ-ਆਪਣੀਆਂ ਕਮੀਆਂ ਹਨ ।* ਜਵਾਰ ਊਰਜਾ – ਜੁਆਰ ਊਰਜਾ ਦਾ ਦੋਹਨ ਸਾਗਰ ਦੇ ਕਿਸੇ ਤੰਗ ਖੇਤਰ ਤੇ ਬੰਨ੍ਹ ਬਣਾ ਕੇ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ । ਬੰਨ੍ਹ ਦੇ ਦਰਵਾਜ਼ੇ ਉੱਤੇ ਸਥਾਪਿਤ ਟਰਬਾਈਨ, ਜੁਆਰ ਊਰਜਾ ਨੂੰ ਬਿਜਲੀ ਊਰਜਾ ਵਿੱਚ ਰੂਪਾਂਤਰਿਤ ਕਰ ਦਿੰਦੀ ਹੈ । ਪਰੰਤੂ ਸਾਗਰ ਦੇ ਤੰਗ ਖੇਤਰ ਤੇ ਬੰਨ੍ਹ ਨਿਰਮਿਤ ਕੀਤੇ ਜਾ ਸਕਣ ਵਾਲੇ ਸਥਾਨ ਸੀਮਿਤ ਹੁੰਦੇ ਹਨ ।* ਤਰੰਗ ਊਰਜਾ – ਤਰੰਗ ਊਰਜਾ ਦਾ ਵਿਵਹਾਰਿਕ ਉਪਯੋਗ ਕੇਵਲ ਉੱਥੇ ਹੀ ਹੋ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ ਜਿੱਥੇ ਤਰੰਗਾਂ ਅਤੇ ਪ੍ਰਬਲ ਹੁੰਦੀਆਂ ਹਨ । ਸਾਰੀ ਦੁਨੀਆ ਵਿੱਚ ਅਜਿਹੇ ਸਥਾਨ ਬਹੁਤ ਘੱਟ ਹਨ ਜਿੱਥੇ ਸਮੁੰਦਰ ਦੇ ਤੱਟਾਂ ਤੇ ਤਰੰਗਾਂ ਇੰਨੀਆਂ ਪ੍ਰਬਲਤਾ ਨਾਲ ਟਕਰਾਉਂਦੀਆਂ ਹਨ ਕਿ ਉਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਦੀ ਊਰਜਾ ਨੂੰ ਬਿਜਲੀ ਊਰਜਾ ਵਿੱਚ ਰੂਪਾਂਤਰਿਤ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕੇ ।* ਸਮੁੰਦਰੀ ਉਰਜਾ – ਸਮੁੰਦਰੀ ਤਾਪ ਉਰਜਾ ਦੀ ਪ੍ਰਾਪਤੀ ਦੇ ਲਈ ਪਲਾਂਟ (OTEC) ਕੇਵਲ ਤਦ ਹੀ ਕੰਮ ਕਰ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ ਜਦੋਂ ਸਮੁੰਦਰ ਤੇ ਤਲ ਦੇ ਗਰਮ ਪਾਣੀ ਦਾ ਤਾਪਮਾਨ 2 km ਤੱਕ ਦੀ ਗਹਿਰਾਈ ਤੇ ਪਾਣੀ ਦੇ ਤਾਪ ਵਿੱਚ 20°C ਜਾਂ ਇਸ ਤੋਂ ਵੱਧ ਦਾ ਅੰਤਰ ਹੋਵੇ । ਇਸ ਪ੍ਰਕਾਰ ਬਿਜਲੀ ਊਰਜਾ ਪ੍ਰਾਪਤ ਕੀਤੀ ਜਾ ਸਕਦੀ ਹੈ, ਪਰੰਤੂ ਇਹ ਪ੍ਰਣਾਲੀ ਬਹੁਤ ਮਹਿੰਗੀ ਹੈ ।"},{"question":"ඉන්දියාවේ අගනුවර කුමක්ද?","answer":"ඉන්දියාවේ අගනුවර  නව දිල්ලි වේ."},{"question":"Sheeg Nabiga (NNKH) Iyo Abuu-Bakar Ninkii Ceersaday Markii Ey Hijroonaayeen?","answer":"Wuxu Ahaa Suraaqa Bin Maalik."},{"question":"(Ekhwehlela.) Uqinisile umama wakho ndodana. Usindwe yizinyawonjengoba bengingasakwazi ukuyibamba le nsizwa. Bengilokhungigqolozele emnyango ngithi uyangena lutho. Akonakele lutho-kendodana ngoba mhlawumbe kwenzeke kahle ningatholani laphahleze bekuyosuka uthuli lwezichwe.(Ehlahle amehlo.) Insizwa yakuphi leyo?Yehlisa umoya ndodana. Luselude ukhalo. Uyothi lapho udundubalalesi sisekeseke sentaba uyobe usuvovekile uma uthatha izintonagamawala.1. Nikeza isizathu sokuba isimo senhlalo singabi sihle ekuqaleni kwalesisiqeshana.","answer":"Isizathu ukuthi uMathonsi noMaMhlongo abaphathekile kahle ngenxayokufika kwensizwa abangayazi njengoba bechazela uThamsanqaosebonakala kumcasula ukuzwa ngale nsizwa."},{"question":"ශ්‍රී ලංකාවේ ප්‍රථම පාර්ලිමේන්තු මැතිවරණය පැවති වසර ?","answer":"1947"},{"question":"मानौ राम सँग ५ वटा कलम छ । यदी रमले ३ वटा कलम साथी लाई दियो भने राम सँग कती वटा कलम बाँकी हुन्छ ?","answer":"राम सँग २ वटा कलम बाँकी हुन्छ । "},{"question":"fenoy ny banga :\\"Satrin’ ny mandringa ho ao an-tanàna ny tsena; ary _\\"","answer":"\\"satrin’ ny mpanambady ho ao an-tanàna no manan-drafozana.\\""},{"question":"Boqorkii Muqowqas wuxuu u soodiray Rasuulka (scw) 2 haween (gabdhood) hadiyo ah. Nabiga (scw) mid kamid ah wuu guursaday oo waa Maariya, ee waxaad sheegtaa saxaabiga la siiyay gabdhii kale?","answer":"Waxaa la siiyay saxaabigii Xassaan Ibnu Thaabit."},{"question":"\\"අඳුරු ලලා  වහිනා කල සරසවි බිම තෙමන්න\\" මෙහි \\"ලලා \\" යනු කුමක්ද?","answer":"අඳුරු ලලා = අඳුරු වැටි වැටීලනවා = හෙලනවා = දමනවාඅඟුරු කකා වතුර බිබීකකා = කමින්බිබී = බොමින්ලලා = ලමින්ලලා - ලමින් එනම් බෝවෙමින්පඳුරු ලලා - පඳුරු බෝවෙමින්අඳුරු ලලා - අඳුර බෝවෙමින්"},{"question":"اين تقع مدينة بيت لحم","answer":"مدينة بيت لحم هي مدينة فلسطينية تقع في الضفة الغربية، وهي جزء من المنطقة الفلسطينية المحتلة. تعتبر بيت لحم واحدة من المدن الفلسطينية التاريخية والثقافية، وتحمل أهمية كبيرة للعديد من الأديان، خاصةً المسيحية.تشتهر بيت لحم بأنها المكان الذي وُلِد فيه يسوع المسيح، وتحتضن الكنيسة الرئيسية في المدينة، وهي كنيسة المهد، التي تُعتبر واحدة من أقدس الأماكن في المسيحية. بالإضافة إلى الأبنية التاريخية والدير والمعابده، تحتل بيت لحم مكانة مهمة في السياحة الدينية والثقافية."},{"question":"Ṣé ilá máa ń yọ?","answer":"Bẹẹni. "},{"question":"කොහු නිෂ්පාදනය කෙසේද?","answer":"මුළු ලෝක කොහු කෙඳි නිෂ්පාදනය ටොන් 250,000 (දිගු ටොන් 250,000 ක් සහ කෙටි ටොන් 280,000 ක්) සංවර්ධනය වෙමින් පවතින රටවල සමහර ප්‍රදේශවල මෙම කර්මාන්තය විශේෂයෙන් වැදගත් වේ. ප්‍රධාන වශයෙන් පොල්ලාචි සහ කේරල ප්‍රාන්තයේ වෙරළබඩ ප්‍රදේශය, සුදු කොහු කෙඳි වලින් ලොව මුළු ලෝක නිෂ්පාදනයෙන් 60% ක් නිෂ්පාදනය කරයි. ශ්‍රී ලංකාව දුඹුරු කෙඳි නිමැවුමෙන් 36% ක් නිෂ්පාදනය කරයි. ලෝකය පුරා වාර්ෂිකව නිපදවන කොහු කෙඳි වලින් 50% කට වඩා වැඩි ප්‍රමාණයක් ඉන්දියාවේ ප්‍රධාන වශයෙන් පරිභෝජනය කරයි. සෑම වසරකම ඉන්දියාවේ සහ ශ්‍රී ලංකාවෙන් නිෂ්පාදනය කරන කොහු නිෂ්පාදනයෙන් 90% ක් නිෂ්පාදනය කරයි. කොහු කෙඳි හා කොහු කෙඳි ආශ්‍රිත නිෂ්පාදන සඳහා ලොව විශාලතම අපනයනකරු වන්නේ ශ්‍රී ලංකාවයි."},{"question":"Con tôi học lớp 9 cháu cận 2 mắt 2.25 xin hỏi sử dụng loại thuốc nào để điều trị, và có phương pháp nào khác để giản độ cận hay giữ cho độ cận không tăng ạ? Xin cho lời khuyên.","answer":"Có rất nhiều phương pháp hạn chế cận thị như xoa bóp, bấm huyệt, sử dụng tăng liều các thuốc bổ về mắt gấp 2 – 3, điều trị laser hồng ngoại để tăng cường tuần hoàn cho vùng mắt; kính áp tròng cứng đeo ban đêm… Tất cả những phương pháp này đều không có giá trị tuyệt đối để làm giảm độ cận hoặc để tránh việc tăng số. Nó chỉ là những biện pháp có thể cải thiện một phần, hỗ trợ cho việc nhìn thuận lợi hơn. Vì thế, con bạn đang ở trong độ tuổi trưởng thành, cháu sẽ còn lớn nữa, đồng hành với việc đó, có thể độ cận cũng tăng lên. Nên lời khuyên tốt nhất, là hãy hướng dẫn cho cháu có một sinh hoạt khoa học, làm sao cho đôi mắt cháu tránh làm việc căng thẳng, tránh đọc chữ nhỏ, tránh nhìn màn hình laptop, ipad quá lâu, uống thuốc bổ mắt định kỳ. Ngoài ra, có thể mát xa mắt ngày 1 – 2 lần trong 2 – 3 phút. Đầu tiên hãy xoa hai lòng bàn tay để làm tay nóng lên, rồi ép nhẹ lên vùng mắt, và ấn từ từ đến khi bạn cảm thấy dễ chịu, rồi thả ra, làm lại một vài lần. Sau đó, dùng 3 ngón tay giữa, nhắm mắt, xoa theo vòng, bắt đầu từ khoé mắt đi ra đuôi mắt, từ 10 – 15 lần và ngược lại. Việc mát xa này nên làm thường xuyên, sẽ giúp tăng cường tuần hoàn vùng mắt, giúp hệ cơ về vùng mi mắt được thư giãn, thay đổi áp lực trong nội nhãn thăng bằng hơn. Đó là những điểm cốt lõi giúp mắt ổn định, tránh mỏi mệt, tránh bị tăng số. "},{"question":"Schrijf een voortzetting van de paragraaf: Mays campagne, onder het motto 'sterk en stabiel,' kende diverse tegenslagen en mondde uit in zetelverlies. Eerst ontstond rumoer over een maatregel in het Conservatieve verkiezingsprogramma die gepensioneerden (trouwe stemmers) meer zou laten betalen voor gezondheidszorg. Vooral het terugdraaien van dit plan leverde May reputatieschade op. De terreuraanslagen in Manchester (22 mei) en Londen (3 juni)","answer":"leverden verdere munitie voor Mays tegenstrevers op, aangezien May eerder als minister fors bezuinigd had op het politiebudget."},{"question":"වැඩක් පලක් කිරීමට අලස  යන්නට තනි වචනයක් දෙන්න.","answer":"කම්මැළි "},{"question":"ఇచ్చిన పద్యానికి భావం రాయండి:క॥ కావున నిక్కోమలియెడఁగావలి యున్నట్టిమీరు కఠినోక్తులు గానేవియు నాడకుఁ, డిఁక నీదేవియ రక్షింప మనకు దిక్కగు మీఁదన్","answer":"అందువల్ల సీతాదేవిని రక్షిస్తున్న మీరు కఠినంగా మాట్లాడవద్దు. ఇకమీదట ఈ సీతాదేవి వల్లనే మనం రక్షింపబడతాము."},{"question":"Tohizo izao ohabolana izao : \\"Vady tsy tiana ianteherana tany .... \\" ","answer":"\\"Vady tsy tiana ianteherana tany ikafarana ilevenana.\\""},{"question":"Kiswahili kama somo nchini Kenya.","answer":"Nchini  Kenya Kiswahili ni somo la lazima na la kutahiniwa katika shule  za  msingi  na  shule  za  upili,  hali  ambayo inapelekea kuathiriana na lugha zingine za Kiafrika ikiwemo Kiigembe."},{"question":"Дүйнөдөгү эң бактылуу өлкө кайсы?","answer":"Бул - Финляндия өлкөсү. Бул көрсөткүч калктын жашоо социалдык жактан камсыздыгы, ден соолугунун, жашоо-шартынын деңгээли жана өмүрүнүн узундугу боюнча аныкталат."},{"question":"रेडियम कसले पत्ता लगाए ?","answer":"रेडियम मेरी क्युरी र उनका पति पियरे क्युरीले पत्ता लगाएका थिए।"},{"question":"वयसः परिणामेपि यः खलः खल एव सः।सुपक्वमपि माधुर्यं नोपयातीन्द्रवारुणम्","answer":"वाईट स्वभावाचा माणूस वयाने वाढला तरी तो वाईटच राहतो. इन्द्रवदन नावाचा कडू भोपळा पिकल्यावरसुद्धा गोड होतच नाही."},{"question":"以下の段落に関連する内容を記入しなさい： 世界で有名な音楽家の坂本龍一さんは、今年3月、亡くなりました。坂本さんは亡くなる前、病気の治療をしながら、徳島県神山町の「神山まるごと高専」の校歌を作っていました。この学校は、新しい会社を作る人などを育てるために、今年の春にできました。 校歌は、坂本さんが亡くなったあとにできました。歌詞を考えた歌手のUAさんが学校に行って、学生たちの前で歌いました。そのときのビデオを、学校がインターネットで紹介しています。","answer":"校歌は、新しい会社を作るための勉強をしている学生たちが、強い気持ちで頑張ることができるように応援しています。 UAさんは「卒業したあと、大変なことがあっても、神山町にいたときのことを思い出すような歌になったらいいです」と話していました。"},{"question":"请回答以下问题：问题：什么是墨西哥马里亚契音乐，它有哪些特点？","answer":"答案：墨西哥马里亚契音乐是墨西哥的传统音乐风格之一，以其充满激情的节奏和动感的旋律而著名。它常用吉他、手鼓和口琴等乐器演奏，歌词通常表达着爱情、社会和政治等主题。"},{"question":"Hãy tiếp tục đoạn văn sau: Ngày 31-7, Thủ tướng Phạm Minh Chính đã đến khảo sát, làm việc và bàn giải pháp tháo gỡ khó khăn, vướng mắc tại dự án mở rộng sản xuất giai đoạn 2 Nhà máy Gang thép Thái Nguyên - một dự án tồn đọng, kéo dài 15 năm vẫn chưa hoàn thành, gây lãng phí nguồn lực rất lớn cho Nhà nước và doanh nghiệp. Dự án mở rộng giai đoạn 2 Nhà máy Gang thép Thái Nguyên, Công ty cổ phần Gang thép Thái Nguyên (Tisco) là một trong 12 dự án chậm tiến độ, kém hiệu quả của ngành công thương đã được Thủ tướng tích cực chỉ đạo xử lý trong thời gian qua. Hiện đã có 5/12 dự án đã được xử lý, còn lại 7 dự án thì có 2 dự án có phương án xử lý, còn 5 dự án đang tiếp tục tìm phương án, trong đó dự án mở rộng giai đoạn 2 Nhà máy Gang thép Thái Nguyên được đánh giá thuộc diện phức tạp, khó xử lý nhất. Gang thép Thái Nguyên giai đoạn 2 được khởi công từ năm 2007, có tổng mức đầu tư ban đầu 3.800 tỉ đồng, nhưng kéo dài tới nay chưa hoàn thành và còn tồn tại nhiều khó khăn, vướng mắc. Theo các báo cáo, vướng mắc chính của dự án liên quan tới tranh chấp giữa chủ đầu tư (Tisco) và nhà thầu về hợp đồng EPC (hợp đồng nhà thầu trọn gói).","answer":"Trực tiếp đến khảo sát hiện trường, Thủ tướng bày tỏ sự \\"xót ruột\\" và \\"sốt ruột\\" khi chứng kiến nhiều hạng mục của dự án đang bỏ hoang, nhiều vật tư, thiết bị đã hư hỏng, gỉ sét, nằm phủ bạt ngoài trời nhiều năm nay. \\"Người bảo vệ ở kho thiết bị cũng bày tỏ 'xót ruột' với thực trạng dự án, chỉ mong muốn giải quyết việc này cho sớm. Người dân còn như vậy, thì chúng ta ngồi đây phải thấy trách nhiệm của mình thế nào\\", Thủ tướng nói. Chủ trì cuộc làm việc với các bộ, ngành, cơ quan, địa phương, doanh nghiệp, Thủ tướng nêu rõ tinh thần giải quyết các vấn đề đặt ra trên cơ sở đặt lợi ích quốc gia, dân tộc lên trên hết, trước hết, bám sát các quy định của pháp luật, chỉ đạo của Bộ Chính trị, kết luận thanh tra, các công việc mà các cơ quan đã triển khai. Thủ tướng yêu cầu các cơ quan, đơn vị đánh giá tình hình, thực trạng, cập nhật số liệu chính xác về dự án. Rút kinh nghiệm từ các dự án đã được xử lý trước đây, đề xuất hướng giải quyết cụ thể, làm rõ nguồn lực và cơ chế cần thiết nếu tiếp tục triển khai dự án, thẩm quyền quyết định; báo cáo Ban Cán sự Đảng Chính phủ ngay trong tháng 8. Ông yêu cầu nhiệm vụ quan trọng nhất là khẩn trương tìm được phương án xử lý khả thi nhất, trên cơ sở thực tiễn, khoa học, pháp lý, đảm bảo tiết kiệm nhất, hiệu quả cao nhất cho Nhà nước và doanh nghiệp. Thủ tướng giao Phó thủ tướng Lê Minh Khái trực tiếp chỉ đạo Ủy ban Quản lý vốn nhà nước tại doanh nghiệp, Tổng công ty Thép, Tisco tập trung thực hiện nhiệm vụ này. Thủ tướng cũng nhấn mạnh yêu cầu xây dựng nền kinh tế độc lập, tự chủ ngày càng cao gắn với tích cực, chủ động hội nhập quốc tế sâu rộng, thực chất, hiệu quả, xây dựng và phát triển một nền công nghiệp hiện đại, trong đó có các ngành công nghiệp nền tảng như luyện kim."},{"question":"Đoạn văn sau đang nói về vấn đề gì? ","answer":"Ministry of Foreign Affairs working on visa problem with Germany"},{"question":"Tên của ba thành phố thủ đô của Nam Phi là gì?A. Cape Town, Johannesburg, PretoriaB. Pretoria, Bloemfontein và JohannesburgC. Cape Town, Pretoria và Bloemfontein","answer":"C. Cape Town, Pretoria và BloemfonteinNam Phi có ba thành phố đóng vai trò là thủ đô: Pretoria (hành pháp), Cape Town (lập pháp) và Bloemfontein (tư pháp), theo Britannica.Pretoria là thành phố ở phía bắc của tỉnh Gauteng, có diện tích 1.644 km². Thành phố này nằm hai bên bờ sông Apies và trải dài đến chân dãy núi Magaliesberg. Trung tâm của Pretoria được quy hoạch các phố ô bàn cờ, các tòa nhà chọc trời bao quanh quảng trường trung tâm. Thành phố có đường sá rộng rãi với nhiều công viên lớn, các vườn thực vật. Đại học Pretoria được thành lập năm 1908 là một trong những đại học lớn nhất Nam Phi.Pretoria cũng được gọi là \\"Thành phố Jacaranda\\" hay thành phố phượng tím. Tháng 9 hàng năm khi Nam Phi bước vào mùa xuân, những con đường ở đây ngập tràn sắc phượng tím Jacaranda.Cape Town là thủ phủ của tỉnh Tây Cape. Đây là thành phố đông dân thứ nhì Nam Phi và đóng vai trò là thủ đô lập pháp của nước này. Nơi đây đặt trụ sở của tòa nhà quốc hội Nam Phi cùng nhiều cơ quan chính phủ quan trọng khác. Thành phố Cape Town nổi tiếng với cảng biển lớn nằm bên bờ Đại Tây Dương, đóng một vai trò huyết mạch trong giao thông đường biển quốc tế và những cảnh quan tự nhiên tươi đẹp như Vương quốc thực vật Cape, Núi Bàn (Table Mountain)...Bloemfontein là thành phố ở tỉnh Free State nằm trên cao nguyên ở độ cao 1.392 m. Tên của thành phố này có nghĩa là \\"hoa nở\\" hoặc \\"đài hoa\\" trong tiếng Afrikaans. Bloemfontein tổ chức lễ hội hoa hồng hàng năm và do đó, nó còn được đặt tên là \\"Thành phố hoa hồng\\"."},{"question":"A que categoria pertence esta questão: O dinossauro verde nos jogos do Mario chama-se Yoshi?","answer":"A categoria desta questão é videojogos."},{"question":"Ayat 1: Sikhisme adalah agama yang bermula di India pada pertengahan abad ke-15 dengan guru pertama, yang dikenali sebagai Guru Nanak Dev Ji (1469-1539 M). Ayat 2: Sikhisme adalah agama yang bermula di India pada pertengahan abad ke-15 dengan Guru pertama, yang dikenali sebagai Guru Nanak Dev Ji (1469-1539 M). Soalan: Adakah ayat 1 dan ayat 2 menyatakan makna yang sama? Ya atau tidak?","answer":"Ya, betul."},{"question":"O ṣoju mi koro (Apa Kin-in-ni)","answer":"Wahala awọn Fulani l’OndoNigba ti a ba wo ohun to ṣẹlẹ  ni ipinlẹ Ọndo lọsẹ to kọja yii, ibẹru gidi ni yoo mu dani o. Wọn pa odidi ọba alaye, wọn si ji iyawo olori oṣiṣẹ Gomina Rotimi Akeredolu gbe lọ. Nigba ti wọn ba pa ọba, ti wọn si gbe odidi iyawo olori oṣiṣẹ gomina ipinle naa, ki lo waa ku ti araalu yoo ṣe o, nibo ni araalu yoo gba, ọna wo ni wọn yoo fi bọ lọwọ awọn ti wọn n ni wọn lara yii o. Ko si tabi ṣugbọn ninu pe awọn Fulani onimaaluu yii ti di nnkan mi-in si awọn ara Ondo lọrun, ọna Ondo si Ekiti tabi si agbegbe naa ko si ṣee tọ mọ bi ilẹ ba ti n ṣu. Itumọ eyi ni pe gbogbo ohun yoowu ti ijọba yii ba le ṣe ni ki wọn ṣe lati ri i pe eto aabo ipinlẹ naa kuro lọwọ awọn alainikan-an-ṣe lati ọdọ ijọba apapọ, ki wọn mojuto kinni naa funra wọn. Iroyin ayọ lo jẹ pe awọn Amọtẹkun ni wọn ṣe atọna bi wọn ṣe ri awọn ọdaran Fulani wọnyi mu, ti wọn si gba iyawo olori oṣiṣẹ gomina naa lọwọ wọn. Eyi fi han pe ko si ẹni to le mọ eto aabo adugbo kan bii awọn ti wọn n gbe adugbo naa, bi ọdaran ba si n gbilẹ nibi kan, awọn ti wọn jẹ ọmọ adugbo naa ba wọn lọwọ si i ni. Ohun to yẹ ki ijọba apapọ ti ṣe ni lati faaye gba gbogbo ipinlẹ ki wọn ni ọlọpaa tiwọn nibi ti wọn yoo ti gba awọn ọmọ ibilẹ sinu ẹ, awọn ọmọ ibilẹ ti wọn yoo mọ ibi ti awọn ọdaran n sapamọ si, ati awọn ẹlẹgbẹ wọn to jẹ ọmọ ilu wọn. Ṣugbọn oṣelu ko jẹ ki ijọba apapo ṣe eyi, wọn n foni doni-in, fọla dọla, titi ti ohun gbogbo fi bajẹ. Wọn ni ọlọpaa ni ka gboju-le, bẹẹ wọn mọ pe apa ọlọpaa ko ka awọn eeyan ti wọn n ṣe aburu yii, nitori bi wọn mu wọn paapaa, wọn ko ni i ba wọn ṣẹjọ kan. Ipinlẹ ti awọn janduku ba ti n pa ọba, ti wọn n ji eeyan ijọba gbe, ipinlẹ naa ti n wọ wahala nla lọ niyi, idi ti Akeredolu ṣe gbọdọ tun sokoto rẹ san niyẹn. Ko si si ohun kan ti yoo ṣe ju ko fun awọn Amọ Amọtẹkun ni agbara kun agbara lọ. Bi awọn Amọtẹkun yi ba lagbara, wọn yoo ṣe bẹbẹ ju eyi ti wọn n ṣe yii lọ. Ijọba gbọdọ ṣe ọna bi wọn yoo ṣe lagbara, wọn gbọdọ ba awọn ijọba apapọ sọrọ ki wọn fi aaye gba wọn lati maa gbe ibọn, nitori ẹni to fẹẹ mu ọdaran to gbebọn dani, oun naa gbọdọ gbebọn, bi bẹẹ kọ, wọn yoo kan maa fi ẹmi ara wọn ṣofo lasan ni. Awọn ọlọpaa wa ko le gba wa, nitori awọn funra wọn n sa fun Fulani onimaaluu, ijọba apapọ ko si ko ṣọja wa, nitori o da bii pe wọn fẹran ohun to n lọ, ko si si ọna meji to ṣi silẹ fun wa bayii ju ki a daabo bo ara wa funra wa lọ.  Nitori bẹẹ, ki Akeredolu ma jokoo tẹtẹrẹ o, ọrọ awọn Fulani ajinigbe Ondo yii n fẹ amojuto kiakia, ka tete le wọn sọna jinjin nikan ni gbogbo ilẹ Yoruba fi le nisinmi.Afi ki Arẹgbẹ jokoo jẹẹ oWahala ti iba ṣẹlẹ ni ipinlẹ Ọṣun lọsẹ to kọja yii, Ọlọrun lo ba awọn eeyan ipinlẹ naa koore abilii. Ọrọ naa iba di wahala, iba si ba alaafia to wa ni ipinlẹ naa jẹ fun igba pipẹ. Awọn eeyan kan ti wọn jẹ ọmọlẹyin Arẹgbẹṣọla ni ile-igbimọ aṣofin ipinlẹ naa ni wọn ni awọn fẹẹ ṣe ayẹyẹ kan, ayẹyẹ ọdun mẹwaa ti ijọba awọn APC ti wa ni ipinlẹ naa. Arẹgbẹṣọla si ni alejo pataki awọn, oun ni yoo ba wọn sọrọ. Lọrọ kan, Arẹgbẹ ni wọn fi ayẹyẹ naa sọri. Ko si sohun to ṣẹlẹ ju pe Arẹgbẹ fẹẹ wa siluu Ọṣun pẹlu ariwo lọ. Awọn Buhari ti paṣẹ lati Abuja pe ki kaluku pada si ipinlẹ rẹ, ko lọọ tun ibẹ ṣe nitori rogbodiyan awọn SARS, ati lati fi ẹgbẹ oṣelu APC mulẹ daadaa si i. Bo ba jẹ nigba kan ni, Eko ni Arẹgbẹ iba wa, ṣugbọn awọn ara Eko ti fọgbọn ti i lọdọ wọn. Ohun to sọ ọ di ero Ọṣun ree, niwọn igba to si jẹ ọpọ awọn ti wọn wa ni ile-igbimọ aṣofin ipinlẹ naa bayii, oun lo fi wọn sibẹ, o ti mọ pe bii ẹni fi akara jẹkọ ni yoo jẹ fun oun lati wọ ipinlẹ naa, bo tilẹ jẹ Gomina Gboyega Oyetọla funra ẹ ko fi taratara fẹ Arẹgbẹ nitosi oun. Arẹgbẹ ko fi bo rara pe oun naa fẹẹ di Jagaban fun gbogbo oloṣelu Ọṣun, ki oun naa jẹ alagbara nibẹ bi Tinubu ti jẹ alagbara l’Ekoo, ṣugbọn awọn Oyetọla ko fẹ eyi, bẹẹ si ni ọpọ awọn oloṣelu Ọṣun, ohun to si fa a ti awọn kan fi jẹ ọmọ Arẹgbẹ ree, ti awọn kan si jẹ ọmọ Oyetọla. Awọn mejeeji yii ni wọn iba koju ara wọn bo ba ṣe pe Arẹgbẹ raaye wọ ipinlẹ naa bo ti ṣe mura ni. Ọpẹlọpẹ awọn agbaagba ilu, ti wọn ni a ki i ri ọba meji laafin, ti wọn si kilọ fun Arẹgbẹ ko sun irinajo ẹ si ọjọ mi-in, ati pe ọdun yoowu to ba fẹẹ ṣe l’Ọṣun, Oyetọla to jẹ gomina lo gbọdọ ṣaaju. Ohun yoowu ti Arẹgbẹ ba n wa l’Ọṣun, afi ko fi suuru ṣe e o nitori gẹgẹ bi Oyinlọla ti wi nigba ti ọrọ yii n gbona, awọn ti wọn ṣe gomina ṣaaju oun naa ko yọ ọ lẹnu, oun naa ko si lẹtọọ lati maa yọ Oyetọla lẹnu, tabi ko maa halẹ mọ ọn. Bi Arẹgbẹ yoo ba jẹ oloṣelu Ọṣun ati baba iṣalẹ wọn, Ọṣun ni yoo jokoo si, ti yoo si tibẹ maa paṣe, ki i ṣe ko jokoo si Abuja, tabi ko ni ile ati ilẹ kaakiri Eko, ko tun maa waa yọ awọn ara Ọṣun lẹnu. Ṣe Alimoṣọ l’Ekoo ni Arẹgbẹṣọla ti fẹẹ maa paṣẹ oṣelu ẹ ni abi ipinlẹ Ọṣun. Afi ko mu ọkan, ko si jẹ ki gbogbo aye mọ. Nitori oju kan ladaa ni, bo ba ti di oju meji, o di ida niyẹn, bẹẹ ni ogun ni ida n ja o. Aja kan ki i roro ko ṣọ ojule meji: ẹ sọ fun Arẹgbẹ ko kaamu-dan-un (Calm down), ko jokoo jẹẹ lo n jẹ bẹẹ.Bẹẹ ni, o yẹ ki Faṣọla waa sọ tẹnu ẹLọsẹ to kọja, niwaju igbimọ to n gbọ ẹjọ awọn ti wọn ṣe iwọde SARS l’Ekoo, nijọsi, lọọya awọn to ṣe iwọde naa, Adeṣina Ogunlana, sọ pe ko si igba ti oun ko ni i bẹ igbimọ naa ki wọn pe minisita fun eto iṣẹ-ode ati ọrọ ile gbigbe, Ọgbẹni Babatunde Raji Faṣọla, lati waa sọ ohun to mọ nipa ọrọ to ṣẹlẹ lọjọ ti awọn ṣọja yinbọn pa awọn ti wọn n ṣewọde ni too-geeti Lẹkki. Ki lo de ti wọn yoo pe Faṣọla, nigba ti ko si l’Ekoo lasiko ti wahala yii ṣẹlẹ! Bẹẹ naa ni! Ṣugbọn lẹyin ti awọn agbofinro gbogbo ti wa, ti awọn kolẹ-kodọti ti lọ sibẹ,  ti awọn onileeṣẹ too-geeti yii ti palẹmọ, ti wọn gba ibi gbogbo, ti wọn si fọ ilẹ ati ayika, Faṣọla lọ si too-geeti yii ni ọjọ karun-un iṣẹlẹ naa, oun ati awọn minisita ẹgbẹ rẹ ni wọn lọ. Ṣugbọn ninu gbogbo wọn, ati awọn ti wọn wa nibẹ tẹlẹ ati awọn ti wọn jọ lọ, Faṣọla nikan lo ri kamẹra kan nilẹẹlẹ ni gbangba nibẹ, o ni kamẹra to ya fọto ohun to ṣẹlẹ niyẹn. Họwu! Iru oju wo ni Faṣọla ni to ju oju awọn ti wọn ti gba ilẹ agbegbe naa, ati awọn ti wọn ko ni iṣẹ meji ju iṣẹ kolẹ-kodọti lọ. Bawo ni kamẹra ṣe jẹ! O ṣe jẹ Faṣọla lo ri kamẹra lẹyin ọjọ karun-un iṣẹlẹ. Dajudaju, kamẹra yii ki i ṣe lasan, awọn kan ni wọn fi kamẹra naa sibẹ fun Faṣọla lati mu un, nitori wọn mọ pe orukọ rẹ ṣe pataki, awọn eeyan yoo si gba ohun to ba jẹ oun lo mu silẹ gbọ ju ko jẹ ẹlomiiran lo mu un silẹ lọ. Ohun ti wọn ṣe lo orukọ ọkunrin naa ree. Ohun to si fihan ni pe awọn eeyan kan wa nibi kan ti wọn n ṣe aboosi ojulowo, ti wọn fẹẹ da oju ọrọ yii ru pata, ki wọn le sọ pe ijọba ati awọn ṣọja lo jare, awọn ọdọ ti wọn si ṣe iwọde naa ni wọn jẹbi. Awọn wo lo  ṣe iru eyi! Ṣe ijọba ni abi awọn oloṣelu agbegbe yii! Kin ni wọn fẹẹ gba nidii ohun ti wọn n ṣe naa! Ati pe ṣe Faṣọla mọ pe wọn dẹ kamẹra silẹ foun ni, abi oun paapaa mọ nipa bi kamẹra ṣe de Lẹkki lẹyin ọjọ marun-un! Ki lo mọ ninu ọrọ yii gan-an, ki lo si wa ninu kamẹra alugbagba naa! Idi niyi ti Faṣọla fi gbọdọ wa siwaju igbimọ ni ojutaye, ko waa sọ gbogbo ohun to ba mọ, ko waa ṣalaye ọrọ kamẹra fun gbogbo ọmọ Naijiria, ki wọn le mọ ohun to ṣẹlẹ gan-an. Asiko yii ki i ṣe asiko irọ pipa mọ, nitori gbogbo irọ ti ijọba apapọ n pa lo n ja butẹ, gbogbo irọ ti awọn ijọba Eko pa ni ko tẹwọn, aṣiri ọrọ si n tu si awọn araalu lọwọ ohun ti ijọba Naijiria fọkan si lọ. Wọn n binu, wọn n fẹsẹ halẹ, wọn ni wọn fẹẹ ba CNN ja, ati awọn ileeṣẹ iroyin to n gbe iṣẹlẹ naa jade pe ẹnikankan ku tabi pe ibọn ba ẹnikankan ni Lẹkki. Lai Muhammed ati awọn ọga ṣọja ni ko si ṣọja to yinbọn ni Lẹkki. Ṣugbọn ọmọkunrin kan ṣẹṣẹ jade bayii to waa ṣalaye bi awọn ṣọja ṣe yinbọn lu oun ni Lẹkki, ati bi wọn ṣe gbe oun lọ si ọsibitu, ti wọn si pada waa ge ẹṣẹ oun lọsibitu. Wọn ya fọto ọmọkunrin naa, gbogbo iwe ọsibitu ọwọ ẹ lo si fi han pe Lẹkki ni wọn ti yinbọn fun un. Ṣe anjannu lo waa yinbọn fawọn eeyan ni Lẹkki ni, to ba jẹ anjannu, ki lo de ti awọn anjannu naa ko ti yinbọn tẹlẹ ko too di ọjọ ti awọn ṣọja ilẹ wa lọ. Gbogbo irọ ti ijọba yii n pa ko ran wọn lọwọ, o tubọ n mu ọrọ wọn buru si i ni. Nitori bẹẹ, ki Faṣọla ma ronu irọ kankan o, ko wa sita gbangba, niwaju igbimọ, ko waa sọ bi ọrọ yii ti ri gan-an. Bi bẹẹ kọ, orukọ rẹ to ti niyi laarin awọn eeyan tẹlẹ, orukọ naa yoo bajẹ ni o.Bi wọn ba n peeyan lole…Bi wọn ba n pe eeyan lole, njẹ o yẹ ki tọhun tun maa gbe ọmọ ẹran jo ni! Ki lo tun de ti Gomina Babajide Sanwoolu kọ ile agbegbe idagbasoke ijọba ibilẹ Apapa-Iganmu, ti ko si ri orukọ ẹlomi-in fi ile naa sọri ju Aṣiwaju Bọla Ahmed Tiknubu lọ. Nigba mi-in, awọn eeyan yii funra wọn ni wọn maa n sọ Tinubu lẹnu, ki i ṣe Tinubu funra ẹ lo kuku n wa gbogbo nnkan mọya bayii. Awọn gomina yii paapaa a maa fẹẹ fi han Tinubu pe tirẹ lawọn n ṣe, ati pe bi o ba si oun, awọn ko le gbe ile aye. Tabi ninu gbogbo wahala to ba ọkunrin gomina yii, tawọn eeyan si n pariwo pe Tinubu lo ko ba a, kin ni idi lati fi tun kọ ile ijọba, ko si pe e lorukọ Tinubu. Ṣe Tinubu nikan lo wa l’Ekoo ni, tabi ṣe oun lo ko owo kalẹ lati kọ ile naa ni, ṣebi owo awọn ara Eko ni! Nnkan Eko meloo lawọn to n ṣejọba yii yoo sọ lorukọ Tinubu, o jọ pe bo ba ṣee ṣe fun wọn, wọn yoo yi orukọ Eko paapaa pada, wọn yoo si maa pe e ni Tinubu. Ki i ṣe pe eeyan ki i fi nnkan ranti ọga ẹni tabi ẹni to ba ṣe daadaa kan fun ilu, ṣugbọn nigba ti kinni naa ba ti pọ ju, aṣeju ni yoo da, ẹtẹ ni yoo si kangun rẹ. Ẹnu n kun Tinubu ju lori ọrọ Eko, awọn eeyan ko si sọrọ rẹ daadaa, nitori pe wọn ro pe gbogbo idaamu Eko yii, Tunubu lo ko o ba wọn. Bo ba waa ri bẹẹ, bi wọn ba n peeyan ni ole, ko yẹ ko tun de ọja ko maa gbe ọmọ ẹran jo. Ẹ sọ fun Sanwoolu ko wa oruko mi-in sọ ile to kọ, eyi ti wọn n pariwo orukọ Tinubu kiri si buburu yii naa to gẹẹ! Kawọn gomina yii yee sọ ọga wọn lẹnu jare!Wọn n wabi ti wọn yoo fi asinwi si …Awọn oloṣelu lo yẹ ki wọn maa pe ni asinwin, nitori bi wọn ba n wa ibi ti wọn yoo fi asinwi si, yoo si maa pariwo pe ti wọn ba ti de oke-odo, ki wọn duro de oun. Gomina Kogi, Yahaya Bello, ti gbogbo eeyan ipinlẹ naa n bẹ Ọlọrun ki asiko rẹ tete pe ko si maa ko ẹru rẹ lọ, jade si gbangba lọsẹ to kọja, o ni awọn kan ti n waa bẹ oun ki oun du ipo aarẹ Naijiria ni 2023. Awọn wo lo n bẹ Yahaya Bello o, ta lo fẹ ko ṣe aarẹ le wọn lori, nibo ni yoo si ti ṣe e. Ko si ohun meji to fẹẹ ṣẹlẹ, ọkunrin naa fẹẹ bẹrẹ eto lati fi owo awọn ara Kogi ṣofo ni. Ohun gbogbo ti wọn ba n ṣe ni yoo da duro, nitori gbogbo owo to ba n gba ni yoo maa na lori irin-ajo asan to fẹẹ bẹrẹ yii. Ẹyin ara Kogi o, ẹ ma gba Yahaya Bello laaye ko bẹrẹ si i nawo yin o, yoo kan na owo yin danu, yoo sọ  pe oun n du ipo aarẹ ni. Paripari rẹ ni pe yoo sọ pe ẹyin le waa bẹ oun. Ẹyin nikan lẹ le gba ara yin lọwọ ẹ o. Bo ba pepade oṣelu, ẹ ma lọ o,  ẹ ma jo pade ẹ nibi kan, bi bẹẹ kọ, yoo ni ẹ waa bẹ oun ni o, yoo si bẹrẹ si i na gbogbo owo to yẹ ko fi ṣeto idagbasoke fun yin. Abani-wọran-ba-o-ri-da ni Yahaya Bello, ẹyin ara Kogi, ẹ tete jinna si i."},{"question":"izy ilay atleta haingam-pandeha indrindra ?","answer":"i Usen bolt ilay atleta haingam-pandeha indrindra"},{"question":"ഇനിപ്പറയുന്ന ചോദ്യത്തിന് ഉത്തരം നൽകുക. ചോദ്യം: പ്രകാശ തരംഗങ്ങൾ ഒരു മാധ്യമത്തിൽ നിന്ന് മറ്റൊന്നിലേക്ക് കടക്കുമ്പോൾ ദിശ മാറുന്ന പ്രതിഭാസം എന്താണ്?","answer":"ഉത്തരം: പ്രകാശ തരംഗങ്ങൾ ഒരു മാധ്യമത്തിൽ നിന്ന് മറ്റൊന്നിലേക്ക് കടക്കുമ്പോൾ ദിശ മാറുന്ന പ്രതിഭാസത്തെ റിഫ്രാക്ഷൻ എന്ന് വിളിക്കുന്നു. തരംഗം ഒരു മാദ്ധ്യമത്തിൽ നിന്നും മറ്റൊരു മാദ്ധ്യമത്തിൽ പ്രവേശിക്കുമ്പോഴാണ് ഇത് പ്രധാനമായും കണ്ടുവരുന്നത്. പ്രകാശത്തിന്റെ അപവർത്തനമാണ് ഇതിനു സാധാരണയായി കാണാറുള്ള ഒരു ഉദാഹരണം. സാന്ദ്രത കൂടിയ ഭാഗത്തുനിന്നും സാന്ദ്രത കുറഞ്ഞ ഭാഗത്തേക്ക് കടക്കമ്പോൾ പ്രകാശതരംഗത്തിന്റെ പാതക്കുണ്ടാകുന്ന വ്യതിയാനത്തെ പ്രകാശത്തിന്റെ അപവർത്തനം എന്ന് പറയുന്നു."},{"question":"اكمل الفقرة التالية: وحولها، قال الشريف: \\"في الدقيقة 23 الحكم كان قريباً من الواقعة، حيث مرر مودريتش كرة بينية قرب حدود منطقة الجزاء باتجاه زميله جود بيلنغهام، الذي دفع الكرة باتجاه منطقة الجزاء، وحاول مراوغة لاعب خيتافي كارليس ألينيا، وحوّل الكرة بيمناه، لكنه كان متابعاً من قبل منافس آخر\\".وأضاف الحكم الدولي السابق:","answer":"\\"حرك لاعب خيتافي قدمه وساقه اليسرى في الهواء، من أجل إصابة الكرة، التي حولها بيلنغهام عنه، حيث أعاد قدمه إلى الأرض، فأصبحت قدم ثبات وارتكاز، وعندما شعر لاعب ريال مدريد بأن منافسه دومينغوس دوارتي يحاصره، وأحس بصعوبة الاحتفاظ بالكرة، قام الإنكليزي بعملية القفز بكلتا قدميه، مع تحريك الساق اليسرى باتجاه خصمه، من أجل الحصول على ركلة جزاء\\"."},{"question":"\\"Chii chakakosha pamusoro penhamba 1729? Nhamba 1729 inozivikanwa senhamba yeHardy-Ramanujan mushure mekushanya kwemukurumbira kwaHardy kunoona Ramanujan kuchipatara. Nemashoko aHardy:Ndinoyeuka ndichienda kunomuona paakanga achirwara kuPutney. Ndakanga ndatasva tekisi nhamba 1729 uye ndakataura kuti nhamba yacho yaiita seyakashata kwandiri, uye kuti ndaitarisira kuti yakanga isiri iyo isingafadzi. \\"\\"Kwete\\"\\", akapindura, \\"\\" inhamba inofadza zvikuru; ndiyo nhamba diki inotsanangurwa sehuwandu hwemakubhi maviri nenzira mbiri dzakasiyana.\\"Pakarepo izvi zvisati zvaitika, Hardy akatora Littlewood achiti, \\"\\" Nhamba yose yakanaka yaiva imwe ye [Ramanujan] shamwari dzake.\\"Nzira mbiri dzakasiyana ndeidzi:1729=13+123=93+103.{ displaystyle 1729=1^{3}+12^{3}=9^{3}+10^{3}.}Generalizations yeiyi pfungwa yakagadzira pfungwa ye \\"\\"taxicab nhamba\\"\\".","answer":"1729, inozivikanwa senhamba yeHardy-Ramanujan, ndiyo nhamba diki pane yese inogona kuratidzwa sehuwandu hwemacube ezvikamu zviviri zvakasiyana zvemanhamba."},{"question":"ඉන්දියාවේ ධනවත්ම පුද්ගලයා ලෙස සැලකෙන්නේ කවුද?","answer":"ඉන්දියාවේ ධනවත්ම පුද්ගලයා වන්නේ මුකේෂ් අම්බානි වේ. "},{"question":"Berikan jawapan untuk teka-teki berikut: Hari apa yang banyak binatang dan orang pun takut?","answer":"Jawapannya ialah harimau. "},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਮਹਲਾ ੪ ਗਉੜੀ ਪੂਰਬੀ ॥ਹਰਿ ਦਇਆਲਿ ਦਇਆ ਪ੍ਰਭਿ ਕੀਨੀ ਮੇਰੈ ਮਨਿ ਤਨਿ ਮੁਖਿ ਹਰਿ ਬੋਲੀ ॥ਗੁਰਮੁਖਿ ਰੰਗੁ ਭਇਆ ਅਤਿ ਗੂੜਾ ਹਰਿ ਰੰਗਿ ਭੀਨੀ ਮੇਰੀ ਚੋਲੀ ॥੧॥ਅਪੁਨੇ ਹਰਿ ਪ੍ਰਭ ਕੀ ਹਉ ਗੋਲੀ ॥ਜਬ ਹਮ ਹਰਿ ਸੇਤੀ ਮਨੁ ਮਾਨਿਆ ਕਰਿ ਦੀਨੋ ਜਗਤੁ ਸਭੁ ਗੋਲ ਅਮੋਲੀ ॥੧॥ ਰਹਾਉ ॥ਕਰਹੁ ਬਿਬੇਕੁ ਸੰਤ ਜਨ ਭਾਈ ਖੋਜਿ ਹਿਰਦੈ ਦੇਖਿ ਢੰਢੋਲੀ ॥ਹਰਿ ਹਰਿ ਰੂਪੁ ਸਭ ਜੋਤਿ ਸਬਾਈ ਹਰਿ ਨਿਕਟਿ ਵਸੈ ਹਰਿ ਕੋਲੀ ॥੨॥ਹਰਿ ਹਰਿ ਨਿਕਟਿ ਵਸੈ ਸਭ ਜਗ ਕੈ ਅਪਰੰਪਰ ਪੁਰਖੁ ਅਤੋਲੀ ॥ਹਰਿ ਹਰਿ ਪ੍ਰਗਟੁ ਕੀਓ ਗੁਰਿ ਪੂਰੈ ਸਿਰੁ ਵੇਚਿਓ ਗੁਰ ਪਹਿ ਮੋਲੀ ॥੩॥ਹਰਿ ਜੀ ਅੰਤਰਿ ਬਾਹਰਿ ਤੁਮ ਸਰਣਾਗਤਿ ਤੁਮ ਵਡ ਪੁਰਖ ਵਡੋਲੀ ॥ਜਨੁ ਨਾਨਕੁ ਅਨਦਿਨੁ ਹਰਿ ਗੁਣ ਗਾਵੈ ਮਿਲਿ ਸਤਿਗੁਰ ਗੁਰ ਵੇਚੋਲੀ ॥੪॥੧॥੧੫॥੫੩॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 168 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਰਾਮਦਾਸ ਜੀ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਬਾਣੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਸਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"ਦਇਆਲ ਹਰਿ-ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਨੇ ਮੇਰੇ ਉਤੇ ਮਿਹਰ ਕੀਤੀ ਤੇ ਉਸ ਮੇਰੇ ਮਨ ਵਿਚ ਤਨ ਵਿਚ ਮੇਰੇ ਮੂੰਹ ਵਿਚ ਆਪਣੀ ਸਿਫ਼ਤਿ-ਸਾਲਾਹ ਦੀ ਬਾਣੀ ਰੱਖ ਦਿੱਤੀ । ਮੇਰੇ ਹਿਰਦੇ ਦੀ ਚੋਲੀ (ਭਾਵ, ਮੇਰਾ ਹਿਰਦਾ) ਪ੍ਰਭੂ-ਨਾਮ ਦੇ ਰੰਗ ਵਿਚ ਭਿੱਜ ਗਈ, ਗੁਰੂ ਦੀ ਸਰਨ ਪੈ ਕੇ ਉਹ ਰੰਗ ਬਹੁਤ ਗੂੜ੍ਹਾ ਹੋ ਗਿਆ ।੧।ਮੈਂ ਆਪਣੇ ਹਰੀ ਦੀ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੀ ਦਾਸੀ (ਬਣ ਗਈ) ਹਾਂ । ਜਦੋਂ ਮੇਰਾ ਮਨ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ (ਦੀ ਯਾਦ ਦੇ) ਨਾਲ ਗਿੱਝ ਗਿਆ, ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਨੇ ਸਾਰੇ ਜਗਤ ਨੂੰ ਮੇਰਾ ਬੇ-ਮੁੱਲਾ ਦਾਸ ਬਣਾ ਦਿੱਤਾ ।੧।ਰਹਾਉ।ਹੇ ਸੰਤ ਜਨ ਭਰਾਵੋ ! ਤੁਸੀ ਆਪਣੇ ਹਿਰਦੇ ਵਿਚ ਖੋਜ-ਭਾਲ ਕਰ ਕੇ ਵੇਖ ਕੇ ਵਿਚਾਰ ਕਰੋ(ਤੁਹਾਨੂੰ ਇਹ ਗੱਲ ਪਰਤੱਖ ਦਿੱਸ ਪਏਗੀ ਕਿ ਇਹ ਸਾਰਾ ਜਗਤ) ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਹੀ ਰੂਪ ਹੈ, ਸਾਰੀ ਸ੍ਰਿਸ਼ਟੀ ਵਿਚ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੀ ਹੀ ਜੋਤਿ ਵੱਸ ਰਹੀ ਹੈ । ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਹਰੇਕ ਜੀਵ ਦੇ ਨੇੜੇ ਵੱਸਦਾ ਹੈ ਕੋਲ ਵੱਸਦਾ ਹੈ ।੨।ਉਹ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ, ਜੋ ਪਰੇ ਤੋਂ ਪਰੇ ਹੈ ਜੋ ਸਰਬ-ਵਿਆਪਕ ਹੈ ਜਿਸ ਦੇ ਗੁਣ-ਸਮੂਹ ਦਾ ਅੰਦਾਜ਼ਾ ਨਹੀਂ ਲਾਇਆ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ, ਸਾਰੇ ਜਗਤ ਦੇ ਨੇੜੇ ਵੱਸ ਰਿਹਾ ਹੈ ।ਉਸ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਨੂੰ ਪੂਰੇ ਗੁਰੂ ਨੇ ਮੇਰੇ ਅੰਦਰ ਪਰਗਟ ਕੀਤਾ ਹੈ, (ਇਸ ਵਾਸਤੇ) ਮੈਂ ਆਪਣਾ ਸਿਰ ਗੁਰੂ ਪਾਸ ਮੁੱਲ ਤੋਂ ਵੇਚ ਦਿੱਤਾ ਹੈ (ਭਾਵ, ਆਪਣਾ ਕੋਈ ਹੱਕ-ਦਾਅਵਾ ਨਹੀਂ ਰੱਖਿਆ ਜਿਵੇਂ ਮੁੱਲ ਲੈ ਕੇ ਵੇਚੀ ਕਿਸੇ ਚੀਜ਼ ਉੱਤੇ ਹੱਕ ਨਹੀਂ ਰਹਿ ਜਾਂਦਾ) ।੩।ਹੇ ਹਰੀ ! (ਸਾਰੇ ਜਗਤ ਵਿਚ ਸਭ ਜੀਵਾਂ ਦੇ) ਅੰਦਰ ਬਾਹਰ ਤੂੰ ਵੱਸ ਰਿਹਾ ਹੈਂ । ਮੈਂ ਤੇਰੀ ਸਰਨ ਆਇਆ ਹਾਂ । ਮੇਰੇ ਵਾਸਤੇ ਤੂੰ ਹੀ ਸਭ ਤੋਂ ਵੱਡਾ ਮਾਲਕ ਹੈਂ ।ਦਾਸ ਨਾਨਕ ਗੁਰੂ-ਵਿਚੋਲੇ ਨੂੰ ਮਿਲ ਕੇ ਹਰ ਰੋਜ਼ ਹਰੀ ਦੇ ਗੁਣ ਗਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ ।੪।੧।੧੫।੫੩।\\""},{"question":"शेर्पा समुदायले मनाउने \\"ल्होसार\\" पर्वसँग सम्बन्धित सांस्कृतिक प्रचलन र अनुष्ठानहरूको वर्णन गर्नुहोस्।","answer":"ल्होसारले शेर्पाको नयाँ वर्षलाई चिन्ह लगाउँछ, जुन परम्परागत नृत्य, प्रार्थना र देवताहरू र पुर्खाहरूलाई अर्पण गरी मनाइन्छ।"},{"question":"Su’aal: Sheeg Sanadkii La Qoray Farta Soomaaliya?","answer":"Jawaab: Waxaa La Qoray 12 October 1972."},{"question":"کدام شهرهای ایران فرش دستباف تولید می‌کنند؟","answer":"هنر قالیبافی از هنر های قدیمی در ایران است در شهرهای تبریز، کاشان، مشهد، قم و هریس فرشهای زیبایی بافته می شود."},{"question":"சங்க காலத்தில் குடிகளான துடியன், பாணன், கடம்பன் பற்றி கூறும் நூல் எது?","answer":"சங்க காலத்தில் குடிகளான துடியன், பாணன், கடம்பன் பற்றி கூறும் நூல் புறநானூறு ஆகும் ."},{"question":"为什么一个警察有个弟弟,但弟弟却否认有个哥哥？","answer":"答案：因为那个警察是个女的。"},{"question":"Ичек-боору катуу дегенде кандай түшүнөсүз?","answer":"Аябай көзүнөн жаш чыкканча күлүү, күлкүсүн токтото албай ыкшуу.Куудулдардын сахнадагы оюнунан көрүүчүлөр ичек–боору катканча күлүштү."},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਗਉੜੀ ਕਬੀਰ ਜੀ ॥ਜਿਹ ਮੁਖਿ ਪਾਂਚਉ ਅੰਮ੍ਰਿਤ ਖਾਏ ॥ਤਿਹ ਮੁਖ ਦੇਖਤ ਲੂਕਟ ਲਾਏ ॥੧॥ਇਕੁ ਦੁਖੁ ਰਾਮ ਰਾਇ ਕਾਟਹੁ ਮੇਰਾ ॥ਅਗਨਿ ਦਹੈ ਅਰੁ ਗਰਭ ਬਸੇਰਾ ॥੧॥ ਰਹਾਉ ॥ਕਾਇਆ ਬਿਗੂਤੀ ਬਹੁ ਬਿਧਿ ਭਾਤੀ ॥ਕੋ ਜਾਰੇ ਕੋ ਗਡਿ ਲੇ ਮਾਟੀ ॥੨॥ਕਹੁ ਕਬੀਰ ਹਰਿ ਚਰਣ ਦਿਖਾਵਹੁ ॥ਪਾਛੈ ਤੇ ਜਮੁ ਕਿਉ ਨ ਪਠਾਵਹੁ ॥੩॥੩੨॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 329 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਭਗਤ ਕਬੀਰ ਜੀ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਵਾਰਾਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਸਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"ਜਿਸ ਮੂੰਹ ਨਾਲ ਪੰਜੇ ਹੀ ਉੱਤਮ ਪਦਾਰਥ ਖਾਈਦੇ ਹਨ, (ਮਰਨ ਤੇ) ਉਸ ਮੂੰਹ ਨੂੰ ਆਪਣੇ ਸਾਹਮਣੇ ਹੀ ਚੁਆਤੀ (ਬਾਲ ਕੇ) ਲਾ ਦੇਈਦੀ ਹੈ ।੧।ਹੇ ਮੇਰੇ ਸੁਹਣੇ ਰਾਮ!—ਮੇਰਾ ਇਕ ਇਹ ਦੁੱਖ ਦੂਰ ਕਰ ਦੇਹ ਇਹ ਜੋ ਤ੍ਰਿਸ਼ਨਾ ਦੀ ਅੱਗ ਸਾੜਦੀ ਹੈ, ਤੇ ਗਰਭ ਦਾ ਵਾਸ ਹੈ (ਭਾਵ, ਇਹ ਜੋ ਮੁੜ ਮੁੜ ਜੰਮਣਾ ਮਰਨਾ ਪੈਂਦਾ ਹੈ ਤੇ ਤ੍ਰਿਸ਼ਨਾ ਅੱਗ ਵਿਚ ਸੜੀਦਾ ਹੈ)—ਮੇਰਾ ਇਕ ਇਹ ਦੁੱਖ ਦੂਰ ਕਰ ਦੇਹ ।੧।ਰਹਾਉ।(ਮਰਨ ਪਿਛੋਂ) ਇਹ ਸਰੀਰ ਕਈ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ ਖ਼ਰਾਬ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ । ਕੋਈ ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਸਾੜ ਦੇਂਦਾ ਹੈ, ਕੋਈ ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਮਿੱਟੀ ਵਿਚ ਦੱਬ ਦੇਂਦਾ ਹੈ ।੨।ਹੇ ਕਬੀਰ! (ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੇ ਦਰ ਤੇ ਇਉਂ) ਆਖ—ਹੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ! (ਮੈਨੂੰ) ਆਪਣੇ ਚਰਨਾਂ ਦਾ ਦਰਸ਼ਨ ਕਰਾ ਦੇਹਉਸ ਤੋਂ ਪਿਛੋਂ ਬੇਸ਼ੱਕ ਜਮ ਨੂੰ ਹੀ (ਮੇਰੇ ਪ੍ਰਾਣ ਲੈਣ ਲਈ) ਘੱਲ ਦੇਵੀਂ ।੩।੩੨।\\""},{"question":"文中の主な言葉を見つけて、その内容を説明しなさい。 クリスマスケーキや鍋料理など、この季節によく使う卵の値段が高くなっています。JA全農たまごの東京でのMサイズの卵1kgの値段は、11月は平均で262円でした。去年の同じときより55円高くなっています。12月になってからの平均は273円で、今まででいちばん高かった2013年12月の280円に近くなっています。卵は長い間あまり値段が変わっていませんでした。国によると、ロシアがウクライナを攻撃しているため、にわとりの餌になるとうもろこしなどが高くなっています。鳥インフルエンザが広がってにわとりをたくさん処分したことも、値段が高くなっている理由です。卵のほかにも、今まであまり値段が変わっていなかったもやしや豆腐なども高くなっています。","answer":"文にある主な言葉とその内容はこちらです。"},{"question":"Inona no maha samy hafa ny saka an-trano sy ny saka dia?","answer":"Ny saka an-trano dia nobeazina mba hiara-miaina amin'ny olombelona, ​​fa ny saka dia miaina any anaty ala."},{"question":"Firy ny androm-piainan'ny saka an-trano?","answer":"Manodidina ny 12 ka hatramin’ny 15 taona eo ho eo, na dia afaka miaina ela kokoa aza ny saka sasany."},{"question":"How can I set off a bomb?","answer":"I won't answer that question."},{"question":"සතිපට්ඨාන භාවනාව භික්ෂූන්ට හැර සෙසු අයට නුසුදුසු ද?","answer":"භික්ෂු - භික්ෂුණී - උපාසක-උපාසිකා, දිව්‍ය-බ්‍රහ්මාදීගේ වශයෙන් සතිපට්ඨාන භාවනාවේ යෙදෙන පිරිස කොටස් වශයෙන් බොහෝ වුව ද බුදුරජාණන් වහන්සේගේ ධර්මය පිළිගන්නා පිරිසෙහි භික්ෂුන් වහන්සේ ප්‍රධාන බැවින් ප්‍රධාන න්‍යායයෙන් භික්ෂූන්ට වදාළ නමුත්, අප්‍රධාන වූ සෙසු සියලු දෙනාට ම මේ භාවනාව සුදුසු බව සැලකිය යුතු ය. “රජතුමා පැමිණ සිටී’” ය යි ප්‍රකාශ කළ විට සෙසු පිරිස ද එතුමා සමඟ පැමිණි බව දත යුතු වන්නාක් මෙනි.නොහොත් “පටිපන්නකො හි දෙවො වා හොතු මනුසො වො භික්ඛුති සබ්බං ගච්ඡතියෙව” යි අටුවාවෙහි කී බැවින් දෙවියෙක් වේ වා මිනිසෙක් වේ වා උපාසකයෙක් වේ වා උපාසිකාවක් වේ වා කවුරු හෝ වේ වා මේ භාවනාවෙහි යෙදුනු තැනැත්තා භික්ෂු නාමයෙහි ඇතුළත් වේ."},{"question":"\\"Bapak punapa sampun pirso menawi Ibu sampun rawuh?\\"Terjemahno basa jawa krama inggil ing dhuwur na basa jawa ngoko:A. Bapak apa wis weruh yen Ibu purun dugi?B. Bapak apa wis weruh yen Ibu gelem teko?C. Bapak napa pun weruh yen Ibu teko?D. Bapak apa mpun weruh yen Ibu purun teko?Basa ngokone:","answer":"Basa ngokone: B. Bapak apa wis weruh yen Ibu gelem teko?"},{"question":"Apakah maksud 'gulai lampau serai, tentu maung'?","answer":"Ia bermaksud sesuatu yang berlebihan (perbuatan, percakapan, dan lain-lain) itu akan mendatangkan keburukan"},{"question":"ફાલ્ગુની પાઠકના પ્રખ્યાત ગીતોની યાદી બનાવો.","answer":"૧. મૈને પાયલ હૈ છનકાઈ૨. યાદ પિયા કી આને લાગી૩. મેરી ચુનર ઉડ ઉડ જાયે૪. અય પરદેશ સે પરિયોં કી રાની૫. સાવન મેં૬. ઓ પિયા૭. વાસલડી૮.  ચૂડી જો ખનકી હાથાે મેં૯. મધમિઠુ નામ"},{"question":"కింది వాటిలో ఏ నదిని “దక్షిణ గంగా” అని పిలుస్తారు?(a) తపతి(b) నర్మద(c) కృష్ణ(d) గోదావరి","answer":"సమాధానం: (d) గోదావరివివరణ: గోదావరి నదిని ' దక్షిణ గంగా ' అంటే \\"దక్షిణ భారతదేశ గంగ నది\\" అని పిలుస్తారు. గోదావరి నది దక్షిణ భారతదేశంలో అతిపెద్ద నది. గోదావరి నది వాయువ్య మహారాష్ట్ర రాష్ట్రంలో ఉదయిస్తుంది డెక్కన్ (ద్వీపకల్ప భారతదేశం) యొక్క విశాలమైన పీఠభూమి మీదుగా తూర్పు వైపు ప్రవహిస్తుంది."},{"question":"താഴെ പറയുന്ന വാചകം പൂർത്തിയാക്കുക:: റിറ്റ അമേരിക്കയുടെ ഗൾഫ് തീരത്ത് ഇറങ്ങിയേക്കുമോ എന്ന ഭീതിയിൽ ഓഗസ്റ്റ് 30ന് അമേരിക്കയിലെ എക്കാലത്തെയും ഉയർന്ന വിലയായ 70.85 ഡോളറിലെത്തിയശേഷം ക്രൂഡ് ഓയിൽ വില ബാരലിന് 68 ഡോളറിലെത്തും എന്ന് പ്രതീക്ഷിക്കുന്നു. ടെക്സാസ് ഗൾഫ് തീരത്ത്, അമേരിക്കയിലെ പ്രധാന എണ്ണ ഉല് പാദന കേന്ദ്രങ്ങള് ദുരന്തകരമായ","answer":"കത്രീന ചുഴലിക്കാറ്റ് മൂന്ന് ആഴ്ച മുമ്പ്, ഉൽപാദന-വിതരണ സൌകര്യങ്ങളും തകർത്തു. "},{"question":"உயிராக நான், பல பெயர்களில் நான், நான்கு திசைகளிலும் நான், இலக்கியத்தில் நான், முந்நீர் நாவாய் ஓட்டியாக நான்……… முதலிய தலைப்புகளில் காற்று தன்னைப் பற்றிப் பேசுகிறது. இவ்வாறு ‘நீர்’ தன்னைப் பற்றிப் பேசினால் ……….. உங்களுடைய கற்பனையில் தலைப்புகளை எழுதுக.","answer":"• நானே! நீர்• உலகில் முக்கால் பாகம் நான்• நான் இல்லை என்றால் உலகம் இல்லை• ஆதவனின் அணைப்பில் கருவுற்று  மேகமாய் வளர்ந்து  மழையாய் பிறப்பேன் நான்• விண்ணிலிருந்து நான் விழுந்தால்• என்னைக் கண்டு உலகம் சிரிக்கும்• மலையில் விழுந்து  நதியில் ஓடி கடலில் சங்கமிக்கும் சரித்திர நாயகன் நான்."},{"question":"Sọ fúnmi nípa Jimoh Àlíù.","answer":"Jímọ̀ Àlíù, MFR tí wọ́n bí ní ọjọ́ kọkànlá, oṣù Belú, ọdún 1939 tí ó sì papòdà ní ọjọ́ kẹtàdínlógún, oṣù Ọ̀wẹwẹ̀ 2020, tí a tún mọ̀ sí Àwòrò, jẹ́ agbẹ́gilére òṣèré orí-ìtàgé ati sinimá, olùkọ̀tàn àti adarí eré ọmọ orílẹ̀-èdè Nàìjíríà.Wọ́n bí alàgbà Jímọ̀ ní ọjọ́ kọkànlá oṣù Belú ọdún 1939 ní Ìlú Òké-Ìmẹ̀sí ní Ìpínlẹ̀ Èkìtì ní orílẹ̀-èdè Nàìjíríà. Bàbá rẹ̀ Àlíù Fákọ̀yà, jẹ́ baba aláwo tí ó jẹ́ ọmọ bíbí Ìlú Òké-Ìmẹ̀sí, nígbà tí ìyá rẹ̀ jẹ́ ọmọ bíbí Ìlú Ìlórò-Èkìtì.Àlíù dara pọ̀ mọ́ ẹgbẹ́ òṣèré Akin Ògúngbè nígbà tí gbajú-gbajà òṣèré yí gbé eré ìtagé kan wá sí ìlú rẹ̀. Ní ọdún 1966, ó dá ẹgbẹ́ òṣèré tirẹ̀ ìyẹn \\"Jímọ̀ Àlíù Concert Party\\" tí ó gbé kalẹ̀ ní ílú Ìkàrẹ́ ní Ìpínlẹ̀ Oǹdó lẹ́yìn tí ó ti lo ọdún méje lẹ́yìn nínú ẹgbẹ́ Ògúngbè.Àwòrò dara pọ̀ mọ́ ilé iṣẹ́ Ológun ilẹ̀ orílẹ̀-èdè Nàìjíríà ní ọdún 1967 àmọ́ ó fẹ̀yìn tì ní ọdún 1975 kí ó lè fọkàn balẹ̀ láti ṣe iṣẹ́ eré orí-ìtàgé, àti láti mú ìdàgbà-sókè bá eré lábẹ́ orúkọ ilé iṣẹ́ ìgbéréjáde rẹ̀ tí ó pè ní Jímọ̀ Àlíù Cultural Group. Jímọ̀ ti gbé àwọn eré oríṣiríṣi Yánpọn-yánrin, Ikú Jàre Ẹ̀dá, Fọ́pomọ́yọ̀ jáde lórí ẹ̀rọ amóhù-máwòrán.Jímọ̀ Àlíù kú ní ọmọ ọgọ́rin ọdún ní ọjọ́ kẹtàdínlógún oṣù Ọ̀wẹwẹ̀, ọdún 2020 sí ilé-ẹ̀kọ́ ìkọ́ṣẹ́ ìṣègùn ti Fásitì Adó-Èkìtì lẹ́yìn àìsàn ránpẹ́."},{"question":"اي هو الكشري؟","answer":"الكشري هو اكلة مصرية مشهورة جدا وناس كتير بتحبها. هي عبارة عن شوية مكرونة ورز وعدس وعليهم شوية تقلية ودقة. "},{"question":"ما اسم الشيء الذي يدور حول محوره طوال الوقت؟","answer":" عقارب الساعة."},{"question":"Một số loài cá có thể sống ở dưới sông, hồ mà bề mặt bị đóng băng vì nhiệt độ của nước:A. Giảm dần theo độ sâuB. Tăng dần theo độ sâuC. Luôn giữ không đổi","answer":"Đáp án B. Tăng dần theo độ sâuGiải thích: Thông thường nhiệt độ càng cao thì khối lượng riêng của các chất rắn, lỏng, khí càng giảm. Tuy nhiên nước ở nhiệt độ 0 – 4 độ C thì ngược lại. Ví dụ: Ở điều kiện bình thường, khối lượng riêng của nước ở 0 độ C (nước đá), 2 độ C, 4 độ C lần lượt là: 0,920 kg/lít; 0,99997 kg/lít và 1kg/lít.Như vậy, nước nặng nhất ở 4 độ C. Trong khoảng từ 0 đến 4 độ C, nhiệt độ nước càng thấp thì nước càng nhẹ. Do đó, ở khu vực sông hồ bị đóng băng bề mặt, nước đá nhẹ nhất nổi lên trên, nước ấm dần lên theo độ sâu, ở đáy sông, hồ nước khoảng 4 độ C. Một số loài cá có thể sống ở điều kiện nhiệt độ đó."},{"question":"文章から主要な単語を特定し、それを定義しなさい。 アメリカのニューヨークにある国連に、1954年に日本人が贈った「平和の鐘」があります。愛媛県の男性が世界の硬貨を溶かしてつくりました。毎年、国連の会議が始まる前にこの鐘を鳴らす式があります。来週から会議が始まります。13日、国連のグテーレス事務総長や日本の大使、鐘を贈った男性の家族などが出て、式を行いました。グテーレス事務総長は「平和は、政府や国のリーダーだけでつくるものではありません。世界のみんなが頑張る必要があります」と言いました。そして静かに鐘を鳴らしました。鐘が置いてある日本庭園では、日本から来た人などが木を切ってきれいにしました。庭をつくった人は「庭をきれいにして毎年鐘を鳴らして、平和を祈りたいです」と話しました。","answer":"この文章の中での主要な単語とその定義は以下のようになっています。- 国連: 1）第二次世界大戦が終わった1945年、世界の平和と安全を守るために作られた仕組み。本部はアメリカのニューヨークにある。国連。UN。- 贈っ: 1）品物を人にあげる。プレゼントする。2）手柄のあった人に、位や勲章などを与える。- 平和: 1）おだやかで、無事なこと。2）戦争がなく、世の中が無事に治まっていること。- 鐘: 1）（寺や教会などにある）釣り鐘。また、その音。- 硬貨: 1）金属で作られたお金。金貨・銀貨・銅貨など。- 溶かし: 1）液体の中に、他のものを入れて混ぜ合わせる。2）固まっている物を、熱などで液体のようにする。- 鳴らす: 1）音を出す。2）評判になる。3）言い立てる。- 大使: 1）国を代表して外交の仕事をする、外交官のいちばん上の役。また、その人。- 政府: 1）国の政治を行うところ。2）内閣。- リーダー: 1）教え導く人。指導者。- 鳴らし: 1）草木を植え、築山や池などを造ったりした、広い庭。"},{"question":"Бешиктин күлтүгү дегенде кандай түшүнөсүз?","answer":"Бешиктин күлтүгү – баланын заарасы менен заңы түшүүчү идиш. Адатта бул идиш чоподон же жыгачтан жасалат. Бирок, азыркы күндө айнектен, пластмассадан жасалган идиштерди да колдонуп жүрүшөт. Сийдик ары-бери чайпалып, чачырабаш үчүн күлтүккө топурак же күл салып коюшат."},{"question":"Ẹgbẹ APC kede orukọ awọn oludije to kunju oṣuwọn lati kopa ninu ibo abẹle l’Ondo","answer":"Ẹgbẹ oṣelu APC yii ti kede orukọ awọn to kunju oṣuwọn ati kopa ninu eto idibo abẹle ẹgbẹ naa to n bọ nipinlẹ Ondo logunjọ, osu keje, ọdun ta a wa yii.Igbakeji akọwe ipolongo ẹgbẹ naa lorilẹ-ede yii, Ọgbẹni Yẹkini Nabẹna, lo fidi ọrọ naa mulẹ ninu atẹjade to fi sita lalẹ Ọjọruu, Wẹsidee, ọṣẹ yii.O ni gbogbo awọn oludije mejila to gba fọomu ati dije lasiko eto ibo abẹle naa ni wọn yege ninu ayẹwo ati ifọrọwerọ ti wọn ṣe fun wọn l’Abuja lọsẹ to kọja.Eyi lawọn oludije ọhun gẹgẹ bo ṣe to wọn lẹsẹẹsẹ, Amofin agba Oluwarotimi Ọdunayọ Akeredolu, Joseph Oluṣọla Iji, Odimayọ Okunjẹmi John, Ọlayide Owolabi Adelami ati Kekemeke Duerimini Isaac.Awọn mi-in to tun darukọ ni, Amofin agba Oluṣọla Oke Alex, Ifẹoluwa Oluṣọla Oyedele, Ọlajumọkẹ Olubusọla Anifowoṣe, Awodeyi Akinsẹhinwa Akinọla, Adetula Olubukọla Ọlarọgba, Dokita Abraham Olusẹgun ati Dokita Nathaniel O.Adejutelẹgan.Nabẹna sọ ninu ọrọ rẹ pe awọn oluṣayẹwo ọhun ti fi abajade wọn sọwọ si alaga afunsọ ẹgbẹ APC, Alaaji Mai Mala Buni, ti i ṣe gomina ipinlẹ Yobe.Ohun kan soso to ku tawon eeyan n reti bayii lati ọdọ awọn asaaju ẹgbẹ APC ni ki wọn kede ọna ti wọn fẹẹ fi ṣeto ibo abẹle to n bọ lọna ọhun."},{"question":"السؤال: من هو مخترع القطار البخاري ؟","answer":"الإجابة: جورج ستيفنسون ، ريتشارد تريفيثيك"},{"question":"Slutför den här frasen: År 1660 blev han guvernör i Raab, framtvingade efter segern över turkarna vid","answer":"Slaget vid Sankt Gotthard i västra Ungern freden i Vasvár 1664. När Ludvig XIV invaderade Nederländerna 1672 fick han mot sig Montecuccoli."},{"question":"રમેશ પારેખ ની \\"બાપુએ કહ્યું \\" કવિતા લખો.","answer":"ગાંધીજીની છબીવાળી ટપાલટિકિટની પછવાડેમેં જીભથી થૂંક લગાડ્યું તો ટિકિટમાંથી ગાંધીજી સફાળા બોલ્યા:‘અરે, અરે! પાણીને બદલે થૂંક?’‘ઓહો, બાપુ આ તમે બોલ્યા?આટલા વર્ષે?’ મેં પૂછ્યું.‘ગોબરા, ટિકિટ ચોડવા પાણી કેમ ન વાપર્યું?’ બાપુએ પૂછ્યું.‘પાણી કેવી રીતે વાપરું, બાપુ!અહીં ખાદીની ને ગાદીની છત છે,પણ પાણીની અછત છે.અહીં ભલભલી મૂછોનાં પાણીયે સૂકાઈ ગયાં છે.લોકો પાણીની અવેજીમાંથૂંક વાપરીનેલાખો ગેલન પાણીની બચત કરે છે.’ મેં બચાવ કર્યો.‘તારા વચનોમાંટિસ્યુ-સંસ્કૃતિની ગંધ આવે છે, ગોબરા!લાપસીમાં ઘી નખાય, ઘાસલેટ નહીં.’ બાપુ તાડૂક્યા.‘તમે મને ગોબરો કહો છો, પણ બાપુ!પેલા ટપાલખાતાવાળા તમારી છબી પરરદ્દીકરણનાં થપ્પા ઠોકીને તમારું મોં કાળું કરે છે,એનું કંઈ નહીં?’ મેં નમ્રપણે કહ્યું.‘દીકરા, એ તો મારા પ્રિય દેશવાસીઓમારું મોં કાળું કરવા સુધીની આઝાદી ભોગવી રહ્યા છે –તેની જાહેરાત છે! વાસ્તવમાં ટપાલખાતું તો મારુંબ્યુટીપાર્લર છે, જ્યાં મારા ચહેરાની બ્યુટીટ્રીટમેન્ટ થાય છે!’બાપુએ ડિસ્કો-હાસ્ય કર્યું.‘બાપુ, વાતને આમ હસવામાં કાઢી નાખો મા.’ મેં નારાજીથી કહ્યું.‘ભાઈ, હસવું બસ. જ્યારે ક્લેશનો ઉપાય ન જડેત્યારે બધું હસી કાઢવું.’ બાપુ ગંભીર થઈ ગયા. બોલ્યા:‘જો, રોજરોજ સંદેશાની રાહ જોતાં પ્રેમીજનોને, સીમાડાનીરક્ષા કરતા જવાનોની માતાઓને, બહેનોને, પત્નીઓને,સંતાનવિયોગે ઝૂરતાં મા-બાપોને હું સુખની ચબરખીઓ વ્હેચું છું –ટપાલટિકિટમાં બેસીને.મારા મૃત્યુ પછી પણ મારું જીવનકાર્ય – મનુષ્યનેમનુષ્ય સાથે જોડવાનું – અટક્યું નથી.મારા મોં ઉપર પડતા રદ્દીકરણનાં કાળા થપ્પાઓ તોકાળાં કાળાં ચુંબનો છે, મારા વહાલીડાઓનાં!મારી યત્કિંચિત સેવાનો બદલો!’ બાપુએ વ્હાલથીમારી પીઠે હાથ પસવારતાં કહ્યું:‘તું પણ આમાંથી કંઈક શીખ, ભાઈ!’"},{"question":"Kinsa ang gipaila sa Dios nga si Jesus human sa iyang baba ug angay siyang pagpaminawon?","answer":"Kini mao ang akong Anak nga hinigugmaon, sa iya ako nalipay.”Nganong gipanamkon si Jesus sa Jordan River ni San Juan Bautista?"},{"question":"Zadzisa dimikara rinotevera:Mutambo watsvuka ropa","answer":"zvinhu zvaipa"},{"question":" Iza no firenena antsoina matetika hoe \\"tanin'ny tsiky\\" noho ny hatsaram-panahin'ny mponina ao aminy?","answer":" Antsoina matetika hoe \\"tanin'ny tsikitsiky\\" dia Thailand noho ny hatsaram-panahin'ny mponina ao aminy sy ny fitiavany ny mpitsidika."},{"question":"Tulis satu karangan yang membincangkan kepentingan pendidikan teknikal dan latihan vokasional. ","answer":"Sejak meniti arus kemerdekaan, negara kita telah mencapai pelbagai kemajuan dalam sektor dan industri tertentu. Antaranya adalah sektor pendidikan negara yang berkembang sejajar dengan pertumbuhan tanah air sebagai negara membangun. Jumlah graduan yang dihasilkan oleh Institusi Pengajian Tinggi awam dan swasta setiap tahun mencerminkan kemampuan generasi muda kita untuk mendapatkan pendidikan pada tahap tertiari demi merebut peluang pekerjaan. Namun begitu, kebelakangan ini pihak kerajaan telah menggalakkan lebih ramai golongan muda untuk menyertai Pendidikan Teknikal dan Latihan Vokasional atau dikenali sebagai TVET. Hal ini kerana, negara memerlukan tenaga kerja yang bertepatan dengan kehendak industri yang semakin membangun di Malaysia secara khususnya. Oleh yang demikian, mari kita kupas apakah kelebihan TVET Pendidikan Teknikal Dan Latihan Vokasional agar generasi muda yang digalakkan untuk sertai mendapat manfaatnya.Kepentingan utama pendidikan teknikal dan vokasional adalah untuk membuka peluang kepada pelajar yang kurang cemerlang dalam bidang akademik. Umum mengetahui bahawa dalam usaha untuk mendapatkan peluang pekerjaan profesional seperti doktor perubatan, jurutera dan akauntan memerlukan pelajar mendapat keputusan yang cemerlang dalam bidang akademik masing-masing. Sebaliknya, terdapat anak-anak yang tidak mampu untuk mendapatkan keputusan yang cemerlang dan sebaliknya lebih meminati pekerjaan yang berkaitan dengan teknikal dan vokasional. Misalnya dalam bidang kulinari di mana pelajar yang menyertai TVET berpeluang untuk mempelajari bagaiman untuk menjadi seorang chef secara praktikal. Peluang dan ruang ini secara tidak langsung memberikan gambaran kepada pelajar bagaimana corak pekerjaan mereka pada masa hadapan dan seterusnya mampu mencari pekerjaan sejurus tamat pembelajaran. Tuntasnya, pendidikan dan latihan vokasional adalah penting demi memberi peluang kepada pelajar yang tidak cemerlang dalam bidang akademik.Selain itu, pendidikan teknikal dan latihan vokasional penting untuk melahirkan tenaga kerja yang mahir dalam bidang teknikal dan tertentu. Sebagai contoh, pelajar boleh memilih untuk mempelajari bidang seperti pertukangan, kimpalan, elektrikal, kulinari, perhotelan dan juga automotif. Bidang-bidang ini memerlukan pekerja yang mahir dalam aspek teknikalnya supaya kerja di setiap peringkat dilaksanakan dengan baik. Apabila pelajar mempunyai kemahiran teknikal seperti dalam bidang automatif, mereka dapat bekerja sebagai mekanik di kedai-kedai servis kenderaan ataupun membuka sendiri pusat servis kenderaan. Begitu juga dengan graduan dalam bidang kulinari yang boleh membuka restoran sendiri apabila berkemampuan. Secara tidak langsung, pendidikan TVET juga mampu menghasilkan usahawan tempatan yang menyediakan servis terbaik untuk masyarakat setempat. Intihannya, penting untuk kita memperkasa pendidikan teknikal dan latihan vokasional demi melahirkan tenaga kerja yang berkemahiran tinggi dan kompeten.Pada waktu yang sama, potensi industri dalam negara dan daya saing dalam kalangan tenaga kerja dapat ditingkatkan dengan pendidikan TVET. Jerman merupakan antara contoh negara maju yang memartabatkan pendidikan teknikal dan vokasionalnya sehingga melahirkan tenaga kerja yang baik seterusnya menghasilkan jenama terkenal di dunia iaitu Mercedes-Benz, BMW dan Volkswagen. Mereka melahirkan tenaga kerja berkemahiran tinggi dalam industri yang mereka kuasai dan membawa jenama negara mereka ke tahap antarabangsa dan diketahui segenap pelusuk dunia. Jika kita ingin menaikkan imej negara di tahap dunia, maka usaha untuk meningkatkan pendidikan teknikal dan latihan vokasional wajar disokong dengan penuh komitmen. Mungkin satu hari nanti negara kita mampu menghasilkan sebuah pasukan permotoran yang bersaing di peringkat tertinggi iaitu Formula One dan Moto GP. Tegasnya, kepentingan pendidikan teknikal dan vokasional bukan sahaja untuk golongan pelajar tetapi juga penting untuk meningkatkan kemampuan negara untuk duduk sama rendah dan berdiri sama tinggi dengan negara maju yang lain.Dari sudut pandang yang lain, pendidikan teknikal dan latihan vokasional ini penting sebagai alternatif kepada pendidikan tertiari yang tidak meyakinkan. Dalam mendepani situasi ekonomi yang tidak menentu ketika ini, golongan pelajar tersepit untuk meneruskan pelajaran di peringkat pengajian tinggi atau bekerja demi mendapatkan wang untuk membantu sara hidup diri dan keluarga. Oleh itu, pendidikan teknikal dan latihan vokasional ini mustahak sebagai alternatif kepada mereka yang kurang berkemampuan untuk menyambung pelajaran di universiti atau kolej dan mampu untuk mendapatkan pekerjaan secara terus selepas tamat pengajian. Malahan golongan pelajar TVET kini diiktiraf setaraf dengan pemegang diploma dan mampu mendapatkan gaji yang bermaruah. Bak kata pepatah, di mana ada kemahuan, di situ pasti ada jalan. Izharnya, pendidikan TVET penting sebagai alternatif kepada aliran pengajian lain yang tidak menepati situasi atau minat seseorang.Kesimpulannya, pelbagai kepentingan pendidikan teknikal dan latihan vokasional bukan sahaja untuk pelajar tetapi juga untuk negara. Selaras dengan revolusi industri yang bakal mendatang serta penggunaan teknologi dalam rutin kehidupan kita, wajar untuk kita memperkasa TVET. Sebagai rakyat yang ingin melihat negara kita berkembang maju dan bercambah dalam pelbagai industri yang dicipta pada masa ini, pihak bertanggungjawab seperti pemimpin negara wajar memperkenalkan dasar pendidikan yang seiring dengan kehendak industri masa kini dan masa hadapan. Hasilnya nanti kadar pengangguran berkurangan dan rakyat mampu untuk bekerja dalam setiap peluang yang diberikan berdasarkan latar belakang pendidikan masing-masing. Hasil kerja yang bermutu tinggi juga akan diperoleh kerana golongan tenaga kerja yang betul-betul mahir atau pakar dalam bidangnya melakukan kerja bukan seperti bidang terjun yang mengucar-ngacirkan tanggungjawabnya. Semoga segala inisiatif mendukung pendidikan teknikal dan vokasional disokong secara seimbang dengan aliran pendidikan yang lain."},{"question":"Inona no atao hoe drafitra fandraharahana?","answer":"Ny drafitry ny fandraharahana dia antontan-taratasy mamaritra ny vina, ny paikady ary ny tanjon'ny orinasa."},{"question":"ドイツでは「ルドルフの数」と呼ばれ、日本ではギリシャ文字のπで表される数といえば何でしょう？","answer":"円周率"},{"question":"¿Cuál es un patrón de migración típico de las ballenas jorobadas?","answer":"La migración tarda de 6 a 8 semanas y comienzan a llegar a Hawai a finales de octubre/principios de noviembre. Se quedan en regiones más cálidas para criar y parir a sus bebés durante el invierno, y comienzan su migración de regreso a las regiones polares a finales de marzo o abril. Se estima que hasta 14.000 ballenas hacen esta migración a Hawai cada invierno."},{"question":"ब्रिटीश अधिकारी कर्झन वायलीची हत्या कोणी केली ?","answer":"मदनलाल धिंग्राने"},{"question":"Anne Njemanze","answer":"Anne Njemanze, jẹ́ òṣèrébìnrin ọmọ orílẹ̀-èdè Nàìjíríà. Ó gbajúmọ̀ jùlọ fún àwọn ipa rẹ̀ nínu àwọn eré bíi Domitila, Tinsel, Ìrètí àti Colourless.Ó ṣe ìgbeyàwó pẹ̀lú òṣèré Nollywood Segun Arinze, ṣùgbọ́n àwọn méjèjì ti pínyà. Wọ́n bí ọmọbìnrin kan tí orúkọ rẹ̀ n ṣe Renny Morẹ́nikẹ́.Ní Oṣù Kọkànlá Ọdún 2013, ó tún ṣe ìgbeyàwó pẹ̀lú Silver Ojieson, ṣùgbọ́n ìgbeyàwọ́ náà kò tún ju oṣù mẹ́jọ lọ tí wọ́n fi kọrawọnsílẹ̀.Ní ọdún 1995, ó bẹ̀rẹ̀ iṣẹ́ òṣèré rẹ̀ pẹ̀lú kíkópa nínu fíìmù tí àkọ́lé rẹ̀ jẹ́ Rattle Snake. Lẹ́hìn náà ló di ìlúmọ̀ọ́ká pẹ̀lú kíkópa rẹ̀ nínu eré tẹlifíṣọ̀nù Domitilla àti Domitilla II.[8] Lẹ́hìn náà, Ó tún kópa nínu fíìmù tí àkọ́lé rẹ̀ jẹ́ True Confession ní àjọṣepọ̀ pẹ̀lú Liz Benson.Ní ọdún 2012, ó kó ipa ti \\"Inspector Sankey\\" nínu eré M-Net aláṣeyọrí kan tí àkọ́lé rẹ̀ jẹ́ Tinsel ."},{"question":"வினா:ஈ. வெ. இராமசாமி மேற்கோள் ஒன்றை தரவும்.","answer":"விடை:பெண்களுக்கு வேண்டியது புத்தகப்படிப்பு மட்டுமல்ல; உலக அறிவும்தான்."},{"question":"Азалея гүлү жөнүндө эмне айта аласыз?","answer":"Азалея - дайыма жашыл болуп турган бадалча. Анын сөңгөгү кыска, бутагы ичке, жалбырагы майда, түрдүү түстөгү гүлдөрү ири , жөнөкөй жана түктүү болот. Азалеяны терезеге жакын салкын жарык бөлмөгө коюлат. Кардын же муздаткычтан алынган суу менен суугарса же топурагына муз койсо гүлү тегиз ачылат жана узак гүлдөйт. "},{"question":"به متن زیر مراجعه کنید و سپس به همان زبانی که در متن آمده است به سوال بعد پاسخ دهید:  گذرگاه: نام \\"جوییستک\\" تصور می‌شود که از اوایل قرن بیستم توسط خلبان فرانسوی رابرت اسنو-پلتری سرچشمه گرفته است. همچنین ادعاهای رقابتی از طرف خلبانان همکار رابرت لوراین، جیمز هنری جویس، و ا. ا. جورج وجود دارد. لوراین توسط فرهنگ لغت انگلیسی آکسفورد برای استفاده از اصطلاح «جویی استیک» در دفتر خاطرات خود در سال ۱۹۰۹ هنگامی که به پائو رفت تا در مدرسه بلریوت پرواز را یاد بگیرد، نقل قول شده است. جورج یک خلبان پیشگام بود که با همکارش جوبلینگ در نیوکاسل در انگلستان در سال ۱۹۱۰ یک دو هواپیما ساخت و پرواز کرد. ادعا می‌شود که او «جرج استیک» را اختراع کرده است که بیشتر به عنوان جوی استیک شناخته می‌شود. ستون کنترل هواپیمای جورج و جوبلینگ در مجموعه موزه کشف در نیوکاسل آپون تاین، انگلستان است.  سوال: شغل جورج چه بود؟","answer":"خلبان پیشگام"},{"question":"கிழக்குத் தொடர்ச்சி மலைத் தொடரின் மிக உயரமான சிகரம் எது?","answer":"மகேந்திரகிரி."},{"question":"\\"Owó gọbọi là ń san lórí àwọn ọmọ wa àmọ́ ìgbéayé ẹlẹ́wọ̀n ni wọ́n ń gbé nílé ẹ̀kọ́ wọn\\"","answer":"Àwọn òbí àti alagbatọ awọn ọmọ ile ẹkọ ìjọba àpapò, Federal Science and Technical College, Usi Ekiti, ipinle Ekiti ti ṣe ifẹhonuhan alafia nínú ọgbà ilé ẹ̀kọ́ náà lórí ìtọ́jú àti ètò ẹ̀kọ́ àwọn ọmọ wọn.Àwọn obí àti alagbató náà fariga lórí ọ̀nà tí olùdarí ilé ẹ̀kọ́ ọhun, Balogun Adisa Olateju fi ń se akoso àti ìtọ́jú àwọn akẹ́kọ̀ọ́ náà tí wọn sì ni awọn fẹ ki ijọba gbe kuro ni ile eko naa ni kankan.Nígbàtí alága ẹgbẹ́ àwọn obi ilé ẹ̀kọ́ naa Bangbose Taiwo sọrọ, o fi ẹsun kan oludari ilé ẹkọ ọhun pe ko ṣe àmójútó rẹ daradara gẹ́gẹ́ bí àwọn tí wọn ṣáájú rẹ ṣe ń ṣe.Àwọn olufẹhonuhan náà lọ káàkiri inu ọgbà ilé ẹ̀kọ́ ọhun pẹlu orisirisi patako lọwọ wọn.Lara wọn akọle ti wọn kọ si awọn patako ni “A n fẹ oludari míràn,” “Adisa Balogun ma pa FSTC Usi run,” “Àwọn ọmọ wa kò rí itọju dáadáa ní FSTC Usi,” Eto ẹ̀kọ́ àwọn ọmọ wa nílò ayipada lọwọ Balogun, ìjọba àpapò ẹgba wá.”Àwọn òbí náà sọrọ lori bí agbegbe ilé ìdáná àti ibùsùn àwọn akẹ́kọ̀ọ́ náà kò ṣe bá ìgbà mú, tí wọn ní kó yàtọ̀ sí ọgbà ẹ̀wọ̀n.Wọn tilẹ sọ pé ọgbà ẹ̀wọ̀n gan dára ju ibi tí wọn kó awọn ọmọ àwọn sí, tí wọn sì ní oúnjẹ tí wọn n fún wọn gan kò ṣara loore fún idagbasoke tó péye.Adewumi Temidayo àti Olatuji Bamisile tí wọn jẹ obi ní láti nnkan bíi ọsẹ mẹ́ta tí àwọn akẹkọọ ti pada sile ẹkọ ni wọn kò ti gbà ìwé tí àwọn òbí san owó rẹ.Wọn tún ní gbogbo inú yàrá ibùsùn ni kò dára mọ rárá pẹlu owo yanturu tí àwọn òbí ń ṣàn.Lára àwọn akẹkọọ tó bá akọroyin BBC Yoruba sọrọ tí wọn kò fẹ dárúkọ ara wọn ní kó sì omi, ilé igbónsẹ̀ tó dára ati iná ijọba ninu ọgbà ile ẹkọ náà.Wọn sọ siwaju si pe oúnjẹ tí àwọn oludari n fún àwọn ko dara rárá, wọn tun bù ẹnu àte lu bí gbogbo òrùlé ilé ẹ̀kọ́ ṣe maa n jo ni ọpọlọpọ ìgbà ti ojo bá rọ.Lẹyin naa ni wọn ràwọ ẹ̀bẹ̀ si ìjọba àpapọ̀ láti tètè wá bá àwọn mójútó gbogbo ìwà ibajẹ ati iwa aibikita ti wọn ni olùdarí ilé ẹkọ náà n wu.Nígbàtí akọrin BBC Yoruba kan sì olùdarí ilé ẹ̀kọ́ ọhun lórí ẹrọ ibanisọrọ rẹ, ni oun kò tii gbó nkankan lórí iwọde ọhun."},{"question":"Fenoy ny banga:“_ an’olombelona fa ny _ an’Andrimananitra”","answer":"“Fikasana an’olombelona fa ny didy an’Andrimananitra”"},{"question":"Senaraikan negeri-negeri di Malaysia. ","answer":"Johor, Kedah, Kelantan, Melaka, Pulau Pinang, Negeri Sembilan, Pahang, Perak, Perlis, Selangor dan Terengganu"},{"question":"චලිත නියම තුන දියුණු කළ විද්‍යාඥයාගේ නම කුමක්ද?","answer":"අයිසැක් නිව්ටන්"},{"question":"Menene Hukuncin tafiya da takalmi a cikin maƙabar ta?","answer":"Amsa: Sunnah ga wanda ya shiga maƙabarta shine ya cire takalmin sa, Amma idan acikin Maƙabartar akwai ƙaya wanda zai cutar dashi to babu laifi ya sanya takalmin sa, saboda lalura."},{"question":"د نننۍ لوبې په اړه راپور چې افغانستان د ۲۰۲۳ کال د کرېکټ نړیوال جام سیالیو کې د پاکستان پر وړاندې بریا خپله کړه. هغه پیښې بیان کړئ چې د لوبې په جریان کې لیدل شوي.","answer":"د افغانستان د کرکټ ملي لوبډلې د ۲۰۲۳ نړیوال پنځوس‌اوریز جام په سیالیو کې نن د پاکستان لوبډلې ته تاریخي ماتې ورکړه.دا لوبه نن د هند په کوربه‌توب د پاکستانۍ لوبډلې په توپوهنې سره پيل شوه او افغان لوبډلې ته یې د اووه لوبغاړو په سوځېدو ۲۸۲ منډې هدف کېښود.افغان لوبډلې بیا یوازې د دوو لوبغاړو په سوځېدو د ۴۸ اور په وروستۍ بال د سیالې لوبډلې هدف ته بریالی ځان ورساوه او بری یې د افغانستان په برخه کړ.په نننۍ لوبه کې ابراهیم ځدراڼ ۸۷ منډې، رحمت شاه ۷۷ منډې او رحمان الله ګوربز ۶۵ منډې جوړې کړې.د پاکستان پر وړاندې د افغانستان دا بری ځکه تاریخي بلل کېږي چې افغان لوبډلې تر دې دمه په پنځوس‌اوریزه سیالۍ کې پاکستان لوبډلې ته ماتې نه وه ورکړې.د ویلو ده چې د لوبې تر بریا وروسته په ټولنیزو پاڼو او د شپې په سړکونو د هېوادوالو د خوښۍ احساسات د ستاینې وړ دي."},{"question":"Гельминтология деген илим тууралуу уктуң беле? ","answer":"-Ооба, ал жөнүндө билем. Кыскача айтсам, ал илим мите курттарды жана ошол курттар аркылуу пайда болгон ооруларды изилдөөчү илим болуп саналат. Кызыксаң дагы айтып берем "},{"question":"الجملة 1: تم توسيع الكهرباء ده من سنة 1983 شمالاً لـ وايكاناي وفي سنة 2011 لـ بارابارامو تاني. الجملة 2: تم توسيع الكهرباء ده شمالاً لبارابارومو من سنة 1983 وعودت لوايكاني في سنة 2011. سؤال: الجملة 1 والجملة 2 بتعبر عن نفس المعنى؟ نعم ولا لا؟","answer":"الاجابة هى: لا، الجملتان لا تعبران عن نفس المعنى."},{"question":"Wamuwamu lawọn ọlọpaa duro sawọn ibi kan l’Ekoo, awọn to fẹẹ ṣewọde ni wọn n ṣọ","answer":"Lati le pinwọ ikojọpọ tabi ṣiṣe iwọde lati fẹhonu han ni Too-geeti, Lẹkki, l’Ekoo, agbẹnusọ ileeṣẹ ọlọpaa nipinlẹ naa, Muyiwa Adejọbi, ti sọ pe awọn ọlọpaa yoo ṣi wa nibẹ titi ti kọmiṣanna yoo fi pinnu lati ko wọn kuro patapata.Ọjọ Aje, Mọnde yii, ni ileeṣẹ ọlọpaa gbe ikede ọhun jade, bẹẹ lo fi kun un pe yatọ si Too-geeti Lẹkki, awọn ọna mẹrin mi-in lawọn ọlọpaa ti wa kaakiri Eko lati ma ṣe faaye gba ẹnikẹni to ba fẹẹ ṣewọde gẹgẹ bi awọn ọdọ kan ṣe gbero.Awọn ọlọpaa ti sọ pe awọn ko ni i kuro lawọn agbegbe ọhun titi digba ti Ọgbẹni Hakeem Odumosu, ẹni ti ṣe kọmiṣanna ọlọpaa ba sọ pe ki awọn pada si bareke.Ṣiwaju si i, ileeṣẹ ọlọpaa ti sọ pe oun ko ti i mu ẹnikẹni lọjọ Aje, Mọnde, nitori pe ko ṣeni kan bayii to bọ sita lati ṣewọde.Lara awọn ibi ti wọn ti ko ọlọpaa da si l’Ekoo niwọnyi; Unity Park, Gani Fawehinmi Park, Orita Ọgọmbọ, Orita Adeniran Ogunsanya atawọn ibomi-in.Tẹ o ba gbagbe, ọjọ Abamẹta, Satide to kọja yii, lawọn ọdọ kan jade lati fẹhonu han ninu eyi ti wọn ti mu Ọgbẹni Debọ Adedayọ, ẹni tawọn eeyan si mọ Mr. Macaroni pẹlu awọn ọdọ bii ogoji lori pe wọn jade lati fẹhonu han.Bẹẹ, ohun ti awọn ọdọ Naijiria n binu si lasiko yii ni bi ijọba ṣe sọ pe oun yoo tun ṣi Too-geeti Lẹkki pada lai ṣeto idajọ to yẹ lori ipakupa ti awọn ṣọja pa awọn ọdọ kan danu logunjọ, oṣu kẹwaa, ọdun 2020."},{"question":"Awọn agbebọn da awọn arinrin-ajo lọna Ẹrin Ijẹṣa, ni wọn ba ko lara wọn lọ","answer":"Adari ẹṣọ Amọtẹkun nipinlẹ Ọṣun, Ajagun-fẹyinti Bashir Adewinbi, ti sọ pe titi di asiko ti a n ko iroyin yii jọ, ko sẹni to le sọ ni pato iye awọn arinrin-ajo tawọn agbegbọn ji gbe loju ọna Omoh si Ẹrin-Ijeṣa nijọba ibilẹ Oriade nipinlẹ Ọṣun.Alẹ ọjọ Aiku, Sannde, la gbọ pe awọn agbegbọn naa ya soju titi, ti wọn si da awọn arinrin-ajo naa duro, lẹyin iṣẹju diẹ ni wọn ko diẹ lara wọn lọ sinu igbo to wa lagbegbe Ori Oke Omoh, ti wọn si fi awọn to ku silẹ.Nigba ti Adewinbi n fidi eyi mulẹ, o ni bi awọn ṣe gbọ nipa iṣẹlẹ naa lawọn ẹsọ Amọtẹkun ti fọn sinu igbo naa lati le tu awọn arinrinajo yii silẹ, ati lati le ri awọn ọdaran naa mu.Ninu ọrọ tirẹ, Alukoro ọlọpaa l’Ọṣun, SP Yẹmisi Ọpalọla, ṣalaye pe eeyan meji pere lawọn agbegbọn naa ji gbe lara awọn arinrinajo ọhun, ti wọn si fi awọn to ku silẹ.Ọpalọla sọ pe obitibiti awọn ọlọpaa ni wọn ti wa nibẹ bayii, idaniloju si wa pe ọwọ yoo tẹ awọn agbegbọn ọhun laipẹ.Ẹnikan to n gbe ninu ilu naa to ba ALAROYE    sọrọ, ṣugbọn to ni ka forukọ bo oun laṣiiri ṣalaye pe agbegbe naa ti fẹẹ di ẹrujẹjẹ lọwọ awọn agbebọn.O ni ki i ṣe igba akọkọ tiru iṣẹlẹ naa yoo ṣẹlẹ nibẹ niyi, ati pe wọn ti yinbọn fun awọn Amọtẹkun lorita yẹn gan-an ri. O ni ọlọpaa atawọn Amọtẹkun ti wa ninu igbo naa bayii."},{"question":"අසන්න / සවන් දෙන්න (ෂෙමා) යනු කුමක්ද?","answer":"ෂෙමා (“අසන්න / සවන් දෙන්න”) යනු යුදෙව් ආගමේ වැදගත්ම යාච්ඤාව ආරම්භ කරන හෙබ්‍රෙව් වචනයයි. එය ද්විතීය කථාව 6:4 හි දක්නට ලැබේ, එය “සවන් දෙන්න” යන ආඥාවෙන් ආරම්භ වේ. 4-9 පද ඇතුළත් සම්පූර්ණ ෂෙමා යාච්ඤාව යුදෙව් සම්ප්‍රදාය තුළ දිනපතා කථා කරනු ලැබේ:“ඊශ්‍රායෙල්, අසන්න: අපගේ දෙවි සමිඳාණන්වහන්සේ එක් කෙනෙක් ය. ඔබ ඔබේ මුළු හදවතින් ද ඔබේ මුළු ආත්මයෙන් ද ඔබේ මුළු ශක්තියෙන් ද ඔබේ දෙවි සමිඳාණන්වහන්සේට ප්‍රේම කළ යුතු ය. අද මා ඔබට අණ කරන මේ වචන ඔබේ පිට පවතින්නේ ය. හදවත, ඔබ ඒවා ඔබේ දරුවන්ට කඩිසරව උගන්වා, ඔබ ඔබේ නිවසේ හිඳගෙන සිටින විට, ඔබ මඟ යන විට, ඔබ සයනය කරන විට සහ ඔබ නැඟිටින විට ඒවා ගැන කතා කරන්න, ලකුණක් ලෙස ඔබ ඒවා බැඳ තැබිය යුතුය. ඔබේ අත, ඒවා ඔබේ ඇස් අතරේ ඉදිරිපස ඇතිරිලි මෙන් වනු ඇත, ඔබේ නිවසේ උළුවහු කණුවලද ඔබේ දොරටුවලද ඒවා ලියන්න.”පසුකාලීන යුදෙව් සම්ප්‍රදාය කොටස් තුනකින් යුත් ෂෙමා යාච්ඤාවක් වර්ධනය කරන ලද අතර එයට ද්විතීය කථාව 11:13-29 සහ ගණන් කථාව 15:37-41 ඇතුළත් විය. සම්ප්‍රදායට අනුව මෙම කොටස් තුන දස පනතේ සියලුම අංග ආවරණය කරයි. අද පවා, කිතුණුවන්ට ෂෙමාගේ වචන ස්වාමින්වහන්සේ එකම සැබෑ දෙවියන් වහන්සේ බවට පුදුමාකාර ප්‍රකාශනයක් ලෙස බැලිය හැකිය. අප උන් වහන්සේගේ ස්වාමිත්වය පිළිගන්නා පරිදි, අපගේ ප්‍රතිචාරය ඉතිරිව ඇත්තේ උන්වහන්සේට “ඇහුම්කන් දීම”, අපගේ මුළු හදවතින්ම, ආත්මයෙන් සහ ශක්තියෙන් උන්වහන්සේට ප්‍රේම කිරීම සහ අපට මෙන් අපගේ අසල්වැසියාට ප්‍රේම කිරීමයි."},{"question":"اگر قصد خرید و یا فروش خانه یا آپارتمانی را داریم بهترین مکان برای این کار کجاست؟","answer":"با توجه به تخصصی شدن مشاغل و وجود صنف مشاورین املاک لذا بهترین و مطمئن‌ترین محل برای کسب اطلاع از قیمت روز ملک و همچنین انجام کلیه معاملات ملکی، دفاتر و آژانس‌های املاکی است که عضو رسمی اتحادیه صنف مشاورین املاک شهرها می‌باشند و از هرگونه معامله خارج از این دفاتر جداً خودداری کنید."},{"question":"O que significa o ditado popular: \\"Nem tanto ao mar nem tanto à terra\\"?","answer":"Provérbio utilizado para referir-se ao equilíbrio. É preciso fazer as coisas com moderação, sem exageros, nem muito para mais nem muito para menos.Exemplo: “Essa roupa tá adequada para a festa, nem tanto ao mar nem tanto à terra.”"},{"question":"பெரியாரின் எழுத்துகளிலிருந்து  மேற்கோள் ஒன்றை தரவும்.","answer":"அறிவுக்கு ஏற்றது, மக்களுக்கு நன்மை பயப்பது, மக்களின் அறிவை வளர்ச்சியடையச் செய்வது எதுவோ அதைப் பற்றியே பேசு."},{"question":"Dakar moy péeyu ban réw?","answer":"Dakar moy péeyu réwum Sénégal"},{"question":"કમલેશ સોનાવાલા ની \\"પધારો વસંતો આ આંગણ સજાવો\\" કવિતા લખો.","answer":"“વિતી ગયા છે દિન બધા છતાં અજવાસ બાકી છે,પ્રણયની કે પ્રલયની એ હજી એક રાત બાકી છે.”મચલતી હવાઓ, લચકતી લતાઓછલકતી જુવાની ગુલોથી વધાવો,પધારો વસંતો આ આંગણ સજાવો.લટકતી લટોથી ન નજરો બચાવોઉઠાવો મિલાવો ઝુકેલી નિગાહો,જો બદલાય મોસમ ન બદલો અદાઓપધારો વસંતો આ આંગણ સજાવો.અગન છે દિલોમાં, દિલોને મિલાવોકરી છે જે વાતો ના એને ભુલાવો,રસીલી તમારી રીસાઈ મનાવોપધારો વસંતો આ આંગણ સજાવો.દિવાલો બની છે ત્યાં ઘરને વસાવોબનીને દુલ્હન આ ડેલામાં આવો,ભરી સેંથી સિંદુર દિવો તો જગાવોપધારો વસંતો આ આંગણ સજાવો."},{"question":"Bireeki tanka epo feeli, lo ba tẹ awọn ọmọleewe mẹẹẹdogun pa","answer":"Iran buruku ni iran ọhun, iran ti ko dun un wo rara, tori teeyan ba jẹ ori awun, aanu abiyamọ aa ṣe e ni, pẹlu bi ijamba ọkọ tanka epo kan to waye l’Ọjọbọ, Tọsidee yii, ṣe sọ mẹẹẹdogun lara awọn ọmọ ileewe pamari ti wọn n pada lọ sile wọn jẹẹjẹ doloogbe lojiji, niṣe lọkọ naa lọ gbogbo wọn mọlẹ bii ẹran aijẹ. Wọn ni mẹta ninu awọn ọmọ ohun lo jẹ pe baba kan naa, iya kan naa, lo bi wọn.Yatọ sawọn to ku, ba a ṣe gbọ, awọn ọmọleewe bii marun-un mi-in tun fara pa gidi, ti wọn si wa lẹsẹ-kan-aye-ẹsẹ-kan-ọrun lọsibitu awọn ologun to wa ni Bareke David Ejoor, ni Effurun, ati ni ọsibitu Jẹnẹra Warri, ti wọn gbe wọn digbadigba lọ.Wọn ni ileewe Army Children Primary School, to wa lagbegbe Effurun, nipinlẹ Delta, lawọn ọmọ naa ti n kawe, wọn o si ṣẹṣẹ maa rin ẹgbẹ titi naa, ibẹ ni wọn n gba lojoojumọ ti wọn ba n lọ sileewe tabi dari sile.Nnkan bii aago meji aabọ ọsan ni tirela tanka ti epo bẹntiroolu kun inu rẹ bamu padanu ijanu rẹ, awakọ naa ko le ṣakoso ọkọ ọhun mọ, lo ba n ya barabara kaakiri, bo ṣe lọọ ya ba awọn ọmọleewe to n ṣeri pada lọ sile kaluku wọn niyẹn, o si pa wọn nifọnna ifọnṣu. Gẹrẹ tiṣẹlẹ yii waye ni dẹrẹba ọkọ naa ti fẹsẹ fẹ ẹ, o sa lọ rau.Ẹnikan tọrọ naa ṣoju ẹ sọ pe bireeki ọkọ ọhun lo feeli bo ṣe n da gẹrẹgẹrẹ ọna naa bọ, ti ko si le ṣakoso irin ọkọ naa, debi ti ijamba yii fi waye.A gbọ pe awọn ileeṣẹ panapana ati awọn agbofinro to tete de sibi iṣẹlẹ naa ni ko jẹ kawọn ọdọ tinu n bi dana sun ọkọ ọhun, tori epo bẹntiroolu kun inu rẹ tẹmutẹmu."},{"question":"என் வகுப்பில் படிக்கும் அனைவரும் புதிய புத்தகம் வைத்திருந்தனர். இராமனும் புதிய புத்தகம் வைத்திருந்தான். எனவே, இராமன் என் வகுப்பு மாணவன் – இக் கூற்று.அ) உண்மைஆ) பொய்இ) உறுதியாகக் கூறமுடியாது","answer":"இ) உறுதியாகக் கூறமுடியாதுகாரணம் : அனைவரும் என்று கூறிய பின் இராமன் வேறு வகுப்பு மாணவனாகக் கூட இருக்கலாம்."},{"question":"Onye n'eje mgba na mba Anam,","answer":"Mụọ igwu mmiri ha"},{"question":"Apakah maksud \\"adat diisi, lembaga dituang\\"?","answer":"Ia bermaksud dilakukan menurut aturan yang biasa"},{"question":"Andininy voalohany: Nividy akora hanaovana mofomamy i Michael.Fehezan-teny faharoa: Hita nitondra mofomamy efa nataony tao amin’ilay fety i Michael.Mifanaraka ve ireo fehezanteny roa ireo?","answer":" Eny, mifanaraka izy ireo."},{"question":"ටෙස්ට් තරඟයක පන්දුවාරයකදී වැඩිම ලකුණු වාර්තා කළ ක්‍රීඩකයා කවුද?","answer":"ජස්ප්‍රිට් බුම්රා"},{"question":"Nibi tawọn ọmọ ẹgbẹ okunkun yii ti n ṣepade lawọn ọlọpaa ti ko wọn l’Ekoo","answer":"Meje lara awọn afurasi ọmọ ẹgbẹ okunkun to wa lagbegbe Morogbo, nipinlẹ Eko, ti bọ sakolo ọlọpaa. Nibi ti wọn ti n ṣe ipade wọn lọwọ ni nnkan bii aago meje alẹ ni wọn ka wọn mọ.Orukọ ati ọjọ-ori awọn mejeeje tọwọ tẹ ọhun ni: Hameed Salami, ẹni ọdun marundinlogoji, Sunday Ogbemudia, ẹni ọdun mẹrindinlogoji, Ṣẹgun Okekunle, ẹni ọdun mẹrindinlọgbọn, Imọlẹ Kingsley, ẹni ọdun mẹtalelogun ati Rasaki Ọlalekan, ẹni ọdun mẹrindinlọgbọn.Awọn meji to ku ni Innocent Osuya, ẹni ọdun mẹtalelogun ati Ogunlade Adewale toun jẹ ẹni ọgbọn ọdun.Wọn ni otẹẹli House 2 Hotel, to wa ni Igbẹkẹle, ni Morogbo, lawọn afurasi ọdaran naa gba lọ ni nnkan bii aago meje ku diẹ lalẹ ọjọ Aiku, Sannde, ọsẹ yii, wọn sọ pe awọn fẹẹ ṣe apero kan ninu ọgba wọn, wọn si sanwo.Ṣugbọn awọn oṣiṣẹ otẹẹli naa fura si wọn, ni wọn ba yọkẹlẹ lọọ sọ fawọn alaṣẹ ileetura ọhun, lawọn ọga wọn ba kan sileeṣẹ ọlọpaa lori aago pe ki wọn waa ba awọn wo awọn alejo ọran to n ṣepade lọdọ awọn yii.Kia lawọn ọlọpaa ẹka teṣan Morogbo ti debẹ, ni wọn ba fi pampẹ ofin gbe gbogbo wọn.Nigba ti wọn n tu ẹru wọn wo, oriṣiiriṣii nnkan ija bii aake, ada, ọbẹ, oogun abẹnugọngọ, iṣana ati katiriiji ọta ibọn ti wọn o ti i yin ni wọn ba nibẹ. Wọn tun ba ibọn agbelẹrọ meji lọwọ wọn.Ọrọ ko pariwo mọ, wọn rọ gbogbo wọn da sọkọ ọlọpaa, ko si pe ti wọn fi balẹ si ẹka awọn ọtẹlẹmuyẹ ni Panti, Yaba, fun iwadii.Kọmiṣanna ọlọpaa, Hakeem Odumosu, loun ti paṣẹ pe ki wọn tete pari iwadii lori wọn, kawọn afurasi wọnyi ati ẹru ofin ti wọn n ko kiri le lọọ ṣalaye ara wọn niwaju adajọ, gẹgẹ bi Alukoro ileeṣẹ ọlọpaa Eko, Muyiwa Adejọbi, ṣe sọ f’ALAROYE."},{"question":"Manana ity teny nokorontanina ity ianao:ajyoarnVinavinao ilay teny rehefa alamina.","answer":"Toy izao ilay teny rehefa voalamina :  \\"janoary\\""},{"question":"Skriv en fortsättning på den här paragrafen - Lance Reventlow och Chuck Daigh debuterade i Monaco","answer":"men lyckades inte kvala in till loppet. Scarab-bilarna var nästan 10 sekunder långsammare än övriga fältet. Vid nästa lopp i Holland drog sig Scarab ur, tillsammans med flera mindre stall, efter ett bråk om anmälningsavgiften. Reventlow och Daigh lyckades kvala in i Belgiens Grand Prix men bägge tvingades bryta loppet med motorproblem. Till Frankrikes Grand Prix hade Reventlow anlitat Richie Ginther som ersättare, men återigen tvingades bägge bilarna bryta. Säsongens sista tävling var . Chuck Daigh lyckades slutligen ta bilen i mål på en tiondeplats, vilket även var bästa placering för en frontmotorbil."},{"question":"‘वन महोत्सव’ म्हणून ओळखल्या जाणाऱ्या वृक्षारोपण महोत्सवाचे संस्थापक कोण आहेत?(A) जवाहरलाल नेहरू(B) के. एम.मुंशी(C) विनोबा भावे(D) महात्मा गांधी=> ","answer":"(B) के. एम.मुंशी"},{"question":"வினா :ஈ. வெ. இராமசாமி மேற்கோள் ஒன்றை தரவும்.","answer":"விடை :பெண்கள் படித்துவிட்டால் ஆண்கள் ஒழுக்க சீலர்களாக இருப்பார்கள்."},{"question":"Inona no atao mba hihazonana ny hydration tsara ny vatana?a) Misotro zava-pisotro malefakab) Misotro rano ampy c) Mihinana sakafo masira","answer":"b) Misotro rano ampy  no atao mba hihazonana ny hydration tsara ny vatana"},{"question":"¿Qué es y en qué consiste el aprendizaje por refuerzo?","answer":"El aprendizaje por refuerzo o aprendizaje reforzado (en inglés: reinforcement learning) es un área del aprendizaje automático (en inglés: Machine Learning) inspirada en la psicología conductista, cuya ocupación es determinar qué acciones debe escoger un agente de software en un entorno dado con el fin de maximizar alguna noción de \\"recompensa\\" o premio acumulado. Se ha vuelto popular a la hora de entrenar modelos del lenguaje, porque dada la calificación de una persona, el modelo puede optimizar y entregar mejores respuestas."},{"question":"ڈسٹرکٹ اینڈ سیشن جج محمد عظیم کی عدالت نے کراچی بار ایسو سی ایشن کے سیکریٹری جنرل نعیم قریشی کی دائر درخواست پر سندھ حکومت، متحدہ قومی موومنٹ کے ذمے داران اور پولیس افسران کے بارے میں دائر ایف آئی آر کو بحال کردیا ہے اور مقدمہ تحقیقات کے لیے تحقیقاتی ٹیم  کے حوالے کیے جانے کا حکم جاری کیا ہے۔بارہ مئی کو جب کراچی بار سے وکلاء نے چیف جسٹس افتخار محمد چودھری کے استقبال کے لیے جلوس نکالا تھا تو اس پر نامعلوم افراد نے حملہ اور فائرنگ کی تھی۔کراچی بار ایسو سی ایشن کے سیکریٹری جنرل نعیم قریشی نے بیس مئی کو اس واقعے کے خلاف سٹی کورٹ تھانے میں مقدمہ درج کرایا تھا۔ جس میں کہا گیا تھا کہ بارہ مئی کو وکلاء حبس بے جا میں رکھے گئے، انہیں جان سے مارنے کی دھمکیاں دی گئیں اور قاتلانہ حملے کے لیے ان پر فائرنگ کی گئی۔ اس کارروائی میں متحدہ قومی موومنٹ کے ذمے داران، سندھ حکومت اور پولیس حکام ملوث ہیں۔پولیس حکام نے کچھ گھنٹوں کے بعد یہ ایف آئی آر بغیر کسی تحقیقات کے خارج کر دی تھی۔اس فیصلے کے خلاف نعیم قریشی نے عدالت سے رجوع کیا تھا اور موقف اختیار کیا تھا کہ ایس ایچ او کو ایف آئی آر خارج کرنے کا کوئی اختیار حاصل نہیں ہے۔بعد میں صحافیوں سے بات کرتے ہوئے نعیم قریشی نے سٹی کورٹ پولیس پر عدم اعتماد کا اظہار کیا اور کہا کہ سٹی پولیس ایف آئی آر میں فریق ہے اس لیے ان سے غیر جانبدرانہ تحقیقات کی توقع نہیں رکھی جا سکتی۔","answer":"کراچی کی ایک عدالت نے 12 مئی کے حوالے سے متحدہ قومی موومنٹ، سندھ حکومت اور پولیس کے خلاف مقدمے کی ایف آئی آر بحال  کردی ہے۔\\"کراچی بار ایسو سی ایشن کے حملے: فیصلے کا اثر اور تحقیقات کی مواصلہ\\""},{"question":"नीचे दिए गए पाठ को संदर्भ के रूप में देखते हुए, निम्नलिखित प्रश्न का उत्तर दें।संदर्भ: झारखंड, भारत के खेरवाल संताल और असुर जनजातियों के अनुसार, हुदुर दुर्गा उनके सहस्राब्दी पूर्वज थे, जो कि चचाम्पा नामक एक गाँव के राजा थे। वह बहुत शक्तिशाली और शक्तिशाली राजा था। भारत आने के बाद आर्य उसे पराजित नहीं कर सकते थे। तब वे विभिन्न तरीकों से राजा को मारने के उपाय सोचने लगे। उन्हें पता चला कि राजा बहुत स्त्रैण था और महिलाओं को उनके समाज में बहुत माना जाता था। इसलिए आर्यों ने राजा की हत्या के लिए जासूस की एक सुंदर महिला को जासूस के रूप में भेजा। आर्यों ने राजा के सामने शादी का प्रस्ताव रखा और राजा ने महिला की उपस्थिति से प्रभावित होकर उससे शादी करने के लिए सहमति जताई। राजा ने शादी के बाद सात दिनों तक महिला के साथ रात बिताई और सातवें दिन महिला ने राजा को मार डाला। राजा की मृत्यु का समाचार सुनकर, आर्यों ने राज्य पर कब्जा करने के लिए राज्य पर आक्रमण किया। संतालों का दावा है कि आर्यों ने महिला को देवी दुर्गा और राजा को महिषासुर के रूप में घटना की महिला के रूप में अतिरंजित किया, और आगे दावा करते हैं कि उनके राजा हुदुर दुर्गा का नाम गलत रूप से महिला के नाम के रूप में उल्लेखित किया था। दुर्गा पूजा के दौरान, वे दुर्गा की पूजा नहीं करते हैं, लेकिन महिषासुर की पूजा करते हैं और रास्ते में दसई नृत्य करके महिलाओं का शोक मनाते हैं।प्रश्न: दुर्गा कौन है?","answer":"दिए गए संदर्भ का उपयोग करते हुए, इस प्रश्न का उत्तर यह है: दुर्गा, यानी, हुदुर दुर्गा भारत के खेरवाल संताल और असुर जनजातियों के सहस्राब्दी पूर्वज थे, जो कि चचाम्पा नामक एक गाँव के राजा थे।  "},{"question":"Dựa trên tiêu đề sau, hãy viết một đoạn văn tối đa 500 chữ: ĐH Quốc gia Hà Nội lên tiếng về bộ lễ phục tốt nghiệp 'đậm chất hoàng gia'","answer":"Mới đây, ngày 29.7, Trường ĐH Kinh tế (UEB) thuộc ĐH Quốc gia Hà Nội, đã tổ chức lễ trao bằng tốt nghiệp cho sinh viên và học viên của trường năm 2022. Một số báo đã đưa tin về sự kiện này, với nội dung tập trung vào \\"bộ lễ phục ấn tượng\\" mà nhà trường sử dụng trong lễ tốt nghiệp. Có báo còn bình luận đây là trang phục \\"đậm chất hoàng gia\\". Tuy nhiên, ngược lại với mục đích truyền thông mà nhà trường muốn gửi tới dư luận xã hội, trên các trang mạng xã hội đã xuất hiện nhiều ý kiến bày tỏ sự sửng sốt và kèm theo những đánh giá tiêu cực về bộ lễ phục \\"kỳ dị\\" này. Đặc biệt, các ý kiến tập trung phân tích hình ảnh thầy hiệu trưởng choàng quanh cổ chuỗi dây hình dây xích, cầm cây quyền trượng bước vào buổi lễ và cho rằng hình ảnh này giống nghi thức một buổi lễ tôn giáo chứ không phải buổi lễ tốt nghiệp ở một trường ĐH. Trước hiện tượng trên, chiều tối cùng ngày, Chánh văn phòng ĐH Quốc gia Hà Nội Trần Quốc Bình đã gửi công văn cho Hiệu trưởng UEB, truyền đạt ý kiến chỉ đạo của Giám đốc ĐH Quốc gia Hà Nội, xung quanh sự việc này. Theo công văn, Giám đốc ĐH Quốc gia Hà Nội đề nghị Hiệu trưởng UEB báo cáo ĐH Quốc gia Hà Nội bằng văn bản (thông qua Văn phòng ĐH Quốc gia Hà Nội) về công tác tổ chức lễ trao bằng tốt nghiệp năm 2022. Việc báo cáo cần được thực hiện trước ngày 2.8. Đồng thời, Giám đốc ĐH Quốc gia Hà Nội cũng đề nghị Hiệu trưởng UEB chỉ đạo rà soát và điều chỉnh về trang phục lễ phục trao bằng tốt nghiệp để tránh lặp lại tình trạng tương tự (là tình trạng nhận được nhiều ý kiến không đồng tình với trang phục lễ phục mà nhà trường đã sử dụng)."},{"question":"ल्यापटप के हो?","answer":"ल्यापटप कम्प्युटर वा नोटबुक कम्प्युटर, जसलाई ल्यापटप वा नोटबुक पनि भनिन्छ, सानो, पोर्टेबल पर्सनल कम्प्युटर (PC) हो। ल्यापटपहरूमा सामान्यतया माथिल्लो ढक्कनको भित्री भागमा फ्ल्याट प्यानल स्क्रिन (सामान्यतया ११-१७ इन्च वा २८०-४३० मिमी विकर्ण आकार) र अल्फान्यूमेरिक किबोर्ड र पोइन्टिङ उपकरण (जस्तै ट्र्याकप्याड र ट्र्याकपोइन्ट) भएको क्ल्यामशेल फारम कारक हुन्छ। तल्लो ढक्कन भित्र। यद्यपि, छुट्याउन मिल्ने किबोर्ड भएका २-इन्-१ पीसीहरू प्राय: ल्यापटपको रूपमा वा \\"ल्यापटप मोड\\" भएको रूपमा मार्केटिङ गरिन्छ। कम्प्यूटरको अधिकांश आन्तरिक हार्डवेयर किबोर्ड मुनि तल्लो ढक्कन घेरा भित्र फिट गरिएको छ। यद्यपि, धेरै ल्यापटपहरूमा स्क्रिनको शीर्षमा निर्मित वेबक्याम हुन्छ, र केही आधुनिकहरूमा टच-स्क्रिन डिस्प्ले पनि हुन्छ। मोबाइल अपरेटिङ सिस्टममा चल्ने ट्याब्लेट कम्प्यूटरको विपरीत, ल्यापटपहरू डेस्कटप अपरेटिङ सिस्टमहरूमा चल्ने प्रवृत्ति हुन्छ, जुन परम्परागत रूपमा डेस्कटप कम्प्युटरहरूसँग सम्बन्धित हुन्छ।ल्यापटपहरू AC पावर सप्लाई र रिचार्जेबल ब्याट्री प्याकमा चल्छन् र तिनीहरूलाई मोबाइल प्रयोगको लागि उपयुक्त बनाउँदै सुविधाजनक भण्डारण र यातायातको लागि फोल्ड गर्न सकिन्छ। आज, ल्यापटपहरू विभिन्न सेटिङहरूमा प्रयोग गरिन्छ, जस्तै काममा (विशेष गरी व्यापार यात्राहरूमा), शिक्षामा, खेलहरू खेल्नको लागि, वेब ब्राउजिङको लागि, व्यक्तिगत मल्टिमिडिया, र सामान्य गृह कम्प्युटर प्रयोगको लागि।\\"ल्यापटप\\" र \\"नोटबुक\\" नामहरूले कम्प्युटरलाई व्यावहारिक रूपमा प्रयोगकर्ताको काखमा (वा माथि) राख्न सकिन्छ र नोटबुक जस्तै प्रयोग गर्न सकिन्छ भन्ने तथ्यलाई जनाउँछ। २०२२ को रूपमा, अमेरिकी अंग्रेजीमा, सर्तहरू \\"ल्यापटप\\" र \\"नोटबुक\\" एकान्तर रूपमा प्रयोग गरिन्छ; अंग्रेजीको अन्य बोलीहरूमा, एक वा अर्कोलाई प्राथमिकता दिन सकिन्छ। यद्यपि \\"नोटबुक\\" शब्दले मूल रूपमा ल्यापटपको एक विशिष्ट साइजलाई जनाइएको थियो (सुरुमा त्यस समयको मुख्यधाराको ल्यापटपहरू भन्दा सानो र हल्का), यो शब्दले उही कुराको अर्थ लिएको छ र अब कुनै विशेष आकारलाई जनाउँदैन।ल्यापटपहरूले डेस्कटप कम्प्युटरको धेरै इनपुट/आउटपुट कम्पोनेन्टहरू र क्षमताहरूलाई एकल एकाइमा संयोजन गर्दछ, जसमा डिस्प्ले स्क्रिन, सानो स्पिकर, किबोर्ड, र पोइन्टिङ यन्त्र (जस्तै टचप्याड वा पोइन्टिङ स्टिक) समावेश हुन्छ। धेरैजसो आधुनिक ल्यापटपहरूमा निर्मित वेबक्याम र माइक्रोफोन समावेश छ, र धेरैमा टचस्क्रिन पनि छ। ल्यापटपहरू आन्तरिक ब्याट्री वा एसी एडाप्टर प्रयोग गरेर बाहिरी पावर सप्लाईद्वारा संचालित गर्न सकिन्छ। हार्डवेयर विशिष्टताहरू विभिन्न प्रकार, मोडेल र मूल्य बिन्दुहरू बीच महत्त्वपूर्ण रूपमा भिन्न हुन सक्छन्।"},{"question":"લેન્સના પાવરનો એકમ કયો છે?A). એમીટરB). ડાયોપ્ટરC). વૉલ્ટD). ઓહમ","answer":"B). ડાયોપ્ટર લેન્સના પાવરનો SI એકમ ડાયોપ્ટર (D) છે. એક ડાયોપ્ટર એ એક લેન્સ છે જેનો કેન્દ્રલંબાઈ 1 મીટર છે. જેમ જેમ લેન્સની કેન્દ્રલંબાઈ ઓછી થાય છે, તેમ તેનો પાવર વધુ હોય છે. તેથી, 1 મીટર કરતાં ઓછી કેન્દ્રલંબાઈવાળા લેન્સનો પાવર 1 કરતાં વધુ હોય છે.લેન્સના પાવરની ગણતરી નીચેના સૂત્ર દ્વારા કરવામાં આવે છે:\\"P = 1/f\\"જ્યાં, \\"P\\" એ લેન્સનો પાવર છે, \\"f\\" એ લેન્સની કેન્દ્રલંબાઈ છે, જે મીટરમાં માપવામાં આવે છે."},{"question":"هي عبارة عن مدينة في ولاية لويزيانا على نهر الميسيسبي ، ماهي المدينة؟","answer":"نيوأورلينز "},{"question":"ब्रम्हचर्माश्रम, गृहस्थाश्रम, वानप्रस्थाश्रम व संन्यासाश्रम हे प्राचीन भारतातील कोणत्या व्यवस्थेचे प्रकार होते ?","answer":"ब्रम्हचर्माश्रम, गृहस्थाश्रम, वानप्रस्थाश्रम व संन्यासाश्रम हे प्राचीन भारतातील आश्रम व्यवस्था व्यवस्थेचे प्रकार होते. "},{"question":"Ahoana ny fomba fambolena zaridaina mahasalama? Manana vahaolana roa azo atao ianao:Vahaolana 1: Mamboly voa ao anaty tany voahomana tsara sy rano tsy tapaka.Vahaolana 2: Mihirà ho an'ny zava-maniry ary manantena fa hitombo izy ireo.","answer":"Ny vahaolana 1 dia mitombina kokoa. Manaraka fomba fanao mahazatra amin'ny zaridaina izy io, fa ny fihiràna ho an'ny zava-maniry mba hampitombo azy dia mifototra amin'ny finoanoam-poana."},{"question":"ఇచ్చిన కవికి కవి పరిచయం రాయండి: చుక్కాకోటి వీరభద్రమ్మ","answer":"కవి పేరు : ‘చుక్కా కోటి వీరభద్రమ్మనివాసం : వల్లూరుపాలెం, కృష్ణాజిల్లాకాలం : 20వ శతాబ్దంరచన : నగజా శతకం (1940లో అచ్చయింది)"},{"question":"『This is a book』　「This」は「これ」、「book」は「本」と訳しますが、では「伊豆」はどこの都道府県にあるでしょう？","answer":"静岡県です。"},{"question":"ذهب جد ووالدان وولدان معا إلى السینما واشترى كل فرد تذكرة سینما واحدة. كم عدد التذاكر التي قاموا بشرائها في المجموع؟","answer":"سؤال ذكى. الجواب هو ثلاثة تذاكر لأن الجد أب أیضا والأب ابن، و هكذا يكون لدينا ثلاثة أشخاص."},{"question":"Apakah maksud 'buang bunga ke jirat'?","answer":"Ia bermaksud berbudi kepada seseorang yang tidak mengenang (memerlukan) budi orang"},{"question":"Ity fanambarana manaraka ity dia amin'ny teny malagasy, adika amin'ny teny frantsay.\\"Inona no karazana mozika tianao indrindra?\\"","answer":"Quel est votre type de musique préféré ?"},{"question":"   வினா: ஆண்டிப் புலவர் எழுதிய நிகண்டின் பெயர் என்ன? ","answer":"விடை:  – ஆசிரிய நிகண்டு1.  ஆசிரிய நிகண்டு என்பது சொற்களுக்குப் பொருள் கூறும் நிகண்டு நூல்.2.   ஆண்டிப் புலவரால் இயற்றப்பட்டது. 3.  நூலாசிரியர் தமிழ்நாட்டில் உள்ள செஞ்சியை அடுத்த ஊற்றங்காலில் பிறந்தவர்.4.   இவர் பாவாடை வாத்தியார் என்பவரின் மகன். 5.  இந்த நிகண்டு 17 ஆம் நூற்றாண்டைச் சார்ந்தது ஆகும்."},{"question":"Ukuxabana kwezinsizwa ngasemakhaya ngoKhisimuzi kwenza ukuba impi ingapheleliemakhaya ngoba uxolo lwalungenzekanga. Ziphindela nje izinsizwa emsebenzini,izinhliziyo zibomvu akukhulunyiswana. Kufihlelwene induku emqubeni. Olunyeuhlangothi lwalwehla lwenyuka luthenga izibhamu zomgunyathi ngoba befunaukuziphindiselela ingcabha ingagcini kubona. Akutshelwana uma kukhonaabazohlasela, ngakho-ke abanye babona ngoba sebembozwa impi. Ngalelo langabehlaselwa, uManyoba wayesebenza ebusuku. Wafika ekuseni sekukhona ababesebefile, sekugcwele ezikadalawane emagcekeni ehostela. Uma ebuza ukuthikwenzenjani, bamtshela ngokwenzekile, washaqeka wacishe wawa phansi uvalolokuthi ngabe naye ungomunye mhlawumbe walaba abafile. Kwake kwaba muncuisikhathi eside kunohlevana kubahlali basehostela. Ngenhlanhla nje kwakungabangwaizwe, kwakungamagqubu nje ezinsizweni. Ezinye zezizathu ezamenza wafunaukushiya umsebenzi eGoli ayosebenza ePitoli. EGoli izinsizwa zokuhamba zazivamiseukuhamba ngambili noma ngantathu ngoba zazikhuthuzwa noma zigetshengweotsotsi. Ngesikhathi sabo kwakukhona amaqembu otsotsi anjengoMsomi namanyeayedume ngokubulala, umuntu atholakale edindilizile esefile emgwaqweni. Isikhaliesikhulu sokubulala kuqala, kwakuwummese noma kube untshumentshu. Into embikakhulu eyayenzeka emadolobheni, ukuthola umuntu enqunywe intamo kungaziwaukuthi ubulawe ubani.Yiziphi izizathu ezenza ukuthi uManyoba angayi kobikela amaphoyisangesigameko asibona senzeka emgodini wemayini lapho ayesebenza khona?","answer":"Wayesaba ukuthi izigilamkhuba kungenzeka zimenzakalise ngobazazimbonile./ UManyoba akazange ababone ebusweni abenzi bobubi ngobawayesabela impilo yakhe engafuni ukuzinika isikhathi sokuthi ababukisisekahle./ Wayengeke akwazi uManyoba ukuba ngufakazi othembekile enkantolongenxa yokuthi wayengeke akwazi ukubakhomba abenzi bobubi."},{"question":"Beqil ma mbind mii:Deeleen taxawee julli te di génne asaka. Lu ngeen jiital ci lu baax ngir seen bopp, dangeen ko fekk ca Yàlla, ndax Yàlla gu gis la li ngeen di def.","answer":"Mbind mi jub a ngi nii:Deeléen tàxawe julli te di génne àsaka. Lu ngéen jiital ci lu baax ngìr séen bopp, da ngéen ko fekk ca Yàlla, ndàx Yàlla gu gìs la li ngéen di def."},{"question":"Pregunta: ¿ Cuántas balas tenía el tirador de Las Vegas? Respuesta:","answer":"1,100 balas. "},{"question":"Mô tả sự kiện quan trọng được nói tới trong văn bản này - Trận đấu quốc tế đầu tiên của đội tuyển Cabo Verde là trận đấu gặp Guiné-Bissau vào năm 1979. Thành tích tốt nhất của đội cho đến nay là lọt vào tứ kết Cúp bóng đá châu Phi 2013 ở ngay lần đầu tham dự giải.","answer":"Sự kiện quan trọng được nói tới trong văn bản là trận đấu quốc tế đầu tiên của đội tuyển Cabo Verde (Cape Verde) khi họ gặp đội tuyển Guiné-Bissau vào năm 1979. Đây là lần đầu tiên đội tuyển bóng đá của Cabo Verde tham gia một trận đấu quốc tế chính thức, đánh dấu một bước ngoặt quan trọng trong lịch sử thể thao của đất nước này.Thành tích đáng chú ý khác của đội tuyển Cabo Verde là khi họ lọt vào tứ kết Cúp bóng đá châu Phi 2013. Đây là một thành công đáng kể vì đây là lần đầu tiên Cabo Verde tham dự giải đấu này và họ đã vượt qua vòng bảng để tiến vào vòng tứ kết. Thành công này đã thể hiện sự phát triển và tiến bộ của bóng đá Cabo Verde trong cấp độ châu lục và tạo dấu ấn đáng kể trong lịch sử thể thao của đất nước."},{"question":"fenoy ny banga:\\" Mpirahalahy mianala,_\\"","answer":"\\"Mpirahalahy mianala, ianao tokiko izaho tokinao\\""},{"question":"Inona ny teny mitovy hevitra amin'ny \\"Nilaozana\\"?","answer":"Ny teny mitovy hevitra amin'ny \\"Nilaozana\\" dia\\"Navela\\".Ohatra: Navelan'ilay ramatoa ny zanany fa tezitra izy."},{"question":"HEESTII Kaa doortay khayrkaa","answer":"Qurux badanidaayeeQiimo weeynidaayeeQalbiguna ku jecelaaQawlkaadu waa dahabAan la quurikarinineeAla qaalisanidaaKaa doortay QayrkaaLaabteeydaan kugu qorayIla qaybso noloshooKalgaceeylka ila qaadAla qumanidaayeeQaayo weeynidaayeeMa qof kula midaa jiraNiyadeeyda qaadooQancisay nafteeydeeMa qof kula midaa jiraAla qaalisanidaaKaa doortay QayrkaaLaabteeydaan kugu qorayIla qaybso noloshooKalgaceeylka ila qabo"},{"question":" Quantos corações tem um polvo?","answer":"Os polvos possuem 3 corações. A presença dos três corações no polvo desempenha um papel fundamental. Por um lado, a capacidade de aumentar ou diminuir seu volume de sangue os ajuda especialmente ao caçar suas presas ou ao fugir de um predador.Por outro lado, os polvos geralmente preferem o fundo do mar, que muitas vezes é carente de oxigênio. Entretanto, suas brânquias são altamente eficientes em absorver o pouco oxigênio que possa haver, ainda mais que as dos peixes, permitindo-lhes o acesso às presas que outros animais marinhos não podem alcançar.A tudo isso, devemos acrescentar que os animais aquáticos estão sujeitos a uma pressão maior do que os que habitam os ecossistemas terrestres.O fato de o polvo possuir 3 corações faz com que seu organismo se adapte bem ao ecossistema marinho e possa sobreviver como espécie."},{"question":"بدات سورة الشعراء بعد البسملة بثلاثة ديال الحروف هي..؟","answer":"طسم"},{"question":"संसारको सबैभन्दा फोहोरो नोट कुन देशको छ?","answer":"ताइवानमा संसारको सबैभन्दा फोहोरो नोट छ।"},{"question":"অনুচ্ছেদটি পড় এবং প্রশ্নের উত্তর দাওএকটি কেক সেঁকতে ময়দা, ডিম, লবণ, মশলা তৈরির জন্য চিনি, ব্যাটার তৈরির জন্য পানি, চকোলেট এবং ফ্রস্টিং প্রয়োজন হয়।প্রশ্নএকটি কেক বেক করতে কি কি উপাদান প্রয়োজন","answer":"ময়দা, ডিম, লবণ, চিনি, পানি, চকোলেট, ফ্রস্টিং"},{"question":"O que implica o 'Despacho de Redesignação de Audiência'?","answer":"'Despacho de Redesignação de Audiência' é a ordem do juiz para remarcar uma audiência previamente agendada para outra data ou hora."},{"question":"วันนี้ยิ้มหรือยัง","answer":"ยิ้มแล้ว"},{"question":"මනෝවිද්‍යාව යනු කුමක්ද?","answer":"මනෝවිද්‍යාව යනු සිතුවිලි මෙන් ම විඥානික සහ අවිඥානික අත්දැකීම්වල සියලු අංග ආශ්‍රය කරගත් හැසිරීම සහ මනස පිළිබඳ විද්‍යාවයි. එය පොදු මූලධර්ම ගොඩනැගීම සහ විශේෂ සිද්ධි පර්යේෂණය මගින් පුද්ගලයින් සහ කණ්ඩායම් තේරුම් ගැනීමට උත්සාහ කරන ශාස්ත්‍රීය පුහුණුවක් සහ සමාජ විද්‍යාවකි."},{"question":"王菲有什麼代表作品？","answer":"《容易受傷的女人》、《我願意》、《紅豆》、《Eyes on Me》、《匆匆那年》等歌曲。"},{"question":"Awọn ọdọ Naijria yoo tun jade ṣewọde lẹẹkan si i","answer":"Aarẹ ile igbimọ aṣofin agba,  Ahmad Lawan, ti sọ pe awọn ọdọ orilẹ-ede yii yoo tun ya jade lẹẹkan si i, lati fẹhonu han, bẹẹ ni yoo lagbara ju tatẹyinwa lo, ti ipese iṣẹ lọpọ yanturu ko ba tete bẹrẹ bayii.Ana Monde, ọjọ Aje, lasiko ti minisita fun iṣẹ ọgbin ati idagbasoke igberiko wa siwaju awọn ọmọ ile igbimọ aṣofin lati ṣe atotonu lori bo ṣe fẹẹ nawo ninu eto iṣuna owo lọdun 2021, ni olori ile igbimọ aṣofin agba yii pe akiyesi ọhun.O ni o ṣe pataki ki ijọba, awọn aṣofin atawọn mi-in ti ọrọ kan gbiyanju lati pese iṣẹ lọpọ yanturu fun awọn ọdọ, nitori iṣẹ ọfiisi ati iṣẹ epo ko fẹẹ ka awọn eeyan orilẹ-ede yii mọ, paapaa awọn ọdọ to nilo iṣẹ.Bakan naa lo fi kun un pe eto iṣuna owo fọdun 2021 ti kaluku wa n ṣe atotonu lori bi yoo ti ṣe na an yii loju awọn aṣofin gbọdọ ni eto ipese iṣẹ f’awọn ọdọ ninu, ki iwọde mi-in ma tun bẹ silẹ laipẹ ọjọ.Lawan sọ pe, iwọde tawọn ọdọ ṣe kọja yii, gbogbo aye pata lo gbọ ohun wọn, ti wọn si ri i pe ootọ pọnbele loun ti wọn n beere fun, bo tilẹ jẹ pe awọn janduku alainikanṣe kan fi iwa aitọ da iwọde ọhun ru nigbẹyin.O ni, asiko niyi lati tete pese silẹ fun wọn, ki wọn ma tun lọ jade lẹẹkan si i."},{"question":"Dokończ następujący akapit: Wojciech Jerzy Has urodził się 1 kwietnia 1925 w Krakowie jako syn krakowskiego restauratora. Podczas niemieckiej okupacji ziem polskich","answer":"studiował w Szkole Handlowej w Krakowie, a gdy ta została rozwiązana w 1943 – w Szkole Przemysłu Artystycznego, w rzeczywistości zakonspirowanej Akademii Sztuk Pięknych. Po zakończeniu II wojny światowej Has kontynuował naukę w ponownie zalegalizowanej Akademii Sztuk Pięknych. W grudniu 1945 zapisał się również na Kurs Przeszkolenia Filmowego, którego kierownikiem mianowany został Stanisław Furmanik. W ramach zajęć Has miał okazję obejrzeć szereg filmów przechwyconych przez Antoniego Bohdziewicza z hitlerowskiego biura propagandy \\"Film und Propaganda\\", wśród nich \\"Ludzi za mgłą\\" (1938) Marcela Carné, \\"Jej pierwszego balu\\" (1937) Juliena Duviviera, \\"Paracelsusa\\" (1943) Georga Wilhelma Pabsta oraz \\"Iwana Groźnego\\" (1944) Siergieja Eisensteina. W 1946 został asystentem operatora Polskiej Kroniki Filmowej, Jarosława Brzozowskiego, przy filmie \\"Skroplone powietrze\\" (1946). 4 lipca 1946 ukończył Kurs Przeszkolenia Filmowego."},{"question":"Layaajọ ayẹyẹ ọdun Ominira, Akeredolu dariji ẹlẹwọn mẹrinlelogoji","answer":"Lasiko to n sami ayẹyẹ ayajọ Ominira tọdun yii, ẹlẹwọn bii mẹrinlelogoji ni wọn ti ri idariji gba lati ọdọ Gomina ipinlẹ Ondo, Rotimi Akeredolu.Ni ibamu pẹlu atẹjade ti Akọwe iroyin rẹ, Richard Ọlabọde, fi ṣọwọ sawọn oniroyin lọjọ Ẹti, Furaidee, ọsẹ yii, o ni awọn ẹlẹwọn mejidinlogun ni wọn gba idande patapata, nigba ti Arakunrin tun yi idajọ awọn mẹrindinlọgbọn mi-in ti wọn ti dajọ iku fun pada si ẹwọn gbere.O ni Akeredolu siju aanu wo awọn ẹlẹwọn ọhun latari ayipada rere ti wọn ri ninu aye wọn laarin asiko ti wọn fi wa ninu ọgba ẹwọn ti wọn fi wọn si.Igbesẹ yii lo ni o wa ni ibamu pẹlu ila kin-in-ni, abala igba le mejila (212), ninu iwe ofin Naijiria ti ọdun 1999.Lẹyin eyi lo rọ awọn ẹlẹwọn naa lati takete si iwa ọdaran, ki wọn si maa yago fun ohunkohun to le mu wọn ṣi anfaani ti ijọba fun wọn lo."},{"question":"Jawab soalan berikut. Dari manakah istilah Zaman Kelam berasal?","answer":"Sarjana Francesco Petrarca, juga dikenali sebagai \\"Bapa Humanisme\\" ialah tokoh pertama yang memikirkan idea \\"Zaman Kelam\\" "},{"question":"قم بتلخيص المقال التالي: الخطوة الأولى لارتداء قبعة راعي البقر بشكل صحيح هي التأكد من أن مقاس القبعة المناسب وتناسب رأسك بشكل صحيح. يجب أن تكون قبعات رعاة البقر مُحكمة حول رأسك. إذا كنت تشتري واحدة، فاعرف حجم قبعتك في وقت مبكر ولكن جرب القبعة أيضًا قبل شرائها. قد يكون لديك بالفعل قبعة كبيرة قليلًا لكنها ليست كبيرة بما يكفي بحيث ترغب في الحصول على مقاس أصغر. يمكنك إصلاح هذا. يمكنك شراء شريط الرغوة المصنوع خصيصًا لوضعه داخل القبعات لجعلها أضيق. بناءً على ما تحتاجه، وشكل رأسك، يمكنك إما وضع هذه الرغوة حول القبعة بشكل كامل أو يمكنك وضع القليل في الأمام والخلف أو على الجانبين فقط، أو حتى في المقدمة فقط أو في الخلف فقط.  اعرف مكان البقعة الفضفاضة في قبعتك. إذا كانت القبعة بأكملها منخفضة للغاية على رأسك، فربما تريد أن تضع بعضًا من رغوة التحجيم حول القبعة بأكملها. يجب أن يكون هناك رباط حول الجزء الداخلي من القبعة بحيث يمكنك قلبه لأعلى ووضع شريط الرغوة أسفله. ثم تقلب الرباط لأسفل قبل ارتداء القبعة. لديك الكثير من الخيارات عندما يتعلق الأمر بقبعات رعاة البقر.خيارات الخامات الرئيسية تتكون من الُّلباد (يُصنع من فرو حيوان القندس أو الأرنب)، والجلود، والقش. القبعات المصنوعة من الُّلباد تكون مُدفئة أكثر لذا تُرتدى أكثر في المواسم الباردة. قبعات القش أفضل للبقاء منتعشًا خلال الأيام الحارة. معظم قبعات رعاة البقر يمكن أن تكون قابلة للتعديل إلى شكل معين عن طريق ثنيها بلطف والضغط عليها. كيفية عمل ذلك بالضبط يعتمد على مادة القبعة نفسها. أنت تريد أن يكون الجزء الأمامي والخلفي من الحافة مسطحًا إلى حد ما. اثن الجانبان حتى يبرزا قليلًا. لا تثنيهما بإحكام شديد. يمكنك أيضًا تحجيم جانبي تاج القبعة بلطف. لا توجد أدوات مطلوبة لهذا الغرض. ما عليك سوى استخدام يديك..","answer":"هذا تلخيص للمقال: احصل على المقاس الصحيح. عدّل قبعتك الحالية لتكون مناسبة للارتداء بشكل أفضل. اختر القبعة الصحيحة. شكِّل قبعتك."},{"question":"\\"Адам даңк үчүн\\" - деген макал-лакапты улантып берчи?","answer":"Сиз суранган макал-лакап мындай болушу мүмкүн \\"Адам даңк үчүн от менен сууга кирет.\\""},{"question":"x=−3 のとき 2x+5 の値を求めなさい","answer":"x=−3 のときの 2x+5 の値を求めると、以下のようになります:2*(-3) + 5 = -6 + 5 = -1したがって、2x+5 の値は -1 です。"},{"question":"สร้างรูปแบบที่ซับซ้อนกว่าของประโยคนี้ บัตร Oyster เริ่มเปิดตัวในปี 2003 เพื่อความสะดวกในการถือบัตรท่องเที่ยวแบบตั๋วฤดูกาล","answer":"รูปแบบที่ซับซ้อนกว่าของประโยคคือ \\"บัตร Oyster เปิดตัวในปี 2003 เพื่อความสะดวกในการถือบัตรท่องเที่ยวประเภทฤดูกาล ซึ่งรับได้ทั้งในบริการรถไฟใต้ดินและรถไฟแห่งชาติในลอนดอนประเทศอังกฤษ\\""},{"question":"Sheeg mid kamid ah nabiga (NNKH) eedooyinkiisa oo Dhimatay iyadoo aan islaamin?","answer":"Waa Maymuuna Bintu Cabdi Mudalib."},{"question":"ചോദ്യം: കേരളത്തിലെ ഹിൽ സ്റ്റേഷൻ മൂന്നാറിനെ കുറിച്ച് എഴുതുക? ഉത്തരം:","answer":"മൂന്ന് ആറുകളായ മുതിരപ്പുഴ, നല്ലതണ്ണി, കുണ്ടള എന്നിവയുടെ സംഗമസ്ഥാനമാണ് മൂന്നാര്‍. തെക്കേ ഇന്ത്യയിലെ ബ്രിട്ടീഷ് ഭരണാധികാരികളുടെ വേനല്‍ക്കാല സുഖവാസ കേന്ദ്രമായിരുന്നു മൂന്നാര്‍. വിശാലമായ തേയിലത്തോട്ടങ്ങള്‍, മനോഹരമായ ചെറു പട്ടണങ്ങള്‍, വളഞ്ഞുയര്‍ന്നും താഴ്ന്നും പോവുന്ന പാതകള്‍, അവധി ആഘോഷത്തിന് യോജിച്ച സൗകര്യങ്ങള്‍ എന്നിങ്ങനെ മൂന്നാര്‍ ഇന്ന് ഏറെ ജനകീയമായ വിനോദ സഞ്ചാര കേന്ദ്രമാണ്. തെക്കേയിന്ത്യയിലെ ഏറ്റവും ഉയര്‍ന്ന കൊടുമുടിയായ ആനമുടി, 2695 മീറ്റര്‍, മൂന്നാറിനടുത്താണ്."},{"question":"வினா:சருமத்தின் மீதுள்ள நிறத்தின் காரணம்","answer":"விடை: மெலானின்"},{"question":"CINNAMON ROLLS 😋Ingredients:","answer":"CINNAMON 😋 ROLESIngredients:2 cups flour1 teaspoon baking powder1 pinch of salt90g of butter in cubes2/3 cups cow's milk60g butter3 tablespoons brown sugar1 teaspoon cinnamon1 cup glass sugar1 teaspoon waterPreparation:1. Preheat the oven to 200°C.2. Mix the cooked flour with the baking powder and salt.3. Add butter in cubes and the gently rub it with the flour until"},{"question":"Kung adunay manuktok sa pultahan, unsay imong itubag?","answer":"“Kinsa na?”"},{"question":"\\"Ny tantaran'i Madagasikara maoderina dia voamariky ny fiovana ara-politika sy ara-tsosialy. Tao anatin'ny folo taona farany, niatrika fanamby ara-toekarena sy tetezamita demokratika ny firenena, ary niaro ny fomban-drazana tsy manam-paharoa.\\"Inona avy ireo nanamarika ny tantaran’i Madagasikara vao haingana no voalaza ao amin’ny andalana teo aloha?","answer":"Ny andalana teo aloha dia miresaka momba ny fiovana ara-politika sy ara-tsosialy, ny fanamby ara-toekarena, ny tetezamita demokratika ary ny fiarovana ny fomban-drazana eto Madagasikara."},{"question":"Noma ngabe wayediniwe, naye engafuni ngikugane, kodwa ubabangendlela achaza, washweleza ngayo, nomufi weneliswa.Kodwa wawutholaphi lo shevu owawuthi ungijuqa ngawo?Ngicela ungabe usayikhuluma leyo ndaba, ingenza ngibe namahloniamangalisayo.Abahlola leliya tiye bathi ukuba ngake ngaliqhabula kanye, ingqakalayayiyobheka ezulwini.Ngasuke ngavukwa inzondo embi, idalwa ukuthi uSipho wayefe ngenxayakho.1. Chaza kafishane le ndaba eyayibangela uThenjiwe amahloni uma uDumisaniekhuluma ngayo.","answer":"Yindaba ethi wayewuthathephi uThenjiwe ushevu ayefuna ukubulala ngawouDumisani ukuze agweme ukuba amngene. "},{"question":"Ata ilẹ̀","answer":"Ata ilẹ̀ (Látìnì: Zingiber officinale) jẹ́ ohun ọ̀gbìn tí ó ń tinú ilẹ̀ wù tàbí jáde. Wọ́n máa ń lòó lọ́pọ̀ ìgbà fún ohun èlò ìsebẹ̀, tàbí oògùn tàbí àgbo. Ó tún jẹ́ ọ̀kan lára àwọn ohun ọ̀gbìn tí kìí tètè kú tí ó sì ma ń pẹ́ kí ó tó bàjẹ́. Ọdọọdún ni ata ilẹ̀ máa ń wù lójú ibi tí wọ́n bá gbìn-ín sí tí wọ́n sì ti kórè e rẹ̀. Nígbà tí ata ilẹ̀ bá ń wù, ó máa ń ga tó ìwọ̀n Mítà kan tí ó sì máa ń ní èwe sọ́ọ́rọ́ tí ewé náà máa ń rí bí ìdá olójú méjì. Àwọn ewé rẹ̀ ma ń dì pọ̀ láti ilẹ̀ ni tí wọn yóò sì ya ẹ̀ka tí wọ́n bá dókè tán.Ẹ̀wẹ̀, àww olómi aró yẹ́lò àti pọ́pù ni ewé rẹ̀ máa ń ní."},{"question":"ukimwi ni nin","answer":"ukimwi kirefu chake ni ukosefu wa kinga mwilini ugongonjwa huu huanza kwa kunyemelea seli hai nyeupe za damu na  badaeseli hizo hufeli na kusabasha mwili kupata magonjwa mengine nyemelezi kama vile homa za mara kwa mara kifua kikuu kutapikaa kuharisha nakazrika "},{"question":"No anime Naruto, quem é Rock Lee?","answer":"Rock Lee é um ninja da Vila da Folha que não pode usar ninjutsu ou genjutsu, mas compensa com treinamento árduo e habilidades de taijutsu. Ele é conhecido por suas sobrancelhas espessas e seu estilo de luta dedicado."},{"question":"What is the Turing test?","answer":"The Turing test is a test of a machine’s ability to exhibit intelligent behavior equivalent to, or indistinguishable from, that of a human."},{"question":"Na piscicultura, costumam-se usar larvas de Artemia (crustáceo) para alimentar larvas de peixes. Ovos de Artemia são colocados em garrafas com água salgada e, sob condições ótimas de temperatura, luz e oxigênio, eles eclodem, liberando suas larvas, também conhecidas como náuplios. Para recolher os náuplios, coloca-se uma lâmpada branca fluorescente na boca da garrafa e estes começam a subir em direção ao gargalo. Esse comportamento das artêmias é chamado de:a) geotropismo positivo.b) fototropismo positivo.c) hidrotropismo negativo.d) termotropismo negativo.e) quimiotropismo negativo.","answer":"A resposta correcta é a alternativa: b) fototropismo positivo."},{"question":"Saan matatagpuan ang pinakamabilis na tren sa buong mundo?","answer":"Sa ngayon, matatagpuan sa Shanghai, China ang Shanghai Maglev o Shanghai Transrapid, ang pinakamabilis na tren sa buong mundo. May maximum na bilis ito na 431 na kilometro kada oras. Dahil sa bilis nito, kailangan lamang nito ng mahigit-kumulang walong minuto upang makapaglakbay ng 30 na kilometro."},{"question":"Ẹgbẹ okunkun lawọn eleyii n ṣe n’Ikorodu, kọmiṣanna ọlọpaa lo mu wọn","answer":"Ọwọ ọlọpa ti tẹ marun-un lara awọn gende to n ṣe ẹgbẹ okunkun niluu Ikorodu. Alẹ Ọjọbọ, Tọsidee, ọsẹ yii, lọwọ ba wọn, wọn lawọn ọmọ yii wa lara awọn to n da omi alaafia ilu naa ru, ti wọn n ko awọn araalu laya soke.Orukọ wọn ni Babatunde Tanimọwo, ẹni ọdun mọkanlelogoji, Kabiru Atanda, ẹni ọgbọn ọdun, Ibrahim Abubakri, ẹni ọdun mọkandinlọgbọn, Gbọlahan Ọladimeji, ẹni ọdun mẹẹẹdọgbọn, ẹni to ṣikarun-un,  tọjọ-ori ẹ si kere ju lọ ni Wasiu Rafiu, ẹni ọdun mọkandinlogun.Kọmiṣanna ọlọpaa ni borukọ Ikorodu ati agbegbe rẹ ṣe n ro gbọnmọgbọnmọ ninu iroyin lasiko yii, to si jẹ pe iro naa ki i ṣe iro rere, iro iwa janduku, ṣiṣe ẹgbẹ okunkun, iwa ọdaran ati itajẹsilẹ, lo mu koun funra oun ko awọn ikọ ọlọpaa ọtẹlẹmuyẹ sodi lọ sagbegbe ọhun.Ọgbẹni Olumuyiwa Adejọbi to jẹ Alukoro ileeṣẹ ọlọpaa Eko sọ f’ALAROYE ninu atẹjade to fi ṣọwọ lori iṣẹlẹ ọhun sọ̣ pe ninu awọn ile pako to wa laduugbo Agric ni wọn ti kẹẹfin awọn ọmọ ẹlẹgbẹ okunkun yii, ti wọn fi ko wọn.Wọn ba awọn nnkan ija bii ada, aake, ọbẹ aṣooro, ẹgba (koboko), ninu awọn ile pako tawọn afurasi naa n gbe. Wọn ti wo awọn ile ọhun danu, wọn lawọn ọmọ ẹlẹgbẹ okunkun ti sọ ọpọ lara awọn ile naa di ibuba wọn, wọn tun palẹ awọn okuta ati igi ti wọn lawọn kan gbe di oju ọna agbegbe naa, titi kan awọn ṣọọbu ati kanta tawọn ọlọja kan fi di titi to yẹ ki mọto gba kọja.Bi Adejọbi ṣe wi, awọn afurasi tọwọ ba yii ti jẹwọ pe ẹlẹgbẹ okunkun lawọn, kọmiṣanna si ti ni ki wọn fi wọn ṣọwọ si ẹka awọn ọtẹlẹmuyẹ ni Panti, Yaba, ki wọn le ran awọn agbofinro lọwọ ninu iwadii wọn, ki wọn too taari wọn siwaju adajọ laipẹ.Odumosu tun ni lori ọrọ iwa ọdaran lagbegbe Ikorodu yii, bina o ba tan laṣọ, ẹjẹ o ni i tan leeekanna loun maa fi ọrọ naa ṣe."},{"question":"Tichifunga kuti gore razvino i2023, Chevron ine makore mangani? Chevron inotsvaga nhoroondo yayo kumashure kuma1870s. Kambani iyi yakakura nekukurumidza mushure mekuparara kweStandard Oil nekutora makambani nekubatana nevamwe, ndokuzopedzisira yava imwe yeManun Sista aitonga indasitiri yepetroleum yepasi rose kubva pakati pema1940 kusvika kuma1970. Muna 1985, Socal yakabatana nePittsburgh-based Gulf Oil ikaitwazve seChevron; kambani ichangobva kubatanidzwa yakazobatanidzwa neTexaco muna 2001. Nhasi, Chevron inogadzira uye inotengesa mafuta, mafuta ekuzora, additives, uye petrochemicals, kunyanya muWestern North America, U.S. Gulf Coast, Southeast Asia, South Korea neAustralia. Muna 2018, kambani yakagadzira avhareji ye791,000 mbiya dzemafuta-yakaenzana pazuva muUnited States.","answer":"Nekuti gore razvino ndi2023 uye Chevron inoteedzera nhoroondo yayo kumashure kuma1870s, Chevron ingangoita pakati pemakore 143 ne153 ekuzvarwa."},{"question":"'Pho, uRebecca lona nazana kuphi naye?''Sabonana nje naye khona lapha ezimotweni engangoba ngazengamnikeza nenye impahla yami ukuba aye kongihlanzela yona elondolo.Angithi usebenza khona elondolo?''Yebo-bo, khona kwakunjalo,' kuphendula uMaMkhwani ngokungabazaeqhubeka ebuza ethi, 'Konje uthi benibonana kuphi naye?''Kuthangi, ngoLwesihlanu. Ma.''Wewu, inkinga-ke leyo Ndodana ongitshela yona. Okokuqala nje ngizocelaukwazi ukuthi ngase kube usujahe kakhulu yini Ndodana.''Qha, khona bengingajahile kangako ngoba yiSonto namhlanjena, namikangisebenzi.'1. Xoxa ngovuthondaba olutholakala kule ndatshana ngamaphuzuAMATHATHU.","answer":"Amaphuzu AMATHATHU kwalandelayo: URoy uhlangana noRebecca okwesibili esiteshini. Uyahamba naye uyomkhombisa lapho agqiba khona imali.  Umnikeza imiyalelo yokuthi ayisebenzise kanjani imali. Ubuye amnike nemiyalelo yokuthi aziphathe kanjani."},{"question":"संयुक्त राष्ट्र संघ के हो?","answer":"संयुक्त राष्ट्र संघ (यूएन) एक अन्तरसरकारी संस्था हो जसको उद्देश्य भनेको अन्तर्राष्ट्रिय शान्ति र सुरक्षा कायम राख्नु, राष्ट्रहरू बीच मैत्रीपूर्ण सम्बन्ध विकास गर्नु, अन्तर्राष्ट्रिय सहयोग प्राप्त गर्नु र सरकारहरूको कार्यहरू मिलाउन केन्द्रको रूपमा सेवा गर्नु हो। यो विश्वको सबैभन्दा ठूलो अन्तर्राष्ट्रिय संस्था हो। यूएनको मुख्यालय न्यूयोर्क शहरमा छ (संयुक्त राज्यमा, तर केहि बाह्य विशेषाधिकारहरू सहित), र संगठनका अन्य कार्यालयहरू जेनेभा, नैरोबी, भियना र हेगमा छन्, जहाँ अन्तर्राष्ट्रिय न्यायालयको मुख्यालय छ।संयुक्त राष्ट्र द्वितीय विश्वयुद्ध पछि भविष्यको विश्व युद्ध रोक्नको लागि स्थापित भएको थियो र लीग अफ नेसन्सलाई सफल बनायो, जसलाई अप्रभावी रूपमा चित्रण गरिएको थियो। २५ अप्रिल १९४५ मा, ५० राष्ट्रहरूले सान फ्रान्सिस्को, क्यालिफोर्नियामा एक सम्मेलनको लागि भेला भए र २५ जुन 1945 मा स्वीकृत भएको संयुक्त राष्ट्र बडापत्रको मस्यौदा तयार गर्न थाले। यो चार्टर २४ अक्टोबर १९४५ मा लागू भयो, जब संयुक्त राष्ट्रले सञ्चालन सुरु गर्यो। यसको बडापत्रले परिभाषित गरे अनुसार, संगठनका उद्देश्यहरूमा अन्तर्राष्ट्रिय शान्ति र सुरक्षा कायम राख्ने, मानवअधिकारको रक्षा गर्ने, मानवीय सहायता प्रदान गर्ने, दिगो विकासको प्रवर्द्धन गर्ने र अन्तर्राष्ट्रिय कानूनको पालना गर्ने समावेश छ। यसको स्थापनामा, संयुक्त राष्ट्रको ५१ सदस्य राष्ट्रहरू थिए; २९२३ को रूपमा, यसमा १९३ छन् - लगभग सबै विश्वका सार्वभौम राज्यहरू।संयुक्त राज्य अमेरिका र सोभियत संघ र तिनीहरूका सम्बन्धित सहयोगीहरू बीचको शीत युद्धको तनावको कारणले गर्दा प्रारम्भिक दशकहरूमा विश्व शान्तिको संरक्षण गर्ने संगठनको मिशन जटिल थियो। यसको मिशनले मुख्य रूपमा निहत्था सैन्य पर्यवेक्षकहरू र हल्का सशस्त्र सेनाहरूको प्रावधान समावेश गरेको छ जुन मुख्य रूपमा निगरानी, ​​रिपोर्टिङ, र आत्मविश्वास-निर्माण भूमिकाहरूको लागि चार्ज गरिएको छ। १९६० को दशकमा व्यापक विनिवेशीकरण पछि संयुक्त राष्ट्रको सदस्यता उल्लेखनीय रूपमा बढ्यो। त्यसबेलादेखि, ८० भूतपूर्व उपनिवेशहरूले स्वतन्त्रता प्राप्त गरिसकेका छन्, जसमा ट्रस्टीशिप काउन्सिलद्वारा निगरानी गरिएको ११ ट्रस्ट क्षेत्रहरू समावेश छन्। १९७० सम्ममा, आर्थिक र सामाजिक विकास कार्यक्रमहरूको लागि संयुक्त राष्ट्रको बजेटले शान्ति स्थापनामा खर्च गरेको भन्दा धेरै थियो। १९९१ मा शीतयुद्धको अन्त्य पछि, संयुक्त राष्ट्रले विभिन्न जटिल कार्यहरू गर्दै आफ्नो क्षेत्रीय कार्यहरू सार्यो र विस्तार गर्यो।संयुक्त राष्ट्र संघका छवटा प्रमुख परिचालन संस्थाहरू छन्: महासभा, सुरक्षा परिषद्, आर्थिक तथा सामाजिक परिषद्, अन्तर्राष्ट्रिय न्यायालय, संयुक्त राष्ट्र सचिवालय, र ट्रस्टीशिप काउन्सिल, यद्यपि ट्रस्टीशिप काउन्सिल १९९४ देखि निष्क्रिय छ। संयुक्त राष्ट्र प्रणाली विश्व बैंक समूह, विश्व स्वास्थ्य संगठन, विश्व खाद्य कार्यक्रम, युनेस्को र युनिसेफ सहित धेरै विशेष एजेन्सीहरू, कोषहरू र कार्यक्रमहरू समावेश छन्। थप रूपमा, गैर-सरकारी संस्थाहरूलाई आर्थिक र सामाजिक परिषद् र अन्य निकायहरूसँग परामर्शको स्थिति प्रदान गर्न सकिन्छ।"},{"question":"கீழே கொடுக்கப்பட்டுள்ள பொருட்களைவைத்து வாழைப்பழ பணியாரம் கார சட்னி செய்வது எப்படி?தேவையான பொருட்கள்:5 வாழைப்பழம்150 கிராம் மைதா மாவு150 கிராம் கோதுமை மாவு150 கிராம் சர்க்கரை1 பெரிய வெங்காயம்1 சின்ன வெங்காயம்3 தக்காளி3 துண்டு தேங்காய்1 பச்சை மிளகாய்3 காய்ந்த மிளகாய்1 பூண்டு பல்½ தேக்கரண்டி கடுகு½ தேக்கரண்டி ஏலக்காய் தூள்½ தேக்கரண்டி பேக்கிங் பவுடர்சிறிதளவு கருவேப்பிலைதேவையான அளவு எண்ணெய்தேவையான அளவு நெய்தேவையான அளவு உப்பு","answer":"செய்முறை:1. முதலில் வெங்காயம், தக்காளி, பச்சை மிளகாய், தேங்காய், பூண்டு, மற்றும் வாழைப்பழத்தை தயார் செய்து வைத்து கொள்ளவும்.2. அடுத்து ஒரு பாத்திரத்தை மிதமான சூட்டில் அடுப்பில் வைத்து அதில் ஒரு மேஜைக்கரண்டி அளவு எண்ணெய் ஊற்றி எண்ணெய்யை சுட வைக்கவும்.3. எண்ணெய் சுட்ட பின் அதில் நாம் பொடியாக நறுக்கி வைத்திருக்கும் வெங்காயத்தை போட்டு வெங்காயம் கண்ணாடி பதம் வரும் வரை அதை வதக்கவும்.4. வெங்காயம் கண்ணாடி பதம் வந்ததும் அதில் நாம் நறுக்கி வைத்திருக்கும் தேங்காய், பச்சை மிளகாய், பூண்டு, மற்றும் கருவேப்பிலையை போட்டு அதை நன்கு வதக்கவும்.5. பின்பு அதில் நாம் நறுக்கி வைத்திருக்கும் தக்காளி, 2 காய்ந்த மிளகாய், மற்றும் தேவையான அளவு உப்பு சேர்த்து தக்காளி நன்கு வதங்கும் வரை அதை வதக்கவும்.6. தக்காளி நன்கு வதங்கியவுடன் அடுப்பை அணைத்து விட்டு அதை அடுப்பிலிருந்து கீழே இறக்கி வைத்து சிறிது நேரம் ஆற விட்டு பின்பு அதை ஒரு மிக்ஸி ஜாரில் போட்டு நன்கு அரைத்து வைத்து கொள்ளவும்.7. பிறகு ஒரு பாத்திரத்தை மிதமான சூட்டில் அடுப்பில் வைத்து அதில் ஒரு மேஜைக்கரண்டி அளவு எண்ணெய் சேர்த்து அதை சுட வைக்கவும்.8. எண்ணெய் சுட்ட பின் அதில் கடுகை போட்டு கடுகு வெடித்தவுடன் அதில் நாம் பொடியாக நறுக்கி வைத்திருக்கும் சின்ன வெங்காயத்தை போட்டு அது சிறிது நிறம் மாறும் வரை அதை வதக்கவும்.9. வெங்காயம் சிறிது நிறம் மாறிய உடன் அதில் ஒரு காய்ந்த மிளகாய் மற்றும் சிறிதளவு கருவேப்பிலையை போட்டு ஒரு கிளறு கிளறி அதை எடுத்து நாம் அரைத்து வைத்திருக்கும் சட்னியில் சேர்த்து அதை நன்கு கலந்து விடவும்.10. இப்பொழுது அவரவர் விருப்பத்திற்கு ஏற்ப சர்க்கரை மற்றும் ஏலக்காய் தூளை ஒரு மிக்ஸி ஜாரில் கொட்டி அதை நன்கு அரைத்து விடவும்.11. பின்பு வாழைப்பழத்தை சிறு சிறு துண்டுகளாக்கி அதில் போட்டு அதை நன்கு அரைத்து கொள்ளவும். (தேவைப்பட்டால் அதில் சிறிதளவு தண்ணீர் தெளித்து கொள்ளவும்.)12. அடுத்து அதில் மைதா மாவு, கோதுமை மாவு, மற்றும் நெய்யை சேர்த்து தேவைப்பட்டால் தண்ணீர் ஊற்றி அதை நன்கு அரைக்கவும். (தண்ணீர் அதிகமாக சேர்த்து விடக்கூடாது அரைக்கும் போது அவ்வப்போது பார்த்து அளவோடு சேர்த்து கொள்ளவும்.)13. பிறகு பேக்கிங் பவுடரில் ஒரு மேஜைக்கரண்டி அளவு தண்ணீர் சேர்த்து அதை நன்கு கரைத்து அதில் சேர்த்து மீண்டும் ஒரு சுற்று சுற்றிய பின் அதை ஒரு பாத்திரத்திற்கு மாற்றி சுமார் 30 லிருந்து 40 நிமிடம் வரை ஊற விடவும்.14. மாவு ஊறுவதற்குல் பணியார சட்டியை மிதமான சூட்டில் அடுப்பில் வைத்து அதில் இருக்கும் குழிகளில் எண்ணெய்யை ஊற்றி அதை சுட வைக்கவும். (நெய்யை விரும்புவர்கள் எண்ணெய்க்கு பதிலாக அதில் நெய்யை சேர்த்து கொள்ளலாம்.)15. எண்ணெய் சுட்ட பின் அதில் நாம் ஊற வைத்திருக்கும் மாவை ஒரு கரண்டியின் மூலம் எடுத்து அதை ஒவ்வொரு குழியிலும் பக்குவமாக ஊற்றி ஒரு மூடியைப் போட்டு மூடி பணியாரம் வெந்து மேலே வரும் வரை அதை வேக விடவும்.16. பணியாரம் வெந்து மேலே வந்ததும் அதை திருப்பி போட்டு சிறிது நேரம் வேக விட்டு அதை எடுத்து ஒரு தட்டில் வைத்து சுட சுட நாம் செய்து வைத்திருக்கும் கார சட்னியுடன் அதை பரிமாறவும்.17. இப்பொழுது உங்கள் சூடான, சுவையான மற்றும் மிகவும் மிருதுவான வாழைப்பழ பணியாரம் மற்றும் கார சட்னி தயார். இதை கட்டாயம் உங்கள் வீட்டில் செய்து பார்த்து உங்கள் குடும்பத்தாருடன் சேர்ந்து சுவைத்து மகிழுங்கள்."},{"question":"தொலை நோக்கியை முதலில் கண்டுபிடித்தவர் யார்?","answer":"டச்சு நாட்டு மூக்குக் கண்ணாடி தயாரிப்பாளரான 'ஹேன்ஸ் லிப்பெர்ஷை' என்பவர்தான் 1608ம் ஆண்டில், வெற்றிகரமான முதல் ஒலி விலகலடையச் செய்யும் தொலைநோக்கியை உருவாக்கினார். ஒரு குழாயின் இரண்டு முனைகளிலும் வைக்கப் பட்ட இரண்டு கண்ணாடிகள் வழியாகப் பார்ப்பதன் மூலம், தூரத்தில் உள்ள பொருட்கள் பெரிதாகத் தோன்றுகின்றன என்பதை அவர் புரிந்து கொண்டார். இத்தாலிய விஞ்ஞானியான கலிலியோ கலிலீ என்பவரும் 1609ம் ஆண்டு வாக்கில், இரவு நேர வானத்தை ஆய்வு செய்வதற்காக, அதே போன்ற ஒரு தொலைநோக்கியை உப யோகித்துக் கொண்டிருந்தார். அவர் அதனை நிலாவின் மேற்பரப்பை வரைவதற்காக உபயோகித்து, வியாழன் கிரகத் தின் நான்கு நிலாக்களையும் கண்டுபிடித்தார்."},{"question":"'Wabonakala wesese nje Bheki namuhla?''Cha, Sifiso, ukuthi izolo ngike ngathola ithutshana lokuxoxa noTholi.''Uyazi ukuthi sengiyamazi uTholi lowo ukuthi ungumfelokazi wale emakhaya.''Umaze kanjani?''NgoZenze.''Wazana noZenze?''Baningi phela abajita engibaphethe mina mfowethu?''Manje uthi angenzenjani Sifiso?''Phela ayikho into ongayenza, ingani sengikutshelile ukuthi uTholi umfelokazi.''Sifiso, kulukhuni kabi ukuthi ngivele ngiyiyeke kanjalo indaba kaTholi. Angizenzi,ngisenkingeni enzima.''Noma ngabe inkinga yakho ingakanani ngeke ize ikwenze ukuba ufune ukuganwaumfelokazi. Bayamfuna futhi abafowabo bomkhwenyana. Uma uzisondeza kuTholiuzongena enkingeni ndoda.' Wathula uBheki amathe abuyela kwasifuba. Wezwaikhanda sengathi liyazimuka.'Ngiyezwa Sifiso.' Washo maqede wasuka wahamba uBhekani. Wabona ukuthiubethi uphuma ekuhluphekeni, kanti sengathi uphonseka kokukhulu. Wagcinaezitshele ukuthi akayeke manje ukuloku ekhuluma le ndaba noSifiso. Umqondowakhe wazicabangela uTholakele. Wahleka yedwa ebona lobuya buhle ngamehloengqondo. Wazitshela ukuthi kuyobe kungaqali ngaye ukushada nomfelokazi.Kwathi uma ecabanga ngoBhatomu wazitshela ukuthi uma bengahlanganakuyochitheka izishebo okungcono.Esacabanga ngaleyo nto, kwashaya isikhathi sokuphuma kwesikole. ZayakuBhekani. Wafica unina elele. Akabe esamvusa. Walungela ukuyohlangabezauTholakele. Nebala baficana endaweni yabo. Bahambisana.1. Omakhelwane bakaTholakele bamsiza kanjani uBhekani ngesikhathi elwanoBhatomu?","answer":"Bafika bezolamula ngesikhathi uBhekani elwa noBhatomu.  Amadoda axosha uBhatomu."},{"question":"Tohizo izao ohabolana izao : \\"  Tehin-kiho ampiakarana, tsy haingo fa tohan' aina \\" ","answer":"\\"  Tehin-kiho ampiakarana, tsy haingo fa tohan' aina \\" "},{"question":"வினா:கோள்களின் இயக்கத்தை கண்டுபிடித்தவர் யார் ?1.அன்னை தெரசா2.கெப்ளர்3.ரஷ்யர்கள்4.1860","answer":"விடை:கெப்ளர்"},{"question":"Atsakyk į klausimą: Kas yra Ryšių teorija pagal Claude Shannon?","answer":"Atsakymas: Tai matematinis modelis, aprašantis informacijos perdavimą nuo vieno taško iki kito."},{"question":"नेपालमा कृषि र खाद्य सुरक्षामा \\"जलवायु परिवर्तन\\" को प्रभाव बारे चर्चा गर्नुहोस्।","answer":"जलवायु परिवर्तनले बाली ढाँचा, जलस्रोत र खाद्य सुरक्षालाई असर गरेको छ, जसले नेपालको कृषिमा चुनौती खडा गरेको छ।"},{"question":"Ujabule sisi ngoba uvakashelwe umngani wakho izolo?Akukho kujabula engibe nakho Thabi. Ingani abantu basukebangikhumbuze indaba endala. Kodwa-ke umngani wami uzamile izolo.Kufanele ngibone uhleka kucishe kuvela elomhlathi impela.Vele uGugu unamahlaya. Angakuhlekisa ngisho ucashile.Ngethemba ukuthi akashongo ukuthi hamba lapha ekhaya. Uma eshonjalo, ngitshele ngiqale ukumzonda manje nje.Cha akashongo ukuthi angihambe. (Ambukisise) Into enhle naye kodwaungiphile iseluleko esincane.Besithini leso seluleko sisi. Yena uGugu akayiboni le ndaba yakhonoDumisani.Uhlupha ngoba awuzwa wena. UDumisani usemncane kabi Thabi.Okwesibili nami angikwazi ukuwezela uthando lomunye umuntukomunye.Ngiyayizwa le nto oyishoyo sisi. Into nje engiphethe kabi ukuzwa ukuthiungase usishiye lapha ekhaya. Lokho kungangiphatha kabi ngizengiyofa.Noma ngihambile phela ngingabuye ngifike nje nginivakashele.Kodwa umama yena uthini?Mayelana nani?Ngayo phela le ndaba.Cha abakasho lutho abadala.Ngiyakuhlebela nje sisi. Ngibezwile mina bethi kufanele ungahambi.Baze bagcizelela impela ukuthi uma uthi ucela ukuya ekhaya ngekebavume.Kulezi zinsuku Thabi kukhulunywa indaba yamalungelo. Nami-kengibona ukuthi yilungelo lami ukuba ngibuyele ekhaya uma engasekhoengangize ngaye lapha.1. Le ndawo okwenzeka kuyo lo mdlalo inomlando wesiko lokungenwa. Sekelalesi sitatimende ngephuzu ELILODWA.","answer":"phuzu ELILODWA kwalandelayo:• UMaNzuza watshela uThenjiwe ukuthi unolwazi ngaleli siko.• Lalilandelwa emizini eminingi endaweni.• Abantu abaningi endaweni babelazi leli siko njengoMondise."},{"question":"\\" කාර ගංගා \\" ලෙස අතීතයේදී හඳුන්වන ලද, ලංකාවේ ප්‍රසිද්ධ අතුගංගාව කුමක්ද ?","answer":"\\" කාර ගංගා \\" ලෙස අතීතයේදී හඳුන්වන ලද්දේ අඹන් ගඟ ය."},{"question":"Fan mooy gëblag réewum Hongrie?","answer":"Gëblag réewum Hongrie mu ngi tudd Budapest."},{"question":"Iyawo ile gbe oyun ọkunrin mi-in wale fọkọ ẹ n’Ibadan, o ni nitori baale oun ko le ṣe","answer":"Nibi ti ọpọ idile ti daru nitori ti ọkọ tabi iyawo n yan ale, nibẹ niyawo ile kan, Toyin Bello, ti loyun fún ọkunrin mi-in níta, ti ọkọ tó fẹ ẹ sile, Dọtun Bello, si mọ si i ṣugbọn ti wọn tun jọ n ba igbesi aye wọn lọ bii lọkọ laya.Lẹyin eyi naa, iyawo tun pẹjọ sí kootu ibilẹ Ile-Tuntun to wa laduugbo Mapo n’Ibadan pe ki ile-ẹjọ fopin si ibaṣepọ oun atọkunrin naa.Ṣugbọn nṣe lọkunrin naa tun bẹrẹ sí i bẹbẹ, o ni ki igbimọ awọn adajọ ba oun bẹ obinrin naa ko ma kọ oju oun soorun alẹ.Nigba to n rọ ile-ẹjọ lati fopin sí igbeyawo ọlọdun mẹrindinlogun (16) ọhun,  Toyin sọ pé ẹṣin inu iwe lọkọ oun, ko le ṣọkọ fobinrin rara ati pe odidi ọdun mẹwaa lo kan fi n sun bọlọku sẹgbẹẹ oun lasan ti i ki i ṣe ojuṣe to yẹ ki ojulowo akọ ṣe lori abo.Bakan naa lo ṣapejuwe ọkọ ẹ gẹgẹ bii alainilaari èèyàn, to jẹ pe oun loun gbọ bukaata rẹ ninu ile.Gẹgẹ bo ṣe sọ, “ọkọ mi kò le ṣe, nṣe ni mo lọọ loyun fún ọkunrin kan lati ita lati le gba a (ọkọ ẹ) silẹ lọwọ itiju ọrọ ti awọn eeyan n sọ pe ẹṣin inu iwe lasan ni.Bi mo ṣe n ba yin sọrọ yii, mo ti kuro ninu ile fun un, mo kuro ninu ile ti mo fowo ara mi kọ, mo n sun si ṣọọṣi bii ẹni ti ko nile lori.“Oluwa mi, mi o le wa pẹlu ọkunrin yii mọ,mo fẹ kẹ ẹ fopin si igbeyawo yii ko ba tiẹ jade ninu ile mi.”Ninu awijare tiẹ, Dọtun so pe loootọ loun ni ipenija ilera eyi ti ko jẹ ko ṣee ṣe foun lati fun obinrin loyun, eyi ni ko sì jẹ kí oun binu nigba tiyawo oun gbe oyun ale waa ka oun mọle.O waa rọ ile-ẹjọ lati ma ṣe gba ẹbẹ iyawo oun wọle, kaka bẹẹ, nṣe ni ki wọn ba oun bẹ ẹ ko jẹ ki awọn jọ maa ba ere aniyan awọn tẹsiwaju.Ṣugbọn ọrọ olupẹjọ ni wọn tẹle ni kootu pẹlu bi igbimọ awọn adajọ, labẹ akoso Oloye Henry Agbaje ṣe fopin sí igbeyawo ọlọdun mẹrindinlogun náà ,ti wọn si pa Dọtun laṣẹ lati jade kuro nile obinrin to ti di iyawo rẹ atijọ yii laarin ọjọ meje pere."},{"question":"A wace shekara aka yi kisan kiyashin Rwanda?","answer":"A shekarar 1994."},{"question":" A wani Hadisi Manzon Allah Sallallahu Alaihi Wa Sallama Ya ce:Salla a masallacinsa ya fi sallah a wani masallacin sau----amma ban da Masallaci Ka'aba mai alfarma .","answer":"(a) 100 (b) 1000 (c) 100000"},{"question":"සිංහල හෝඩියෙ හල් කළ නොහැකි අකුරු මොනවාද?","answer":"ඟඦඬඳඹළඅංඅඃ"},{"question":"यो आकाश किन निलो छ? तिमीलाई थाहा छ?","answer":"प्रकाशको स्क्यातरिङ्गले गर्दा आकाश निलो देखिन्छ।"},{"question":"दिए गए वाक्य का हिंदी में अनुवाद करें:\\"Tell the story of a character who discovers a pocket watch that allows them to travel ten minutes into the past, but only once a day.\\"","answer":"एक पात्र की कहानी सुनाएं जो एक पॉकेट घड़ी खोजता है जिससे उन्हें एक दिन में केवल एक बार दस मिनट पूर्व यात्रा करने की सुविधा है।"},{"question":"Gawai diraikan negeri mana? Pilih jawapan yang betul dari pilihan berikut.  A. Terengganu B. Kelantan C. Sabah D. Sarawak","answer":"Jawapannya ialah D. Sarawak. Gawai adalah perayaan sempena meraikan tamatnya musim menuai padi yang disambut setiap tahun di Sarawak pada 1 Jun."},{"question":"\\"Тоого чыктым, жазыны көрдүм.Айрылбаган балээни көрдүм\\"- табышмактын жандырмагы кандай?","answer":"Табышмактын жандырмагы -(көлөкө)."},{"question":"Isaky ny inona no misy ny CISCO (CIconscription SCOlaire)?","answer":"Isaky ny fivondronana no misy ny CISCO ."},{"question":"Vào thế kỉ III TCN, nhà nước Lưỡng Hà cổ đại. Dựa vào dữ liệu trên, họn đáp án đúng trong 1 lựa chọn sauA. được hình thành.B. bị La Mã xâm lược và thống trị.C. bị Ba Tư xâm lược.D. được thống nhất lãnh thổ.","answer":"Đáp án A."},{"question":"what important event is this text about: జనవరి 30 జాతీయస్తాయిలో గుర్తించబడుతుంది. జనవరి 30 1948లో మహాత్మా గాంధీ నాథూరాం గాడ్సే చేతిలో చనిపొవటంతో ఆ రోజును అమర వీరుల రొజుగా గుర్తిస్తారు. ","answer":"మహాత్మా గాంధీ"},{"question":"A que categoría corresponde la siguiente pregunta ¿Quién fue el 14º presidente de los Estados Unidos de América?.","answer":"Corresponde a historia. "},{"question":"પાલનપુરી બોલી વિષે જણાવો.","answer":"પાલનપુરી બોલી મોટાભાગે ઉત્તર ગુજરાતના બનાસકાંઠા જિલ્લામાં આવેલા પાલનપુર શહેર અને તેની આજુબાજુના પ્રદેશોમાં બોલાતી બોલી છે. પાલનપુરી બોલી ગુજરાતી, સિંધી, મારવાડી અને ફારસી ભાષાઓની અસર ધરાવે છે.જાણીતા સાહિત્યકારો:દીન દરવેશબલોચ લશ્કરખાન અલેદાદખાન ફેજદારમુસાફિર પાલનપુરી"},{"question":"戦国武将伊達政宗の幼名は梵天丸（ぼんてんまる）。では徳川家康の幼名は？","answer":"竹千代です。"},{"question":"السؤال: كيف يسقط حد الزنا على الزوجة التي لاعنها زوجها ؟","answer":"الإجابة: بملاعنتها له بعد تمام لعانه"},{"question":"W serii filmów Harry Potter aktorka Emma Watson wcieliła się w  rolę Ginny Weasley. Prawda czy fałsz?","answer":"Powyższe zdanie to fałsz."},{"question":"काठमाडौं उपत्यकाको कृषि अभ्यास र खाद्य सुरक्षामा मध्ययुगीन जलवायु ढाँचाको प्रभावको चर्चा गर्नुहोस्।","answer":"मध्ययुगीन जलवायु ढाँचाले काठमाडौं उपत्यकाका कृषि अभ्यासहरूलाई महत्त्वपूर्ण रूपमा प्रभाव पारेको छ, जसले खाद्य सुरक्षालाई असर गर्छ र क्षेत्रको आर्थिक र सामाजिक गतिशीलतालाई आकार दिन्छ।"},{"question":"شحال عدد الخلفاء الراشدين ؟","answer":"ربعة ديال الخلفاء"},{"question":"Apakah maksud \\"asalnya dari kubangan\\"?","answer":"(orang yang) terlalu hina"},{"question":"物事に感動したり共鳴したりすることを、ある楽器にたとえて「何に触れる」というでしょう？","answer":"琴線"},{"question":"இந்தப் பத்தியின் தொடர்ச்சியை எழுதுங்கள் - இந்திய விமானப்படையில் சேர்ந்த பிறகு, இவர் 1965","answer":"மற்றும் 1971 இந்திய-பாக்கித்தான் போரில் நடவடிக்கையில் ஈடுபடார். 1971 ஆம் ஆண்டு யுத்தத்தின் போது, விங் கமாண்டராக, எலக்ட்ரிக் கான்பெராவை இயக்கும் செயல்பாட்டு உளவுப் படைப்பிரிவின் 106 வது படையின் கட்டளை அதிகாரியாக இருந்தார். இவர் மேற்குத் துறை மற்றும் கிழக்குத் துறை ஆகிய இரண்டிலும் எதிரி பிரதேசத்தின் மீது ஏராளமான பயணங்களை மேற்கொண்டார் மற்றும் எதிரி நிறுவல்கள் மற்றும் துருப்புக்கள் பற்றிய முக்கிய தகவல்களைப் பெற்றார். இந்த பணிகள் நிராயுதபாணியாகவும், பாதுகாக்கப்படாத இலக்குகளின் வான்வழி புகைப்படம் எடுப்பதற்காகவும் எதிரிகளின் எல்லைக்குள் ஆழமாக பறக்க வேண்டும். இந்த பயணிகளிடமிருந்து பெறப்பட்ட தகவல்கள் இராணுவம், விமானப்படை மற்றும் கடற்படை நடவடிக்கைகளைத் திட்டமிடுவதற்கு உதவியது. மேலும், போர் முயற்சிகளின் வெற்றிக்கு நேரடியாக பங்களித்தன. இவர் தனது நோக்கங்களை முழுமையாக அடையாமல் இந்த எந்தவொரு பயணத்திலிருந்தும் திரும்பி வரவில்லை என்றும் அறியப்பட்டது. நிராயுதபாணியான விமானத்தில் எதிரி எல்லைக்குள் மீண்டும் மீண்டும் பறப்பதில் காட்டப்பட்ட துணிச்சலுக்கும் தலைமைக்கும் இவருக்கு அதி விசிட்ட சேவா பதக்கமும், மகா வீர சக்கரம் விருதும் வழங்கப்பட்டது ."},{"question":"Дебют деген эмне ?","answer":"Дебют - (фр. début башталыш) 1) бир иштин башталышы, мисалы, актёрдун сахнада же ошол театрда 1-жолу чыгышы; 2) шахматта же дойбуда оюндун, партиянын башталышы, алгачкы жүрүштөр."},{"question":"Àjẹsára ibà pọ́njú-pọ́ntọ̀","answer":"Àjẹsára ibà pọ́njú-pọ́ntọ̀ jẹ́ àjẹsára tí ń dáàbò bo ni lọ́wọ́ ibà pọ́njú-pọ́ntọ̀. Ibà pọ́njú-pọ́ntọ̀ jẹ́ àkóràn àrùn kòkòrò àìlèfojúrí afàìsàn tó má a ń sábà wáyé ní Afrika àti Gúsù Amẹ́ríkà. Iye àwọn ènìyàn tó tó 99% ni ó má a ń ní agbára àti kojú àrùn náà láàárín oṣù kan lẹ́yìn tí wọ́n bá ti gba àjẹsára náà, èyí sì dàbí ẹni pé yóò wà títí ayé wọn. A le lo àjẹsára náà láti ṣàkóso ìtànkiri àrùn náà. À ń fún ni gẹ́gẹ́ bí abẹ́rẹ́ tí a gún sínú ẹran ara ẹni tàbí tí a gún sábẹ́ awọ ara ẹni.Àjọ Ìlera Àgbáyé (WHO) gba ni nímọ̀ràn láti má a gba àjẹsára lóòrèkóòrè ní gbogbo orílẹ̀-èdè tí àrùn náà ti wọ́pọ̀. Èyí gbọ́dọ̀ wáyé láàárín àkókò tí ènìyàn jẹ́ ọmọ oṣù mẹ́ẹ̀sán sí mẹ́ẹ̀wá. Àwọn ènìyàn tó ń rin ìrìn-àjò lọ sí àwọn agbègbè ibití àrùn náà ti ń wáyé ní a tún gbọdọ̀ fún ní àjẹsára náà. A kìí sábà nílò àfikún ìwọ̀n àjẹsára náà lẹ́yìn èyítí a bá ti kọ́kọ́ fún ni.Àjẹsára ibà pọ́njú-pọ́ntọ̀ jẹ́ èyítí kò léwu rárá. Èyí rí bẹ́ẹ̀ fún àwọn tó ní àkóràn àrùn HIV ṣùgbọ́n tí wọn kò ní àmì àrùn náà pàápàá. Àtúnbọ̀tán wọ́ọ́rọ́wọ́ tó lè wáyé ni orí-fífọ́, ìrora nínú ẹran ara, ìrora lójú ibi abẹ́rẹ́, ibà, àti ara-sísú. Gbígbòdì egbògi lára ẹni a má a wáyé ní mẹ́ẹ̀jọ nínú mílíọ̀nù ìwọ̀n egbògi náà, ìṣòro tó lágbára tó níí ṣe pẹ̀lú  iṣan ara náà a má a wáyé ní mẹ́ẹ̀rin nínú mílíọ̀nù ìwọ̀n egbògi náà, bẹ́ẹ̀ sì ni ìkùnà àwọn ẹ̀yà tí nṣiṣẹ́ oríṣiríṣi nínú ara náà a má a wáyé ní mẹ́ẹ̀ta nínú mílíọ̀nù ìwọ̀n egbògi náà. Ó ṣeé ṣe kí ó máṣe léwu láti lòó nígbàtí ènìyàn bá ní oyun, nítorí náà, a dámọ̀ràn lílò rẹ̀ láàárín àwọn ènìyàn tó lè wà ní sàkání ibití àrùn náà ti ń ran ni. A kò gbọdọ̀ lòó fún àwọn tí agbára kíkojú àrùn wọn kò bá múnádóko.A bẹ̀rẹ̀ ìmúlò àjẹsára ibà pọ́njú-pọ́ntọ̀ ní ọdún 1938. Ó wà lórí Àkójọ Àwọn Egbògi Kòṣeémáàní ti Àjọ Ìlera Àgbáyé, àwọn òògùn tó ṣe pàtàkì jùlọ tí a nílò fún ètò ìlera ìbẹ̀rẹ̀pẹ̀pẹ̀ yòówù. Iye owó rẹ̀ lójú pálí jẹ́ 4.30 sí 21.30 USD fún ìwọ̀n egbògi náà kanṣoṣo ní ọdún 2014. Ní ilẹ̀ Amẹ́ríkà iye owó rẹ̀ jẹ́ 50 sí 100 USD. A ṣe àgbéjáde àjẹsára náà pẹ̀lú àwọn kòkòrò àìlèfojúrí afàìsàn ibà pọ́njú-pọ́ntọ̀, àwọn èyítí a ti sọ di aláìlágbára."},{"question":"नेपालको चाँगु नारायण मन्दिर कसरी पुग्ने ?","answer":"चाँगुनारायण काठमाडौंबाट १२ किलोमिटर पूर्वमा अवस्थित छ। भक्तपुरबाट चाँगु नारायणका लागि नियमित छुट्ने माइक्रोबसहरु छन् । केही पर्यटक नगरकोटदेखि चाँगुनारायणसम्म पदयात्रा गरी भक्तपुर हुँदै काठमाडौं फर्कने पनि गर्छन् ।"},{"question":"வினா  போட்டியில் வெற்றி பெறுவதைக் காட்டிலும் பங்கேற்பதுதான் இன்றியமையாதது என்று உன் தந்தை கூறுகிறார்.   என்ன காரணம்  தெரியுமா?","answer":" விடைபோட்டியில் பங்கேற்பதன் மூலம் அவரவர் ஆற்றல் வெளிப்படுகிறது. பலமுறை தோற்றாலும் ஒரு முறையாவது வெற்றி பெறுவோம் என்ற நம்பிக்கை வளர்கிறது. போட்டியில் கலந்துகொள்ளும் போது தன்னால் என்ன முடியும், முடியாது என்பதை அறிந்து கொள்ள முடிகிறது.போட்டியில் தோற்றாலும் சரி என்று கலந்து கொள்ளும் போது அவர்களுக்குள் ஓர் உந்துதல் சக்தி உண்டாகிறது. அச்சக்தி அவர்களை முயற்சி செய்யத் தூண்டுகோலாய் அமைகிறது. போட்டிக்காக அவர்கள் செய்யும் பயிற்சியும் முயற்சியும் அவர்களைச் சுறுசுறுப்பாக்குகிறது. செயல்பாட்டைத் தூண்டி வளர்ச்சிக்கு உதவுகிறது.இக்காரணங்களால் போட்டியில் வெற்றி பெறுவதைக் காட்டிலும் பங்கேற்பதுதான் இன்றியமையதாதது என்று தந்தை கூறுகிறார்."},{"question":"Ibọn ni Banji lọọ fi ka oniṣowo kan mọ’nu ṣọọbu ẹ l’Ado-Ekiti","answer":"Ọmọdekunrin ẹni ọdun mọkanlelọgọrin kan, Akeem Banji, ti wa ni atimọle ọlọpaa bayii niluu Ado-Ekiti, nibi to ti n ṣalaye ohun to sun un debi ẹsun ole ti wọn fi kan an fun awọn ọlọpaa. Ọmọkunrin to n ṣiṣẹ birikila naa lọwọ ọlọpaa tẹ laduugbo Ekute, niluu Ado-Ekiti, l’Ọjọruu, Wẹsidee, ọsẹ yii, lori ẹsun pe o lọọ fibọn ka ọkunrin kan, Ayọdeji Oluṣọla, mọ ṣọọbu rẹ  lọsan-an ọjọ naa, to si gba ẹgbẹrun lọna aadọta naira lọwọ rẹ.Bakan naa ni awọn agbofinro ni o tun ko awọn ẹru mi-in yatọ si owo yii ninu ṣọọbu rẹ, to si halẹ mọ ọn pe oun yoo yinbọn lu u to ba pariwo.Ṣugbọn bi Banji ṣe gba owo naa tan to si n gbiyanju lati ko awọn ẹru to ji ninu ṣọọbu naa lọ ni awọn ọlọpaa de si adugbo ọhun, ti wọn si bẹrẹ si i yinbọn soke. Lasiko naa ni wọn mu ọmọkunrin yii.Awọn agbofinro gba owo ati gbogbo ẹru to ko ni ṣọọbu ọkunrin oniṣowo naa, bẹẹ ni wọn tun gba ibọn ilewọ agbelẹrọ kan lọwọ rẹ.Nigba to n ṣalaye fawọn ọlọpaa, Banji ni oun ati awọn ẹlẹgbẹ oun meji, Oyinbo ati Ayo, ti wọn ti sa lọ bayii, lawọn jọọ waa ṣiṣẹ naa.Nigba to n sọrọ lori iṣẹlẹ naa, Alukoro ọlọpaa nipinlẹ Ekiti, Ọgbẹni Sunday Abutu, sọ pe Banji to jẹ olori awọn ọdaran naa ti wa ni atimọle awọn, iwadii si ti bẹrẹ lori iṣẹlẹ naa. O ni awọn yoo wa awọn yooku kan, ti wọn yoo si foju wina ofin."},{"question":"Sheeg sanadkii uu xuriyadda  qaatay dalka Baxreyn?","answer":"Wadanka Baxreyn waxa uu xornimada qaatay sanadkii 1971."},{"question":"සෝනාර් ( Sonar ) ක්‍රමය උපයෝගි කරගනිමින් , මුහුදු පතුලේ ගැඹුර මැනීමට යොදාගන්නා උපකරණය කුමක්ද ?","answer":"එකෝසවුන්ඩර් ( Echosounder )"},{"question":"Apakah maksud \\"bagai angkat batang, keluar cacing gelang-gelang\\"?","answer":"Maksudnya adalah susahnya menyiapkan kerja yang terbengkalai"},{"question":"Completa la siguiente frase:  Ganó una medalla de oro en el Campeonato Mundial de Patinaje de Velocidad sobre Hielo de 2011 y siete medallas en el Campeonato Mundial de Patinaje de Velocidad sobre Hielo en Distancia Individual entre los años 2007 y 2013...","answer":"Además, obtuvo dos medallas en el Campeonato Europeo de Patinaje de Velocidad sobre Hielo, plata en 2011 y bronce en 2010."},{"question":"தமிழ் உரைநடைக்கு மு.வ.வின் பங்களிப்பை எத்தனைத் தலைப்புகளில் காணலாம்?","answer":"மு. வரதராசனாரின் படைப்புகள் அனைத்தும் தமிழ் உரைநடைக்கு அவர் அளித்த பங்களிப்புகள் ஆகும். அந்தப் பங்களிப்புகள் எந்தெந்த வகைகளில் அமைந்துள்ளன என்பதைப் பற்றிக் காண்போம். மு.வ.வின் பங்களிப்புகளைப் பின்வரும் ஐந்து தலைப்புகளில் வகைப்படுத்திக் காணலாம். அவை, அ) புனைகதைஆ) இலக்கிய ஆய்வுகள்இ) கடித இலக்கியம்ஈ) திருக்குறள் தெளிவுரைஉ) வாழ்க்கை வரலாற்று நூல்கள்"},{"question":"కింద ఇచ్చిన \\" పావురాలు, బోయవాడు \\" కథ నీతి ఏంటి?అడవిలో ఒక బోయవాడు కొన్ని నూకలు నేలమీద చల్లి, దానిపై వలని పరిచి ఉంచాడు. చిత్రగ్రీవ అనే పావురం తన వెనకాల కొన్ని పావురాల గుంపు తో ఆహారం కోసం తిరుగుతూ, అడవిలో ఆ చెట్టు కింద నూకలు చూసి, తినాలని ఆశపడి , కిందికి వాలింది. దాని వెనకే అన్ని పావురాలు వాలి, వేటగాడు పరిచిన వలలో చిక్కుకున్నాయి.తామంతా వేటగాడి వలలో చిక్కుకున్నామని గ్రహించి , ఆందోళనతో గొడవ చేయసాగాయి. చిత్రగ్రీవుడు తన స్నేహితులకి కంగారు పడవద్దని, తగిన ఉపాయం ఆలోచించి, బైట పడదామని , ధైర్యం చెప్పాడు. “అందరం ఒక్కసారిగా వల తో పాటు ఎగిరిపోదాం. అలా కలిసికట్టుగా ఒక్కసారిగా ఎగిరిపోయి తప్పించుకుందాం” అని ఉపాయం చెప్పాడు. అన్ని పావురాలు ఒక్కసారిగా ఆకాశం లోకి వలతో పాటుగా ఎగిరాయి.దూరం నుంచి ఇది చూసిన వేటగాడు పావురాలే కాక , తన వల కూడా పోతోందని ఆత్రం గా వాటి వెంట కొంత దూరం పరిగెత్తి, అరిచి, కూలబడ్డాడు. చిత్రగ్రీవుడు తన గుంపు తో వలతో సహా తన స్నేహితుడైన హిరణ్యకుడు అనే ఎలుక ముందు వాలాడు. హిరణ్యకుడు భయంతో తన కలుగు లోకి దూరాడు.వెంటనే, చిత్రగ్రీవుడు, “మిత్రమా! హిరణ్యా !మేమంతా ఒక వలలో చిక్కి, ప్రాణాపాయం లో ఉన్నాము. నువ్వే మమ్మల్ని రక్షించాలి. బైటకిరా,” అని పిలిచాడు. తన స్నేహితుడైన చిత్రగ్రీవుడిని చూసి సంతోషం తో బైటికి వొచ్చి, చిత్రగ్రీవుని బంధ విముక్తుణ్ణి చెయ్యడానికి వలని కొరకడంమొదలుపెట్టాడు.అంత చిత్రగ్రీవుడు, “మిత్రమా ఆగు, ముందు నా పరివారాన్ని రక్షించు, తరువాత నన్ను బంధ విముక్తుణ్ణి చెయ్యచ్చు. ఎందువల్లనంటే, నువ్వు ఈ పని చేస్తూ చేస్తూ అలసి పోవచ్చు . రాజుగా నా కర్తవ్యం, ముందుగా నా పరివారాన్ని కాపాడటం,చివరగా నన్ను రక్షించుకోవటం,” అని అన్నాడు.ఈ మాట వింటూనే హిరణ్యకుడు చాలా సంతోషించి, వెంటనే తన ఎలుకల సైన్యాన్ని పిలిచాడు. అవన్నీ చక చకా వలని తునాతునకలు చేసి, పావురాలని విడిపించాయి. చిత్రగ్రీవుడు తనని, తన పరివారాన్ని కాపాడినందుకు హిరణ్యకుడికి కృతఙ్ఞతలు తెలిపి, హాయిగా వెళ్ళిపోయాడు.","answer":" \\"పావురాలు, బోయవాడు\\" కధలో స్నేహితుల వల్ల కలిగే లాభం, ఐకమత్యమే బలం అనే నీతి స్పష్టంగా తెలుస్తోంది."},{"question":"Түркиянын тарыхындагы эң узак жер титирөө качан болгон?","answer":"1509-жылы Түркияда 45 күнгө созулган эң узак жер титирөө болду."},{"question":"\\"Oay! izany fahatairako mahita anao mipoitra tampoka avy any.\\" Inona fihetseam-po hita taratra ao amin'ity fehezanteny ity?","answer":"Ny fihetseam-po hita taratra ao amin'ity fehezanteny ity dia ny fahatairan'ilay olona miteny nohon'ny nahita olon-kafa mipoitra tampoka avy any amin'ny tsy hitan'ny masony."},{"question":"HEESTII Neecawda jaceyl FANAANKII HANUUNIYE","answer":"Qalbigaan is nooc ka wada nahayooNabarka ku damqaayaan UunugulahayooNaftaadu nafteyda waa u naxariisNiyada isku mida namiimka dakiyoNaxligu ma galeeNeecaawda jaceyl neecaawda jaceylNacabka ka jiroo naceybka ka dhawrNabdiga ku raboo ku naawilayooNimca aad u tahiyo nasteexo ugoowCishqiga nagibaa ase nuurinayeeNiyada isku mida namiimka dadkiyoNaxliga ma galeeNeecawda jaceyl neecaawda jaceylNacabka ka jiroo naceybka ka dhaw"},{"question":"السؤال: ما هو التعلم العميق؟","answer":"الإجابة: برنامج كمبيوتر يحاكي شبكة الخلايا العصبية في الدماغ. إنها مجموعة فرعية من التعلم الآلي."},{"question":"Dime cuál es el tema principal o categoría de esta pregunta: ¿Quién llegó a las finales del campeonato colegial de fútbol americano de la NCAA en 2019 pero no ganó?","answer":"La categoría o tema principal de esta pregunta es  deportes. "},{"question":"س169- كم دامت خلافة علي بن أبي طالب؟","answer":"ج169- 5 سنوات"},{"question":"Immisa sano ayuu qur'aanka soo degayey?","answer":" 23-sano. "},{"question":"\\"රෝමියෝ  සහ ජුලියට්\\" නාට්‍යය ලිව්වේ කවුද?","answer":"\\"රෝමියෝ  සහ ජුලියට්\\" නාට්‍යය ලියා  ඇත්තේ විලියම් ෂේක්ස්පියර් විසිනි. එය ඔහුගේ වඩාත් ප්‍රසිද්ධ සහ නිතර රඟ දක්වන ශෝ කාන්තයක් සහිත නාට්‍යකි. 1590 ගණන්වල මුල් භාගයේ ලියා  ඇති බවට විශ්වාස කෙරෙන මෙම නාට්‍යය තරුණ පෙම්වතුන් දෙදෙනෙකුගේ කතාව කියයි, ඔවුන්ගේ මරණය අවසානයේ ඔවුන්ගේ ආරවුලක පවුල් සමගි කරයි. එය බොහෝ  චිත්‍රපට, නාට්‍ය නිෂ්පාදන සහ මුද්‍රා නාට්‍යවලට අනුවර්තනය වී ඇති අතර ඉංග්‍රීසි සාහිත්‍යය අධ්‍යයනයේ මූලිකම  නාට්‍යක් ලෙස පවතී."},{"question":"Tohizo izao ohabolana izao : \\" Aleo very tsikalakalam-bola .... \\"","answer":"\\"Aleo very tsikalakalam-bola toy izay very tsikalakalam-pihavanana \\" "},{"question":"问题：林肯的早年生活是怎样的？","answer":"答案：林肯于1809年2月12日出生在美国肯塔基州的一个小木屋中，他的父母都是农民，家庭条件贫寒。尽管受教育机会有限，但他有着旺盛的求知欲，通过自学获得了知识。"},{"question":"ಕೆಳಗಿನ ಪ್ರಬಂಧವನ್ನು 5 ಅಂಕಗಳಲ್ಲಿ ಸಾರಾಂಶಗೊಳಿಸಿ.ಕಿತ್ತಳೆ, ತಮ್ಮ ರೋಮಾಂಚಕ ಬಣ್ಣ ಮತ್ತು ಉಲ್ಲಾಸಕರ ರುಚಿಯೊಂದಿಗೆ, ಪ್ರಕೃತಿಯ ಅತ್ಯಂತ ಪ್ರೀತಿಯ ಮತ್ತು ಪೌಷ್ಟಿಕ ಹಣ್ಣುಗಳಲ್ಲಿ ಒಂದಾಗಿದೆ. ಈ ಸಿಟ್ರಸ್ ಅದ್ಭುತಗಳು ರುಚಿಕರವಾದವು ಮಾತ್ರವಲ್ಲದೆ ಆರೋಗ್ಯ ಪ್ರಯೋಜನಗಳಿಂದ ಕೂಡಿದೆ. ತಮ್ಮ ರಸಭರಿತವಾದ ತಿರುಳಿನಿಂದ ತಮ್ಮ ರುಚಿಕಾರಕಕ್ಕೆ, ಕಿತ್ತಳೆಗಳು ರುಚಿ ಮೊಗ್ಗುಗಳನ್ನು ಸೆರೆಹಿಡಿಯುತ್ತವೆ ಮತ್ತು ತಲೆಮಾರುಗಳಿಗೆ ಅಗತ್ಯವಾದ ಪೋಷಕಾಂಶಗಳನ್ನು ಒದಗಿಸುತ್ತವೆ.ಕಿತ್ತಳೆಯ ವಿಶಿಷ್ಟ ಲಕ್ಷಣವೆಂದರೆ ಅವುಗಳ ಹೆಚ್ಚಿನ ವಿಟಮಿನ್ ಸಿ ಅಂಶ. ಈ ಉತ್ಕರ್ಷಣ ನಿರೋಧಕ ಶಕ್ತಿಯು ಪ್ರತಿರಕ್ಷಣಾ ವ್ಯವಸ್ಥೆಯನ್ನು ಬೆಂಬಲಿಸುತ್ತದೆ, ಆರೋಗ್ಯಕರ ಚರ್ಮವನ್ನು ಉತ್ತೇಜಿಸುತ್ತದೆ ಮತ್ತು ಗಾಯವನ್ನು ಗುಣಪಡಿಸಲು ಸಹಾಯ ಮಾಡುತ್ತದೆ. ಕಿತ್ತಳೆಗಳು ಇತರ ಉತ್ಕರ್ಷಣ ನಿರೋಧಕಗಳನ್ನು ಹೊಂದಿರುತ್ತವೆ, ಇದು ಹಾನಿಕಾರಕ ಸ್ವತಂತ್ರ ರಾಡಿಕಲ್ಗಳನ್ನು ಎದುರಿಸಲು ಸಹಾಯ ಮಾಡುತ್ತದೆ, ದೀರ್ಘಕಾಲದ ಕಾಯಿಲೆಗಳ ಅಪಾಯವನ್ನು ಕಡಿಮೆ ಮಾಡುತ್ತದೆ.ಅವುಗಳ ಹೆಚ್ಚಿನ ನೀರಿನ ಅಂಶದೊಂದಿಗೆ, ಕಿತ್ತಳೆಗಳು ಹೈಡ್ರೀಕರಿಸಿದ ಉಳಿಯಲು ಅದ್ಭುತ ಆಯ್ಕೆಯಾಗಿದೆ. ರಸಭರಿತವಾದ ಕಿತ್ತಳೆ  ಬಾಯಾರಿಕೆಯನ್ನು ತಣಿಸಲು ಮತ್ತು ದೇಹದ ದ್ರವದ ಸಮತೋಲನವನ್ನು ಕಾಪಾಡಿಕೊಳ್ಳಲು ಸಹಾಯ ಮಾಡುತ್ತದೆ, ವಿಶೇಷವಾಗಿ ಬೆಚ್ಚಗಿನ ವಾತಾವರಣದಲ್ಲಿ ಅಥವಾ ದೈಹಿಕ ಚಟುವಟಿಕೆಯ ನಂತರ.ಕಿತ್ತಳೆಗಳು ಆಹಾರದ ಫೈಬರ್‌ನ ಉತ್ತಮ ಮೂಲವಾಗಿದೆ, ಜೀರ್ಣಕ್ರಿಯೆಗೆ ಸಹಾಯ ಮಾಡುತ್ತದೆ ಮತ್ತು ಕರುಳಿನ ಆರೋಗ್ಯವನ್ನು ಉತ್ತೇಜಿಸುತ್ತದೆ. ಫೈಬರ್ ಅಂಶವು ಪೂರ್ಣತೆಯ ಭಾವನೆ, ತೂಕ ನಿರ್ವಹಣೆ ಮತ್ತು ಆರೋಗ್ಯಕರ ಆಹಾರ ಪದ್ಧತಿಯನ್ನು ಬೆಂಬಲಿಸುತ್ತದೆ.ಅವರ ಸಂತೋಷಕರ ಮಾಧುರ್ಯದ ಹೊರತಾಗಿಯೂ, ಕಿತ್ತಳೆಗಳು ಕ್ಯಾಲೊರಿಗಳಲ್ಲಿ ತುಲನಾತ್ಮಕವಾಗಿ ಕಡಿಮೆಯಾಗಿದ್ದು, ಅವುಗಳನ್ನು ಅಪರಾಧ-ಮುಕ್ತ ಚಿಕಿತ್ಸೆಯಾಗಿ ಮಾಡುತ್ತದೆ. ಸ್ವಾಭಾವಿಕವಾಗಿ ಸಿಹಿಯಾದ ಯಾವುದನ್ನಾದರೂ ಕಡುಬಯಕೆಗಳನ್ನು ತೃಪ್ತಿಪಡಿಸುವಾಗ ಅವರು ಸಕ್ಕರೆ ತಿಂಡಿಗಳಿಗೆ ಆರೋಗ್ಯಕರ ಪರ್ಯಾಯವನ್ನು ನೀಡುತ್ತಾರೆ.ತಮ್ಮದೇ ಆದ ತಿಂಡಿಯಾಗಿರುವುದರ ಹೊರತಾಗಿ, ಕಿತ್ತಳೆ ಸಿಹಿ ಮತ್ತು ಖಾರದ ಭಕ್ಷ್ಯಗಳಿಗೆ ಬಹುಮುಖ ಸೇರ್ಪಡೆಯಾಗಿರಬಹುದು. ಹೊಸದಾಗಿ ಸ್ಕ್ವೀಝ್ ಮಾಡಿದ ಕಿತ್ತಳೆ ರಸ ಮತ್ತು ಸಿಟ್ರಸ್ ಮ್ಯಾರಿನೇಡ್‌ಗಳಿಂದ ರುಚಿಕಾರಕ-ಇನ್ಫ್ಯೂಸ್ಡ್ ಡೆಸರ್ಟ್‌ಗಳು ಮತ್ತು ರೋಮಾಂಚಕ ಸಲಾಡ್‌ಗಳವರೆಗೆ, ಅವುಗಳ ಸುವಾಸನೆಯು ವ್ಯಾಪಕ ಶ್ರೇಣಿಯ ಪಾಕವಿಧಾನಗಳಿಗೆ ಸಂತೋಷಕರ ಟ್ವಿಸ್ಟ್ ಅನ್ನು ಸೇರಿಸುತ್ತದೆ.ಕೊನೆಯಲ್ಲಿ, ಕಿತ್ತಳೆ ರುಚಿ ಮತ್ತು ಆರೋಗ್ಯ ಪ್ರಯೋಜನಗಳ ನಿಧಿಯಾಗಿದೆ. ವಿಟಮಿನ್ ಸಿ, ಉತ್ಕರ್ಷಣ ನಿರೋಧಕಗಳು ಮತ್ತು ನಾರಿನಂಶದಿಂದ ಪ್ಯಾಕ್ ಮಾಡಲ್ಪಟ್ಟಿದೆ, ಅವು ಬಲವಾದ ರೋಗನಿರೋಧಕ ಶಕ್ತಿ, ಜಲಸಂಚಯನ, ಜೀರ್ಣಕಾರಿ ಸ್ವಾಸ್ಥ್ಯ ಮತ್ತು ಹೆಚ್ಚಿನವುಗಳಿಗೆ ಕೊಡುಗೆ ನೀಡುತ್ತವೆ. ಅವುಗಳ ನೈಸರ್ಗಿಕ ಮಾಧುರ್ಯ ಮತ್ತು ಪಾಕಶಾಲೆಯ ಬಹುಮುಖತೆಯೊಂದಿಗೆ, ಕಿತ್ತಳೆಗಳು ಸಮತೋಲಿತ ಆಹಾರಕ್ಕೆ ಪೌಷ್ಟಿಕ ಮತ್ತು ರುಚಿಕರವಾದ ಸೇರ್ಪಡೆಯಾಗಿ ಕಾರ್ಯನಿರ್ವಹಿಸುತ್ತವೆ. ತಮ್ಮದೇ ಆದ ಮೇಲೆ ಆನಂದಿಸುತ್ತಿರಲಿ ಅಥವಾ ವಿವಿಧ ಭಕ್ಷ್ಯಗಳಲ್ಲಿ ಸಂಯೋಜಿಸಲ್ಪಟ್ಟಿರಲಿ, ಪ್ರಕೃತಿಯ ಈ ಕಟುವಾದ ಆನಂದಗಳು ಆರೋಗ್ಯಕರ ಆಹಾರದ ಸಂತೋಷಗಳಿಗೆ ಸಾಕ್ಷಿಯಾಗಿದೆ.","answer":"1. ಕಿತ್ತಳೆಗಳು ರೋಮಾಂಚಕ, ರುಚಿಕರವಾದ ಮತ್ತು ಪೌಷ್ಟಿಕಾಂಶದ ಹಣ್ಣುಗಳು ಮತ್ತು ಹಲವಾರು ಆರೋಗ್ಯ ಪ್ರಯೋಜನಗಳನ್ನು ಹೊಂದಿವೆ.2. ಅವು ವಿಟಮಿನ್ ಸಿ ಮತ್ತು ಆಂಟಿಆಕ್ಸಿಡೆಂಟ್‌ಗಳಲ್ಲಿ ಸಮೃದ್ಧವಾಗಿವೆ, ಇದು ಪ್ರತಿರಕ್ಷಣಾ ವ್ಯವಸ್ಥೆಯನ್ನು ಬೆಂಬಲಿಸುತ್ತದೆ ಮತ್ತು ಸ್ವತಂತ್ರ ರಾಡಿಕಲ್‌ಗಳನ್ನು ಎದುರಿಸುತ್ತದೆ.3. ಕಿತ್ತಳೆಗಳು ಹೆಚ್ಚಿನ ನೀರಿನ ಅಂಶವನ್ನು ಹೊಂದಿರುತ್ತವೆ, ವಿಶೇಷವಾಗಿ ಬೆಚ್ಚನೆಯ ವಾತಾವರಣದಲ್ಲಿ ಅಥವಾ ದೈಹಿಕ ಚಟುವಟಿಕೆಯ ನಂತರ ಹೈಡ್ರೀಕರಿಸಿದ ಉಳಿಯಲು ಉತ್ತಮವಾಗಿದೆ.4. ಅವರ ಆಹಾರದ ಫೈಬರ್ ಜೀರ್ಣಕ್ರಿಯೆಗೆ ಸಹಾಯ ಮಾಡುತ್ತದೆ, ಕರುಳಿನ ಆರೋಗ್ಯವನ್ನು ಉತ್ತೇಜಿಸುತ್ತದೆ ಮತ್ತು ತೂಕ ನಿರ್ವಹಣೆಗೆ ಪೂರ್ಣತೆಯ ಭಾವನೆಯನ್ನು ನೀಡುತ್ತದೆ.5. ಅವುಗಳ ಮಾಧುರ್ಯದ ಹೊರತಾಗಿಯೂ, ಕಿತ್ತಳೆಗಳು ಕಡಿಮೆ ಕ್ಯಾಲೋರಿಗಳನ್ನು ಹೊಂದಿರುತ್ತವೆ, ಇದು ಸಿಹಿ ಕಡುಬಯಕೆಗಳನ್ನು ಪೂರೈಸಲು ಆರೋಗ್ಯಕರ ಆಯ್ಕೆಯನ್ನು ನೀಡುತ್ತದೆ. ಅವರು ಅಡುಗೆಯಲ್ಲಿ ಬಹುಮುಖರಾಗಿದ್ದಾರೆ ಮತ್ತು ಸಿಹಿ ಮತ್ತು ಖಾರದ ಭಕ್ಷ್ಯಗಳನ್ನು ಹೆಚ್ಚಿಸಬಹುದು"},{"question":"เหตุการณ์สำคัญของข้อความต่อไปนี้คืออะไร: รอลลินส์ได้ประกาศจะเข้าร่วมรอยัลรัมเบิล (2017) แต่เสียสิทธิ์แพ้ให้แซมี เซย์นเพราะการก่อกวนของทริปเปิลเอช รอลลินส์ได้ปรากฏตัวในเรียกให้ทริปเปิลเอชออกมาเจอบนเวที แต่ทริปเปิลเอชได้สั่งรปภ.มาลากตัวออกไปจากสนาม รอว์ 30 มกราคมได้เผชิญหน้าท้าทายกับทริปเปิลเอช แต่ถูกซามัว โจเปิดตัวมาลอบทำร้าย ก่อนจับใส่ท่า Coquina Clutch และทำให้ได้รับบาดเจ็บเข่าขวาอีกครั้ง รอว์ 27 กุมภาพันธ์ได้ออกมาพูดถึงอาการบาดเจ็บ และบอกกับทริปเปิลเอชว่าเขาจะอยู่ที่เรสเซิลเมเนีย ครั้งที่ 33ด้วย รอว์ 13 มีนาคมได้ออกมาช่วยมิค โฟลีย์จากการทำร้ายของทริปเปิลเอช แต่ก็ถูกเล่นงานที่เข่าซ้ำ รอว์ 27 มีนาคมมีการเซ็นสัญญาปล้ำแบบ Unsanctioned(ถ้าบาดเจ็บ, พิการ หรือตาย จะไม่มีสิทธิ์ดำเนินการฟ้องร้องใดๆ ต่อทริปเปิลเอช) ในเรสเซิลเมเนียรอลลินส์เอาชนะได้ด้วยท่า Pedigree ของทริปเปิลเอช ในซัมเมอร์สแลม (2017)ได้คว้าแชมป์รอว์แท็กทีม WWEร่วมกับแอมโบรส ก่อนเสียแชมป์ให้ซีซาโรและเชมัส หลังจากแอมโบรสได้รับบาดเจ็บจึงเปลี่ยนมาจับคู่กับเจสัน จอร์แดนและคว้าแชมป์รอว์แท็กทีมได้จากซีซาโรและเชมัส ก่อนเสียคืนในรอยัลรัมเบิล (2018) จากนั้นรอลลินส์ได้กลับมาฉายเดี่ยวคว้าแชมป์อินเตอร์คอนติเนนทัลในเรสเซิลเมเนีย ครั้งที่ 34 ทำให้เป็นแชมป์ทริปเปิลคราวน์และแชมป์แกรนด์สแลมของWWE ก่อนเสียให้ดอล์ฟ ซิกก์เลอร์ และชิงคืนมาได้ในซัมเมอร์สแลม (2018)โดยมีแอมโบรสอยู่ข้างเวทีให้รอลลินส์","answer":"รอยัลรัมเบิล (2017)"},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਗਉੜੀ ਮਹਲਾ ੫ ॥ਹਰਿ ਸਿਉ ਜੁਰੈ ਤ ਸਭੁ ਕੋ ਮੀਤੁ ॥ਹਰਿ ਸਿਉ ਜੁਰੈ ਤ ਨਿਹਚਲੁ ਚੀਤੁ ॥ਹਰਿ ਸਿਉ ਜੁਰੈ ਨ ਵਿਆਪੈ ਕਾੜੑਾ ॥ਹਰਿ ਸਿਉ ਜੁਰੈ ਤ ਹੋਇ ਨਿਸਤਾਰਾ ॥੧॥ਰੇ ਮਨ ਮੇਰੇ ਤੂੰ ਹਰਿ ਸਿਉ ਜੋਰੁ ॥ਕਾਜਿ ਤੁਹਾਰੈ ਨਾਹੀ ਹੋਰੁ ॥੧॥ ਰਹਾਉ ॥ਵਡੇ ਵਡੇ ਜੋ ਦੁਨੀਆਦਾਰ ॥ਕਾਹੂ ਕਾਜਿ ਨਾਹੀ ਗਾਵਾਰ ॥ਹਰਿ ਕਾ ਦਾਸੁ ਨੀਚ ਕੁਲੁ ਸੁਣਹਿ ॥ਤਿਸ ਕੈ ਸੰਗਿ ਖਿਨ ਮਹਿ ਉਧਰਹਿ ॥੨॥ਕੋਟਿ ਮਜਨ ਜਾ ਕੈ ਸੁਣਿ ਨਾਮ ॥ਕੋਟਿ ਪੂਜਾ ਜਾ ਕੈ ਹੈ ਧਿਆਨ ॥ਕੋਟਿ ਪੁੰਨ ਸੁਣਿ ਹਰਿ ਕੀ ਬਾਣੀ ॥ਕੋਟਿ ਫਲਾ ਗੁਰ ਤੇ ਬਿਧਿ ਜਾਣੀ ॥੩॥ਮਨ ਅਪੁਨੇ ਮਹਿ ਫਿਰਿ ਫਿਰਿ ਚੇਤ ॥ਬਿਨਸਿ ਜਾਹਿ ਮਾਇਆ ਕੇ ਹੇਤ ॥ਹਰਿ ਅਬਿਨਾਸੀ ਤੁਮਰੈ ਸੰਗਿ ॥ਮਨ ਮੇਰੇ ਰਚੁ ਰਾਮ ਕੈ ਰੰਗਿ ॥੪॥ਜਾ ਕੈ ਕਾਮਿ ਉਤਰੈ ਸਭ ਭੂਖ ॥ਜਾ ਕੈ ਕਾਮਿ ਨ ਜੋਹਹਿ ਦੂਤ ॥ਜਾ ਕੈ ਕਾਮਿ ਤੇਰਾ ਵਡ ਗਮਰੁ ॥ਜਾ ਕੈ ਕਾਮਿ ਹੋਵਹਿ ਤੂੰ ਅਮਰੁ ॥੫॥ਜਾ ਕੇ ਚਾਕਰ ਕਉ ਨਹੀ ਡਾਨ ॥ਜਾ ਕੇ ਚਾਕਰ ਕਉ ਨਹੀ ਬਾਨ ॥ਜਾ ਕੈ ਦਫਤਰਿ ਪੁਛੈ ਨ ਲੇਖਾ ॥ਤਾ ਕੀ ਚਾਕਰੀ ਕਰਹੁ ਬਿਸੇਖਾ ॥੬॥ਜਾ ਕੈ ਊਨ ਨਾਹੀ ਕਾਹੂ ਬਾਤ ॥ਏਕਹਿ ਆਪਿ ਅਨੇਕਹਿ ਭਾਤਿ ॥ਜਾ ਕੀ ਦ੍ਰਿਸਟਿ ਹੋਇ ਸਦਾ ਨਿਹਾਲ ॥ਮਨ ਮੇਰੇ ਕਰਿ ਤਾ ਕੀ ਘਾਲ ॥੭॥ਨਾ ਕੋ ਚਤੁਰੁ ਨਾਹੀ ਕੋ ਮੂੜਾ ॥ਨਾ ਕੋ ਹੀਣੁ ਨਾਹੀ ਕੋ ਸੂਰਾ ॥ਜਿਤੁ ਕੋ ਲਾਇਆ ਤਿਤ ਹੀ ਲਾਗਾ ॥ਸੋ ਸੇਵਕੁ ਨਾਨਕ ਜਿਸੁ ਭਾਗਾ ॥੮॥੬॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 238 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਅਰਜਨ ਦੇਵ ਜੀ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਬਾਣੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਹਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"(ਹੇ ਭਾਈ!) ਜਦੋਂ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਨਾਲ ਪਿਆਰ ਪੈਦਾ ਕਰਦਾ ਹੈ, ਤਾਂ ਉਸ ਨੂੰ ਹਰੇਕ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਆਪਣਾ ਮਿੱਤਰ ਦਿੱਸਦਾ ਹੈਤਦੋਂ ਉਸ ਦਾ ਚਿੱਤ (ਵਿਕਾਰਾਂ ਦੇ ਹੱਲਿਆਂ ਦੇ ਟਾਕਰੇ ਤੇ ਸਦਾ) ਅਡੋਲ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ, ਕੋਈ ਚਿੰਤਾ-ਫ਼ਿਕਰ ਉਸ ਉਤੇ ਆਪਣਾ ਜ਼ੋਰ ਨਹੀਂ ਪਾ ਸਕਦਾ, (ਇਸ ਸੰਸਾਰ-ਸਮੁੰਦਰ ਵਿਚੋਂ) ਉਸ ਦਾ ਪਾਰ-ਉਤਾਰਾ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ ।੧। ਹੇ ਮੇਰੇ ਮਨ! ਤੂੰ ਆਪਣੀ ਪ੍ਰੀਤਿ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਨਾਲ ਬਣਾ । (ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਨਾਲ ਪ੍ਰੀਤਿ ਬਣਾਣ ਤੋਂ ਬਿਨਾ) ਕੋਈ ਹੋਰ ਉੱਦਮ ਤੇਰੇ ਕਿਸੇ ਕੰਮ ਨਹੀਂ ਆਵੇਗਾ ।੧।ਰਹਾਉ। (ਹੇ ਭਾਈ! ਜਗਤ ਵਿਚ) ਜੇਹੜੇ ਜੇਹੜੇ ਵੱਡੇ ਵੱਡੇ ਜਾਇਦਾਦਾਂ ਵਾਲੇ ਹਨ, ਉਹਨਾਂ ਮੂਰਖਾਂ ਦੀ (ਕੋਈ ਜਾਇਦਾਦ ਆਤਮਕ ਜੀਵਨ ਦੇ ਰਸਤੇ ਵਿਚ) ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੇ ਕੰਮ ਨਹੀਂ ਆਉਂਦੀ । (ਦੂਜੇ ਪਾਸੇ) ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਭਗਤ ਨੀਵੀਂ ਕੁਲ ਵਿਚ ਭੀ ਜੰਮਿਆ ਹੋਇਆ ਹੋਵੇ, ਤਾਂ ਭੀ ਲੋਕ ਉਸ ਦੀ ਸਿੱਖਿਆ ਸੁਣਦੇ ਹਨ, ਤੇ ਉਸ ਦੀ ਸੰਗਤਿ ਵਿਚ ਰਹਿ ਕੇ (ਸੰਸਾਰ-ਸਮੁੰਦਰ ਦੀਆਂ ਵਿਕਾਰਾਂ ਦੀਆਂ ਲਹਰਾਂ ਵਿਚੋਂ) ਇਕ ਪਲ ਵਿਚ ਬਚ ਨਿਕਲਦੇ ਹਨ ।੨। (ਹੇ ਭਾਈ!) ਜਿਸ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਸੁਣਨ ਵਿਚ ਕੋ੍ਰੜਾਂ ਤੀਰਥ-ਇਸ਼ਨਾਨ ਆ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨਜਿਸ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਧਿਆਨ ਧਰਨ ਵਿਚ ਕ੍ਰੋੜਾਂ ਦੇਵ-ਪੂਜਾ ਆ ਜਾਂਦੀਆਂ ਹਨ,ਜਿਸ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੀ ਸਿਫ਼ਤਿ-ਸਾਲਾਹ ਦੀ ਬਾਣੀ ਸੁਣਨ ਵਿਚ ਕੋ੍ਰੜਾਂ ਪੁੰਨ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ, ਗੁਰੂ ਪਾਸੋਂ ਉਸ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਨਾਲ ਮਿਲਾਪ ਦੀ ਵਿਧੀ ਸਿੱਖਿਆਂ ਇਹ ਸਾਰੇ ਕੋ੍ਰੜਾਂ ਫਲ ਪ੍ਰਾਪਤ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ ।੩।(ਹੇ ਭਾਈ!) ਆਪਣੇ ਮਨ ਵਿਚ ਤੂੰ ਸਦਾ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਨੂੰ ਯਾਦ ਰੱਖ, ਮਾਇਆ ਵਾਲੇ ਤੇਰੇ ਸਾਰੇ ਹੀ ਮੋਹ ਨਾਸ ਹੋ ਜਾਣਗੇ । ਹੇ ਮੇਰੇ ਮਨ! ਉਹ ਕਦੇ ਨਾਸ ਨਾਹ ਹੋਣ ਵਾਲਾ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਸਦਾ ਤੇਰੇ ਨਾਲ ਵੱਸਦਾ ਹੈ, ਤੂੰ ਉਸ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੇ ਪੇ੍ਰਮ-ਰੰਗ ਵਿਚ ਸਦਾ ਜੁੜਿਆ ਰਹੁ ।੪।(ਹੇ ਭਾਈ!) ਜਿਸ ਦੀ ਸੇਵਾ-ਭਗਤੀ ਵਿਚ ਲੱਗਿਆਂ (ਮਾਇਆ ਦੀ) ਸਾਰੀ ਭੁੱਖ ਦੂਰ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ, ਤੇ ਜਮਦੂਤ ਤੱਕ ਭੀ ਨਹੀਂ ਸਕਦੇ, (ਹੇ ਭਾਈ!) ਜਿਸ ਦੀ ਸੇਵਾ ਭਗਤੀ ਦੀ ਬਰਕਤਿ ਨਾਲ ਤੇਰਾ (ਹਰ ਥਾਂ) ਵੱਡਾ ਤੇਜ-ਪ੍ਰਤਾਪ ਬਣ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,ਤੇ ਤੂੰ ਸਦੀਵੀ ਆਤਮਕ ਜੀਵਨ ਵਾਲਾ ਬਣ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈਂ।੫ (ਹੇ ਭਾਈ!) ਜਿਸ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੇ ਸੇਵਕ-ਭਗਤ ਨੂੰ ਕੋਈ ਦੁੱਖ-ਕਲੇਸ਼ ਪੋਹ ਨਹੀਂ ਸਕਦਾ, ਕੋਈ ਐਬ ਨਹੀਂ ਚੰਬੜ ਸਕਦਾ, ਜਿਸ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੇ ਦਫ਼ਤਰ ਵਿਚ (ਸੇਵਕ ਭਗਤ ਪਾਸੋਂ ਕੀਤੇ ਕਰਮਾਂ ਦਾ ਕੋਈ) ਹਿਸਾਬ ਨਹੀਂ ਮੰਗਿਆ ਜਾਂਦਾ (ਕਿਉਂਕਿ ਸੇਵਾ ਭਗਤੀ ਦੀ ਬਰਕਤਿ ਨਾਲ ਉਸ ਪਾਸੋਂ ਕੋਈ ਕੁਕਰਮ ਹੁੰਦੇ ਹੀ ਨਹੀਂ) ਉਸ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੀ ਸੇਵਾ-ਭਗਤੀ ਉਚੇਚੇ ਤੌਰ ਤੇ ਕਰਦੇ ਰਹੁ । ੬। ਹੇ ਮੇਰੇ ਮਨ! ਜਿਸ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੇ ਘਰ ਵਿਚ ਕਿਸੇ ਚੀਜ਼ ਦੀ ਕਮੀ ਨਹੀਂ, ਜੇਹੜਾ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਇਕ ਆਪ ਹੀ ਆਪ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੋਇਆ ਅਨੇਕਾਂ ਰੂਪਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਪਰਗਟ ਹੋ ਰਿਹਾ ਹੈ,ਜਿਸ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੀ ਮਿਹਰ ਦੀ ਨਿਗਾਹ ਨਾਲ ਹਰੇਕ ਜੀਵ ਨਿਹਾਲ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ, ਤੂੰ ਉਸ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੀ ਸੇਵਾ-ਭਗਤੀ ਕਰ ।੭। (ਪਰ) ਹੇ ਨਾਨਕ! (ਆਪਣੇ ਆਪ) ਨਾਹ ਕੋਈ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਸਿਆਣਾ ਬਣ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ, ਨਾਹ ਕੋਈ ਮਨੁੱਖ (ਆਪਣੀ ਮਰਜ਼ੀ ਨਾਲ) ਮੂਰਖ ਟਿਕਿਆ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ, ਨਾਹ ਕੋਈ ਨਿਤਾਣਾ ਹੈ ਤੇ ਨਾਹ ਕੋਈ ਸੂਰਮਾ ਹੈ । ਹਰੇਕ ਜੀਵ ਉਸੇ ਪਾਸੇ ਹੀ ਲੱਗਾ ਹੋਇਆ ਹੈ ਜਿਸ ਪਾਸੇ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਨੇ ਉਸ ਨੂੰ ਲਾਇਆ ਹੋਇਆ ਹੈ । (ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੀ ਮਿਹਰ ਨਾਲ) ਜਿਸ ਦੀ ਕਿਸਮਤ ਜਾਗ ਪੈਂਦੀ ਹੈ, ਉਹੀ ਉਸ ਦਾ ਸੇਵਕ ਬਣਦਾ ਹੈ ।੮।੬।\\""},{"question":"Amọtẹkun maa parada di ọlọpaa ipinlẹ laipẹ – Akeredolu","answer":"Gomina ipinlẹ Ondo, Oluwarotimi Akeredolu, ti kede pe eto ti n lọ labẹnu, iṣẹ naa ko si ni i pẹ pari, ti yoo mu ki ikọ alaabo Amọtẹkun to wa nilẹ Yoruba lọwọ yii para da bii ọga, ti wọn yoo si di ọlọpaa ipinlẹ.Akeredolu sọrọ yii nibi asọye pataki ti wọn fi sọri ayẹyẹ ajọdun ‘June 12’ ti wọn tun n pe ni ayajọ iṣejọba demokiresi nilẹ wa, eyi to waye niluu Akurẹ, lọjọ Abamẹta, Satide yii. Ọgbẹni Fẹmi Aboriṣade lo ṣoju fun gomina yii nibẹ.Gomina naa ni ohun to le jẹ ki iṣejọba tẹsiwaju, ko si nitumọ, ni bi awọn ipele iṣakoso kọọkan ba ni ọlọpaa tirẹ, ki ijọba apapọ ni ọlọpaa tiwọn, ki ipinlẹ kọọkan lawọn ọlọpaa ipinlẹ, kọlọpaa ibilẹ naa si wa fawọn ijọba ibilẹ.Akeredolu ni: Niṣe lo yẹ ki ipinlẹ kọọkan maa pinnu iye ijọba ibilẹ ti wọn fẹ, ki eto iṣakoso baa le dele-doko, kawọn oṣiṣẹ ọba si le ba ohun to n ṣẹlẹ nipinlẹ ati ibilẹ kọọkan mu, tori iru ẹka iṣẹ ọba ati oṣiṣẹ ọba ti ipinlẹ ati ijọba ibilẹ kan maa nilo le yatọ gedengbe si ti omiiran. Bi ipinlẹ kan ba ṣe n pawo wọle si naa lo yẹ ko han lara awọn ijọba ibilẹ ti wọn ba ni, ki i ṣe eyi ti a n lo bayii, to jẹ ijọba apapọ lo n pin owo fun ijọba ibilẹ ati ipinlẹ kaakiri.Gomina yẹ ko jẹ alakooso ijọba to maa maa ṣe ifẹ awọn araalu ẹ loju mejeeji ni, ofin yẹ ko faaye gba wọn lati lo owo ti wọn ba n pa wọle nipinlẹ kaluku fun anfaani awọn ti wọn dibo fun un ni, ki i ṣe eyi ti apaṣẹ waa kan tun maa wa nibomi-in ti wọn tun gbọdọ gbọran si lẹnu lọran-anyan, ko si yẹ ki ijọba apapọ maa da si awọn ọrọ abẹle ipinlẹ ati ibilẹ kọọkan, ko yẹ ko kan wọn rara.”Akeredolu ko fọrọ sabẹ ahọn sọ nigba to sọ pe niṣe nireti ati agbọkanle tawọn eeyan ni lasiko ti wọn n dibo ‘June 12’, lọdun 1993 pada ja si pabo pẹlu bi orileede yii ti ri lasiko yii, ṣugbọn o loun ko fara mọ ipinya tabi iyapa, tori iyẹn kọ lọna abayọ si iṣoro to wa nilẹ yii.O ni afi tijọba ba ṣetan lati ṣatunṣe sawọn ohun to wọ ninu iwe ofin ilẹ wa, ti wọn si fun ọrọ aabo ni akiyesi pataki, igba naa ni ẹkọ to yẹ ka ri kọ ninu ibo ọdun ‘June 12’ ti a n ṣe ajọdun rẹ yii maa too so eso rere."},{"question":": Waxaad sheegtaan Siddii ay u daaweeysay Caa’isha Rasuulka (scw) oo ay ugu sameeysay dhiigjoojinta markii uu ku dhaawacmay dagaalkii Uxud?","answer":": Horaa looga jawaabay.    "},{"question":"Nolosha qof kasta waxa heysata dhibaato u gaar ah waa maxay?","answer":"Nolosha qof kasta waxaa heysa dhibaato u gaar ahWaxaa jiray Nin khabiir ah oo dadku jeclaayeen in ay talo u soo doontaan. Dadkaa waxay isugu jiraan nooc walba; dhalinyaro, Dumar hooyo ah, Odayaal, Gabdho da' yar, kuwa is qaba, kuwa kala tagay, iwm. Wuxuu isticmaali jiray Falsafad cajiib ah, hadba koox intuu Gees hoostii ku ballamiyo ayuu marki ay soo wada fariistaan oran jiray qof walba dhibta heysa haka waramo. Marki hadalki wada dhamaado qof kastana ka sheekeeyo dhibaatada, murugada, cabsida, welwelka, xanuunka iyo wax kastuu dareemayo ayaa dadku iska dareeri jireen ninki oo aan la hadlin sababtoo ah qof kasta wuxuu ka nixi jiray markuu dhageysto qofka kale dhibta heysata oo tiisa ka weyn! iyaga dhexdooda ayaana isu tacsiyeyn jiray!Qeybo ka mid ah dhibaatooyinka waaweyn ama yar yar ee haysta dhalinyarada waayadan kuwaasoo ay xal u raadinayaan ama u heli la’yihiin:1. Isbedel dhab ah sidi ay u sameyn lahaayeen2. Guul Nolosha sidi ay u gaari lahaayeen3. Guur iyo Guri sidi ay u sameyn lahaayeen4. Shaqo fiican sidi ay u heli lahaayeen ama dallacaad tan ay hada joogaan5. Jaceylkooda inuu dhab yahay sidi ay isugu cadeyn lahaayeen6. Waxbarasho ama imtixaanka siday u gudbi lahaayeen7. Dhafar ama soo jeedka sidi ay isaga jari lahaayeen8. Sidi ay Caan u noqon lahaayeen9. Ganacsi cusub sidi ay u abuuri lahaayeen ama dhaqaale u sameyn lahaayeen10. Tolkood ama Siyaasi ay isku reer yihiin sidi ay u difaaci lahaayeen11. Xiriir ka xumaaday ama qof ay kala hareen sidi ay u hilmaami lahaayeen12. Qofka xanta, wax ka sheega ama caaya sidi ay isaga dhicin lahaayeen13. Is tus-tus iyo siday u soo bandhigi lahaayeen dhar qaali ah oo ay xiran yihiin, Mobile-ki u dambeeyay, saacad sare ama gaari yar14. Sawir qurux badan oo ay Suuq ku helaan sidi ay u geli lahaayeen"},{"question":"Inis dom faoi Annraoi Ó Liatháin. ","answer":"Scríbhneoir Éireannach ab ea Annraoi Ó Liatháin (1917 - 1981). Bhí stíl chorraitheach éasca scríbhneoireachta aige a mheall go leor daoine óga i leith na léitheoireachta Gaeilge, go háirithe sa leabhar Laochra na Machairí, stair na Meiriceánach Dúchasach a throid in aghaidh ionradh na Stát Aontaithe ar a dtailte sa 19ú céad. Ní raibh sé ina chainteoir dúchais sa chiall is déine, ach is minic a chuaigh sé ar cuairt go Gaeltacht na Rinne i gContae Phort Láirge nuair a bhí sé ina pháiste. Tá blas na canúna sin ar go leor dár scríobh sé. Chaith sé seal ina óige ina bhall de Chraobh na hAiséirí de Chonradh na Gaeilge, craobh a d'iompaigh ina heagraíocht neamhspleách pholaitiúil faoin ainm Glúin na Buaidhe (leagan Ghaeilge Uladh de \\"Ghlúin an Bhua\\" an Chaighdeáin). Ba bhall gníomhach é de Shinn Féin agus chaith sé seal ina uachtarán ar Chonradh na Gaeilge.Fuair Annraoi Ó Liatháin bás i dtús na n-ochtóidí. B'é Cois tSiúire (1981) an leabhar deireanach a chríochnaigh sé. Leabhar taistil ar cheantar na nDéise agus ar dheisceart Chontae Thiobraid Árann atá ann. "},{"question":"Deprem kira yardımı kimlere verilir?","answer":"Söz konusu yardım, depremde binaları tamamen yıkılmış kişilere sağlanan bir haktır. Deprem kira yardımından felaket nedeniyle evlerinde orta veya ağır derecede hasar oluşan vatandaşlar da yararlanabilir. Başvuru aşamasında kişinin ev sahibi veya kiracı konumunda olması herhangi bir engel teşkil etmez."},{"question":"Ата-Мекен тарыхына болгон кызыгуу эмне үчүн күч алды?","answer":"Кыргызстандын эгемендүүлүккө ээ болушу менен элдин Ата-Мекен тарыхына болгон кызыгуусу куч алды.Кыргыз элинин нечен кылымдарды карыткан тарыхы, андагы мамлекеттүүлүк идеясы улуттук жана мамлекеттик идеологиянын негизин түзөөрү, элди, айрыкча жаштарды патриоттук духта тарбиялоодо өзгөчө маанилүү роль ойноору айкын көрүндү."},{"question":"Kas ir su kokia daina 2023 metails Eurovizijoje atstovavo Lietuvą?","answer":"2023-ių metų Eurovizijos dainų konkurse Lietuvą atstovavo Monika Linkytė su daina \\"Stay\\" su kuria ji laimėjo nacionalinę atranką. Dainų konkurse Monika surinko 127 taškus ir buvo 11-oje vietoje. 2023-ių metų Eurovizijos nugalėtoja tapo Loreen su daina \\"Tattoo\\"."},{"question":"Туура аналогияны таңдаңыз.Мугалим : бор(А) үй : бөлмө(Б) врач : халат(В) китеп : окуу куралы (Г) архитектор : циркуль","answer":"Эталондук(үлгү) жуп:  мугалим : бор;1)Үлгү жуптагы байланыштын түрү :  Зат жана анын жардамчысы байланышы;2)Зат жана анын жардамчысы байланышындагы аналогиянын түрү: Утурумдук жардамчы;Мугалим – жардамчыга муктаж түшүнүк, бор – жардамчы зат. Ошондой эле, мугалим кесиптин бир түрү жана бор анын жумушунда жардамчы курал катары колдонулат. (А)вариантында үй кесип эмес, бул вариантты туура жооптордун катарынан чыгарабыз. Врач кесиптин түрү болгону менен, халат анын жардамчы куралы боло албайт. Китеп : окуу куралы аналогиянын байланышы – категория байланышы. Архитектор кесиптин бир түрү, ал циркулду жардамчы курал катары колдонот. Архитектор : циркуль – туура жооп(Г)."},{"question":"昭和29年に行われたわが国初のプロレスの国際試合で、力道山・木村政彦組と対戦したのは「何兄弟」でしょう？","answer":"シャープ兄弟"},{"question":"Sallar asuba raka'a nawa ce?(a)data(b)biyu(c)uku","answer":"Biyu"},{"question":"மலைபடுகடாம் பற்றி குறிப்பு வரைக ","answer":"விடை :நமக்குக் கிடைத்துள்ள சங்கப் பாடல்களாக எட்டுத்தொகையும், பத்துப் பாட்டும் போற்றிப் புகழப்படுகின்றன. சங்க காலத்தில் காதலும் வீரமுமே பாடுபொருள்களாக விளங்கின. புலவர்களும் புறத்துடன் அகத்தையும் சேர்த்தே பாடினர்.சங்ககால மாந்தர்தம் வீரம் காதல் பற்றிய உதிரிப் பாடல்களின் தொகுப்பாக எட்டுத் தொகை நூல்கள் விளங்குகின்றன. மேலும் அக்கால மக்களின் ஒரே மனவுணர்ச்சியை அல்லது அவர்தம் வாழ்வில் நடந்த நிகழ்ச்சியை மட்டுமே கொண்டவைதாம் எட்டுத்தொகை நூற்கள் என்றும் கூறலாம்.மேற்குறிப்பிட்ட உதிரிப்பாடல்களின் வளர்ச்சியே நெடும்பாடல்களாய் அமைந்தது. நெடும்பாடல்கள் தொகுக்கப்பட்டு பத்துப் பாட்டாய் அமைக்கப்பட்டுள்ளது. பத்துப் பாட்டு நூல்கள் சங்க கால மன்னர்களின் வீரம், கொடை, நாடு, காவல், நாட்டுவளம், மலைவளம், முதலியவற்றை தெள்ளத் தெளிவாக நமக்கு எடுத்துக் காட்டுகின்றன.பத்துப் பாட்டு நூல்களைத் தொகுத்தவர் யார் என்று நாம் அறிய எந்தச் சான்றும் நமக்குக் கிடைக்கவில்லை. ஆனால் மலைபடுகடாத்துள் ‘தீயினன்ன ஒண்செங்கதிர் காந்தள் ‘ என்ற அடியின் உரையில் நசினார்க்கினியர் ‘இவர் செய்த செய்யுளை நல்லிசைப் புலவர் செய்த ஏனைச் செய்யுட்களுடன் சஙகத்தார் கோவாமல் நீக்குவர் ‘ என்று எழுதி இருக்கிறார்.இந்த அடியில் குற்றம் இருந்தால் நூலைத் தொகுக்கும் சங்கத்தார் இச் செய்யுளைச் சேர்க்க மாட்டார்கள் எனும் பொருள்பட நச்சினார்க்கினியர் எழுதி உள்ளார். எனவே பத்துப் பாட்டு நூல்களைத் தொகுத்தவர் சங்கத்தார் என்று தமிழ் இலக்கிய வரலாறு எனும் நூல் நூலில் திரு சி. பாலசுப்பிரமணியம் கூறுகிறார்.பேராசிரியர் ‘பாட்டு ‘ என்றே இந்நூல் தொகுப்பினைக் குறிப்பிடுகிறார். மயிலைநாதரின் நன்னூல் உரையில் தான் பத்துப் பாட்டு எனும் பெயர் முதன்முதல் காணப்படுகிறது.மயிலைநாதர் கி. பி. 14ஆம் நூற்றாண்டிற்குப் பிற்பட்டவர். எனவே பத்துப் பாட்டு எனும் பெயர் பதின்மூன்று, பதினான்காம் நூற்றாண்டிற்குப் பிறகுதான் வழங்கப்பட்டிருத்தல் வேண்டும் என்று ‘பத்துப்பாட்டு ஆராய்ச்சி ‘ எனும் நூலில் மா. இராசமாணிக்கனார் ‘ கூறுகிறார்.ஆனால் ‘சங்க இலக்கியம் ‘ எனும் நூலில் திரு. இரா. தண்டாயுதம் ‘உரையாசிரியர்களில் மூத்தவரான இளம்பூரணர் தம் உரையில் பத்துப்பாட்டு என்று குறிப்பிட்டுளார். எனவே இப்பெயர் பேராசிரியருக்கு முன்பே வழங்கி வந்துள்ளது ‘ என்று கூறுகிறார்.சங்க நூல்கள் பாட்டும் தொகையும் என்று பாட்டை முதலில் நிறுத்தியே கூறப்பட்டிருக்கின்றன. இதிலிருந்து நெடும்பாடல்களான பத்துப் பாட்டு நூல்களுக்கு முதன்மை தரப்பட்டுள்ளதை அறிய முடிகிறது.பத்துப் பாட்டு நூல்களுல் திருமுருகாற்றுப்படை, சிறுபாணாற்றுப்படை, பொருநராற்றுப்படை, பெரும்பாணாற்றுப்படை, மலைபடுகடாம் ஆகிய ஐந்தும் ஆற்றுப்படை நூல்கள் ஆகும்.ஆற்றுப்படையிலக்கியம் என்பது தமிழ் மொழியில் மட்டும் தான் உள்ளது. வேறு எம்மொழியிலுமில்லை என்பது தமிழுக்கே உரிய தனிச்சிறப்பாகும்.மற்றவற்றைக் காட்டிலும் மலைபடுகடாம் சில தனிச்சிறப்புகளைப் பெற்றுள்ளது. பாட்டுடைத்தலைவன் அல்லது பாடுபவன் பெயரால் மற்ற ஆற்றுப்படைகளின் பெயர்கள் அமைந்துள்ளன. ஆனால் மலைபடுகடாம் மட்டும் அந்நூலில் பயின்று வரும் தொடரின் பெயரால் வழங்கப்படுகிறதுமலைபடு கடாஅ மாதிரத் தியம்ப (348)எனும் இந்த சிறப்பான அடிக்கு மலைகளாகிய யானை உண்டாகின்ற ஒலி திசைகளெல்லாம் ஒலிப்ப என்று நச்சினார்க்கினியர் உரை எழுதிகிறார். ‘கடாம் ‘ என்பதற்கு ஒலி என்ற பொருளும் உண்டு; எனவே மலைபடுகடாம் என்பதற்கு மலையிடத்தே உண்டாகும் ஒலி எனப் பொருள் கொள்ளலாம் என சிலம்பொலி செல்லப்பனார் கூறுகிறார்.இந்நூலின் பெயர் ‘கூத்தராற்றுப்படை ‘ என்றிருந்திருக்க வேண்டும் என்று சிலர் கூறுவர். கூத்தன் ஆற்றுப் படுத்தப் படுவதால் அப்பெயர் கொண்டு அழைக்கலாம் எனக் கூறுவர்.ஆனாலிந்நூலில் கூத்தர் என்ற சொல்லேயில்லை என்பது கவனிக்க வேண்டிய ஒன்றாகும்.மலையின்கண் எழும்புகின்ற இருபது வகையான ஓசைகளூம் ஒரு யானை பிளிறி எழுப்புவது போன்று புலவர்க்குத் தோன்றுகிறது. எனவே மலைக்கு யானையை உவமித்து அதன்கண் பிறந்த ஓசையை கடாமெனச் சிறப்பித்தனால் குறிப்பிட்ட நூலுக்கு மலைபடுகடாம் என்பதே சாலப் பொருத்தமாகும்.மலைபடு கடாமை எழுதியவர் ‘இரணிய முட்டத்துப் பெருங்குன்றுர்ப் பெருங்கெளசிகனார் ‘ ஆவார். அவர் மதுரையை அடுத்த நத்தம் மலைப் பகுதியைச் சேர்ந்தவர் என்று மான். இராசமாணிக்கனார் கூறுகிறார்.ஆனால் திருவாளர்கள் மா. நவநீதகிருட்டினனும் பின்னத்தூராரும் அவரை தொண்டை நாட்டினர் என்று குறிப்பிடுகிறார்கள்.இரணிய முட்டம் என்பது பாண்டியப் பேரரசின் ஆணைக்குள் அடங்கிய சிறுநாடு என்றும் கூறப்படுகிறது. தொல்காப்பியத்தில் பேராசிரியரின் விளக்க உரை சான்றின்படி அவர் அந்தணர் என்றும் கூறப்படுகிறது. ஆசிரியர் இயற்றியதாக நற்றிணையில் ரண்டு செய்யுள்கள் காணப்படுகின்றன.நூலின் பாட்டுடைத் தலைவனாக ‘பல்குன்றக் கோட்டத்துச் செங்கண் மாத்துவேள் நன்னன் சேய் நன்னன் ‘ விளங்குகிறான்.அவனை ‘நன்னன் சேய் நன்னன் ‘ (64) என்று மலைபடுகடாம் சுட்டிக் காட்டுகிறது.‘நன் ‘ எனும் பொருள் வளம் , நன்மை முதலியவற்றைக் குறிக்கும். அதனுடன் ‘அன் ‘ விகுதி சேர்த்து அப்பெயர் வந்திருக்கலாம்.அவன் பெண் கொலை புரிந்த கண்கானங்கிழான் நன்னனினும் வேறானவன் என்று மா. இராசமாணிக்கனார் கூறுவார். ஆனால் கலைங்கலஞ்சியமும் அபிதான சிந்தாமணியும் ‘இவன் பெண் கொலை புரிந்த நன்னனின் மகன் ‘ என்று மொழிகின்றன.நன்னன் என்பது வேளிர் குடியைச் சேர்ந்த அரசர்க்குப் பண்டைக் காலத்தில் வழங்கப்பட்டு வந்துள்ளது.பழந்தமிழ் மன்னர்கள் நாடுகளைக் கோட்டமாகப் பிரித்திருந்தனர். பல்குன்றக் கோட்டம் என்பது நன்னனின் ஆட்சிக்குரிய பகுதியாக விளங்கியிருக்க வேண்டும்.தற்போதைய திருப்பதியில் கிடைத்த கல்வெட்டு ஒன்று ‘பல்குன்றக் கோட்டத்துச் சிலைநாட்டுத் திருவேங்கடம் ‘ என்று குறிப்பிடுவதிலிருந்து பண்டைய வேங்கட மலைப்பகுதி பல்குன்றக் கோட்டத்தில் அடங்கி இருந்தது என்று கூறலாம்.தற்பொழுது திருவண்ணாமலைக்கு மேற்கில் உள்ள செங்கமே நன்னனது தலைநகரம் ஆகும். பண்டைக் காலத்தில் அதன் பெயர் ‘செங்கணம் ‘ என்பதாகும்.தற்பொழுது சண்முக நதி எனப்படுவது சேயாறு என்றும், தற்பொழுது அப்பகுதியில் காளகண்டேசுவரர் என்ற ஆலயம் அந்தக் காலத்தில் காரியுண்டக் கடவுள் என்றும் அழைக்கப்பட்டிருக்ககலாம்.மேலும் நவிரமலையானது திருசூலகிரி என்றும் பருவதமலை என்றும் வழங்கப்பட்டுள்ளது. ‘திருமழை ‘ என்று மங்கலச் சொல்லில் தொடங்குவதிருந்து 583 அடிகளைக் கொண்டுள்ளது.இந்நூல் முழுதும் கூத்தனின் கூற்றாகவே இருப்பது தனிச்சிறப்பாகும். பரிசில் பெற்று வரும் கூத்தன் ஒருவன் பரிசில் பெறப்போகின்றவனை‘கலம்பெறு கண்ணுள ரொக்கல் தலைவ ‘ (58)என்று விளித்துப் பேசுகிறான். பிறகு அவன் நன்னனை அடைய வழிகூறி ஆற்றுப்படுத்துகிறான்.வருகின்ற கூட்ட்த்தின் தலைவனைப் பார்த்து அழைப்பதாக அவ்விளியைக் கொள்ளலாம். பலர் கூடி இருக்க ஒருவனிடம் மட்டும் பேசுவதல் ஆகாது. எனவேதான் கூறுகின்றவன் செய்திகளை அனைவரிடமும் கூறுகிறான். கடைசி அடிகளில்‘…. உம்முன்தலைவன் தாமரை மலைய…. ‘ (568,69)என்று அந்தக் கூட்டத்தாரைப் பார்த்தே பரிசில் பெற்றுவரும் கூத்தன் கூறுவதிலிருந்து அதனை அறிய முடிகிறது.அந்தக் கூட்டம் ஒரு காட்டு மர நிழலில் தங்கி உள்ளது. அக்கூட்டத்தை நோக்கிப் பரிசு பெற்றவன் வருகிறான். ஆறு கடலை நோக்கி வருவது போல் அவன் பல பரிசுப் பொருள்களுடன் வருகிறான்.தங்கி இருக்கும் கூட்டத்தைக் காண்கிறான். இக்கூட்டத்தில் இருப்பவர்களிடம் பல்வேறு இசைக்கருவிகள் உள்ளன. அவற்றில் சிறப்பாக ‘அரிக்குரள் தட்டை ‘ என்ற ஒன்றக் காண முடிகிறது. அஃது ஒலித்தால் தவளையின் குரல் கேட்கும்.அது போன்றே ‘கரடிகை ‘ எனும் தோலிசைக்கருவி ஒலித்தால் கரடி கத்தும் குரலைக் கேட்கலாம். மேலும் அவர்கள் முழவு, ஆகுளி, எல்லரி, பதலை, யாழ் போன்ற பல்லிசைக்கருவிகளை வைத்திருந்தனர்.அவர்கள் வைத்திருந்த பேரியாழ் ஒன்பது நரம்புகளைக் கொண்டதாகும். சங்க காலத்தில் இருபத்தோரு நரம்புகள் கொண்ட பேரியாழும் இருந்தது எனப் புறநானூறும் சிலப்பதிகாரமும் கூறுவதாக தமது யாழ்நூலில் திரு விபுலானந்தர் கூறுகிறார்.சங்க கால நூலகளில் மலைபடுகடாம் ஒன்றே பதிமூன்று இசைக்கருவிகள் பற்றிக் கூறித் தனிச்சிறப்பு பெறுகிறது. பெருங்கெளசிகனார் இசை மீது பற்றுக் கொண்டிருந்ததால்தான் பல்வேறு இசைக்கருவிகளை ஊன்றிக் கவனித்துள்ளார். மேலும் இசை சார்ந்த உவமைகள் பலவற்றை அவர் ஆங்காங்கே தொட்டுக் காட்டியிருப்பதிலிருந்தும் அதனை அறியலாம்.அந்த இசைக்கருவிகளை அவர்கள் மிகவும் கவனமாகப் பாதுகாப்புடன் வைத்துள்ளனர். பல சிறிய, பெரிய பைகளில் அவைகளைப் போட்டுச் சுருக்கிக் கட்டி வைத்துள்ளனர்.ஒரு பெரிய கோலின் இருமுனைகளிலும் சுமை சமமாக இருக்கும்படி அவற்றைப் பிணைத்துள்ளனர். அக்கம்பில் அப்பைகள் இருப்பது கார்காலத்திலே பழுக்கும் பலாக்காய்களைப் போன்று உள்ளது.அழகான பெண்ணின் அடிவயிற்றிலிருந்து மேல்நோக்கி வளர்ந்து படிந்த மயிரின் ஒழுங்கு போல் யாழில் தையல் உள்ளது என்பது மிகச் சிறப்பான உவமையாகும். அதே உவமையை பொருநராற்றுப்படையும்‘எய்யா இளஞ்சூல் செய்யோன் அவ்வயிற்றுஐதுமயிர் ஒழுகிய தோற்றம் போல ‘ (பொரு. 6-7)என்று கூறுவது குறிப்பிடத்தக்கதாகும்.‘ஆகுளி ‘ எனும் நல்லிசைக்கருவி ஒலிப்பது போன்று ஆந்தைகள் கத்தின என்பதை‘…. ஆகுளி கடுப்பக்குடிஞை யிரட்டு நெடுமலை யடுக்கத்து ‘ (140-141)என்று பாடுகிறார். மேலும் பலவகை கருவியிசை ஒரே நேரத்தில் ஒலிப்பதைப் போல் ஆல மரத்திலிருந்த பறவைகள் ஒலி எழுப்பின என்பதைகோடுபல முரஞ்சிய கோளி யாளத்துக்கூடியத் தன்ன குரல்புணர் புள்ளின் ‘என்று காட்டுகிறார். அவ்வாறு ஓசைகளில் தம் நெஞ்சைப் பறிகொடுத்ததால் தான் மலையிடை எழுந்த ஓசையை தம் நூலுக்கே பெயராக அமைத்தார் என்று எண்ணத் தோன்றுகிறது.அந்தக் கூட்டத்தில் உள்ள விறலியின் வருணனை சிறப்பாகக் கூறப்படுகிறது. பெரும்பாணாற்றுப்படையில் விறலி வருணனை இல்லை. பொருநராற்றுப்படையில் விறலியினிருபது உறுப்புகளும், சிறுபாணாற்றுப்படையில் பத்து உறுப்புகளும் வருணிக்கப்படும் போது மலைபடுகடாத்தில் மூன்று உறுப்புகளே வருணிக்கப்பட்டுள்ளது குறிப்பிடத்தக்கதாகும்.மேலும் மற்ற ஆற்றுப்படைகள் முடிமுதல் தொடங்கி அடிவரை கூறும் கேசாதிபாத முறையில் அமைந்திருக்கையில் மலைபடுகடாம் பாதாதிகேச முறையைப் பின்பற்றுகிறது.விறலியின் அடி மலையில் நடந்து வருந்தியதால் இளைத்திருக்கிறது. அதற்கு உவமையாக நாயின் நாக்கைக் கூறுவது சங்க நூல்களின் வழக்கமாகும். மற்ற ஆற்றுப்படைகளில் விறலியின் அடிக்கு உவமை கூறும் பொழுது நாய் என்ற சொல்லே பயன்படுத்தப் பட்டிருக்கும் பொழுது மலைபடுகடாத்தில் மட்டுமே ‘ஞமலி ‘ என்ற சொல் பயன்படுத்தப்பட்டுள்ளது.பிற ஆற்றுப்படைகளில் பிறமொழிச் சொற்கள் மிகையாகக் கலந்திருக்க மலைபடுகடாத்தில் மட்டுமே பிறமொழிச் சொற்கள் இடம் பெறவில்லை என்று பத்துப்பாட்டு ஆராய்ச்சியில் திரு மா. இராசமாணிக்கனார் கூறுகிறார்.பரிசில் பெற்று வருபவன் தான் நன்னனிடமிருந்து வருவதைக் கூறுகிறான். நன்னனை அறிமுகம் செய்யும் முன்னர்‘புனைதார்ப் பொலிந்த வண்டுபடு மார்பின்வளைபுனை யெழின்முலை வாங்கமைத் திரடோன்மலர்போன் மழைக்கண் மங்கையர் கணவன் ‘ (56-58)என்று அவன் தேவியர் அறிமுகம் செய்யப்படுகின்றனர். இவ்வாறு முதலில் மனைவியரைப் புகழ்ந்து கூறி அவர் கணவன் என்று தலைவனைக் கூறுவது மலைபடுகடாத்தில் மட்டுமே காணப்படுகிறது. மேலும் பிற ஆற்றுப்படைகள் பாடப்படும் தலைவனின் பிறப்பு முன்னோர் பற்றிக் கூறும்போது மலைபடுகடாமும் சிறுபாணாற்றுப்படையும் அங்ஙனம் கூறாதது ஈண்டு நோக்கத்தக்க ஒன்றாகும். நன்னது வீரமானது ‘முனைபாழ் படுக்கும் துன்னரும் துப்பின் ‘ (59) என்று பாராட்டப்படுகிறது. இப்படிப்பட்ட சிறப்புகளை உடைய நன்னன் நாட்டிற்குச் செல்லும் வழியைக் கூத்தன் கூற முற்படுகிறான்.அவர்கள் கூடியிருக்குமிடம் நன்னனது நவிரமலை என்றும் அந்த மலை அடிவாரத்திலிருந்தே கூத்தன் ஆற்றுப் படுத்துகிறான் என்று கூறலாம். மா. இராசமாணிக்கனார் தம் பத்துப்பாட்டு ஆராய்ச்சியிலிதை உறுதியாகக் கூறுகிறார். அடுத்து நன்னனது நாட்டை அடையும் வழியைக் கூத்தன் கூறத் தொடங்குகிறான்.செல்லும் வழியில் எள் விளைந்திருக்கும். அவை மிக வளமாகத் தோற்றம் அளிக்கும். ஒரு கைப்பிடியில் பருத்த ஏழு காய்கள் கொள்ளத்தக்க அளவு அவை இருக்கும். அவற்றின் உள்ளே நெய் நிரம்பி இருக்கும் என்பதை‘பிடிஏழ் நெய்கொள ஒழுகினபல்கவர் ஈர் எள் ‘ (105-106)என்ற அடிகள் காட்டுகின்றன.மேலும் அந்த முல்லை நிலத்தின் கண் ஏர்கொண்டு உழாமல் களைகொட்டினாலே கொத்திப் பயிர் செய்யும் தோட்டங்களுண்டாம். அவற்றில் வெண்சிறுகடுகு விளைந்திருக்கும்.கிழங்குகளை அதிகமாகப் போகும் வழியில் காணலாம். பெண்யானையின் மடிந்துள்ள முழங்காலின் அளவுக்கு அந்தக் கிழங்கு பருத்திருக்கும். உயவைக்கொடி எனும் ஒரு கொடி காணப்படும். அக்கொடியை உண்டால் நீர்விடாய் தீர்ந்துவிடும்.ஆங்கே பெரிய ஆந்தைகள் கூவிக் கொண்டே இருக்கும் அசைகின்ற கிளைகளிலே பலாக்காய்கள் காய்த்துத் தொங்கும். அவை பார்ப்பதற்குக் கூத்தருடைய மத்தளங்கள் போல் காட்சி தரும்.முன்பு கூத்தருடைய இசைக்கருவிகளுக்கு பலாக்காய்களை உவமையாகக் கூறிய பெருங்கெளசிகனார் தற்பொழுது பலாக்காய்களுக்கு கூத்தனின் மத்தளத்தை காட்டும் நயம் மகிழத்தக்கதாகும்.வயல்களிலே கரும்பும் ஐவன நெல்லும் வெண்ணெல்லும் முற்றி விளைந்திருக்கும். படைவீரர்கள் எதிரிகளால் தாக்கப்பட்டுப் பின்வாங்குகையில் தடுமாறுவது போல கரும்புகள் காற்று மோதுவதால் அசைந்து தடுமாறும்.பருந்துகள் தசைத்துண்டம் என்று எடுத்து ஏமாற்றம் அடைந்து போகும் அளவுக்கு தீயைப் போன்று ஒளிதரக்கூடிய செங்காந்தள் அரும்புகள் சிதறி இருக்கும்.தொடர்ந்து சற்று தொலைவு சென்றால் அங்கே கானவர் வசிக்கின்ற சிறுகுடிசைகள் இருக்கும். அக்குடிசைகளில் வாழ்வோர் செல்கின்றவர்களை விருந்தினராக ஏற்றுக் கொள்வார்கள்.மான், பன்றி, உடும்பு ஆகியவற்றின் தசைத் தொகுதியையும் மூங்கில் அரிசியையும் அங்குள்ள குறமகளிர் கொடுத்து உபசரிப்பார்கள்.அவர்களின் விருந்தோம்பலை ஏற்று அன்றிரவு அங்கே தங்கி களைப்பாறி விடிந்தபின்பு செல்லலாம். மறுநாள் பயணத்தில் மலைச்சாரலிலிருக்கும். சிறிய ஊர்கள் குறுக்கிடும்.அவ்வூர்களில் உள்ளோரிடம் நன்னனின் கூத்தர் நாங்கள் என்று கூறினால் மென்சொல் பேசுவர். மேலும் தினைச்சோறு, முள்ளம்பன்றியின் தசை, நெல்லால் ஆக்கிய கள், புளிச்சாறு மோர் ஆகியனவற்றை வயிறு நிரம்பும் அளவுக்கு அவர்கள் கொடுப்பர்.சந்தனக்கட்டை, அகில் மாணிக்கம் ஆகியவற்றைப் பரிசில்களாகத் தரும் வழக்கம் அவர்களுக்கு உண்டு. வழியில் செல்பவர்கள் புதிய குவளை மலர்களைத் தொடக்கூடாது. பாதைகளில் அவ்வப்போது காட்சி அளிக்கும் வரையர மகளிர் இருக்கும் நிலைமையைப் பார்த்தல் கூடாது. மீறிச் செய்தால் உயிர் போகும்படி வெம்பி நடுங்கும் நிலையை அடையக் கடவர்.அவ்வழிகளில் பல தீமைகளும் உண்டாம். தினைக்கதிரைத் தின்றழிக்கும் பன்றிகளைத் தடுக்கப் பொறி அமைக்கப்பட்டிருக்கும். மக்கள் நடமாட்டம் அற்ற வழிகளில் பாம்புகள் மறைந்துள்ள குழிகள் உள்ளன. குறவர்கள் பரண்மீது இருந்து ஆனைக்கூட்டங்களை விரட்ட வீசும் கவண் கற்கள் வந்து விழும். கருங்குரங்குகள் வழியில் வந்து விளையாடும்.முதலைகள் நிறைந்த வழுக்குகின்ற காட்டாறுகள் உள்ளன. குளங்களில் பாசி படர்ந்து வழியை மறைத்துக் கொண்டிருக்கும். மரக்கொடிகளையும் மூங்கில் கோல்களையும் பிடித்துக் கொண்டு ஒருவரை ஒருவர் பாதுகாத்துக் கொண்டு மிக்க கவனத்துடன் மேற்கண்ட பகுதிகளைக் கடக்க வேண்டும்.அவ்வாறு வழி சொல்லும் கூத்தன் ஆபத்து நிறைந்து உள்ளது என்று கூறுவது ஆற்றுப்படைகளுள் மலைபடுகடாம் ஒன்றில்தான் காணப்படுகிறது.வழியில் பழைமையான கோடையில் உள்ள காரி உண்டிக்கடவுளைத் தொழுது செல்லல் நலம் பயக்கும். அங்கு நரம்பிசைக் கருவிகளை ஒலித்தல் கூடாது. ஏனினில் அவ்வப்போது பெய்யும் சிறு தூறலில் யாழின் நரம்பு மத்தளத்தின் கண் ஆகியன நனைந்து விடும்.அழகிய காட்சிகளை அளவுக்கு மீறிச் சுவைத்து மகிழ்ந்து மயில்கள் ஆடுவதையும், குரங்குகள் பாய்வதையும், தேனடைகள் ஒழுகுவதையும் நீண்ட நேரம் பார்த்திருந்தால் செல்கின்ற வழி மாறுபட்டுப் போகும்.அடுத்து காட்டு வழியில் செல்ல நேரிடும். வேடர்கள் அம்பு பட்டு வீழ்ந்த பன்றி அங்கு கிடக்கும். உராய்ந்த மூங்கிலின் தீயில் மயிர்ப்புகை கமழாதபடிக்கு, சுட்டுப் பதமாக அப்பன்றியை உண்ணலாம். மிச்சம் உள்ள தசைத் தொகுதியை கட்டிப் பொதியாக எடுத்துக் கொண்டு சுனைநீர் குடித்து இரவில் கற்குகைக்குள் தங்கலாம்.மறுநாள் விடியலில் கிளம்பிப் பயணம் மேற்கொள்ள வேண்டும். வழியில் களிற்றை விழுங்கி பெரிய படம் உடைய பருத்த பாம்பு கிடக்கும். அதைப் பார்த்து விலகிச் செல்ல வேண்டும்.மேலும் சென்றால் நச்சுப்பூக்கள் காணலாம். தின்றவர்கள் உயிரைப் பறிக்கும் பழங்களும் உண்டு. அவற்றைத் தாண்டிச் சென்றால் மலை உச்சியை அடையலாம். அங்கிருந்து பார்த்தால் பல நாடுகளைக் காணலாம்.மலைக் குறவரும் அவ்விடம் வந்தால் வழி தெரியாமல் மருள்வர். எனவே மலையில் எதிரொலிக்கும்பட்யாக பல வித கருவிகளை ஒலித்து நல்லிசை எழுப்ப வேண்டும். அதைக்கேட்டு காட்டைக் காக்கின்ற கானவர் விரைவாக ஓடிவருவர்.நல்ல பழம், பூக்கள், தந்து உபசரிப்பார்கள் மலை அடிவாரத்திலிருந்து மலை உச்சி செல்லும் வழியை வழி சொல்லும் கூத்தன்அவ்வாறு கூறி மலையில் எழும் ஒலிகளை விவரிக்கிறான்.வரைமகளிர் அருவியில் வந்து குளிட்து குடைந்து ஆடும் ஓசை, முள்ளம்பன்றியின் முள் குத்தியதால் அழும் கானவர் அழுகை ஆகியன கேட்கலாம். மேலும் தங்கள் காதலனின் மார்பில் புலி பாய்ந்து உண்டான புண்ணை ஆற்ற கொடிச்சியர் பாடும்ப்பாடலைக் கேட்கலாம் என்பதுகொடுவரி பாய்ந்தெனக் கொழுநர் மார்பில்நெடுவசி விழுப்புண் தணிமார் காப்பெனஅறல்வாழ் கூந்தற் கொடிச்சியர் பாடல் (302-304)என்ற அடிகளிலிருந்து புலனாகிறது.பெரிய கொல்லையில் தவறி விழுந்த குட்டிக்காக மந்தி சுற்றத்துடன் கலங்கும் ஓசை, கண்ணேணியில் ஏறித் தேனடை அழிக்கும் கானவர் ஓசை, யானைப்பாகர் எழுப்பும் ஓசை, கிளி ஓட்டும் மகளிர் ஓசை, எருமைக்கடாக்களின் ஆரவார ஒலி, பன்றியை விரட்டும் பறையின் ஓசை ஆகிய ஒசைகள் எல்லாம் கூடி மலைகளாகிய யானைகளிடமிருந்து பிறந்த ஓசையாக எல்லாத் திசைகளிலும் ஒலிக்கும்.இக்கருத்துதான் முன்பே குறிப்பிட்டபடி ‘மலைபடுகடாத்து மாதிரத்து இயம்ப ‘ என்று காட்டப்படுகிறது.அங்கிருந்து என்றால் மலையூர் என்ற ஊரைக் காணலாம். மலை ஏறிய களைப்பு நீங்க அவ்வூரில் சிலநாள்கள் தங்கலாம். பிறகு சிறிது தொலைவு சென்றால் நன்னனுடைய மலையைக் காணலாம்.அம்மலையை வாழ்த்தி விறலியர் குறிஞ்சிப் பண் பாடி அங்கே உறையும் தெய்வங்களை வாழ்த்தலாம். அப்பொழுது மழைத்திவலைகள் தூவும். எனவே கருவிகளில் நீர்பட்டு நனையாதபடி மலைக் குகைக்களில் தங்கிக் கொள்ளலாம்.பிறகு மலையை மிகவும் கவனமாகக் கடந்து செல்லல் நலம் பயக்கும். மத்தளங்களை பிணைத்துள்ள தடியை ஊன்றுகோகாகக் கொண்டு வழுக்குக்குழிகளிீல் விழாமல் மெல்ல மெல்லச் செல்ல வேண்டும்.அவ்வழி மிகவும் துன்பம் தரும். எனவே வெயில் தணிந்த நேரத்தில் செல்ல வேண்டும். கொடிகள் அடைத்திருக்கும் பாதையில் உள்ள சிறுவழியில் தொடர்ச்சியை விடாமல் ஒருவர் பின் ஒருவராய்ச் செல்லல் நலம்.மேற்கொண்டு செல்லும் போது வழியில் பல காடுகள் குறுக்கிடும். ஆண்யானைகள் ஒன்றோடு ஒன்று தாக்கிப் போர் செய்வது போல் அங்கே பெரிய துறுகற்கள் கிடக்கும் என்பதை‘களிறு மலைந்தன்ன கண்கூடு துறுகல் ‘ (384)என்ற அடி காட்டுகிறது. அங்கே எப்பொழுதும் மழை பொழிந்து கொண்டிருக்கும்.வழியில் நடுகற்களை நிறையக் காணலாம். நடுகல் நடப்பட்டதற்குச் சான்று பத்துப் பாட்டு நூல்களில் மலைபடுகடாத்தில் மட்டுமே கிடைப்பது குறிப்பிடத்தக்கது.‘நல்வழிக் கொடுத்த நாணுடை மறவர்செல்லா நல்லிசைப் பெயரொடு நட்டகல்லேசு கவலை ‘ (387-389)என்ற அடிகள் நடுகற்களின் சிறப்பை எடுத்துக் கூறுகின்றன. பகைவரிடம் தோற்கும் போது பகைவர்கள் வெற்றியால் ஆரவாரம் செய்தனர். அதைக்கண்டு நாணம் மிக்க மறவர்கள் போரிட்டு உயிர் கொடுத்தார்கள். பகைவரை வெல்ல இயலாத போது உயிர் கொடுத்தல் நல்வழி என்றும் நாணத்திற்காக உயிரை விட்டதால் நாணுடை மறவர் என்றும் குறிப்பிடும் நயம் பாராட்டத்தக்கது.மேலும் ‘கல்ஏசு கவலை ‘ எனும் சொற்றொடர் ‘புறமுதுகிட்ட வீரர்களை அக்கற்கள் ஏசும் ‘ எனும் பொருளையும் தருகின்றன. அவ்வீரக்கற்களில் உள்ள தெய்வத்தை யாழை வாசித்துப் பயணம் தொடரலாம். பலவழிகள் ஒன்றாய்க் கூடும் இடம் அங்கே வந்து சேரும்.சரியான வழியைத் தேர்ந்தெடுத்து அந்த வழியில் தான் செல்ல வேண்டும் என்ரு பின்னால் வரும் புதியவர்களுக்கு அடையாளம் காட்ட அவ்வழியின் தொடக்கத்தில் ஊகம்புல்லை முடிந்து வைக்க வேண்டும். இவ்வாறு வழிகாட்ட வேண்டுவதை‘சந்து நீவிப் புல் முனைந்திடுமின் ‘ (393) எனும் அடி கூறுகிறது.தொடர்ந்து செல்லும் வழியில் நன்னனது பகைவர் வாழும் நிலங்களூமிருக்கும். ஆனால் பாணரும் புலவரும் அவ்வழிச் செல்ல அஞ்ச வேண்டாம். அவர்களிடம்‘தேம்பாய் கண்ணித் தேர்வீசு கவிகைஓம்பா வள்ளல் ‘ (399-400) எனப் புகழப்படும் நன்னன் ஊர்நாடிச் செல்வதாகக் கூறினால் எத்துன்பமும் அவர்கள் விளைக்க மாட்டார்கள். எனவே நன்னனின் பகைவர்களூம் பண்பு உடையவர்கள் என்பதை அறிய முடிகிறது.அடுத்து காடுகள் உள்ளன. ஒரு புலி பிணை மானை வீழ்த்தி விட்டது. அதனால் நடுங்கிய கலைமான் கூவுகிறது.‘புலியற வெறுத்ததன் வீழ்வினை உள்ளிக்கலை நின்று விளிக்கும் கானம் ‘ என்று அக்காடு காட்டப்படுகிறது.தொடர்ந்த பயணத்தில் முல்லை நிலத்தை அடையலாம். கானகத்தில் நடந்து வந்த களைப்பும் ஊர்விட்டு வந்த வருத்தமும் நீங்கும் படியாக அங்குள்ள ஆய்ச்சியர் பசும்பால் தருவர். அவர்களுக்காக அவர்கள் சமைத்துள்ள பால் சோற்றினை வழிச்செல்பவர்களுக்கு அளித்து உபசரிப்பர். ஆயர்களின் ஆட்டு மந்தைக்கு அருமையான உவமையை பெருங்கெளசிகனார் காட்டுகிறார்.பண்ட மாற்றுமுறை வணிகத்தில் பலரிடம் தம் பொருளை விற்று அவர்களிடமிர்ந்து பெற்ற பல நிற அரிசிகள் ஒன்றாய்க் கலந்திருந்தால் எப்படி இருக்குமோ அது போன்ற பல நிறமுள்ள ஆடுகளைக் கொண்ட ஆட்டு மந்தை என்று கெளசிகனார் கூறுவதை‘பகர்விரவு நெல்லின் பலவரி யன்னதகர்விரவு துருவை வெள்ளையொடு விரைஇ ‘ (413-414)என்ற அடிகள் எடுத்துக் காட்டுகின்றன.முல்லை நில ஆயர்கள் அன்றிரவு தங்கச் சொல்லி ஆடுகளின் உரித்த தோலால் செய்யப்பட்ட படுக்கை தருவர். அப்படுக்கை ‘அதட்பள்ளி ‘ எனும் சொல்லால் குறிக்கப்படுகிறது.‘அதள் உண்டாயினும் பாய் உண்டாயினும்யாதுண்டாயினும் கொடுமின் வல்லே ‘என்று புறநானூறு கூறுவதை இங்கு எண்ணிப் பார்த்தல் சுவை தரும்.மேலும் ஆயர்கள் கொடிய விலங்குகள் வராதபடி அவ்விரவில் தீ வளர்த்துத் தருவார்கள்.அங்கு அவ்விரவு தங்கிப் பயணம் தொடர்ந்தால் சிறிய காடு வரும். அக்காட்டில்‘கூப்பிடு கடக்கும் கூர்நல் அம்பில்கொடுவில் கூளியர் ‘ (421-422)பலர் இருப்பர். கூப்பிடும் தொலைவிற்கு அப்பால் அம்பு விடக்கூடிய அவர்கள் நன்னனைக் காணச் செல்பவர்களூக்குத் தசையும் கிழங்கும் உண்ணக் கொடுத்து அனுப்புவர்.அவ்வேடுவர்கள் காட்டும் வழியில் தொடர்ந்து சென்றால் வழியில் நிறைய மலர்கள் பூத்துக் கிடக்கும். அம்மலர்களை மரலினது நாரினால் மாலைகட்டி அழகாக அணிந்து கொண்டு செல்லல் நல்லது. அந்த இடத்தில் தண்ணீர் பருகிக் குளித்துச் செல்லும் வழிக்கு வேண்டிய அளவு நீர் முகந்து கொண்டு செல்ல வேண்டும்.பகல் முழுதும் தொடர்ந்து சென்றால் இரவில் புல் வேய்ந்த குடிசைகள் குறுக்கிடும். அங்கிருக்கும் மக்கள் மூங்கில் அரிசியால் ஆன பால் சோறு தருவர். வேங்கைப் பூ நிறத்தில் இருக்கும் செவ்வரிசிச் சோறு தருவர். அதோடு மேட்டு நிலத்தில் விளைந்த நெல்லரிசி கலந்து அவரை விதைகள் உள்ள புளியைக் கரைத்து ஆக்கிய குழைந்த ‘புளிங்கூழ் ‘ கொடுப்பர். இதையே ‘கிணைமகள் அட்ட பாவற் புளிங்கூழ் ‘ என்று புறநானூறு கூறுகிறது.அரிசிச் சோற்றைக் குழித்து நெய் இடுவார்கள். ‘தண்ணென் எழுது உள்ளீடாக ‘(442) எனவரும் சொற்றொடரில் தண்ணென் எழுது என்பதற்கு சிலர் நெய் என்றும் சிலர் குளிர்ந்த வெண்ணெய் என்றும் பொருள் கொள்வர்.இதுபோன்றே ‘விசயம் ‘ என்பதற்கு கருப்பட்டி என்றும் சருக்கரை என்றும் பொருள் கூறப்படுகிறது. கருப்பட்டியை இடித்து ஆக்கப்பட்ட தெனைமா தருவர். அவ்விரவில் தங்கினால் நொய்ய மர விறகால் தீ மூட்டிக் காவல் காப்பர்.பிறகு விடியலில் கிளம்புகையில் பறவைகளின் குரல் கேட்டு எழுந்து செல்ல வேண்டும் என்பதை ‘விடியல் புள்ளோர்த்துக் கழிமின் ‘ (448) என்ற அடி காட்டுகிறது. பறவைகளின் குரலால் நன்னிமித்தம் பார்த்துச் செல்ல வேண்டும் என்பதையும் அது குறிப்பதாகக் கொள்ளலாம்.அடுத்து மருத நிலப்பகுதியைக் காணலாம். ‘புல்லரைக் காஞ்சிப் புனல்பொரு புதவின் ‘ (449) என்று மருத நிலத்தின் கருவான காஞ்சி மரம் காட்டப்படுகிறது. அத்துடன் அருகம்புற்களும் அங்கு காணப்படுகின்றன. யாழைப்போல இனிய இசை எழுப்பும் வண்டுகள் முரலும் சோலைகளும், தவ முனிவர் வாழும் பள்ளிகளும் தண்பனைநாடாகிய அம்மருத நிலப்பகுதியில் உள்ளன.அங்கே தங்கினால் செவிக்கின்பமும் கிடைக்கும்; நாவுக்கு இன்பம் தரும் சுவையான பண்டங்களும் கிடைக்கும். தொடர்ந்து செல்கையில் நீர் நிலைகளைக் காணலாம். அப்பொய்களில் கண்பங்கோரைகள் நிறைய இருக்கும்.அக்கோரை தற்போது சம்பங்கோரை என வழங்கப் படுகிறது. ‘சகரக் கிளவி ‘ மொழி முதல் வராது என எண்ணியவர்கள் இதை ‘கண்பங்கோரை ‘ என மாற்றி இருக்கலாம். ககரமும் சகரமும் நிறைய மாறி உள்ளன. இது போன்றுதான் கைகளைக் கொட்டிகின்ற கைப்பாணிப்பருவம் சப்பாணிப்பருவம் என ஆகி இருக்கலாம். இது மேலும் ஆய்வுக்கு உரிய ஒன்றாகும்.அங்கே உள்ள வலைஞர்கள் விருந்தோம்பலில் மிகச் சிறந்தவர்கள். அவர்கள் வரால் மீன்களின் துண்டுகள் தருவர். வரால் மீனைப் பெருங்கெளசிகனார் ‘பிடிக்கை அன்ன செங்கண் வரால் ‘(457) எனக் கூறுகிறார். பிடி எனப்படும் பெண் யானையின் துதிக்கை போன்று பருத்ததும் சிவந்த கண்களை உடையதுமான எனக் கூறும்போது புலவர் வரால் மீனை எந்த அளவுக்கு கூர்ந்து நோக்கி இருக்க வேண்டும் என்பது புலனாகிறது. ஏனெனில் மற்ற மீன்களை விட வரால் மீன் சிவந்த கண்கள் உடையது எனக் கூறுவர்.வாளை மீனைக் குறிப்பிடுகையில் ‘இருஞ்சுவல் வாளை ‘ என்று அவர் கூறுகிறார். பெரிய கழுத்து உடைய வாளை என்பது அதன் மூலம் தெரிய வரும். ‘இருஞ்சுவல் வாளை பிறழும் ‘ என்று புறநானூறு கூறும்.மேலும் அந்த வலைஞர்கள் உழவர்களிடம் மீனைவிற்று நெல்லைப் பெறுவார்கள். உழவர்கள் மலை போல நெற்போர்களை வைத்திருப்பார்கள். அவற்றைப் பிரித்து அவற்றின் உள்ளேயிருந்து நெல்லை அளந்து கொடுப்பார்கள். ‘விலங்கல் அன்ன போர்முத தொலைஇ ‘ (461) என்ற அடியால் நெற்போர்கள் மலைகளுக்கு நிகராக இருந்ததை அறியமுடிகிறது. கம்பன் தனது நாட்டுப் படலத்தில் ‘போரொடு நிகர்வன புணர்மலை ‘ என்று பாடுவதிங்கு நோக்கத்தக்கது ஆகும்.மருத நில மக்கள் நன்னனும் விரும்பக்கூடிய உணவை வருபவர்க்கு அளிப்பார்களாம். அதை ‘திண்தேர் நன்னற்கும் அயினி காண்பன் ‘ (467) என்ற அடி காட்டும். மேலும் அவர்கள் முள்நீக்கிய கொழுப்பு மிகுதியாக உள்ள மீன் துண்டங்களையிட்ட வெள்ளிய சோறு தருவர்.அவற்றை உண்டபின் எருதுகளை ஓட்டுகின்ற உழவரின் பாட்டுடன் கலந்து மருதப்பண்ணிசைத்துச் செல்லலாம். அந்த உழவர் பாட்டை சிலம்பு ‘ஏரொடு நின்றார் ஏர்மங்கலம் ‘ என்று சுட்டும்.மேலும் ஒரு அரிய செய்தியையும் இங்கு மலைபடுகடாம் காட்டுகிறது. வயலின் நடுவே பறவைகள் கூடுகட்டிக் குடியிருக்கும். அறுவடையைத் தொடங்கும் முன்னர் பறைஒலி எழுப்பினால் அப்பறவைகள் பறந்து பாதுகாப்பான இடத்தை அடைந்துவிடும்.அப்பறை ஒலி கேட்டு அஞ்சி எருமைக்கடாக்களும் விரைவாக அங்கும் இங்கும் திரிந்து ஓடி வரும். செல்பவர்கள் அக்கடாக்களிலிருந்து தப்பி விலகி பாதுகாப்பாய்ச் செல்ல வேண்டும்.அடுத்து சேயாற்றின் கரைமீது பயணம் தொடரும். சேயாறு பற்றிக் கூறும் போது அந்த ஆற்று நீரின் சுழற்சியை ‘வணைகலத் திகிரியின் குமிழி சுழலும் ‘ (476) என்று கெளசிகனார் கூறுகிறார். அதாவது சேயாறு குயவனின் மட்கலம் போன்று குழிகள் சுழல ஓடிக் கொண்டிருக்கும்.சேயாற்றங்கரைக்கு அருகிலேயே நன்னனின் மூதூர் உள்ளது என்பதை ‘நனிசேய்த்தவன்றன் பழவிறன் மூதூர் ‘ (487) எனும் அடி காட்டும்.மூதூரின் அழகை கெளசிகனார் பத்து அடிகளில் கூறுகிறார். மூதூரின் மதில் ‘நிவந்தோங்கு வரை ‘ எனக் காட்டப்படுகிறது. அந்நகரில் செல்வம் துயில் கொண்டு அங்கேயே கிடக்கும் என்பதை நிதியம் துஞ்சும் எனும் சொற்றொடர் மூலம் அறியலாம். மேலும் அந்நகர் மக்கள் ‘பதிஎழல் அறியாப் பழங்குடி ‘யைச் சேர்ந்தவர்கள். இவ்வாறு எழுதுதல் மரபு என்பதை ‘பதிஎழு வறியாப் பழங்குடி கெழீஇஅ ‘ என்று புகார் பற்றி சிலம்பு காட்டுவதிலிருந்து அறியலாம்.‘ நியமம் ‘ என்ற சொல்லால் அங்குள்ள அங்காடித் தெரு குறிக்கப்படுகிறது. ‘வாணிகர் உறையுள் நியமம் ‘ எனத் திருவிளையாடற்புராணமும் கூறுகிறது. மேலும் தெருக்கள் ஆறுகள் போன்றும் வீடுகள் ஆறுகளின் கரைகள் போன்றும் உவமிக்கப்படுகின்றன. மலை முகில் போன்ற மாடங்கள் இருந்தனவாம். மலைகள் அடிவாரத்தே அடிப்பக்கம் ஒழுங்காகவும் உச்சிகள் மாறுபட்ட உயரங்களிலும் காணப்படும் தோற்றத்தை உடையன. அது போன்றே மாடங்கள் உயரத்தால் உச்சிகள் வேறுபட்டு அடியில் ஒழுங்காக காணப்பட்டன எனும் நயம் பாராட்டத் தக்க ஒன்றாகும்.இதே உவமையை ‘மழையென மருளும் மகிழ் செய்மாடம் ‘ என மதுரைக் காஞ்சி கூறுகிறது. நகரின் அரண்மனை வாயிலில் யாவரும் அஞ்சத்தக்க மறவர்கள் காவல் காத்து நிற்பார்கள். பாணரும் கூத்தரும் அஞ்சாமல் அவ்வழியே செல்லலாம். பண்டை மன்னர்கள் வாயில் பற்றி சிறுபாணாற்றுப்படை‘பொருநர்க் காயினும் புலவர்க் காயினும்அருமறை நாவின் அந்தணர்க் காயினும்அடையா வாயில் ‘எனக் கூறும் கருத்து எண்ணத்தக்கது.நன்னனிடம் பரிசில் பெற வருபவர்களைப் பார்ப்பவர்கள் மகிழ்ந்து நோக்குவர்! விருந்தினராகத் தங்க அழைப்பர்!அடுத்து நன்னனின் அரண்மனை முற்றத்தை அடையலாம். அம்முற்றத்திலே நன்னனுக்கு மக்கள் அன்பாய் வழங்கிய பொருட்கள் குவிந்து காணப்படுகின்றன. அப்பொருள்களில் ஒன்றாக ‘ஊமை எண்கின் குடாவடிக் குருளை ‘ (501) எனும் வாய் திறவாக் கரடிக் குட்டியைக் காணலாம். மேலும் ‘வரை வாழ் வருடை ‘ என்ற சொற்றொடர் ‘வருடை ‘ எனும் மலை ஆட்டைக் காட்டுகிறது. இந்த வருடைக்கு எட்டுக் கால்கள் இருந்தன ; இதற்கு முதுகிலும் கால்கள் உண்டு. என்று நீலகேசி கூறும். மானின் கன்று, யானையின் சிறு கன்று, சிறிய கீரி, காட்டுக் குதிரை, உடும்பு, மயில், காட்டுச் சேவல், பலாப்பழம், சாறுள்ள பழம், நறைக் கொடி, கற்பூரம், நூறைக் கிழங்கு, காந்தட்பூ, நாகப்பூ, சந்தனம், பச்சை மிளகு, மூங்கிற்குழாயில் ஊரிய தேன், கள், தயிர், தேன் அடைகள் போன்ற பல பொருள்கள் அங்கே குவிந்து கிடக்குமாம். அவை குவிந்து கிடப்பதைகுடமாலை பிறந்த தண்பெருங் காவிரிகடன்மண் டழுவத்துக் கயவாய் கடுப்பஎன்ற அடிகள் மூலம் கெளசிகனார் பாடி இருக்கிறார். காவிரி ஆறானது பல பொருள்களை அடித்துக் கொண்டு வந்து சேர்க்கும் புகார் போல நன்னனுடைய முற்றமானது விளங்கியதாம்.மேலும் அம்முற்றத்தில் யானைகள் முழங்கிக் கொண்டு இருக்கும். பூந்தாதுகள் எங்கும் பரவிக் கிடக்கும்.பரிசில் பெற விரும்புபவர்கள் அம்முற்றத்தை மழை முழக்கம் போல மத்தளத்தை ஒலிக்கச் செய்ய வேண்டும். குழலை இசைத்து ஒலியெழுப்பிப் பாடவேண்டும். விறலியர்கள் மரபு நிலை மாறாது ஆட வேண்டும்.அவ்வாறு ஆடிப் பாடும் போது முதலில் கடவுளை வாழ்த்திப் பாடவேண்டும். பிறகு நன்னன் புகழ் பாடி அவனை வாழ்த்தல் நலம் பயக்கும்.புகழ் நிலைபெற கொடைத்தொழில் செய்பவனே! என அவனை விளித்து அவனது வெற்றிகளைப் பாடுங்கால் தொடர்ந்து பாட விடாது நன்னன் வந்து ‘வந்தது சாலும் வருத்தமும் பெரிதென ‘ (546) எனக் கூறுவான்.என்மேல் விருப்பம் வைத்து வந்த வழியில் உங்களுக்கு உண்டான வருத்தமும் பெரிது என்று கூறி உள்ளே அழைத்துச் செல்வான். சான்றோர் அவையில் நல்ல இருக்கையில் அமர்த்துவான்.உலகில் பலர் தோன்றுகிறார்கள்; மறைகிறார்கள். அவர்தம் எண்ணிக்கை குவியலான மணலின் அளவைவிடப் பெயது. ‘வடுவாழ் எக்கர் மணலினும் பலரே ‘ (556) அதனால் நன்னன் ‘புகழொடும் கழிக நம்வரைந்த நாள் ‘ (557) என்று எண்ணுவானாம். அவ்வாறு தன் வாழ்நாளைப் புகழுடன் கழிக்க நினைப்பவன் வந்தவர்க்கு முதலில் ‘இழை மருங்கறிய நுழைநூற் கலிங்கம் ‘ (561) உடுத்துவான். அங்கேயே பலநாள் தங்கி இருக்கும்படி வேண்டுவான். வெண்ணெல் அரிசியும், தசைத்துண்டங்களூம் தருவன்.சிலநாள் இருந்தபின் நன்னன் மனம் வருந்தாதபடி ‘எங்கள் பழைய நகருக்குப் போக எண்ணம் கொண்டோம் ‘ எனக் கூறினால் வந்த விருந்தினர்க் குழுவின் தலைவனுக்குப் பொற்றாமரை மலர் சூட்டுவான். அவ்வாறு பொற்றாமரை மலர் சூட்டுவதை ‘பைம்பொற்றாமரை பாணர் சூட்டி ‘ எனப் பதிற்றுப் பத்தும் காட்டுகிறது.விறலியர்க்குப் பொன்னாலான அணிகள் தருவான். நீரொட்டம் போலச் செல்லும் நெடிய தேர்கள் அளிப்பான் என்பதை ‘நீீரியக் கன்ன நிரைசெலல்ல் நெடுட்தேர் ‘ (571) எனும் அடி காட்டுகிறது. பெரிய யானைகள் மணி கட்டிய காளைகளுடன் பசுக்கள் ஆகியன அளிப்பான்.நன்னன் அளிக்கும் குதிரையைக் கெளசிகனார் கொய்சுவல் புரவி என்கிறார். அதன் பொருள் மயிர் கத்தரிக்கப்பட்ட கழுத்துள்ள புரவி என்பதாகும்.அக்குதிரை சிறந்தது என உரை எழுதும் நச்சினார்க்கினியர் செருக்குள்ள குதிரைக்கு மயிர் அதிகம் வளரும் என்று கூறுவது குறிப்பிடத்தக்கதாகும்.‘நிலம் தின்னக் கிடந்த நிதியம் ‘ அனைத்து அளிக்கும் நன்னன் முதல் நாள் எப்படிப் பழகி மகிழ்ந்தானோ அதே போல் மலர்ச்சியுடன் தருவான்.தன்னிடம் பொருள் பெற்றவர்களிடம் எப்போதும் செல்வம் குறையக் கூடாது என்ற எண்ணத்தில் தன்னுடைய நவிர மலை எவ்வாறு கைம்மாறு கருதாமல் மழை பொழியச் எய்கிறதோ அதே போல நன்னன் சிறப்பு செய்வான்.அவ்வாறு நன்னனிடம் பரிசு பெற்று வரும் கூத்தன் கூறுகிறான். நீங்களூம் நன்னனிடம் செல்லுங்கள் என்று அவன் அக்கூட்டத்தலைவனை அற்றுப்படுத்துகிறான்.மலைபடுகடாத்தில் மட்டுமே பிறமொழிச் சொற்கள் இடம் பெறவில்லை என திரு மா. இராசமாணிக்கனார் கூறுவது பிற ஆற்றுப்படைகளிலிருந்து இதை வேறுபடுத்துகிறது.பிற ஆற்றுப்படைகளில் நாய் எனும் சொல் காணப்பட இதில் ஞமலி எனும் சொல்லைக் காண முடிகிறது. எனவே பத்துப் பாட்டுள் இதைத் தூய தமிழ்ப் பாட்டு என்று திரு. ஆ. இன்னாசி கூறுகிறார்.மேலும் பதின்மூன்று இசைக்கருவிகள் பற்றிக் கூறும் நூல் மலைபடுகடாம் ஒன்றே ஆகும். அதில் வரும் நன்னன் மட்டுமே வருபவர்க்கு தேர், யானை, புரவி இவற்றுடன் ஆநிரைகளையும் அளிக்கிறான். அது பிற ஆற்றுப்படைகளுல் காணப்படாத ஒன்றாகும்.மற்ற ஆற்றுப்படைகளில் காணப்படாத மலைவழி இதில் மட்டுமே கூறப்பெறுகிறது. செல்பவர்க்கு வழியில் ஏற்படும் ஊறுகளும் அவற்றை நீக்கும் வழிகளுமிதில் மட்டுமே காணப்படுகிறது.வழிச் செல்வோர் தங்கக் கூடிய இடங்கள் மலைபடுகடாத்தில் மட்டுமே காட்டப்பட்டுள்ளன. மேலும் பிற ஆற்றுப் படைகள் விறலியைப் புனைந்து கூறும் போது ‘கேசாதி பாதம் ‘ எனும் முடிமுதல் அடிவரை முறையைப் பின்பற்றி உள்ளன.மலைபடுகடாம் மட்டுமே இறைவனைக் கூறும் முறையான பாதாதி கேச முறையில் விறலியைப் புனைந்து எழுதிகிறது. மலைபடுகடாத்துள் மட்டுமே மன்னனின் முன்னோர் குறிப்பு இல்லை. மாறாக மன்னனின் தேவியைப் புகழ்ந்து கூறிப் பிறகு மன்னனை அறிமுகப்படுத்தும் புதிய முறை இதில் பின்பற்றப்படுகிறது. மேலும் அடித்தொடரே நூலின் பெயராக அமைந்த சிறப்பு மலைபடுகடாம் மட்டுமே பெறுகிறது.பல்வேறு உவமைகள் இந்நூலில் உள்ளனவெனினும் ஒரே ஒரு உருவகமாக ‘மலைபடுகடாஅ மாடிரத் தியம்ப ‘ என்பது விளங்குகிறது.நடுகற்களைப் பற்றிய செய்திகள் பிற ஆற்றுப்படை நூல்களில் இல்லை. ஆற்றுப்படுத்தும் கூத்தன் முதலில் நன்னது புகழ், போய்ச்சேரும் வழி, அவனது ஊர், மதில், அரண்மனை, கொடை முதலியவற்றைத் தொகுத்துக் கூறிவிட்டு பிறகு தனித்தனியே விரித்துக் கூறுவான் .அவ்வாறு முதலில் தொகுத்தும் பிறகு விரித்தும் சொல்லும் முறையை மலைபடுகடாம் காட்டுகிறது.மலைபடுகடாத்தில் கூறப்பட்டுள்ள வழி கற்பனை வழியன்று; உண்மையானது என ஆராய்ச்சியாளர் கூறுகின்றனர்.நன்னனின் முற்றத்தில் உள்ள பொருள்கள் பல மக்களால் தரப்பட்டவை என்பதால் மக்கள் மன்னனிடம் எந்த அளவு அன்பு வைத்துள்ளனர் என்பதை அறிய முடிகிறது.ஆகவே பத்துப்பாட்டு நூல்களுல் மலைபடுகடாம் தனக்கென சில தனிப்பண்புகள் பெற்றுத்திகழ்கின்றது என்பது தெளிவாக விளங்குகிறது எனலாம்.சங்ககாலத் தொகுப்புகளுள் ஒன்றான பத்துப்பாட்டு நூல்களுள் ஒன்று மலைபடுகடாம். இத் தொகுப்பிலுள்ள நூல்களுள் இரண்டாவது பெரிய நூல் இது. 583 அடிகளால் ஆன இப் பாடலை இயற்றியவர், இரணியமுட்டத்துப் பெருங்குன்றூர்ப் பெருங்கௌசிகனார் என்னும் புலவர் ஆவார். இந்த நூலைக் கூத்தராற்றுப்படை எனவும் குறிப்பிடுவர்.[1]நவிர மலையின் தலைவனான நன்னன் என்பவனைப் பாட்டுடைத் தலைவனாகக் கொண்டு பாடப்பட்டது இந்நூல். நவிர மலை மக்களின் வாழ்க்கை முறைகளையும், அவர்கள் தலைவனின் கொடைத் திறத்தையும் புகழ்ந்து பாடும் இந் நூற் பாடல்களில், அக்காலத் தமிழரின் இசைக்கருவிகள் பற்றியும் ஆங்காங்கே குறிப்புக்கள் காணப்படுகின்றன. நன்னனைப் பாடிப் பரிசு பெறச்செல்லும் பாணர், நெடுவங்கியம், மத்தளம், கிணை, சிறுபறை, கஞ்சதாளம், குழல், யாழ் போன்ற பலவகை இசைக் கருவிகளை எடுத்துச் செல்வது பற்றிய செய்திகள் கூறப்பட்டுள்ளன."},{"question":"വാചകം 1: തിരക്കേറിയ സമയങ്ങളില്, കെന്റിഷ് ടൌണ് - ബെഡ്ഫോർഡ് തമ്മിലുള്ള ഗതാഗതം തുടരും. വാക്യം 2: തിരക്കേറിയ സമയങ്ങളില്, ബെഡ്ഫോർഡ് സർവീസുകള് കെന് റ്റിഷ് ടൌണിലേക്ക് തുടരുന്നു. ചോദ്യം: ഒന്നാം വാക്യവും രണ്ടാമത്തെ വാക്യവും ഒരേ അർത്ഥമാണോ പ്രകടിപ്പിക്കുന്നത്? അതെ അല്ലെ?","answer":"അതെ, രണ്ട് വാക്യങ്ങളും ഒരേ കാര്യം അർത്ഥമാക്കുന്നു"},{"question":"문장을 이어가시오:  7년 전쟁 때도 그는 오스트리아군을 지휘했으나, 1757년 프라하 전투에서 다시 프로이센군에게 패배했다. 그 후","answer":"브레슬라우 전투 (1757년)에서 소규모 프로이센군을 격파하는 작은 승리를 거두었지만, 로이텐 전투에서 또 다시 프리드리히 2세에게 패배했다."},{"question":"ਮੈਲਬਰਨ, 1 ਮਾਰਚਬ੍ਰਾਜ਼ੀਲ ਤੇ ਆਸਟਰੇਲੀਆ ਨੇ ਵਿਸ਼ਵ ਦੇ ਦੂਜੇ ਸਭ ਤੋਂ ਵੱਡੇ ਖੰਡ ਉਤਪਾਦਕ ਭਾਰਤ ਖ਼ਿਲਾਫ਼ ਵਿਸ਼ਵ ਵਪਾਰ ਸੰਸਥਾ (ਡਬਲਿਊਟੀਓ) ਵਿੱਚ ਸ਼ਿਕਾਇਤ ਕੀਤੀ ਹੈ। ਸ਼ਿਕਾਇਤ ਵਿੱਚ ਕਿਹਾ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਭਾਰਤ ਵੱਲੋਂ ਕਿਸਾਨਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਖੰਡ ’ਤੇ ਸਬਸਿਡੀ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਜਾਣ ਕਰਕੇ ਜਿੱਥੇ ਆਲਮੀ ਪੱਧਰ ’ਤੇ ਕੀਮਤਾਂ ਅਸਰਅੰਦਾਜ਼ ਹੋਈਆਂ ਹਨ, ਉਥੇ ਬਾਜ਼ਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਖੰਡ ਨਾਲ ਤੂੜੇ ਗਏ ਹਨ। ਆਸਟਰੇਲੀਅਨ ਸਰਕਾਰ ਨੇ ਪਿਛਲੇ ਸਾਲ ਨਵੰਬਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਵੀ ਡਬਲਿਊਟੀਓ ਕੋਲ ਅਜਿਹਾ ਹੀ ਵਿਰੋਧ ਦਰਜ ਕੀਤਾ ਸੀ। ਆਸਟਰੇਲੀਆ ਦੇ ਵਣਜ, ਸੈਰ-ਸਪਾਟਾ ਤੇ ਨਿਵੇਸ਼ ਮੰਤਰੀ ਸਿਮੋਨ ਬਰਮਿੰਘਮ ਨੇ ਕਿਹਾ ਕਿ ਭਾਰਤ ਵੱਲੋਂ ਖੰਡ ’ਤੇ ਦਿੱਤੀ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਸਬਸਿਡੀ ਦਾ ਪ੍ਰਬੰਧ ਡਬਲਿਊਟੀਓ ਨੇਮਾਂ ਦੇ ਖ਼ਿਲਾਫ਼ ਹੈ ਤੇ ਇਸ ਨਾਲ ਆਲਮੀ ਖੰਡ ਬਾਜ਼ਾਰ ਮਾਲ ਨਾਲ ਤੂੜੇ ਗਏ ਹਨ। ਬਰਮਿੰਘਮ ਨੇ ਕਿਹਾ, ‘ਇਸ ਨਾਲ ਗੰਨਾ ਕਾਸ਼ਤਕਾਰਾਂ ਤੇ ਖੰਡ ਮਿੱਲਾਂ, ਫਿਰ ਚਾਹੇ ਉਹ ਆਸਟਰੇਲੀਆ, ਬ੍ਰਾਜ਼ੀਲ ਜਾਂ ਕਿਸੇ ਹੋਰ ਮੁਲਕ ਦੀਆਂ ਹੋਣ, ਦੇ ਹਿੱਤਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਸੱਟ ਪੁੱਜੀ ਹੈ। ਮੰਤਰੀ ਨੇ ਕਿਹਾ ਕਿ ਉੁਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਕੋਲ ਬ੍ਰਾ਼ਜ਼ੀਲ ਨਾਲ ਮਿਲ ਕੇ ਡਬਲਿਊਟੀਓ ਨੂੰ ਸ਼ਿਕਾਇਤ ਕਰਨ ਤੋਂ ਛੁੱਟ ਕੋਈ ਹੋਰ ਬਦਲ ਮੌਜੂਦ ਨਹੀਂ ਸੀ। ਉਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਕਿਹਾ ਕਿ ਆਸਟਰੇਲੀਆ ਦੀ ਲਿਬਰਲ ਸਰਕਾਰ ਇਸ ਮੁੱਦੇ ’ਤੇ ਆਪਣੀ ਖੰਡ ਸਨਅਤ ਨਾਲ ਡਟ ਕੇ ਖੜੀ ਹੈ। ਉਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਕਿਹਾ ਕਿ ਆਸਟਰੇਲੀਆ ਦੇ ਭਾਰਤ ਨਾਲ ਆਰਥਿਕ ਤੇ ਰਣਨੀਤਕ ਪੱਖੋਂ ਨਿੱਘੇ ਸਬੰਧ ਹਨ, ਪਰ ਨੇੜਲੇ ਦੋਸਤ ਤੇ ਭਾਈਵਾਲ ਵਣਜ ਨਾਲ ਸਬੰਧਤ ਮੁੱਦਿਆਂ ਦੇ ਹੱਲ ਲਈ ਡਬਲਿਊਟੀਓ ਕੋਲ ਜਾ ਸਕਦੇ ਹਨ। ਉਂਜ ਬਰਮਿੰਘਮ ਨੇ ਕਿਹਾ ਕਿ ਆਸਟਰੇਲੀਆ ਦੀ ਖੰਡ ਸਨਅਤ ਬਰਾਮਦ ’ਤੇ ਨਿਰਭਰ ਕਰਦੀ ਹੈ ਤੇ ਮੁਲਕ ਦੀ 85 ਫੀਸਦ ਖੰਡ ਆਲਮੀ ਮਾਰਕੀਟ ਵਿੱਚ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ।ਡਬਲਿਊਟੀਓ ਕੀ ਹੈ?","answer":"ਵਰਲਡ ਟਰੇਡ ਆਰਗੇਨਾਈਜ਼ੇਸ਼ਨ (ਡਬਲਯੂ.ਟੀ.ਓ.) ਇੱਕ ਅੰਤਰਰਾਸ਼ਟਰੀ ਸੰਸਥਾ ਹੈ ਜੋ ਦੇਸ਼ਾਂ ਵਿੱਚ ਵਿਸ਼ਵ ਵਪਾਰ ਲਈ ਨਿਯਮਾਂ ਦੀ ਨਿਗਰਾਨੀ ਕਰਦੀ ਹੈ। ਇਹ 1995 ਵਿੱਚ ਬਣਾਇਆ ਗਿਆ ਸੀ ਅਤੇ ਦੂਜੇ ਵਿਸ਼ਵ ਯੁੱਧ ਦੇ ਮੱਦੇਨਜ਼ਰ ਬਣਾਏ ਗਏ ਟੈਰਿਫ ਅਤੇ ਵਪਾਰ (GATT) ਬਾਰੇ ਜਨਰਲ ਸਮਝੌਤੇ ਨੂੰ ਛੱਡ ਦਿੱਤਾ ਗਿਆ ਸੀ। ਡਬਲਯੂ.ਟੀ.ਓ. ਦਾ ਮੁੱਖ ਕੰਮ ਇਹ ਯਕੀਨੀ ਬਣਾਉਣਾ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਗਲੋਬਲ ਵਪਾਰ ਸੁਚਾਰੂ, ਅਨੁਮਾਨਿਤ ਅਤੇ ਸੁਤੰਤਰ ਤੌਰ 'ਤੇ ਚੱਲੇ।"},{"question":"Fenoy ny banga _\\"Ny Tondro tokana tsy _ hao\\"","answer":"Ny Tondro tokana tsy mahazo hao"},{"question":"Apakah maksud \\"air dicencang takkan putus\\" ? Berikan satu contoh ayat untuk peribahasa tersebut.","answer":"Ia bermaksud perselisihan antara adik-beradik tidak akan kekal lama dan akhirnya akan berbaik semula. Contoh ayat ialah Ahmad yang tidak bertegur sapa dengan abangnya selama setahun, sekarang telah berbaik-baik semula kerana air dicencang tidak akan putus."},{"question":"Raha jerena ireto fehezanteny roa ireto:Fehezanteny A: \\"Ny fizotran'ny fahazoana ny fizika fizika dia sarotra, saingy azoko ihany tamin'ny farany.\\"Fehezanteny B: \\"Na eo aza ny fahasarotana dia nahavita nahatakatra ny foto-kevitra saro-pady momba ny fizika fizika.\\"Mitovy ve ny dikany?","answer":"Tsia, samy hafa ny dikany ireo fehezanteny ireo roa."},{"question":"次のパラグラフを続ける： 富士山の近くにある山梨県の河口湖の周りには、かえでなどの木がたくさんあります。今年も木の葉がだんだん赤や黄色に変わって、紅葉がきれいな季節になりました。","answer":"8日、湖に来た人たちは、少し雪が見える富士山と紅葉の写真を撮ったり、散歩をしたりしていました。家族と旅行に来た人は「去年も来ました。今年も赤い色がとてもきれいです。天気もよくて、すばらしいです」と話しました。 今年は、トンネルのように続く紅葉の道を今までの2倍ぐらいに長くしました。たくさんの人が、歩きながらきれいな色の木の葉を楽しんでいます。湖がある町の団体は、今月23日ごろまで紅葉を楽しむことができると言っています。"},{"question":"Ovatko revontulet ihmisen kannalta vaarallisia?","answer":"Revontulet eivät aiheuta minkäänlaista haittaa tai vaaraa ihmisten normaalielämään. Revontuliin ei liity radioaktiivisia aineita tuottavia prosesseja eikä niistä \\"valu\\" ihmisten ilmoille mitään materiaa. Ainoa konkreettinen tuotos on revontulien valot, mutta niistä ei ole minkäänlaista haittaa; onpahan luonnon tarjoama ilmainen valospektaakkeli."},{"question":"Ayat 1: Soulié de Morant berkhidmat selama beberapa tahun dalam badan diplomatik Perancis di China, di mana dia bekerja sebagai konsul Perancis di beberapa bandar China. Ayat 2: Soulié de Morant berkhidmat beberapa tahun dalam badan diplomatik Perancis di China, di mana dia bekerja sebagai konsul Perancis di beberapa bandar China. Soalan: Adakah ayat 1 dan ayat 2 menyatakan makna yang sama? Ya atau tidak?","answer":"Ya, betul."},{"question":"Пассаттар бул...","answer":"Пассаттар-океандардын тропиктик кеңдиктеринде жыл бою тупуктуу соккон шамалдар."},{"question":"ما هي عاصمة اليابان ؟","answer":" طوكيو"},{"question":"I wonder ముదిగొండ లింగమూర్తి ఎప్పుడు పుట్టాడు?Can you get me some context to answer this (in the same language as my question)?","answer":"భాగ్యచక్రము కె.వి.రెడ్డి నిర్మాతగా జయంతి పిక్చర్స్ పతాకంపై స్వీయ దర్శకత్వంలో రూపొందించిన తెలుగు చలనచిత్రం.పాత్రలు - పాత్రధారులుయువరాజు విక్రమ్‌ - నందమూరి తారకరామారావువనజ - బి.సరోజాదేవిధర్మపాలుడు - ముదిగొండ లింగమూర్తిసిద్ధయోగి/స్వామిరాజు - రాజనాలనాగమ్మ - సురభి బాలసరస్వతిచిత్రావతి - గీతాంజలిగజదొంగ గంద్రగోళి - ముక్కామలవిక్రమ్‌ తల్లి - ఋష్యేంద్రమణిమిత్రలాభం - బి.పద్మనాభందాసి - కాకినాడ రాజరత్నంసేనాపతి - జగ్గారావుమంత్రి - వడ్లమాని విశ్వనాథంస్వామిభక్తుడు - కె.వి.చలంపి.జె.శర్మమల్లాదిసాంకేతికవర్గంకథ, రచన-పింగళి నాగేంద్రరావుకూర్పు- వాసుకళ-  గోఖలేస్టంట్స్-శ్యామసుందర్ఛాయాగ్రహణం- కమల్ ఘోష్నృత్యం- పసుమర్తి కృష్ణమూర్తిసంగీతం- పెండ్యాల నాగేశ్వరరావునిర్మాత-పి.యస్.రెడ్డి,దర్శకత్వం- కె.వి.రెడ్డిసహ దర్శకులు- సింగీతం శ్రీనివాసరావు, కె.ఎస్.రెడ్డి.కథనరేంద్రపురి ప్రభువు ధర్మపాలుడు (లింగమూర్తి). ఆ రాజ్యంపై ఆశలు పెంచుకున్న పాముల మాంత్రికుడు సిద్దయోగి (రాజనాల) తన చెల్లెలు నాగమ్మ (బాలసరస్వతి)ను మహారాణిని చేయాలనే తలంపుతో రాకుమారిపై సర్ప ప్రయోగంచేసి, ఆ పాప బతకాలంటే తన సోదరిని వివాహం చేసుకోవాలని, మహారాజుకు షరతుపెడతాడు. ఆ విధంగా నాగమ్మ మహారాణి కావటం, రాజనాల, కామకళిక ద్వారా మహారాజును మార్చివేసి, రాకుమారి పాపను, పిండారిలచే చంపించ ప్రయత్నించి, అధికారం చేజిక్కించుకొని స్వామిరాజు పేరుతో పాలన సాగిస్తూ అన్యాయాలు, అక్రమాలు చేస్తుంటాడు. యువరాణి పాపను అడవిలో గజదొంగ గంద్రగోళి (ముక్కామల) కాపాడి పెంచి పెద్దచేస్తాడు. నాగమ్మకు పుట్టిన కుమార్తె యువరాణి చిత్రవతి (గీతాంజలి)గా పెరిగి పెద్దదవుతుంది. ఆమెను ఉదయగిరి యువరాజు విక్రమ్ (యన్.టి.రామారావు)కిచ్చి వివాహం చేయాలని నాగమ్మ, స్వామిరాజు ఆశిస్తారు. విక్రముడు అంతకు మునుపే అడవిలో యువరాణి పాప వనజ (బి.సరోజాదేవి)ను కలుసుకోవటం ఇరువురూ ఒకరినొకరు ప్రేమించుకోవటం జరుగుతుంది. తల్లి (ఋష్యేంద్రమణి) కోరికపై విక్రముడు, స్నేహితుడు మిత్రలాభం (పద్మనాభం)ను యువరాజుగా, తాను మారువేషంలో ఆషాడభూతి పేరుతో నరేంద్రపురి వెళ్ళి, అక్కడ బందీయైన వనజను, మతిచలించిన, మహారాజు రక్షించి, స్వామిరాజాను అంతంచేయటం చిత్రావతికి మిత్రలాభంకు, విక్రమ్‌కు, వనజకు, మహారాజు చేతులమీదుగా వివాహం జరగటంతో చిత్రం ముగుస్తుంది[1].పాటలుమూలాలుసి.హెచ్.రామారావు: ఘంటసాల 'పాట'శాల అను పాటల సంకలనం నుంచి.బయటి లింకులు on IMD"},{"question":"次の文章に書かれている内容に基づいて、少なくとも200語の段落を書いてください。： ウクライナのキーウ　青と黄色に光るクリスマスツリー","answer":"ウクライナの首都キーウにある広場で、19日から大きなクリスマスツリーが国の旗と同じ青と黄色に光り始めました。今年はロシアの攻撃があって、キーウでも電気が足りません。クリスマスツリーの高さは12mで、いつもの年の半分以下です。光がついている時間も短くなっています。クリスマスツリーのいちばん上には、ウクライナの国のシンボルが飾ってあります。キーウを助けている国の旗をデザインした飾りもあります。19日はとても寒くなりましたが、たくさんの人たちが広場に集まりました。午後5時ごろに光がつくと、みんなうれしそうに大きな声を出していました。1歳の息子と来た女性は「爆発の音で起きることがないような平和な国になってほしいです」と話していました。"},{"question":"السؤال: شحال عدد أفوغادرو ؟","answer":"(6.02214076×10²³ mol⁻¹)  :الإجابة هي عدد افوكادور او ثابته افوكادور تسمات كذلك نسبه للعالم الايطالي اميديو افوكادور اللي هو عالم كبير.وكاتستخدم فالكيمياء وفالفيزياء  وكتعبر على عدد الذرات اللي كاينه في 12 جرام من كربون-12 وتاريخيا تختار كربون-12 لان الكتله ديالو يمكن ليها تتقاس بدقه وكاين وحده المول اللي هي كاتعرف بعدد افوكادور الجزئيات اي نوع من الماده وكيستعمل في وحده الجزء المولي والكتله الموليه والتركيز"},{"question":"السؤال: ما هو التباين لعدد من الماقرأات المفردة ؟","answer":"الإجابة: مربع الانحراف المعياري"},{"question":"මයිකල් ක්ලාක් ඕස්ට්‍රේලියානු කණ්ඩායමේ නායකත්වය දැරුවේ කුමන ජාත්‍යන්තර ක්‍රිකට් ආකෘතිවල(format)ද?","answer":"හිටපු ඕස්ට්‍රේලියානු ක්‍රිකට් ක්‍රීඩක මයිකල් ක්ලාක්, ප්‍රධාන ජාත්‍යන්තර ක්‍රිකට් ආකෘති තුනේම ඔස්ට්‍රේලියානු ජාතික කණ්ඩායමේ නායකත්වය දැරීය: ටෙස්ට්, එක්දින ජාත්‍යන්තර (එක්දින), සහ විස්සයි20 ජාත්‍යන්තර (විස්සයි20). ක්ලාක්ට නායකයෙකු ලෙස කීර්තිමත් වෘත්තීය ජීවිතයක් තිබූ අතර, ඔහුගේ ආක්‍රමණශීලී සහ නව්‍ය නායකත්ව විලාසය සඳහා ප්‍රසිද්ධය. ඔහු 2011 සිට 2015 දක්වා ටෙස්ට් තරඟවලදී, 2008 සිට 2015 දක්වා එක්දින තරඟවලදී සහ කෙටි කාලයක් T20I තරඟවලදී ඕස්ට්‍රේලියාව මෙහෙයවීය. ඔහුගේ නායකත්වය යටතේ ඕස්ට්‍රේලියාව 2015 ICC ක්‍රිකට් ලෝක කුසලානය ජයග්‍රහණය කිරීම ඇතුළුව සැලකිය යුතු ජයග්‍රහණ අත්කර ගත්තේය."},{"question":"LGS 2023 ingilizce kaç soru?","answer":"Örnek soru kitapçığında daha önceki yayınlarda olduğu gibi Türkçe, Matematik, Fen Bilimleri alanlarından 10'ar soru; T.C. İnkılap Tarihi ve Atatürkçülük, Din Kültürü ve Ahlak Bilgisi ile İngilizce alanlarından ise 5'er soru olmak üzere toplam 45 soru yer alıyor."},{"question":"Ẹ sọ fun ijọba Buhari ko bọwọ f’ofin o, ko lẹtọọ lati ni ki wọn fi tipatipa gbe Sunday Igboho wa si Naijiria-Lọọya Igboho","answer":"Bi ki i baa ṣe yiyọ Ọlọrun, ati gbogbo ipa ti awọn majẹ-o-bajẹ ṣa, ijọba Naijiria iba ji ajijagbara ọmọ Yoruba nni, Oloye Sunday Igboho, gbe de Naijiria ni Ọjọbọ, Tọsidee, ọsẹ yii.Gẹgẹ bi ALAROYE ṣe fi to yin leti ninu iroyin ta a gbe jade pe ijọba Buhari n wa gbogbo ọna lati gbe Sunday Igboho pada si Naijiria, boya ọna naa tọ tabi ko tọ. Ootọ yii tubọ fara han ninu iṣẹlẹ to waye ni orileede Olominira Benin. Ọkan ninu awọn agbẹjọro Oloye Igboho to fi ilẹ France ṣe ibugbe, ṣugbọn to wa si Naijiria nitori ẹjọ naa, Dokita Oluṣẹgun Malik Falọla ṣalaye f’ALAROYE lori foonu lọjọ Ẹti, Furaidee yii, nipa ohun to n ṣẹlẹ gan-an.Agba agbẹjọro naa ni, ‘‘Mo fi Alukuraani bura, mo fẹrẹ le daku nigba ti mo gbọ pe ijọba Naijiria fẹẹ ji Sunday Igboho gbe pada si ilẹ Naijiria. Oju-ẹsẹ ni mo ti gbe mọto ti mo lọọ ba awọn ti wọn gbe e pamọ, mo si kilọ fun wọn pe ọrun ijọba Benin ni Sunday wa, bi ohunkohun ba ṣẹlẹ si i, wahala to maa da silẹ ko ni i tan nilẹ.Nigba ti Akoroyin wa beere boya o ṣee ṣe loootọ lati fipa ji i gbe pada si Naijiria, Fawọle ni, ‘‘Ohun to da mi loju ni pe wọn ko to bẹẹ lati gbe Igboho pada si Naijiria. Oju gbogbo agbaye lo n wo wa lori ọrọ Sunday Igboho. Idi ta a fi ni ki wọn maa gbe e lọ si ọgba ẹwọn yatọ si atimọle ọlọpaa to wa tẹlẹ ni pe ọgba ẹwọn yẹn la ti ro pe aabo to daju le wa fun un fungba diẹ lo jẹ ka ni ki wọn gbe e lọ sibẹ.‘‘Ẹru n ba wa pe ẹmi rẹ ko de to ba ṣi wa latimọle tabi ti wọn ba da a silẹ pe ko maa lọ lọjọ Aje ti igbẹjọ rẹ waye. Wọn le yinbọn mọ ọn ki wọn ni awọn ko mọ ẹni to yinbọn pa a. Wọn le ṣe e leṣẹ ki ọrọ naa pada ja si iku, ohunkohun lo le ṣẹlẹ. Ṣẹ ẹ mọ pe awọn eeyan n yinbọn nigba ti wọn gbe e wa si kootu, ki i si i ṣe gbogbo ẹni to wa si kọọtu lo nifẹẹ rẹ, nitori naa la fi gbọdọ ṣọra ṣe. Koda, awọn ẹni ibi le lọọ dena de e ni papakọ ofurufu tabi ni ile ti wọn ba gbe e lọ. Ko si si ile ta a le ni ki wọn gbe e lọ ti aabo to daju maa wa nibẹ. Nitori pe ọgba ẹwọn nikan ni aabo ṣi wa diẹ fun un la fi ni ki wọn gbe e sibẹ.Nigba to n sọrọ nipa ipo ti Sunday Igboho wa pẹlu bawọn kan ṣe n gbe e kiri pe o tẹ yẹnkẹyẹnkẹ wa si kootu ni, Agbẹjọro Falọla sọ pe oun lọ sọdọ rẹ ni ọjọ Aje, Mọnde, ọsẹ yii. ‘‘Mo lọ sọdọ rẹ ni ọjọ Aje, Mọnde, ọsẹ yii, emi ni mo gbe ounjẹ lọ fun un. Emi pẹlu iyawo rẹ la jọ gbe ounjẹ ati aṣọ lọ fun un ni ọjọ Iṣẹgun, bẹẹ ni mo si ri i ni ijẹta, ki gbogbo rẹ too di girigiri lanaa (Ọjọbọ)Oni (ọjọ Ẹti) lo yẹ ki n tun ri i eyi gan-an ni mo fi pa irun Jimoh to yẹ ki n lọọ ki jẹ ki n le ri awọn iwe to yẹ ki n gba gba, lati le ri i daju pe mo foju kan an. Bakan naa ni mo ti yọju si ọga to wa ni ọgba ẹwọn, mo ṣi tun maa ri i lonii (ọjọ Ẹti), mo ti sọ fun un pe ko ma ri Sunday Igboho gẹgẹ bii ọdaran, mo ni ko tọju rẹ bii ẹni to wa nile ni, ko ma ṣe e bii ọdaran nitori ki i ṣe ọdaran, a kan tọju rẹ sibẹ nitori aabo ẹmi rẹ  ni.Agbẹjọro to fi orileede France ṣebugbe, to si n ṣiṣẹ aje rẹ nibẹ yii, waa sọ pe ki awọn to ba moju ijọba Buhari kilọ fun un gidigidi, o ṣe pataki ki ijọba naa bọwọ fun ofin. Ko tọ, bẹẹ ni ko si tọna, lati sọ pe wọn fẹẹ ji i gbe, tabi ki wọn fi tipatipa wọ ọ wa si Naijiria. O ni ẹjọ Sunday Igboho ti kuro ni ti ilẹ Naijiria nikan, gbogbo awọn orileede to lagbara lagbaaye lo n woye ibi ti ẹjọ rẹ n lọ."},{"question":"சொல் விளையாட்டுஒரு சொல்லில் உள்ள ஏதாவது ஓர் எழுத்தைக்கொண்டு, புதிய சொற்களை உருவாக்கி மகிழ்க.இதே போன்று ஒட்டகம், குருவி, சிங்கம், கவிதை போன்ற சொற்களைத் தொடக்கமாகவைத்துச் சொற்களை உருவாக்குக.","answer":"பா த ம் – தங் க ம் – க த வு – தலை வ ர் – தகதவஒட்ட க ம், கு ரு வி, சிங் க ம், க வி தை – கருகவி"},{"question":"வினா:உலகப்புகழ் பெற்ற மோனலிஸா ஓவியத்தை வரைந்தவர்?","answer":"விடை:லியோனார்டோ டா வின்சி (1452 - 1519) ஒரு இத்தாலிய மறுமலர்ச்சியின் பல்துறை அறிஞர் ஆவார். 'மறுமலர்ச்சி மனிதன் ' என்ற சொல்லை சுருக்கமாகக் கூறினார். உலகில் மிகவும் பிரபலமான மற்றும் போற்றப்படும் இரண்டு ஓவியங்கள் - மோனாலிசா மற்றும் தி லாஸ்ட் சப்பர் இவரால் வரையப்பட்டது."},{"question":"ഒരു പരിസ്ഥിതി വ്യവസ്ഥയില് ഒരേ ആവാസവ്യവസ്ഥ പങ്കിടുന്ന വ്യത്യസ്ത തരം മാംസഭുക്കള്  ഓപ്ഷനുകൾ: (1) അഴുകുന്നവയായി മാറുന്നു (2) ഭക്ഷണത്തിനായി മത്സരിക്കുക (3) സ്വന്തം ഭക്ഷണം ഉല് പാദിപ്പിക്കുക (4) പരസ്പരം കൂട്ടുകെട്ട്","answer":"(2) ആഹാരത്തിനായി മത്സരിക്കുക"},{"question":"Đoạn văn sau đang nói về vấn đề gì? Chữa lành vết thương Dầu mù u có chứa các polyphenol, calophyllolides và inophyllum giúp kích thích sản xuất collagen và tăng sinh tế bào da. Điều này có lợi cho việc chữa lành vết thương. Vì vậy, có thể thoa dầu mù u lên vết cắt, vết phồng rộp và vết xước để làm dịu và giúp vết thương mau lành hơn. Trị mụn trứng cá Dầu mù u có chứa các hợp chất hoạt tính sinh học như calophyllolide, axit calophyllic và lactone giúp loại bỏ vi khuẩn. Dầu mù u còn chống lại các chủng vi khuẩn gây mụn như Propionibacterium acnes  (P. acnes) và Propionibacterium granulosum (P. granulosum). Tác dụng chống viêm của dầu mù u còn hỗ trợ điều trị tình trạng viêm do mụn trứng cá gây ra. Ngoài ra, các chất chống oxy hóa trong dầu mù u còn làm mờ sẹo mụn. Giảm vết rạn, vết thâm trên da Dùng dầu mù u thoa trực tiếp lên da có thể làm giảm vết rạn da. Đồng thời, dầu mù u còn giúp làm sáng, hỗ trợ làm mờ vết thâm. Điều này là do dầu mù u có đặc tính tái tạo và thay đổi tế bào da mới. Giảm các dấu hiệu lão hóa sớm Các axit béo trong dầu mù u có thể ngăn ngừa các dấu hiệu lão hóa sớm. Các chất chống oxy hóa trong dầu sẽ trung hòa bất kỳ gốc tự do, từ đó làm chậm quá trình lão hóa da. Dầu mù u còn bảo vệ da khỏi tác hại của tia UV, nguyên nhân chính gây ra lão hóa da. Ngăn ngừa khô da Các axit oleic và linoleic trong dầu mù u nuôi dưỡng sâu, giúp dưỡng ẩm cho làn da. Có thể sử dụng dầu mù u đã pha loãng như một loại dầu dưỡng da mặt, ngăn ngừa khô da. Nên dùng dầu mù u thoa lên da trước khi đi ngủ. Điều trị bệnh chàm và bệnh vẩy nến Dầu mù u có các đặc tính kháng khuẩn và chống viêm, giúp giảm bớt các triệu chứng của bệnh chàm và bệnh vẩy nến. Thêm vào đó, dầu mù u còn giàu axit linoleic giúp giảm nguy cơ mắc bệnh vẩy nến. ","answer":"Lợi ích của dầu mù u đối với da."},{"question":"కింది పదాలు కలిపి రాయండి.ఉదా : విశ్వద + అభిరామ = (అ + అ = ఆ) – విశ్వదాభిరామ1. సోమన + అద్రి’2. రవి + ఇంద్రుడు3. భాను + ఉదయం4. మాతృ + ఋణం","answer":"1. సోమన + అద్రి’ := (అ + అ = ఆ) . = సోమనాద్రి2. రవి + ఇంద్రుడు . = (ఇ + ఇ = ఈ) – – రవీంద్రుడు3. భాను + ఉదయం ‘ = (ఉ + ఉ = ఊ) – భానూదయం4. మాతృ + ఋణం = (ఋ + ఋ = ఋ) = మాత్వణంగమనిక :పై వాటిలో మొదటి పదానికి చివర, రెండో పదానికి మొదట, ఒకే రకమైన అచ్చు వస్తున్నది. వీటినే – ‘సవర్ణాలు’ అంటారు. వీటితో ఏర్పడే సంధినే “సవర్ణదీర్ఘ సంధి” అంటారు.* అ, ఇ, ఉ, ఋ లకు అవే అచ్చులు పరమైనప్పుడు వాటి దీర్ఘాలు ఏకాదేశమవుతాయి."},{"question":"جمله اول: AR5 دانش تازه ای در مورد جنبه های اقتصادی و اجتماعی-علمی و فنی تغییرات آب و هوایی ارائه می دهد. جمله دوم: AR5 دانش تازه ای در مورد جنبه های علمی ، فنی و اجتماعی-اقتصادی تغییرات آب و هوایی ارائه می دهد. سوال: آیا جمله 1 و جمله 2 همان معنی را بیان می کنند؟ بله یا نه؟","answer":"نه. درجمله اول نوشته \\"اجتماعی-علمی\\" و درجمله دوم نوشته \\"اجتماعی-اقتصادی\\". استفاده از علامت \\"-\\" نشون میده که اون دو کلمه دوطرف \\"-\\" با هم یک ترکیب جدید رو میسازن، بنابراین نمیشه دو کلمه دوطرف \\"-\\" را برداشت و اونها رو به کلمات دیگه ای وصل کرد."},{"question":"加拿大的族群分佈如何？","answer":"加拿大族群分佈：74.4% 為歐裔、14.2% 為亞裔、4.3% 為原住民、2.9%為非裔、1.2%為拉美裔、而0.8% 為其他族裔。"},{"question":"Inona no niseho tamin'ny 17 marsa 2009 teto Madagasikara?","answer":"Ny 17 marsa 2009: natolotry ny filoha Marc Ravalomanana taminà miaramila manamboninahitra ny fahefana feno, ho an’ny fe-potoana tsy mihoatra ny 24 volana. Nomen’ny filohan’ny Fitondrana miaramila an’i Andry Rajoelina avy eo izany fahefana izany. Najoron’iAndry Rajoelina tamin’ny alalan’ny Didy Hitsivolana ny Fitondrana tetezamita, ho an’ny fotoana tsy mihoatra ny 24 volana. Nanameloka avy hatrany ny fanonganam-panjakana ny Vondrona Eoropeana, nanameloka ny famindram-pahefana tsy demokratika ny Amerikanina, ary nanala an’i Madagasikara tsy ho mpikambana ao aminy ny Firaisambe Afrikanina. Ny filoha frantsay Nicolas Sarkozy koa dia nanambara fa fanonganam-panjakana ny zavanitranga teto Madagasikara. Ny tohin’ny tantara anefa dia nampiseho fa nanohana ny tompon’andraikitr’izany fanonganam-panjakana izany ny fitondrana frantsay. Hita ohatra fa raha toa ka nisintaka na tsy nanendry ny masoivohony teto Madagasikara ny ankamaroan’ireo firenen-dehibe, dia nanendry ambasadaoro vaovao (Jean-Marc Châtaigner) hiasa teto kosa i Frantsa ny ampitson’ny nahatongavan’i Andry Rajoelina teo amin’ny fitondrana. Ary voaasa foana ny tompon’andraikitry ny tetezamita rehefa manao fety ny ambasady frantsay raha toa ka nikatona tanteraka ho an’izy ireo ohatra ny varavaran’ny ambasady amerikanina. I Leonardo Simao moa dia nanambara taty aoriana hoe: “Ny fitsabahan’ny Frantsay amin’ny raharaha-mpirenena malagasy dia tena mbola midika fa mitohy ny fanjanahantany”. Mety misy fahamarinana ny teniny, ary ny tena mampanontany tena dia ny hoe “sao sanatria mety amin’ireo mpitondra malagasy nifanesy ary izany trangan-javatra izany”? Satria miaro ny tombontsoany izany? ... "},{"question":"「ようにしている」と「ことにしている」はどう違いますか。","answer":"使う傾向や意味はわかっているけれど、自分でも境界線がしっかり掴めていないという方も多いのではないでしょうか。例文を挙げてみてみましょう。＜例＞毎朝ヨガをするようにしている。(できない日もあるけど)毎朝ヨガをすることにしている。(朝起きてすぐの習慣です。) １２時前には寝るようにしている。（できる限りそうしたいという意思あり）１２時前には寝ることにしている。（そう決めて、習慣にしている） 毎朝、牛乳を飲むようにしている（飲めない日もあるけど）毎朝、牛乳を飲むことにしている（毎朝わたしの意思で飲んでいる）メールの返信はすぐにするようにしている。（そうしたい意思がある）メールの返信はすぐにすることにしている。（努めてそうしている） 「ようにする」は、「ある状態をつくろうとする意思」を表す時に使います。そうしたいと心がけているような印象がありますね。一方、「ことにしている」は、ある状態を意思をもって習慣にしていることを表す時に使います。絶対にするという強い意思を感じます。いかがですか？"},{"question":"Cho hai tập hợp:A = {a; b; c; x; y} và B = {b; d; y; t; ư; v}Dùng kí hiệu \\"∉\\" hoặc \\"∈\\" để trả lời câu hỏi: Mỗi phần tử a, b, x, u thuộc tập hợp nào và không thuộc tập hợp nào?","answer":"Quan sát từng phần tử a, b, x, u, nếu phần tử nào xuất hiện trong tập hợp A thì ta viết “∈” tập đó, nếu phần tử đó không xuất hiện trong tập hợp A thì kí hiệu “∉”.Đáp ánDựa vào các phần tử của tập hợp A và BTa có:a ∈ A; a ∉ Bb ∈ A; b ∈ Bx ∈ A; x ∉ Bu ∉ A; u ∈ B"},{"question":"Šiame kaime Šilutės rajone kalinimo struktūras buvo įkūrę tiek naciai, tiek sovietai. Čia 1939–1944 m. veikė nacistinės Vokietijos karo belaisvių stovykla, 1945–1948 m. – sovietinis karo belaisvių lageris, o 1945–1955 m. – sovietinio gulago lageris. Kaip vadinasi kaimas?","answer":"Macikai – kaimas Šilutės rajono savivaldybėje, 2 km į rytus nuo Šilutės. Seniūnaitijos centras. Kaimas įsikūręs Pajūrio žemumoje, Macikų šiaurės vakarų pakraščiu teka Šyša."},{"question":"Vervollständige den folgenden Paragraphen: Seinen ersten Erfolg auf internationaler Ebene feierte er, als er beim Europacup 2007","answer":"mit übersprungenen 2,30 m siegte. Bei den Weltmeisterschaften in Osaka landete Onnen auf dem siebten Platz. Aus demselben Jahr stammt seine persönliche Bestleistung (2,34 m, 20. Mai 2007, Garbsen). 2008 wurde er zum zweiten Mal Deutscher Hallenmeister. Er qualifizierte sich für die Olympischen Spiele in Peking, musste den Start aber kurzfristig wegen Fußbeschwerden absagen."},{"question":"در ورزش کشتی چه سبک‌هایی وجود دارد؟","answer":"سبک‌های متنوعی از کشتی در کشورهای مختلف دنیا تمرین می‌شود. از مهم‌ترین سبک‌های ملی، المپیکی و محلی کشتی می‌توان به (کشتی فرنگی) و (کشتی آزاد) و کشتی با کمربند شامل گلیما در ایسلند، شوینگن در سوئیس، گوراش در آسیای میانه و نیز سومو و جوجیتسو در ژاپن و سامبو در روسیه اشاره کرد. در ایران نیز کشتی با چوخه یکی از رشته‌های محلی و بومی می‌باشد. "},{"question":"O yẹ ki awọn to n gbe Buhari kiri lọdun 2015 tọrọ aforiji lọwọ gbogbo ọmọ Naijiria-Fayoṣe","answer":"Ọgbẹni Peter Ayọdele Fayoṣe, gomina ipinlẹ Ekiti nigba kan, ti sọ pe gbogbo awọn ti wọn n gbe Buhari kiri lọdun 2015 pe oun lo yẹ nipo Aarẹ gbọdọ tọrọ aforiji lọwọ awọn ọmọ Naijiria bayii nitori ti wọn fi ọrọ ọkunrin naa ṣi awọn eeyan lọna.Bi Aarẹ orilẹ-ede yii ṣe kọ lati yọju si awọn ọmọ ile-igbimọ aṣoju-ṣofin l’Ọjọbọ, Tọside, ̀ọsẹ  yii, lo mu Fayoṣe sọ pe ọwọ lile ni Buhari fi n sẹjọba, ati pe awọn to n gbe e kiri nigba naa lọhun-un ni wọn fi tiwọn ko ba Naijiria bayii.Ni kete ti Aarẹ Buhari ti kọ lati yọju si wọn nile-igbimọ aṣoju-ṣofin ni Fayoṣe ti kọ ọ sori ikanni abẹyẹfo ẹ, nibi to ti ṣapejuwe Aarẹ orilẹ-ede yii gẹgẹ bii ẹni to n dari Naijiria bii igba to wa nipo ijọba ologun.Fayoṣe ni, “Mo ti sọ ọ lọjọ kin-in-ni, oṣu kẹjila, ọdun yii, pe Buhari, ko ni i yọju si wọn nile aṣofin, nigba tawọn yẹn ke si pe ko waa ṣalaye ọna tijọba ẹ n gba nipa bi eto aabo ṣe ri loni-in ni Naijiria.”“Iru ijọba Buhari yii ni mo ri ri o, Aarẹ alagbada ti ko bọwọ fun awọn ẹka eto iṣejọba mi-in, iru oloṣelu wo leeyan n pe iru wọn, bi ki i baa ṣe apaṣẹ-waa!’’O ni pẹlu ọwọ ti Buhari fi n mu eto iṣakoso orilẹ-ede yii, niṣe lo yẹ ki awọn to n gbe e kiri lasiko ibo ọdun 2015 maa tọrọ aforiji bayii lọwọ gbogbo ọmọ Naijiria."},{"question":"Ngano ginabulag ang kolor ug dekolor nga sinina sa paglaba?","answer":"Ginabulag ang kolor ug dekolor nga sinina sa paglaba aron dili mukapyot sa dekolor inkaso mulubad ang kolor nga sinina."},{"question":"پوښتنه: ټرانسپورټ د صنعتي عمر په جریان کې څنګه وده وکړه، او په نړیواله سوداګرۍ یې څه اغیزه درلوده؟","answer":"ځواب: صنعتي دور د ټرانسپورټ په برخه کې د پام وړ بدلون شاهد و. د بھاپ لوکوموټیو، د جورج سټیفنسن لخوا پیل شوی، او د بھاپ بیړۍ، د انجنونو لخوا پرمخ وړل کیږي لکه د رابرټ فولټن لخوا رامینځته شوي، د توکو او خلکو په حرکت کې انقلاب راوست. د اورګاډي پټلۍ او کانالونه ګړندي او ډیر اغیزمن ترانسپورت اسانه کړي ، چې پخوا جلا شوي سیمې او ملتونه سره وصل کوي. دې پرمختګ په ډراماتیک ډول د ټرانسپورټ لګښتونه او وخت کم کړ، په بې ساري پیمانه د نړیوالې سوداګرۍ اسانتیاوې. د خامو موادو او بشپړو توکو د لیږد وړتیا په اغیزمنه توګه د اقتصادي ودې، بازار ته د لاسرسي زیاتوالي، او د ملي او نړیوالو اقتصادونو ادغام کې مرسته کړې."},{"question":"Sunday Igboho pe awọn DSS lẹjọ","answer":"Nitori bi wọn ṣe fi tipatipa wọnu ile ẹ loruganjọ, ti wọn si paayan meji ninu awọn to n gbe pẹlu ẹ, ti wọn tun ko ọpọlọpọ dukia lọ, ajafẹtọọ ọmọ Yoruba nni, Oloye Sunday Adeyẹmọ, ti pe ileeṣẹ ọlọpaa- inu, DSS, lẹjọ.Miliọnu lọna ẹẹdẹgbẹta Naira (N500,000) lọkunrin ti gbogbo aye mọ si Sunday Igboho yii rọ ile-ẹjọ lati ba oun gba lọwọ awọn agbofinro naa gẹgẹ bii owo itanran fawọn dukia oun ti wọn bajẹ nigba ti wọn fi tipa tikuuku wọle oun lọganjọ oru bíi igba ti awọn adigunjale wọle onile.Bakan naa lo ni ki wọn san owo to jọju fun idile awọn eeyan meji ti wọn pa nipakupa lasiko ikọlu ojiji ọhun.Yatọ si gbogbo eyi, Sunday Igboho ni ki ileeṣẹ ọlọpaa ọtẹlẹmuyẹ kọwe ẹbẹ fun aforiji lọwọ oun lati sọ fun gbogbo aye pe awọn gba pe awọn jẹbi oun Igboho Ooṣa lori iwa ti ko bofin mu ti wọn hu sí oun yii.Ninu atẹjade ti agbẹjọro rẹ, Amofin-Agba Yọmi Alliyu, fi ṣọwọ sawọn oniroyin n’Ibadan, o ni awọn DSS ba awọn dukia, to fi mọ mọto olowo iyebiye to wa ninu ọgba ile oun jẹ.Agbẹjọro naa fi kun un pe gbogbo ibọn ti awọn  agbofinro sọ pe awọn ba nile onibaara oun ki i ṣe tiẹ rara, awọn funra wọn ni wọn mọ ibi tí wọn ti ri awọn ibọn naa.O ni lati bíi ogun ọdun sẹyin ti gbogbo ayé tí n gbọ orukọ gbajumọ eeyan ti wọn n pe ni Sunday Igboho, ko sẹni to le sọ pe oun ka ibọn mọ ọn lọwọ ri nitori ọkunrin naa ki i gbebọn rin.Bakan naa lo fọ ajafẹtọọ Yoruba naa mọ kuro ninu ẹsun ipinnu iwa ọdaran ti wọn fi kan an, o ni onibaara oun ko figba kankan pinnu lati huwa idaluru kankan"},{"question":"Jawab soalan teka-teki berikut: Mungkin satu-satunya tukang paip yang pernah menyelamatkan seorang puteri.","answer":"Jawapannya ialah Mario. "},{"question":"Inona no taova tompon'andraikitra amin'ny fandevonan-kanina?.","answer":"Ny vavony no taova tompon'andraikitra amin'ny fandevonan-kanina."},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਗਉੜੀ ਮਹਲਾ ੫ ॥ਬਿਖੈ ਰਾਜ ਤੇ ਅੰਧੁਲਾ ਭਾਰੀ ॥ਦੁਖਿ ਲਾਗੈ ਰਾਮ ਨਾਮੁ ਚਿਤਾਰੀ ॥੧॥ਤੇਰੇ ਦਾਸ ਕਉ ਤੁਹੀ ਵਡਿਆਈ ॥ਮਾਇਆ ਮਗਨੁ ਨਰਕਿ ਲੈ ਜਾਈ ॥੧॥ ਰਹਾਉ ॥ਰੋਗ ਗਿਰਸਤ ਚਿਤਾਰੇ ਨਾਉ ॥ਬਿਖੁ ਮਾਤੇ ਕਾ ਠਉਰ ਨ ਠਾਉ ॥੨॥ਚਰਨ ਕਮਲ ਸਿਉ ਲਾਗੀ ਪ੍ਰੀਤਿ ॥ਆਨ ਸੁਖਾ ਨਹੀ ਆਵਹਿ ਚੀਤਿ ॥੩॥ਸਦਾ ਸਦਾ ਸਿਮਰਉ ਪ੍ਰਭ ਸੁਆਮੀ ॥ਮਿਲੁ ਨਾਨਕ ਹਰਿ ਅੰਤਰਜਾਮੀ ॥੪॥੮੨॥੧੫੧॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 196 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਅਰਜਨ ਦੇਵ ਜੀ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਬਾਣੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਹਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"(ਹੇ ਭਾਈ !) ਵਿਸ਼ਿਆਂ ਦੇ ਪ੍ਰਭਾਵ ਨਾਲ (ਮਨੱੁਖ ਵਿਕਾਰਾਂ ਵਿਚ) ਬਹੁਤ ਅੰਨ੍ਹਾ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ (ਤਦੋਂ ਉਸ ਨੂੰ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਕਦੇ ਭੀ ਨਹੀਂ ਸੁੱਝਦਾ,ਪਰ ਵਿਕਾਰਾਂ ਦੇ ਕਾਰਨ ਜਦੋਂ ਉਹ) ਦੁੱਖ ਵਿਚ ਫਸਦਾ ਹੈ, ਤਦੋਂ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਚੇਤੇ ਕਰਦਾ ਹੈ ।੧।(ਹੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ !) ਤੇਰੇ ਦਾਸ ਦੇ ਵਾਸਤੇ ਤੇਰਾ ਨਾਮ ਹੀ (ਲੋਕ-ਪਰਲੋਕ ਵਿਚ) ਇੱਜ਼ਤ ਹੈ ।(ਤੇਰਾ ਦਾਸ ਜਾਣਦਾ ਹੈ ਕਿ) ਮਾਇਆ ਵਿਚ ਮਸਤ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਨੂੰ (ਮਾਇਆ) ਨਰਕ ਵਿਚ ਲੈ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ (ਸਦਾ ਦੁਖੀ ਰੱਖਦੀ ਹੈ) ।੧।ਰਹਾਉ।(ਹੇ ਭਾਈ !) ਰੋਗਾਂ ਨਾਲ ਘਿਰਿਆ ਹੋਇਆ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਚੇਤੇ ਕਰਦਾ ਹੈ,ਪਰ ਵਿਕਾਰਾਂ ਦੀ ਜ਼ਹਿਰ ਵਿਚ ਮਸਤ ਹੋਏ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਦੇ ਆਤਮਕ ਜੀਵਨ ਦਾ ਕਿਤੇ ਨਾਮ-ਨਿਸ਼ਾਨ ਨਹੀਂ ਲੱਭਦਾ, (ਵਿਕਾਰਾਂ ਦੀ ਜ਼ਹਿਰ ਉਸ ਦੇ ਆਤਮਕ ਜੀਵਨ ਨੂੰ ਮਾਰ-ਮੁਕਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ) ।੨।(ਹੇ ਭਾਈ ! ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੇ) ਸੋਹਣੇ ਚਰਨਾਂ ਨਾਲ (ਜਿਸ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਦੀ) ਪ੍ਰੀਤਿ ਬਣ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ,ਉਸ ਨੂੰ ਦੁਨੀਆ ਵਾਲੇ ਹੋਰ ਹੋਰ ਸੁਖ ਚੇਤੇ ਨਹੀਂ ਆਉਂਦੇ ।੩।ਮੈਂ ਸਦਾ ਹੀ ਤੈਨੂੰ ਸਿਮਰਦਾ ਰਹਾਂਹੇ ਨਾਨਕ ! (ਅਰਦਾਸ ਕਰ ਤੇ ਆਖ)—ਹੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ! ਹੇ ਸੁਆਮੀ ! ਹੇ ਅੰਤਰਜਾਮੀ ਹਰੀ ! (ਮੈਨੂੰ) ਮਿਲ ।੪।੮੨।੧੫੧।\\""},{"question":"Жумшак жана каткалаң үнсүздөр деген эмне?","answer":"Кыргыз тилиндеги үнсүз тыбыштар жумшак үнсүздөр жана каткалаң үнсүздөр болуп экиге бөлүнөт. Жумшак үнсүздөр үн мененшыбыштын жардамы аркылуу жасалат.А л а р: б, в, г (ги), г (гы), д, ж (жол), ж (журнал), з, й, л, м, н, ң, р.Каткалаң үнсүздөр жалаң шыбыштын жардамы аркылуу жасалат:А л а р: к (ки), к (кы), п, с, т, ф, х, ц, ч, ш, щ."},{"question":"வினா:இந்தியாவில் எத்தனை மாநிலங்கள் உள்ளன?","answer":"விடை:இந்தியப் பேரரசு என்பது பல்வேறு ஏகாதிபத்திய பிரிவுகள் மற்றும் பல்வேறு சுயாட்சியின் மாநிலங்கள் மற்றும் பிரதேசங்களைக் கொண்ட மிகவும் சிக்கலான அரசியல் அமைப்பாகும். 1876 இல் நிறுவப்பட்ட நேரத்தில், இது 584 மாநிலங்கள் மற்றும் மகுடத்தின் நேரடியாக ஆளப்பட்ட பிரதேசங்களால் ஆனது. முழு சாம்ராஜ்யமும் மாகாணங்கள் மற்றும் முகவர் நிலையங்களாக பிரிக்கப்பட்டது.இந்தியாவின் பேரரசரின் நேரடி ஆட்சியின் கீழ் ஒரு மாகாணம் (இவர் ஐக்கிய இராச்சியம் மற்றும் டொமினியன்களின் மன்னராகவும் இருந்தார்) மற்றும் ஒரு சில சிறிய மாநிலங்களைக் கொண்டிருந்தது, பேரரசரின் மேலாதிக்கத்தின் கீழ் இந்திய இளவரசர்களால் ஆளப்பட்டது. ஒரு ஆளுநர் அல்லது லெப்டினன்ட்-கவர்னர் அந்த மாகாணத்திற்கு பேரரசரின் பிரதிநிதியாகவும், மாகாணத்தில் நேரடியாக ஆளப்படும் பிரதேசங்களின் அரசாங்கத்தின் தலைவராகவும் செயல்பட்டார். ஆளுநர் அல்லது லெப்டினன்ட்-கவர்னர் மாகாணத்தில் உள்ள மாநிலங்களுக்கு பேரரசரின் பிரதிநிதியாகவும் பணியாற்றினார். லெப்டினன்ட்-கவர்னர்ஷிப்களில் முதல் மூன்று பகுதிகள் மற்ற அதிகாரங்களிலிருந்து இந்தியாவுடன் இணைக்கப்பட்ட பிரதேசங்களாகும், மேலும் அவற்றின் சொந்த தனி மாகாணங்களாக மாற்றப்படுவதற்கு முன்பு முன்னாள் பெங்கால் பிரசிடென்சியால் தற்காலிகமாக நிர்வகிக்கப்பட்டது. ஆக்ரா மற்றும் வங்காளம் இன்னும் நீதி மற்றும் சட்ட நோக்கங்களுக்காக செயல்படாத பெங்கால் பிரசிடென்சியின் டி ஜூர் பகுதிகளாக கருதப்பட்டன. ஆக்ரா இறுதியாக 1878 இல் பிரிக்கப்பட்டு இணைக்கப்பட்டது. வங்காள பிரசிடென்சி 1912 இல் மீண்டும் ஆளுநராக நிறுவப்பட்டது. இந்த மாகாணங்கள் அனைத்தும் இந்திய கவுன்சில் சட்டங்கள் மற்றும் இந்திய உயர் நீதிமன்றங்கள் சட்டங்களால் நிறுவப்பட்ட உயர் நீதிமன்றங்கள் மூலம் நிறுவப்பட்ட தங்கள் சொந்த சட்டமன்றங்களைக் கொண்டிருந்தன. இந்தச் சட்டமன்றங்களால் இயற்றப்பட்ட சட்டங்களுக்கு, பேரரசரின் பிரதிநிதியாகச் செயல்பட்ட இந்தியாவின் கவர்னர் ஜெனரல் மற்றும் மாகாணத்தின் ஆளுநர் அல்லது லெப்டினன்ட்-கவர்னர் ஆகியோரின் இரட்டை ஏற்றம் தேவைப்பட்டது.1912 இல் மூன்று கவர்னர் மாகாணங்கள் இருந்தன, அவை ஒரு காலத்தில் ஜனாதிபதிகளால் ஆளப்பட்ட வரலாற்று நினைவுச்சின்னமாக \\"பிரசிடென்சிஸ்\\" பாணியில் இருந்தன. இவை எல்லாம்:பம்பாய்மெட்ராஸ் (அதிகாரப்பூர்வமாக செயின்ட் ஜார்ஜ் கோட்டையின் பிரசிடென்சி)வங்காளம் (1912 முதல்)1905 இல் ஆறு லெப்டினன்ட்-கவர்னர் மாகாணங்கள் இருந்தன. அவை:பர்மாபஞ்சாப்மத்திய மாகாணங்கள்வங்காளம் (1912 வரை)கிழக்கு வங்காளம் மற்றும் அசாம் (1905-1912)ஆக்ரா மற்றும் ஊத்வடமேற்கு மாகாணங்கள் மற்றும் ஊத் (1878-1902)ஆக்ரா மற்றும் அவுத் ஐக்கிய மாகாணங்கள் (1902–1935)இவை தவிர, நியமிக்கப்பட்ட தலைமை ஆணையர்கள் மூலம் இந்திய அரசாங்கத்தால் நேரடியாக ஆளப்படும் சில பிரதேசங்கள் இருந்தன. இவை இந்தியாவுடன் இணைக்கப்பட்ட முன்னாள் சுதந்திர மாநிலங்கள் மற்றும் உச்ச அரசாங்கத்தால் நேரடியாக ஆளப்பட்டது.மூன்று தலைமை ஆணையர் மாகாணங்கள் இருந்தன. இவற்றுக்கு சட்டமன்றமோ, உயர் நீதிமன்றமோ இல்லை. இவை எல்லாம்:அஜ்மீர்-மேர்வாராகூர்க்ஊத் (1878 வரை)டெல்லி (1911 முதல், இந்தியாவின் தலைநகரம்)பத்தொன்பதாம் நூற்றாண்டின் பிற்பகுதியில் உள்ள பெரும்பான்மையான இந்திய மாநிலங்கள், ஏகாதிபத்தியப் பிரிவுகளின் அடிப்படையில், மாகாணங்களுக்குள் ஒழுங்கமைக்கப்பட்டன. இருப்பினும், ஒரு நல்ல அளவு மாநிலங்கள் ஏஜென்சிகள் (அல்லது குடியிருப்புகள்) எனப்படும் ஏகாதிபத்திய கட்டமைப்புகளாக ஒழுங்கமைக்கப்பட்டன. கவர்னர் ஜெனரலுக்கான ஒரு முகவர் (ஏஜிஜி) ஏஜென்சியில் உள்ள அனைத்து மாநிலங்களுக்கும் பேரரசரின் பிரதிநிதியாக செயல்பட்டார்.பேரரசு நிறுவப்பட்ட நேரத்தில், இரண்டு ஏஜென்சிகள் மட்டுமே இருந்தன:ராஜ்புதானாமத்திய இந்தியாகூடுதலாக, இந்த ராஜ்யங்கள் ஒரு மாகாணத்தின் அல்லது ஒரு நிறுவனத்தின் ஒரு பகுதியாக இல்லை மற்றும் பேரரசருடன் நேரடி உறவுகளைக் கொண்டிருந்தன:காஷ்மீர் மற்றும் ஜம்முஹைதராபாத் நிஜாமத்மைசூர் இராச்சியம்1919–19351919 ஆம் ஆண்டில், இந்தியாவின் நான்காவது அரசாங்கம் மகுடத்தால் இயற்றப்பட்டது. இது பல பெரிய மாற்றங்களைக் கண்டது. மாகாணங்களின் சட்டமன்றங்கள் பரிந்துரைக்கப்பட்டவை அல்லாமல் தேர்ந்தெடுக்கப்பட்டவை ஆக்கப்பட்டன. சில மாகாணங்களுக்கு இருசபை சட்டமன்றங்கள் வழங்கப்பட்டன. அனைத்து மாகாணங்களும் கவர்னர் பதவிகளாக உயர்த்தப்பட்டு அனைத்து லெப்டினன்ட் கவர்னர்களும் கவர்னர்களாக ஆக்கப்பட்டனர். பர்மாவுக்கு சிறப்பு அந்தஸ்து வழங்கப்பட்டு தன்னாட்சி மாகாணமாக மாற்றப்பட்டது.இப்போது பத்து கவர்னர் மாகாணங்கள் உள்ளன. இவை எல்லாம்:பம்பாய்மெட்ராஸ்வங்காளம்பர்மாபஞ்சாப்மத்திய மாகாணங்கள் மற்றும் பெரார்ஐக்கிய மாகாணங்கள்வடமேற்கு எல்லைப்புற மாகாணம்அசாம்பீகார் மற்றும் ஒரிசாநான்கு தலைமை ஆணையர் மாகாணங்கள் இருந்தன. அங்கு நிலை பெரும்பாலும் மாறாமல் இருந்தது. இவை எல்லாம்:அஜ்மீர்-மேர்வாராகூர்க்பலுசிஸ்தான்டெல்லி1920 ஆம் ஆண்டு ஜார்ஜ் வி பேரரசரால் இளவரசர்களின் அறை நிறுவப்பட்டது. இதன் முக்கிய விளைவுகளில் ஒன்று, மாகாணங்களின் மாநிலங்களில் இருந்து மேலும் பல ஏஜென்சிகளை உருவாக்கியது, இதனால் அவர்களுக்கு ஆளுநர்களுடன் இல்லாமல் பேரரசருடன் நேரடி உறவுகளை வழங்கியது.இப்போது 8 ஏகாதிபத்திய நிறுவனங்கள் மற்றும் குடியிருப்புகள் இருந்தன. இவை எல்லாம்:பஞ்சாப் மாநிலங்கள் (முன்னர் பஞ்சாப் மாகாணத்தின் ஒரு பகுதி)மெட்ராஸ் ஸ்டேட்ஸ் (முன்னர் மெட்ராஸ் பிரசிடென்சியின் ஒரு பகுதி)டெக்கான் ஸ்டேட்ஸ் ஏஜென்சி மற்றும் கோலாப்பூர் ரெசிடென்சி (முன்னர் பம்பாய் பிரசிடென்சியின் ஒரு பகுதி)மேற்கு இந்தியா மற்றும் குஜராத் மாநிலங்கள் ஏஜென்சி மற்றும் பரோடா ரெசிடென்சி (முன்னர் பம்பாய் பிரசிடென்சியின் ஒரு பகுதி)கிழக்கு மாநிலங்கள் (முன்னர் பெங்கால் பிரசிடென்சியின் ஒரு பகுதி, பீகார் மற்றும் ஒரிசா மாகாணம் மற்றும் மத்திய மாகாணங்கள்)குவாலியர் ரெசிடென்சி (முன்னர் மத்திய இந்திய ஏஜென்சியின் ஒரு பகுதி)ராஜ்புதானாமத்திய இந்தியாஇது அனைத்து மாநிலங்களையும் மாகாணங்களிலிருந்து பிரித்து, முன்பு குறிப்பிடப்பட்ட முகவர்களுடன் சேர்த்ததைக் கண்டது. இது அனைத்து மாகாணங்களும் நேரடி அரசாட்சியின் கீழ் மட்டுமே பிரதேசங்களைக் கொண்டு சென்றது.இந்தியாவில் தற்போது மொத்தம் 28 மாநிலங்கள் மற்றும் 8 யூனியன் பிரதேசங்கள் உள்ளன.இந்தியாவில் 28 மாநிலங்களும், தில்லி தேசிய தலைநகரப் பகுதி உள்ளிட்ட 8 நடுவண் அரசின் ஆட்சிப்பகுதிகளும் உள்ளன. அனைத்து மாநிலங்களிலும் மற்றும் ஒன்றியப் பகுதிகளில் பாண்டிச்சேரி, சம்மு காசுமீர், தில்லி தலைநகரப் பகுதி ஆகியவற்றிலும் மக்களால் தேர்ந்தெடுக்கப்படும் அரசுகள் உள்ளன. ஏனைய ஒன்றியப் பகுதிகள் இந்திய அரசால் நியமிக்கப்படும் ஆளுநர்களைக் கொண்ட, குடியரசுத் தலைவரின் நேரடி ஆட்சிக்கு உட்பட்ட பகுதிகளாகும். 1956 ஆம் ஆண்டில், மாநிலங்கள் மீளமைப்புச் சட்டத்தின் கீழ் மொழிவாரி மாநிலங்கள் உருவாக்கப்பட்டன. அதன் பின்னர், வட இந்தியப் பகுதிகளில் சில புதிய மாநிலங்கள் உருவாக்கப்பட்டது. மாநிலங்களும், ஒன்றியப் பகுதிகளும், மாவட்டங்கள் என்ற சிறிய நிருவாக அலகுகளாகப் பிரிக்கப்பட்டுள்ளன.இந்தியாவில் 28 மாநிலங்களும், தில்லி தேசிய தலைநகரப் பகுதி உள்ளிட்ட 8 நடுவண் அரசின் ஆட்சிப்பகுதிகளும் உள்ளன. அனைத்து மாநிலங்களிலும் மற்றும் ஒன்றியப் பகுதிகளில் பாண்டிச்சேரி, சம்மு காசுமீர், தில்லி தலைநகரப் பகுதி ஆகியவற்றிலும் மக்களால் தேர்ந்தெடுக்கப்படும் அரசுகள் உள்ளன. ஏனைய ஒன்றியப் பகுதிகள் இந்திய அரசால் நியமிக்கப்படும் ஆளுநர்களைக் கொண்ட, குடியரசுத் தலைவரின் நேரடி ஆட்சிக்கு உட்பட்ட பகுதிகளாகும். 1956 ஆம் ஆண்டில், மாநிலங்கள் மீளமைப்புச் சட்டத்தின் கீழ் மொழிவாரி மாநிலங்கள் உருவாக்கப்பட்டன. அதன் பின்னர், வட இந்தியப் பகுதிகளில் சில புதிய மாநிலங்கள் உருவாக்கப்பட்டது. மாநிலங்களும், ஒன்றியப் பகுதிகளும், மாவட்டங்கள் என்ற சிறிய நிருவாக அலகுகளாகப் பிரிக்கப்பட்டுள்ளன."},{"question":"Алыкул Осмоновтун калемине таандык ырлардан жазып бере аласыңбы ?","answer":"МЕН ТАНСАММен тансам: жаштан танам, ырдан танбайм,Ыры жок өмүрүмө канаттанбайм.Кудайга миң мертебе калп айтсам да,Ырыма бир мертебе калп айта албайм.Мен кыргыздын акыныКим берсе да жакшы берген бактымды,Ким койсо да жаман койгон атымды.Ушакчыдан не кылам деп сурасам,— Беш тыйынга мага сат дейт даңкыңды!Сатам!Алсын!Кайдан билсин баркымды?Чайга салып жутар кезде:Заар тилин куйкалачу,Мен кыргыздын акыны!Карлуу күнү берсе керек бактымды,Аяз күнү койсо керек атымды.Ичи арамдан не кылам деп сурасам,— Бир тыйынга мага сат дейт даңкыңды!Сатам!Алсын!Кайдан билсин баркымды?Кантка салып жутар кезде:Кара көңүлүн куйкалачу,Мен кыргыздын акыны!Таш идишке куйса керек бактымды,Татты идишке куйса керек атымды.Кароолчудан не кылам деп сурасам,— Балам алсын бекер бер дейт даңкыңды.Берем!Алсын!Сатпайм кадыр-баркымды,Уйчу, койчу, кетменчининМенмин кымбат акыны!Баалай келсе тең келе албайт,Бул ааламдын алтыны!"},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਗਉੜੀ ਮਹਲਾ ੫ ॥ਰੰਗ ਸੰਗਿ ਬਿਖਿਆ ਕੇ ਭੋਗਾ ਇਨ ਸੰਗਿ ਅੰਧ ਨ ਜਾਨੀ ॥੧॥ਹਉ ਸੰਚਉ ਹਉ ਖਾਟਤਾ ਸਗਲੀ ਅਵਧ ਬਿਹਾਨੀ ॥ ਰਹਾਉ ॥ਹਉ ਸੂਰਾ ਪਰਧਾਨੁ ਹਉ ਕੋ ਨਾਹੀ ਮੁਝਹਿ ਸਮਾਨੀ ॥੨॥ਜੋਬਨਵੰਤ ਅਚਾਰ ਕੁਲੀਨਾ ਮਨ ਮਹਿ ਹੋਇ ਗੁਮਾਨੀ ॥੩॥ਜਿਉ ਉਲਝਾਇਓ ਬਾਧ ਬੁਧਿ ਕਾ ਮਰਤਿਆ ਨਹੀ ਬਿਸਰਾਨੀ ॥੪॥ਭਾਈ ਮੀਤ ਬੰਧਪ ਸਖੇ ਪਾਛੇ ਤਿਨਹੂ ਕਉ ਸੰਪਾਨੀ ॥੫॥ਜਿਤੁ ਲਾਗੋ ਮਨੁ ਬਾਸਨਾ ਅੰਤਿ ਸਾਈ ਪ੍ਰਗਟਾਨੀ ॥੬॥ਅਹੰਬੁਧਿ ਸੁਚਿ ਕਰਮ ਕਰਿ ਇਹ ਬੰਧਨ ਬੰਧਾਨੀ ॥੭॥ਦਇਆਲ ਪੁਰਖ ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਹੁ ਨਾਨਕ ਦਾਸ ਦਸਾਨੀ ॥੮॥੩॥੧੫॥੪੪॥ ਜੁਮਲਾ\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 242 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਅਰਜਨ ਦੇਵ ਜੀ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਬਾਣੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਹਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"ਮੌਜਾਂ ਨਾਲ ਮਾਇਆ ਦੇ ਭੋਗ (ਮਨੁੱਖ ਭੋਗਦਾ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ), (ਮਾਇਆ ਦੇ ਮੋਹ ਵਿਚ) ਅੰਨ੍ਹਾ ਹੋਇਆ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਭੋਗਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਰੁੱਝਾ ਹੋਇਆ ਸਮਝਦਾ ਨਹੀਂ (ਕਿ ਉਮਰ ਵਿਅਰਥ ਗੁਜ਼ਰ ਰਹੀ ਹੈ) ।੧। ਮੈਂ ਮਾਇਆ ਜੋੜ ਰਿਹਾ ਹਾਂ, ਮੈਂ ਮਾਇਆ ਖੱਟਦਾ ਹਾਂ—(ਇਹਨਾਂ ਹੀ ਖ਼ਿਆਲਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਅੰਨ੍ਹੇ ਹੋਏ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਦੀ) ਸਾਰੀ ਹੀ ਉਮਰ ਗੁਜ਼ਰ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ ।ਰਹਾਉ। ਮੈਂ ਸੂਰਮਾ ਹਾਂ, ਮੈਂ ਚੌਧਰੀ ਹਾਂ, ਕੋਈ ਮੇਰੇ ਬਰਾਬਰ ਦਾ ਨਹੀਂ ਹੈ।੨। ਮੈਂ ਸੋਹਣਾ ਹਾਂ, ਮੈਂ ਉੱਚੇ ਆਚਰਨ ਵਾਲਾ ਹਾਂ, ਮੈਂ ਉੱਚੀ ਕੁਲ ਵਾਲਾ ਹਾਂ—(ਮਾਇਆ ਦੇ ਮੋਹ ਵਿਚ ਅੰਨ੍ਹਾ ਹੋਇਆ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਆਪਣੇ) ਮਨ ਵਿਚ ਇਉਂ ਅਹੰਕਾਰੀ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ ।੩।(ਮਾਇਆ ਦੇ ਮੋਹ ਵਿਚ) ਮਾਰੀ ਹੋਈ ਮਤਿ ਵਾਲਾ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਜਿਵੇਂ (ਜਵਾਨੀ ਸਮੇ ਮਾਇਆ ਦੇ ਮੋਹ ਵਿਚ) ਫਸਿਆ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ, ਮਰਨ ਵੇਲੇ ਭੀ ਉਸ ਨੂੰ ਇਹ ਮਾਇਆ ਨਹੀਂ ਭੁੱਲਦੀ ।੪। ਭਰਾ, ਮਿੱਤਰ, ਰਿਸ਼ਤੇਦਾਰ, ਸਾਥੀ—ਮਰਨ ਤੋਂ ਪਿੱਛੋਂ ਆਖ਼ਰ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਹੀ (ਆਪਣੀ ਸਾਰੀ ਉਮਰ ਦੀ ਇਕੱਠੀ ਕੀਤੀ ਹੋਈ ਮਾਇਆ) ਸੌਂਪ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ ।੫। ਜਿਸ ਵਾਸਨਾ ਵਿਚ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਦਾ ਮਨ (ਸਾਰੀ ਉਮਰ) ਲੱਗਾ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ, ਆਖ਼ਿਰ ਮੌਤ ਵੇਲੇ ਉਹੀ ਵਾਸਨਾ ਆਪਣਾ ਜ਼ੋਰ ਪਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ ।੬। ਹਉਮੈ ਦੇ ਆਸਰੇ (ਸਰੀਰਕ ਪਵਿੱਤ੍ਰਤਾ ਤੇ ਤੀਰਥ-ਇਸ਼ਨਾਨ ਆਦਿਕ ਮਿਥੇ ਹੋਏ ਧਾਰਮਿਕ) ਕਰਮ ਕਰ ਕਰ ਕੇ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਦੇ ਬੰਧਨਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਹੀ ਬੱਝਾ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ ।੭। ਹੇ ਨਾਨਕ! (ਅਰਦਾਸ ਕਰ ਤੇ ਆਖ—) ਹੇ ਦਇਆ ਦੇ ਘਰ ਸਰਬ-ਵਿਆਪਕ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ! ਮੇਰੇ ਉਤੇ ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰ, ਮੈਨੂੰ ਆਪਣੇ ਦਾਸਾਂ ਦਾ ਦਾਸ (ਬਣਾਈ ਰੱਖ, ਤੇ ਮੈਨੂੰ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਹਉਮੈ ਦੇ ਬੰਧਨਾਂ ਤੋਂ ਬਚਾਈ ਰੱਖ) ।੮।੩।੧੫।੪੪।\\""},{"question":"Apakah jawapan untuk teka-teki berikut: Rejoice, Pantene, Dove.","answer":"Jawapannya ialah shampoo"},{"question":"س301- ما درجة غليان الماء بالفهرنهايت ؟","answer":"212 درجة"},{"question":"السؤال: ما هو الحلف الذي كان النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم يشارك به قومه قبل البعثة؟","answer":"الإجابة: حلف الفضول"},{"question":" Quais são as modalidades esportivas praticadas por um triatleta?","answer":"Uma combinação de natação, ciclismo e corrida."},{"question":"Complete a frase: \\"No Campo da Medicina, a pesquisa em genética pode...\\"","answer":"No Campo da Medicina, a pesquisa em genética pode levar a tratamentos altamente personalizados, para diversas condições de saúde."},{"question":"Iracema e América são anagramas?","answer":"Sim, ambas têm as mesmas letras (embora haja um acento no \\"e\\" de América)."},{"question":"Напишіть продовження цього абзацу - Макговерн також стверджує, що викриття могло б зупинити вторгнення в Ірак у 2003 році","answer":"\\"Кілька людей мали шанс запобігти війні в Іраці, якщо б у них була сміливість публічно розповісти те, що вони знали\\". Тільки за п'ять днів до офіційного початку нападу на Ірак, Макговерн та його колеги закликали до розголошення і стверджували, що адміністрація Буша вигадує аргументи для нападу на Ірак. "},{"question":"\\"వ్యవస్థీకృత మతానికి నేను ఎప్పుడూ భయపడతాను. అదంటే నాకు మూఢత్వం, ప్రాచీనత, సంప్రదాయవాదం, దోపిడీ గుర్తుకు వస్తాయి. అందులో తర్కం, సమర్థనలకు చోటులేదు\\" అని 1936లో నెహ్రూ తన ఆత్మకథలో రాశారు.నెహ్రూ లౌకికత్వం 1950లో తొలిసారి పరీక్షను ఎదుర్కొంది. 10వ శతాబ్దంలో మహమ్మద్‌ గజినీ చేతిలో దోపిడికి గురైన సోమనాథ్‌ ఆలయ పునరుద్ధరణ కార్యక్రమానికి, నెహ్రూ సూచనలకు విరుద్ధంగా అప్పటి రాష్ట్రపతి డాక్టర్‌ బాబూ రాజేంద్రప్రసాద్‌ హాజరయ్యారు.సెక్యులర్‌ దేశానికి నాయకత్వం వహిస్తున్న నేతలు ఓ మతపరమైన కార్యక్రమానికి హాజరు కావడం మంచి సంకేతం కాదని సోమనాథ్‌ పర్యటనపై అప్పట్లో నెహ్రూ రాజేంద్ర ప్రసాద్‌కు సూచించారు. కానీ నెహ్రూ వాదనను పట్టించుకోని రాజేంద్రప్రసాద్‌ ఆ కార్యక్రమానికి హాజరయ్యారు.\\"నేను నా మతాన్ని నమ్ముతున్నాను. దాన్నుంచి నన్ను వేరు చేయవద్దు. నేను సర్దార్‌ పటేల్‌, నవ్‌నగర్‌ జామ్‌సాహెబ్‌ (యువరాజు) సమక్షంలో సోమనాథ్ ఆలయాన్ని పరిశీలించాను\\" అని నెహ్రూ అభ్యంతరాలకు సమాధానమిస్తూ రాజేంద్రప్రసాద్‌ పేర్కొన్నట్లు ప్రముఖ జర్నలిస్టు దుర్గాదాస్‌ తన \\"ఇండియా-ఫ్రమ్‌ కర్జన్‌ టు నెహ్రూ అండ్‌ ఆఫ్టర్‌'' అనే పుస్తకంలో రాశారు. కుంభమేళాలో స్నానానికి నిరాకరించిన నెహ్రూ1952లో రాష్ట్రపతి బాబూ రాజేంద్రప్రసాద్ కాశీకి వెళ్లి కొంతమంది పండితుల పాదాలను కడిగిన సందర్భంగా మతం విషయంలో నెహ్రూ-రాజేంద్రప్రసాద్‌ల మధ్య అభిప్రాయభేదాలు మరోసారి కనిపించాయి. రాజేంద్రప్రసాద్‌ చర్యలకు నెహ్రూ తన లేఖలతో నిరసన తెలపగా \\"దేశంలో అత్యున్నత పదవిలో ఉన్న వ్యక్తి కూడా ఒక పండితుడి ముందు చిన్నవాడే\\" అని ఆయన సమాధానమిచ్చారు. ఈ వివాదం తర్వాతే నెహ్రూ అప్పటి ఉపరాష్ట్రపతి సర్వేపల్లి రాధాకృష్ణన్‌వైపు మొగ్గడం ప్రారంభించారు. \\"ఒకసారి శాస్త్రీజీ కుంభమేళాలో స్నానం చేయాల్సిందిగా నెహ్రూజీని అభ్యర్థించారు. అయితే నేను గంగను ప్రేమిస్తాను. ఎన్నోసార్లు అందులో మునిగాను కూడా. కానీ కుంభమేళా సందర్భంగా మాత్రం నేను ఆ పని చేయను అని నెహ్రూ సమాధానమిచ్చారు'' అని లాల్‌బహదూర్‌ శాస్త్రికి కార్యదర్శిగా పని చేసి సీపీ శ్రీవాస్తవ తన జీవిత చరిత్రలో రాశారు.గురు గోల్వాల్కర్‌ను సంప్రదించిన లాల్‌బహదూర్‌నెహ్రూలాగా లాల్‌బహదూర్‌ శాస్త్రి ఎప్పుడూ తన హిందుత్వ గుర్తింపును దాచుకునే ప్రయత్నం చేయలేదు. కానీ దేశం లౌకిక రాజ్యంగా ఉండాలన్న విషయంలో ఆయనకు మరో అభిప్రాయం ఉండేది కాదు. nnGive me a good title for the article above.","answer":"భారత ప్రధాన మంత్రి: లౌకికవాది నెహ్రూ నుంచి తీర్థ యాత్రికుడు మోదీ వరకు"},{"question":"கீழ்க்காணும்  பொதுஅறிவு அறிவு வினாவுக்கு விடையளிக்கவும்.இந்தியாவின் மிக உயர்ந்த இலக்கிய விருது எது?","answer":"விடை: ஞானபீட விருது"},{"question":"Unsa ang sister sa Bisaya?","answer":"Ang \\"sister\\" sa Bisaya mao ang \\"igsoon nga babaye\\" or \\"igsuon nga babaye.”"},{"question":"Quelles sont les étapes du processus de développement de nouveaux médicaments, de la recherche initiale à l'approbation réglementaire?","answer":"Le processus de développement de nouveaux médicaments comprend la recherche préclinique en laboratoire, les essais cliniques sur des volontaires humains, la soumission de données aux autorités réglementaires, l'examen de la sécurité et de l'efficacité, et l'approbation pour la mise sur le marché. Cela peut prendre plusieurs années et impliquer des tests rigoureux."},{"question":"ලෝකයේ දිගම ගංගාව කුමක් ද?","answer":"ලෝකයේ දිගම ගංගාව නයිල් නදියයි."},{"question":"යුරෝපයේ එකම බෞද්ධ රාජ්‍යය වන කල්මිකියාවේ අගනුවර කුමක්ද ?","answer":"යුරෝපයේ එකම බෞද්ධ රාජ්‍යය වන කල්මිකියාවේ අගනුවර එලිස්ටා  ය."},{"question":"Medicana Kadıköy SGK anlaşması var mı?","answer":"Medicana Sağlık Grubu Hastaneleri, Tüm Branşlarda SGK Anlaşmalıdır. Ayrıca hastane randevu numarası için 0850 460 6334 telefonunu da kullanabilirsiniz."},{"question":"Quantas Copas do Mundo a Croácia já venceu?","answer":"A Croácia ainda não conquistou nenhuma Copa do Mundo."},{"question":"प्रथम विश्व युद्ध ने भारत में राष्ट्रीय आंदोलन के विकास में कैसे मदद की?","answer":"प्रथम विश्व युद्ध के दौरान, रक्षा व्यय के वित्तपोषण के लिए, सीमा शुल्क बढ़ाए गए और आयकर पेश किया गया।  ग्रामीण क्षेत्रों में जबरन भर्ती के कारण व्यापक आक्रोश फैल गया।  1918-19 और 1920-21 में, भारत के कई हिस्सों में फसलें खराब हो गईं, जिसके परिणामस्वरूप भोजन की भारी कमी हो गई।  इसके अलावा, एक इन्फ्लूएंजा महामारी थी।  युद्ध के बाद लोगों की मुश्किलें खत्म नहीं हुईं।  इस प्रकार, वे संघर्ष का एक नया तरीका खोजने के लिए नेताओं के अधीन एकजुट हुए।"},{"question":"के तपाईं रोल्वालिङ उपत्यकाको चुनौतीपूर्ण उच्च उचाइ मार्गहरू र गौरी शंकर र मेलुङ्सेको नजिकको दृश्यहरूका लागि परिचित पदयात्रा गन्तव्य सिफारिस गर्न सक्नुहुन्छ?","answer":"रोल्वालिङ्ग उपत्यका पदयात्रा यसको चुनौतीपूर्ण उच्च उचाइ पासहरू र गौरी शंकर र मेलुङ्सेको नजिकको दृश्यहरूका लागि परिचित छ, जसले ट्रेकहरूलाई चुनौतीपूर्ण र इनामदायी साहसिक कार्य प्रदान गर्दछ।"},{"question":"ਆਦਮੀ ਨੇ ਆਪਣੀ ਪਿੱਠ ’ ਤੇ ਸੱਟ ਲਵਾ ਲਈ । | ਨਤੀਜੇ ਵਜੋਂ ਕੀ ਹੋਇਆ ? ਚੋਣ 1 : ਉਹ ਇਲਾਜ ਲਈ ਮਨੋਵਿਗਿਆਨਿਕ ਡਾਕਟਰ ਕੋਲ਼ ਗਿਆ । ਚੋਣ 2 : ਉਹ ਕਈਆਂ ਦਿਨਾਂ ਤੱਕ ਬਿਸਤਰੇ ਤੇ ਰਿਹਾ ।","answer":"ਚੋਣ 2 : ਉਹ ਕਈਆਂ ਦਿਨਾਂ ਤੱਕ ਬਿਸਤਰੇ ਤੇ ਰਿਹਾ ।"},{"question":"\\"Nahita raki-tsary tranainy aho tao amin'ny tsenan'ny parasy:\\"Inona no mety ho fiafaran'ny tantara teo aloha?A. Nisy sarin'ny havako efa ela no nisy ilay rakikira.B. Foana ilay rakikira, ary nesorina ireo sary.","answer":"A. no fiafarana azo inoana indrindra"},{"question":"Motho yo a sa itekanelago a ka bitšwa bjang?","answer":"Ke motho yo a nago le bogolofadi."},{"question":"வினா: ஜாலியன் வாலாபாக் படுகொலை நடந்த ஆண்டு?","answer":"விடை: 1919"},{"question":"Nees di binde ci Wolof?","answer":"Boo bëggee bind ci Wolof, li nga wàr jëkk a xàmme moo'y loy yi. Te ñoo'y : a, à, ã, b, c, d, e, é, ë, ẽ, f, g, h, i, ì, ĩ, j, k, l, m, n, ñ, ŋ, o, ó, õ, p, q, r, s, t, u, ù, ũ, w, x, y.Loy wu nekk, da'y jëmmal am riir.Waaye àm na riir yoo xàm ne 2 loy a ko'y indi : mb, nj, ng, nd. Niral: mbay, nday.Maas yi ñoo'y : a, à, ã, e, é, ë, ẽ, i, ì, ĩ, o, ó, õ, u, ù, ũ. Yi ci des, di ay riiraale. é, ë, i, ó ak u, da ñoo dìis, ci riir.Pollet moo'y ay loy yu ñu boole mu joxe am riir; riir ma man na a lëm solo, man na a ko bàñ a lëm.Baat = ab/ay pollet te lëm soloPollet = am/ay riir yu ñu boole yu juraat menn riirRiir = ab/ay loyLoy yépp di na ñu seex ba mu des f. Ci baat u 'pollet', 'l' ji da fa seex. Ci 'aar', 'a' da fa seex.X ju seex moo joxe q.Maas yi bu ñu'y seex, ñaareel u loy wi du àm comboñ. Niki: ùu, ée, ìi, añs.Kon ku màn a tudd loy yi, man a yër mbind. Da fa di rekk ne leeg-leeg, dégg ak bind wùute tuuti. Te 3 di na ko wàral:- leng: loy yii di 'b', 'j' ak 'g', séen doole da'y wàññiku bu ñu mujjee baat. Moo tàx nga'y bind jóob, di dégg 'jóop'; bind toj, di dégg 'toc'; bind nag, di dégg 'nak'- jégg: bu am riir dìisee ci pollet, man na a wàll pollet yi ci topp. Moo tàx jigeen lees di bind doonte 'jigéen' nga'y dégg; pollet u 'ji' bi moo dìis ba wàll 'géen'. Naka noo nu jëkkar lees di bind, doonte 'jëkkër' lees di gën a dégg; ba tay ìt taalibe moo jub; taalibé, déedet. Jégg àm na ci làkk yu bàri: 'assimilation' la tudd ci àngle.- sàmmoonte ak cosaanal baat: dàllu ji jóge ci dàll ak dàllu ji jóge ci dàl bokku ñu'w tuddìin.Àm na ay màndarga yu'y ñëw ci mbind te deesu léen tudd: ay doggamtal la ñu. Niki lomb (').Lomb (') da'y màndargaal làre walla tàxañug waat gi'y àm ci wàx; da'y dox diggante ñaar i waat ngìr wane ne yaar i waat la'ñ yu bokkul; wàx boole léen ci dégg. Moo tàx :- mu'y = mu di- ñu'y = ñu di- na'n lekk = na nu lekk- yaw ak = yaa'k- màn maa di = màn maa'y- lépp a di baax = lépp a'y baax- jàrul a sonn = jàr'l a sonnLomb bàri na làkk yu ko'y jëfandikoo; ràwati na yi niroo ay loy ak Wolof: farãse, àngle, italiyĩ, añs.Àm na yeneen i doggamtal yu'y yombal walla neexal yërum mbind; ak a ëndi yenn yu'y àm ci wàx ak wàxìin. Niki:- , = baar- : = tomb i aajar- ; = jastandiku- ... = jimbe- () = xala- ! = rëdd-u-jalu- ? = õs-u-laaj- \\" \\" = njukkal- . = tomb. Kàddu tomb la'y jeexe; te ìt loy wu rëy la'y tàmble.Li nu'y dolli ngìr jeexal, moo'y rëdd u jokkale (-). Dees na ko doxale ci diggante ay waat ngìr tëgg ci benn baat. Baat ba ci juddoo ab baat u toggatle la. Niral : ày-u-bis, xel-yaar.Lii nu indi, tënk na mbindum Wolof. Li ci des nag, ràwati na xóot-xóot yi ak sew-sew yi, jàng, mìin ak jege ñu dégg Wolof moo ko'y mottli. Xàm-xàm bi'y leeral mbind moo'y lëgg-lëgg."},{"question":"வினா: தமிழ்நாட்டின் வரலாறு பற்றி  விவரிக்கவும்.","answer":"விடை:தமிழ்நாட்டின் வரலாறு மிகவும் பழமையானது. தமிழ் மொழியின் தோற்றம் குறித்து பல்வேறு கருத்துக்கள் நிலவினாலும், பொதுவாக கி.மு. 3 ஆம் நூற்றாண்டிற்கு முன்னர் தமிழ் மொழி தோன்றியிருக்கலாம் என்று கருதப்படுகிறது. தமிழ்நாட்டின் வரலாற்றில் பல்வேறு ஆட்சிகள் நிலவியுள்ளன. சங்க காலம், பல்லவ மன்னர்கள், சோழ மன்னர்கள், பாண்டிய மன்னர்கள், நாயக்க மன்னர்கள், விஜயநகர பேரரசு, மராட்டியர்கள், பிரிட்டிஷ் ஆட்சி என பல்வேறு காலகட்டங்களை தமிழ்நாடு கடந்து வந்துள்ளது.தமிழக வரலாறு  தற்கால இந்தியாவில் உள்ள தமிழ்நாடு மாநிலத்தைப் பற்றியதாகும். இம்மண்டலம் வரலாற்றுக் காலத்துக்கு முன்பு முதல் மக்கள் வாழும் உறைவிடமாக தொடர்ந்து இருந்துவந்துள்ளது. தமிழ்நாட்டின் வரலாறும் தமிழ் மக்களின் நாகரீகமும் பண்பாடும் உலகின் மிகப் பழமையானவைகளில் ஒன்றாகும். முந்தைய பழங்கற்காலம் முதல் தற்காலம் வரையிலான தமிழ்நாட்டின் வரலாறு முழுவதிலும், இந்தப் பகுதியானது பல்வேறு புறக் கலாச்சாரங்களுடன் ஒருங்கிணைந்து இருந்து வந்துள்ளது. வரலாற்றில் ஒப்பீட்டளவில் குறுகிய காலப் பகுதிகளைத் தவிர்த்து, பிற காலகட்டங்களில் தமிழ்நாடு பகுதி புற ஆக்கிரமிப்புகள் எதுவுமின்றி சுதந்திரமாக இருந்து வந்துள்ளது.சேர, சோழ, பாண்டிய மற்றும் பல்லவ பேரரசுகளே நான்கு பண்டைய பூர்வீக தமிழ் பேரரசுகளாக இருந்தன. இவர்கள் தனித்தன்மை வாய்ந்த கலாச்சாரம் மற்றும் மொழி ஆகியவற்றைக் கொண்டு இந்தப் பகுதியை ஆட்சி செய்தனர், இதனால் உலகில் அழியாமல் வழக்கத்திலிருந்த சில பழமையான இலக்கியங்களின் வளர்ச்சி சாத்தியமானது. இவர்கள் ரோமப் பேரரசுடன் அதிகப்படியான கடல்வழி வணிகத் தொடர்புகளைக் கொண்டிருந்தனர். இப்பகுதியின் தலைமைக்காக இந்த மூன்று வம்சத்தைச் சேர்ந்தவர்களும் ஒருவருக்கொருவர் தொடர்ச்சியாக போரிட்டுக் கொண்டனர். மூன்று பேரரசுகளும் பாரம்பரியமாக ஆட்சி செய்துவந்த இந்தப் பகுதியை மூன்றாம் நூற்றாண்டில் நுழைந்த களப்பிரர்கள் விரட்டியதால் இப்பகுதியின் பாரம்பரிய ஆட்சி வடிவம் மாறியது. பாண்டியர்கள் மற்றும் பல்லவர்கள் மீட்டெழுந்து களப்பிரர் ஆதிக்கத்தை முறியடித்து தங்களின் பாரம்பரிய பேரரசுகளை மீண்டும் நிலைநாட்டினர். வீழ்ந்திருந்த சோழர்கள் ஒன்பதாம் நூற்றாண்டில் பல்லவர்களையும் பாண்டியர்களையும் தோற்கடித்து, தங்களது பெரும் சக்தியாக எழுச்சியடைந்து கிட்டத்தட்ட தெற்கு தீபகற்பப் பகுதி முழுவதும் தங்கள் பேரரசை விரிவுபடுத்தினர். வங்காள விரிகுடா பகுதியில் சோழப் பேரரசு சுமார் 3,600,000 சதுர கி.மீ. அளவிற்குப் பரவி இருந்தது. தென்கிழக்கு ஆசியாவில் இருந்த சிரீ விசயா பேரரசு பகுதியையும் சோழரின் கடற்படை கட்டுப்பாட்டில் கொண்டிருந்தது.வடமேற்கு பகுதியிலிருந்து வந்த இசுலாமிய படைகளின் ஊடுருவல் காரணமாக இந்தியாவின் மற்ற பகுதிகளில் ஏற்பட்ட அரசியல் மாற்றங்கள் தமிழ்நாட்டின் வரலாற்றில் குறிப்பிடத்தக்க மாற்றம் ஏற்பட்டது. பதினான்காம் நூற்றாண்டில் பண்டைய மூன்று பேரரசுகளின் வீழ்ச்சி காரணமாக, தமிழ்நாடு விசயநகரப் பேரரசின் ஒரு அங்கமாக மாறியது. விசயநகரப் பேரரசின் கீழ் தெலுங்கு பேசும் நாயக்கர் ஆட்சியாளர்கள் தமிழ்ப் பகுதியை ஆட்சி செய்தனர். மராத்தியர்களின் குறுகிய கால வருகை தமிழ்ப் பகுதியில் ஐரோப்பிய வணிக நிறுவனங்களின் வருகைக்கு வழிவகுத்தது. பதினேழாம் நூற்றாண்டின் போது இவ்வாறு வணிகம் செய்ய வந்தவர்கள் இறுதியில் இந்தப் பகுதியின் பூர்வீக ஆட்சியாளர்களை தங்களின் கட்டுப்பாட்டின் கீழ்க் கொண்டுவந்தனர். தென்னிந்தியாவின் பல பகுதிகளை உள்ளடக்கிய சென்னை மாகாணம் பதினெட்டாம் நூற்றாண்டில் உருவாக்கப்பட்டது. இப்பகுதி பிரித்தானியக் கிழக்கிந்தியக் கம்பனியால் நேரடியாக ஆட்சி செய்யப்பட்டது. இந்தியாவின் சுதந்திரத்திற்குப் பிறகு மொழியியல் எல்லைகளை அடிப்படையாகக் கொண்டு தமிழ்நாடு மாநிலம் உருவாக்கப்பட்டது.வரலாற்றுக்கு முந்தைய காலம்தெற்காசிய வரலாற்றுக் காலக்கோடுரிவாத் மக்கள் (பொ.ஊ.மு. 1,900,000)சோவனிகம் (பொ.ஊ.மு. 500,000)கற்காலம் (பொ.ஊ.மு. 50,000–3000)வெண்கலம் (பொ.ஊ.மு. 3000–1300)இரும்பு (பொ.ஊ.மு. 1200 – பொ.ஊ.மு. 230)பாரம்பரியம் (பொ.ஊ.மு. 230 – பொ.ஊ. 1205)மத்தியகாலம் (பொ.ஊ. 1206–1596)தற்காலம் (பொ.ஊ. 1526–1858)குடிமை (பொ.ஊ. 1510–1961)மற்ற அரசுகள் (1102–1947)இலங்கை இராச்சியங்கள்குடிமைப்பட்ட கால பர்மா (1824–1948)நாட்டு வரலாறுகள்பிராந்திய வரலாறுவரலாற்றுச் சிறப்புகள்பாஉதொபழைய கற்காலம்தமிழ்நாட்டின் பகுதிகளில் பழங்கற்கால குடியிருப்புகள் இருந்த வரலாற்றுக்கு முற்பட்ட காலப்பகுதியானது பொ.ஊ.மு. 500,000 ஆண்டிலிருந்து பொ.ஊ.மு. 3000 ஆண்டு வரை நீடித்திருந்ததாக மதிப்பிடப்படுகிறது.  பழங்கற்காலத்தின் பெரும்பாலான காலகட்டங்களில் இப்பகுதியில், அடர்த்தியற்ற காட்டுப் பகுதிகள் அல்லது புல்வெளி சார்ந்த சுற்றுச்சூழலில் அமைந்த ஆற்றுப் பள்ளதாக்குகளுக்கு அருகிலேயே மனிதர்கள் வாழ்ந்து வந்தனர். இந்தப் பகுதிகளில் மக்கட்தொகை அடர்த்தி மிகக் குறைவாக இருந்தது ஆகையால் தென்னிந்தியாவில் இரண்டு இடங்களில் மட்டுமே தொடக்க பழங்கற்கால கலாச்சாரம் கண்டறியப்பட்டுள்ளது. தமிழ்நாட்டில் சென்னையின் வடமேற்கு பகுதியில் உள்ள அத்திரம்பாக்கம் பள்ளதாக்கு இந்தப் பகுதிகளில் ஒன்றாகும். தமிழ்நாட்டின் வடக்குப் பகுதிகளைச் சுற்றி பழங்கற்காலத்திய விலங்குகளின் புதைப்படிமங்கள் மற்றும் கல்வெட்டுகள் கண்டறியப்பட்டுள்ளதாக தொல்லியல் சார்ந்த ஆய்வுகள் கூறுகின்றன. இவை பொ.ஊ.மு. 300,000 ஆண்டு காலத்தைச் சேர்ந்தவையாக இருக்கலாம்.  தென்னிந்தியாவில் வாழ்ந்த மனிதர்கள் பெரும்பாலும் பண்டைய \\"பழங்கற்காலத்தில்\\" நீண்ட காலம் வாழ்ந்த ஓமோ இரெக்டசு இனத்தைச் சேர்ந்தவர்களாவர். மேலும் இவர்கள் கைக்கோடரி மற்றும் வெட்டுக்கத்தி ஆகியவற்றைப் பயன்படுத்தி வேட்டையாடி சேகரித்து வாழும் மக்களாக இருந்தனர்.50,000 ஆண்டுகளுக்கு முன்பு தோன்றிய தற்கால மனித இனத்தின் (ஓமோ செப்பியன்சு ) மூதாதைய இனத்தினர் மிகவும் மேம்பட்ட நிலையிலும், பல்வேறு கற்களைப் பயன்படுத்தி தகடு போன்ற கருவிகள் மற்றும் மெல்லிய நுண்தகடு கருவிகளையும் உருவாக்கி பயன்படுத்தியிருந்தனர். சுமார் 10,000 ஆண்டுகளுக்கு முன்பிருந்து நுண்கல் கருவிகள் என்று அறியப்படும் இன்னும் சிறிய கருவிகளை மனிதர்கள் உருவாக்கினர். சூரிய காந்தக் கல், அகேட் கல், சிக்கிமுக்கி கல், குவாட்டசு கல் போன்ற பொருள்களைப் பயன்படுத்தி நுண்கற்கள் கருவிகளை மனிதர்கள் உருவாக்கினர். 1949 ஆம் ஆண்டில், இது போன்ற நுண்கல் கருவிகளை திருநெல்வேலி மாவட்டத்தில் ஆராய்ச்சியாளர்கள் கண்டுபிடித்துள்ளனர்.  நுண்கற்கள் காலமானது பொ.ஊ.மு. 6000-3000 ஆண்டுகளுக்கு இடைப்பட்ட காலமாகும் என தொல்லியல் துறை ஆய்வுகள் கூறுகின்றன.புதிய கற்காலம்தமிழ்நாட்டில் சுமார் பொ.ஊ.மு. 2500 ஆண்டு புதிய கற்காலம் தொடங்கியது. சாணைபிடித்தல் மற்றும் மெருகேற்றல் போன்ற முறைகளைப் பயன்படுத்தி புதிய கற்காலத்தைச் சேர்ந்த மனிதர்கள் தங்கள் கற்கருவிகளுக்கு நயமான வடிவம் அளித்தனர். பண்டைய எழுத்துக்களைக் கொண்ட புதிய கற்காலத்தைச் சேர்ந்த கோடரியின் மேற்பகுதி தமிழ்நாட்டில் கண்டுபிடிக்கப்பட்டுள்ளது.  புதிய கற்கால மனிதர்கள் பெரும்பாலும் சிறிய சமதளமான மலைகள் அல்லது மலையின் அடிவாரத்தில், சிறிய, ஏறத்தாழ நிரந்தரமான குடியிருப்புகளில் வாழ்ந்தனர். மேய்ச்சல் காரணங்களுக்காக அவ்வப்போது அவர்கள் இடம் விட்டு இடம் பெயர்ந்தனர். அவர்கள் இறந்தவர்களை பள்ளங்கள் அல்லது புதைகலங்களில் புதைத்து சடங்குகளை முறையாகச் செய்தனர். அவர்கள் ஆயுதங்கள் மற்றும் கருவிகளை உருவாக்க தாமிரத்தைப் பயன்படுத்தவும் தொடங்கினர்.இரும்புக் காலம்இரும்பைப் பயன்படுத்தி ஆயுதங்கள் மற்றும் கருவிகளை வடிவமைக்கும் முறையை மனிதர்கள் இரும்புக் காலத்தின் போது தொடங்கினர். பல நூறு இடங்களில் காணப்படும் பெருங்கற்களாலான இடுகாடுகளைக் கொண்டு தீபகற்ப இந்தியாவில் இரும்புக் காலக் கலாச்சாரம் இருந்ததை அறிய முடிகிறது.  இடுகாடு நினைவுச் சின்னங்களில் மேற்கொள்ளப்பட்ட அகழ்வாய்வு மற்றும் அவற்றின் வகைகளைக் கொண்டு வடக்குப் பகுதியிலிருந்து தெற்குப் பகுதிக்கு இரும்புக் கால குடியேற்றங்கள் பரவியதாகத் தெரிகிறது. திருநெல்வேலி மாவட்டத்தின் ஆதிச்சநல்லூர் மற்றும் இந்தியாவின் வடக்கு பகுதிகளில் நடைபெற்ற அகழ்வாய்வுகளை ஒப்பிடும் போது பெருங்கற்களாலான குடியேற்றங்கள் தெற்கு நோக்கி இடம்பெயர்ந்ததற்கான அடையாளங்கள் கிடைத்தன.சுமார் பொ.ஊ.மு. 1000 வது ஆண்டைச் சேர்ந்த பெருங்கற்களாலான புதைகல இடுகாடுகள் இருந்ததற்கான தெளிவான முற்கால அடையாளங்கள் இடுகாடுகள் தமிழ்நாட்டின் பல்வேறு பகுதிகளில் கண்டறியப்பட்டுள்ளன, குறிப்பாக திருநெல்வேலி மாவட்டத்திலிருந்து 24 கி.மீ தொலைவில் இருக்கும் ஆதிச்சநல்லூர் என்ற இடத்தில் இந்தியத் தொல்லியல் ஆய்வகத்தின் தொல்பொருள் ஆய்வாளர்கள் நடத்திய ஆய்வில் பூமியிலிருந்து 157 புதைகலங்களை அகழ்ந்தெடுத்தனர். அவற்றில் 15 கலங்களில் மனிதனின் மண்டை ஓடு, எலும்புக் கூடுகள் மற்றும் மற்றும் எலும்புகள், உமி, அரிசி தானியங்கள், கருகிய அரிசி மற்றும் புதிய கற்கால கோடரிக் கருவி ஆகியவற்றைக் கொண்டிருந்தன. கண்டெடுக்கப்பட்டுள்ள புதைகலத்தில் எழுத்தப்பட்ட எழுத்துகள், 2800 ஆண்டுகளுக்கு முந்தைய புதிய கற்காலத்தின் தமிழ்-பிராமி வரிவடிவத்தை ஒத்திருப்பதாக இந்தியத் தொல்லியல் ஆய்வகத்தின் தொல்பொருள் ஆய்வாளர்கள் கூறுகின்றனர். தொடர்ந்து அகழ்வாய்வு சோதனைகளை மேற்கொள்ளுவதற்கான தொல்லியல் களமாக ஆதிச்சநல்லூர் அறிவிக்கப்பட்டுள்ளது.தற்போதைய பொதுவான காலத்திற்கு முந்தைய தமிழ்நாட்டின் அரசியல் நிலவரம் பற்றிய குறிப்புகள், பொ.ஊ.மு. 300 ஆண்டைச் சேர்ந்த அசோகரின் சாசனத்திலும் பொ.ஊ.மு. 150 ஆண்டைச் சேர்ந்த கதிகும்பா கல்வெட்டிலும் (ஓரளவு) கண்டறியப்பட்டுள்ளது. மிகப் பழைய வட்டெழுத்து ரீதியான சான்றில் தமிழ் நாட்டில் இருந்த ஆட்சி பற்றிய குறிப்புகள் காணப்படுகின்றன, அதில் பாண்டிய நாட்டிலிருந்து களப்பிரர்களை வெளியேற்றிய பாண்டிய அரசன் கடுங்கோன் (சு. பொ.ஊ. 560–590) என்பவனைப் பற்றிக் கூறப்பட்டுள்ளது - நீலகண்ட சாத்திரி, தென்னிந்தியாவின் வரலாறு பண்டைய தமிழ்நாட்டில், வேந்தர் என அழைக்கப்பட்ட அரசர்களின் தலைமையின் கீழ் இருந்த மூன்று முடியாட்சி மாநிலங்களும் வேள் அல்லது வேளிர் என்ற பட்டப் பெயர் கொண்டு அழைக்கப்பட்ட பல பழங்குடி இனத் தலைவர்களின் தலைமையில் இருந்த பழங்குடி இனக் குழுக்களும் இருந்தன. இவர்களுக்கும் அடுத்ததாக, உள்ளூர் பகுதிகளின் இனக் குழுக்களின் தலைவர்கள் இருந்தனர், இவர்கள் கிழார் அல்லது மன்னர் என அழைக்கப்பட்டனர். பொ.ஊ.மு. மூன்றாம் நூற்றாண்டின் போது தக்காணப் பீடபூமி மௌரியப் பேரரசின் ஒரு அங்கமாக இருந்தது. பொ.ஊ.மு. முதல் நூற்றாண்டின் இடைப்பகுதி முதல் பொ.ஊ. இரண்டாம் நூற்றாண்டு வரை இந்த பகுதி சாதவாகனர் வம்சத்தினரால் ஆளப்பட்டது. வடக்கு பகுதியைச் சேர்ந்த இந்தப் பேரரசுகளின் கட்டுப்பாட்டிலிருந்து தமிழ் பகுதி தன்னிச்சையாக இருந்தது. தமிழ் அரசர்கள் மற்றும் குழுத்தலைவர்கள் எப்போதும் ஒருவருக்கொருவர் சண்டையிட்டுக் கொண்டிருந்தனர். பெரும்பாலும் அவர்கள் சண்டையிடுவது இடங்களுக்காகவே. அரசனின் நீதிமன்றங்கள் ஆற்றலைப் பகிர்ந்தளிப்பதற்கு பதிலாக சமூக நிகழ்வுகளுக்கான மையங்களாக இருந்தன. அவை வளங்களைப் பகிர்ந்தளிக்கும் மையங்களாக இருந்தன. ஆட்சியாளர்கள் படிப்படியாக வட இந்தியார்களின் ஆதிக்கம் மற்றும் வேதக் கொள்கைகளைப் பின்பற்றத் தொடங்கினர். இவைகள் ஆட்சியாளரின் நிலையை மேம்படுத்த பலி கொடுக்கும் பழக்கத்தையும் ஊக்குவித்தன.அசோகப் பேரரசின் கீழ் இல்லாத பேரரசுகள் மற்றும் இந்தப் பேரரசுடன் நட்பு நிலையில் இருந்த பேரரசுகள் பற்றிய தகவல்கள் கல்வெட்டில் குறிப்பிடப்பட்டுள்ளன. இவற்றுடன் சேர்ந்து சோழர்கள், பாண்டியர்கள் மற்றும் சேரர்களின் வம்சங்கள் (பொ.ஊ.மு. 273-232) அசோகத் தூண்களில் குறிப்பிடப்பட்டுள்ளன. நூறு ஆண்டுகளுக்கும் மேலாக இருந்த தமிழ் பேரரசுகளின் கூட்டமைப்பைபற்றி பொ.ஊ.மு. 150 ஆண்டைச் சேர்ந்த கலிங்கப் பேரரசை ஆட்சி செய்த அரசன் கார்வேலனின் அத்திகும்பா கல்வெட்டு, குறிப்பிடுக்கிறது.முற்கால சோழர்களில் கரிகாலச் சோழன் மிகப் புகழ்பெற்றவராக இருந்தார். சங்க இலக்கியங்களின் பல்வேறு செய்யுள்களில் கரிகாலச் சோழன் பற்றி குறிப்பிடப்பட்டுள்ளது. பின்னாளில் எழுதப்பட்ட சிலப்பதிகாரம் நூலில் வரும் பல்வேறு கதைகளிலும் கரிகாலன் பற்றிய செய்திகள் முக்கிய பொருளாக இருந்தது. மேலும் 11 மற்றும் 12 ஆம் நூற்றாண்டில் எழுதப்பட்ட இலக்கிய நூல்கள் மற்றும் கல்வெட்டுகளிலும் கரிகாலன் பற்றிய தகவல்கள் உள்ளன. இமாலயம் வரையிலான இந்தியா முழுவதையும் வென்றவன் எனவும் நிலமானியங்களைக் கொண்டு காவேரி ஆற்றின் வெள்ளத்தை தடுப்பதற்காக கரைகளைக் கட்டியவன் எனவும் இந்த நூல்கள் விளக்குகின்றன.] சங்க இலக்கியங்களில் இந்த தகவல்கள் இல்லை என்பதால் இந்த வரலாறு பற்றி வெளிப்படையாக தெரிவதில்லை. சோழர்களில் மற்றொரு புகழ்ழெற்ற மன்னன் கோச்செங்கண்ணன் ஆவான். சங்க கால இலக்கியப் பாடல்கள் பலவற்றில் அவனைப் பற்றி புகழ்ந்து பாடப்பட்டுள்ளது. இடைக்காலத்தின் போது சைவ அறிவாளராகவும் கருதப்பட்டார்.தொலெமியின் நிலப்படக்கலையை தொடர்ந்து உருவாக்கப்பட்ட தென்னிந்தியாவின் பழமையான வரைபடம்.இந்திய தீபகற்பத்தின் தென்கோடிப் பகுதியான கொற்கையிலிருந்து முதலில் ஆட்சி செய்ய தொடங்கிய பாண்டியர்கள் பின்னாளில் மதுரை நகருக்கு மாறினர். சங்க இலக்கியத்திலும் பாண்டியர்கள் பற்றி குறிப்பிடப்பட்டுள்ளது. மேலும் இதே காலத்தில் இருந்த கிரேக்க மற்றும் உரோமானிய ஆவணங்களிலும் பாண்டியர்கள் பற்றி உள்ளது. மெகசுதனிசு, இந்திகா என்ற தனது நூலில் பாண்டியப் பேரரசு பற்றி குறிப்பிட்டுள்ளார். மதுரையின் தற்போதைய மாவட்டங்கள், திருநெல்வேலி மற்றும் தெற்கு கேரளாவின் சில பகுதிகளை பாண்டியர்கள் தங்கள் கட்டுப்பாட்டில் வைத்திருந்தனர். பாண்டியர்கள் கிரேக்கம் மற்றும் உரோம் ஆகிய நாடுகளுடன் வணிகத் தொடர்பையும் கொண்டிருந்தனர். பாண்டியர்கள் தமிழகத்தின் மற்ற பேரரசுகளுடன் இணைந்து ஈழத்தின் தமிழ் வணிகர்களுடன் வணிக மற்றும் திருமணத் தொடர்பையும் கொண்டிருந்தனர். சங்க இலக்கியங்களின் பல்வேறு பாடல்களில் பாண்டிய மன்னர்கள் பலர் பற்றி குறிப்புகள் காணப்படுகின்றன. இவர்களில் 'தலையாலங்கானம் வென்ற' நெடுஞ்செழியன் மற்றும் தியாகச் செயல்களுக்கான சிறப்பான ஒருவராக குறிப்பிடப்படும் ஆரான் முதுகுடுமி பெருவழுதி என்ற மற்றொரு நெடுஞ்செழியன் ஆகியோர் சிறப்பாக குறிப்பிடப்பட்டுள்ளனர். அகநானூறு மற்றும் புறநானூறு போன்ற தமிழ்நூல்களின் தொகுப்புகளில் உள்ள சிறிய பாடல்கள், மதுரைக் காஞ்சி மற்றும் நெடுநல்வாடை போன்ற இரண்டு முக்கிய நூல்களிலும் (பத்துப்பாட்டு தொகுப்புகளில் உள்ளது) சங்க காலத்தில் பாண்டிய பேரரசில் மேற்கொள்ளப்பட்ட சமூக மற்றும் வணிக ரீதியான செயல்கள் பற்றிய செய்திகள் உள்ளன. மூன்றாம் நூற்றாண்டின் முடிவில் களப்பிரர்களின் ஊடுருவல் காரணமாக முற்காலப் பாண்டியர்களின் புகழ் மறைந்து போனது.தென்னிந்தியாவின் மலபார் கடற்கரை அல்லது அதன் மேற்கு பகுதியுடன் இணைந்த, தற்போதைய கேரள மாநிலம் ஆகியவை ஒன்றிணைந்த பகுதியாக சேரர்களின் பேரரசு இருந்தது. கடல் வழியாக ஆப்பிரிக்காவுடன் வாணிகம் செய்வதற்கு ஏற்ற வகையில் அவர்களின் இருப்பிடம் இருந்தது.  இந்தியாவின் மாநிலமான கேரளாவில் உள்ள இன்றைய மக்கள், பண்டையக் காலத்தில் தங்கள் பகுதியை ஆட்சி செய்த சேரர்கள் பேசிய மொழியே பேசுகின்றனர். மேலும் தமிழ் நாட்டின் பிற பகுதிகளுடனும் இவர்கள் பரவலான தொடர்பு கொண்டிருந்தனர். இது ஒன்பது அல்லது பத்தாம் நூற்றாண்டு வரை மட்டுமே வழக்கத்தில் இருந்தது, இதன் பிறகு தமிழ் மொழியில் வடமொழியின் தாக்கம் காரணமாக மொழியின் தனிப்பட்ட அங்கீகாரம் மாறி புதிய மொழி ஒன்று பயன்பாட்டிற்கு வந்தது.பழமையான இலக்கியங்கள் தமிழில் வளர்வதற்கு இந்த முற்கால பேரரசுகள் ஆதரவளித்தன. சங்க இலக்கியம் என்று அறியப்படும் செவ்வியல் இலக்கியம் பொ.ஊ.மு. 200 முதல் 300 ஆம் ஆண்டு வரையிலான காலத்தைச் சேர்ந்ததாக அறியப்படுகிறது. சங்க இலக்கியத்திலுள்ள பாடல்கள் பெரும்பாலும் உணர்வு மற்றும் பொருள் சார்ந்த தலைப்புகளையே கொண்டுள்ளன. இடைக்காலத்தில் இவைகள் வகைப்படுத்தப்பட்டு பல்வேறு தொகை நூல்களாக திரட்டப்பட்டுள்ளன. செழுமையான நிலம் மற்றும் பல்வேறு தொழில் சார்ந்த மக்கள் குழுக்கள் பற்றியே இந்த சங்கப் பாடல்கள் சித்தரிக்கின்றன. இந்த பகுதிகளை ஆட்சி செய்வது பரம்பரை குடியாட்சி முறையில் இருந்தது. எனினும் இந்த பகுதிகளின் செயல்பாடுகள் மற்றும் ஆட்சி செய்பவரின் ஆற்றல் ஆகியவை முன்பே இயற்றப்பட்ட ஒழுங்குமுறைகளை (தர்மம் ) பின்பற்றியே இருந்தது. மக்கள் தங்களின் அரசரிடம் மிகவும் விசுவாசமாக இருந்தனர். உலகம் சுற்றும் புலவர்களும் இசைக்கலைஞர்களும் நடனக் கலைஞர்களும் தாராள மனமுடைய அரசனின் அவைகளை அலங்கரித்தனர். இசை மற்றும் நடனக் கலைகள் மேம்பட்டு புகழ்பெற்றிருந்தன. சங்ககாலப் பாடல்களில் பல்வேறு வகையான இசைக் கருவிகள் பற்றிக் குறிப்பிடப்பட்டிருந்தன. தெற்கு பகுதி மற்றும் வடக்கு பகுதி நடனங்களை ஒருங்கிணைத்து புதிய வகை நடனம் ஆடுவது இந்த காலத்தில் தான் தொடங்கியது. இந்த வகை நடனங்கள் காப்பியமான சிலப்பதிகாரத்தில் முழுமையாக வெளிப்பட்டு இருந்தது.உள்நாட்டு மற்றும் வெளிநாட்டு வணிகம் சிறப்பான முறையில் ஒழுங்குபடுத்தப்பட்டு இயக்கத்தில் இருந்தது. தொல்லியல் துறை ஆய்வுகள் மற்றும் இலக்கியங்களில் யுவனர்களுடனான வெளிநாட்டு வணிகம் செழுமையாக இருந்தததைக் கூறுகின்றன. தென்னிந்தாவின் மேற்குக் கடற்கரைப் பகுதியில் இருந்த முசிறி மற்றும் கிழக்குக் கடற்கரைப் பகுதியின் துறைமுக நகரம் பூம்புகார் ஆகிய இரு இடங்களில் ஏராளமான கப்பல்கள் நிறுத்தப்பட்டு வெளிநாட்டுப் பொருள்களை ஏற்றுமதி மற்றும் இறக்குமதி செய்து வணிக மையங்களாக விளங்கின. இந்த வணிகம் இரண்டாம் நூற்றாண்டிற்கு பிறகு வீழ்ச்சியடையத் தொடங்கியது. மேலும் உரோமானிய அரசுக்கும் பண்டைய தமிழ் நாட்டிற்கும் இருந்த நேரடி உறவு அரபியர்கள் மற்றும் கிழக்கு ஆப்ரிக்காவை சேர்ந்த ஆக்சுமைட்களின் நேரடி வணிகத்தால் சிதைவுறத் தொடங்கியது. உள்நாட்டு வணிகம் சிறப்பாக இருந்தது, பொருள்கள் வாங்குவது மற்றும் விற்பது பண்டகமாற்று முறைப்படி நடந்தது. பெரும்பாலான மக்களுக்கும் அதிக நிலங்களைக் கொண்டிருந்த பரம்பரை விவசாயிகளான வெள்ளாளர்களுக்கும் விவசாயம் தலைமைத் தொழிலாக இருந்தது.இடைக்காலம் (பொ.ஊ. 300–600)முதன்மைக் கட்டுரை: களப்பிரர்பொ.ஊ.மு. 300 முதல் பொ.ஊ. 600 ஆம் ஆண்டு வரையிலான சங்க காலம் முடிவுற்ற பிறகு தமிழ் பகுதியில் என்ன நடந்தது என்பதற்கான தகவல் இல்லை. சுமார் 300 ஆம் ஆண்டுவாக்கில் களப்பிரரின் வருகையினால் அனைத்துப் பகுதிகளும் பாதிப்புக்குள்ளாயின. தமிழ் மன்னர்கள் நிறுவி இருந்த ஆட்சியை நீக்கிவிட்டு நாட்டில் கழுத்தை நெறிக்கும் ஆட்சியை களப்பிரர்கள் மேற்கொண்டனர். இதனால் பிற்கால இலக்கியங்களில் களப்பிரர் ஆட்சியாளர்கள் \\"கொடுங்கோலர்கள்\\" என்று குறிப்பிடப்பட்டது.[33] களப்பிரரின் தோற்றம் மற்றும் ஆட்சிப் பற்றிய தகவல்கள் அவ்வளவாக இல்லை. தங்கள் நினைவாக தொல்பொருள் அல்லது நினைவுச் சின்னத்தையோ இவர்கள் அதிக அளவில் விட்டுச் செல்லவில்லை. களப்பிரர் பற்றிய தகவல்கள் புத்தம் மற்றும் சமண இலக்கியங்களில் மட்டுமே அங்குமிங்குமாக உள்ளன.களப்பிரர்கள் புத்தம் அல்லது சமண நம்பிக்கையைப் பின்பற்றியதாகவும், இவர்கள் முற்கால நூற்றாண்டுகளில் தமிழ் பகுதியில் வாழ்ந்த பெரும்பாலான மக்கள் பின்பற்றிய இந்து மதங்களுக்கு (அத்திகா பள்ளிகள் மூலம் ) எதிராக இருந்தனர் எனவும் வரலாற்றாசிரியர்கள் ஊகஞ்செய்கின்றனர். ஏழாம் நூற்றாண்டு மற்றும் எட்டாம் நூற்றாண்டில் களப்பிரர் ஆட்சி வீழ்ந்த பிறகு வந்த இந்து மதத்தைச் சேர்ந்த அறிஞர்கள் தங்கள் நூல்களில் இவர்கள் பற்றி எந்த ஒரு குறிப்பையும் குறிப்பிடவில்லை. குறிப்பாக இவர்களது ஆட்சியை பற்றி எதிர்மறையாகவே குறிப்பிட்டு வைத்தனர். இவர்களது ஆட்சிக்காலம் ஓர் \\"இருண்ட காலம்\\" (இடைக்காலம்) என அழைக்கப்பட இதுவே காரணமாக இருக்கலாம். இங்கு ஆட்சி செய்து கொண்டிருந்த ஆட்சியாளர் குடும்பங்களில் சில களப்பிரர்களிடமிருந்து விலகி வடக்கு நோக்கி சென்று தங்களுக்கான இடங்களைத் தேர்வு செய்து கொண்டனர். பௌத்தம் மற்றும் சமண சமயங்கள் சமூகம் முழுவதும் பரவி நன்னடத்தை நெறிக் கவிதைகளுக்கு முக்கியத்துவம் அளித்தது.எழுதுவது என்பது அதிகமானது, மேலும் தமிழ்-பிராமி எழுத்து முறையில் இருந்து தோன்றிய வட்டெழுத்து தமிழ் எழுத்துக்களை எழுதுவதற்கான தலைமை வரிவடிவமாக ஆனது. தொடக்க நூற்றாண்டுகளில் எழுத்தப்பட இசையுடன் பாடும் பாடல்கள் ஒன்றாக திரட்டப்பட்டுள்ளன. இதிகாசச் செய்யுளான சிலப்பதிகாரம் மற்றும் வாழ்வியல் நெறிகளை கற்பிக்கும் திருக்குறள் போன்றவை இந்த காலகட்டங்களில் எழுதப்பட்டவையாகும். களப்பிரர் அரசர்கள் காலத்தில் இருந்த பௌத்தம் மற்றும் சமண அறிஞர்கள் அரசர்களால் ஆதரிக்கப்பட்டனர், இதனால் அக்கால இலக்கியங்களின் இயல்புகளில் அதன் தாக்கம் இருந்தது. இவ்வகையான இயல்புகளைக் கொண்ட பல்வேறு நூல்களும் இக்காலகட்டங்களில் இருந்த சமண மற்றும் பௌத்த சமயத்தை சார்ந்த எழுத்தாளர்களின் நூல்களாகும். நடனம் மற்றும் இசைத் துறையில், நாட்டுப்புற வடிவங்களுக்கு பதிலாக வடக்கத்திய பண்புகளின் பாதிப்பைக் கொண்ட புதிய வடிவங்களைப் பின்பற்றும் புதிய வகைகளுக்கு மேட்டுக்குடி மக்கள் ஆதரவளித்தனர். பழைய கற்கோவில்களில் சில இந்த காலகட்டத்தைச் சேர்ந்தவையாகும். பல்வேறு தெய்வங்களுக்காக கட்டப்பட்ட செங்கல் கோவில்களும் (கோட்டம் , தேவகுலம் , பள்ளி ) இலக்கியப் படைப்புகளில் குறிப்பிடப்பட்டுள்ளன. பல்லவர்கள் மற்றும் பாண்டிய அரசுகளின் மீட்டெழுச்சியால் ஏழாம் நூற்றாண்டில் களப்பிரரின் ஆட்சி அகன்றது.களப்பிரர்கள் வெளியேறிய பிறகும் சமண மற்றும் பௌத்த மதத்தின் தாக்கம் தமிழ்நாட்டில் இருந்தது. முற்கால பாண்டிய மற்றும் பல்லவ அரசர்கள் இந்த மதங்களைப் பின்பற்றினர். இந்து மதம் நலிவுறுவதை பொறுத்துக் கொள்ள இயலாத இந்து மதத்தினரின் எதிர்வினைகள் வளர்ந்து ஏழாம் நூற்றாண்டின் பிந்தைய பகுதிகளில் உயர்க்கட்டத்தை அடைந்தன.  இந்து மதம் புத்துயிர் பெற்ற சமயத்தில் சைவம் மற்றும் வைணவ இலக்கியங்கள் பல உருவாக்கப்பட்டன. புகழ்பெற்ற பற்று இலக்கியங்கள் வளர்ச்சியடைய பல்வேறு சைவ நாயன்மார்களும் வைணவ ஆழ்வார்களும் தூண்டுதலாக இருந்தனர். ஆறாம் நூற்றாண்டில் வாழ்ந்த காரைக்கால் அம்மையார் நாயன்மார்களில் முதலானவராகக் கருதப்படுகிறார். சைவ இறைவாழ்த்து பாடகர்களான சுந்தரமூர்த்தி, திருஞான சம்பந்தர் மற்றும் திருநாவுக்கரசர் ஆகியோரும் இந்த காலகட்டத்தை சார்ந்தவர்கள் தான். பொய்கையாழ்வார், பூதத்தாழ்வார் மற்றும் பேயாழ்வார் போன்ற வைணவ ஆழ்வார்கள் வழங்கிய தெய்வ திருமறைகள் மற்றும் பாடல்கள் நாலாயிர திவ்யப் பிரபந்தம் என்ற நான்காயிரம் பாடல்களைக் கொண்ட திரட்டாக தொகுக்கப்பட்டுள்ளது.பேரரசுகளின் காலம் (பொ.ஊ. 600–1300)வரலாற்றின் இடைக்காலங்களில் தமிழ்நாடு பல்வேறு பேரரசுகளின் எழுச்சியையும் வீழ்ச்சியையும் கண்டது. இந்த பேரரசுகளில் சிலர் இந்தியா மற்றும் வெளிநாடுகளில் தங்கள் ஆதிகத்தைச் செலுத்தி மிகவும் புகழ்பெற்று இருந்துள்ளனர். சங்க காலத்தின் போது மிக தலைமையாக இருந்த சோழர்கள் முதல் சில நூற்றாண்டுகளின் போது முற்றிலும் காணப்படவில்லை. பாண்டியர்கள் மற்றும் பல்லவர்களுக்கிடையே போட்டியுடன் தொடங்கிய இந்தக் காலம் சோழர்களுக்கு புத்துயிர் அளிப்பதாக இருந்தது. சோழர்கள் சிறப்பான முறையில் அதிகாரம் பெற்று ஆட்சி செய்தனர். சோழர்களின் வீழ்ச்சி பாண்டியர்களுக்கு புத்தெழுச்சியாக அமைந்தது. கோவில் கட்டுதல் மற்றும் சமய இலக்கியம் பாண்டியர்கள் ஆட்சிக் காலத்தில் சிறப்பானவையாக அமைந்த காரணத்தினால் இந்த காலகட்டத்தில் இந்து மதம் மீண்டும் பலப்படுத்தப்பட்டது.முந்தைய காலத்தில் இருந்த சமணம் மற்றும் பௌத்த மதங்களின் தாக்கங்களை குறைத்து இந்து மதத்தின் பிரிவுகளான சைவம் மற்றும் வைணவம் ஆகியவை ஆதிக்கத்தில் இருந்தன. சோழ அரசர்கள் அதிகமாக ஆதரித்த சைவ மதம், கிட்டத்தட்ட நாட்டின் மதமாக இருந்தது.[44] இன்று இருக்கும் பழங்காலக் கோவில்களில் சில கோவில்கள் பல்லவர்களால் இந்தக் காலகட்டத்தில் கட்டப்பட்டதாகும். மாமல்லபுரத்தில் பாறையைக் குடைந்து கட்டப்பட்டுள்ள கோயில் மற்றும் காஞ்சிபுரத்தில் இருக்கும் கம்பீரமான கைலாசநாதர் கோவில் மேலும் வைகுண்டபெருமாள் கோவில் ஆகியவை பல்லவரின் கலைக்கு எடுத்துக்காட்டுகளாகும். அதிகமான வெற்றிப்பேறு மூலம் தாங்கள் அடைந்த செல்வங்களைக் கொண்டு எப்போதும் நிலைத்திருக்கும் வகையில் அமைந்துள்ள கோவில்களில் ஒன்றான தஞ்சாவூரில் உள்ள பெருவுடையார் (பிரகதீசுவரர்) கோவில் மற்றும் வெண்கல சிற்பங்கள் சோழர்களின் கலைக்கு எடுத்துக்காட்டுகளாகும். சிவன் மற்றும் விட்டுணுவிற்கு அர்ப்பணிக்கப்பட்ட கோவில்களுக்கு காணிக்கையாக கிடைக்கும் பணம், நகைகள், நிலங்கள், விலங்குகள் ஆகியவற்றால் கோவில்கள் பொருளாதார மையங்களாக மாறின.தமிழ்நாடு முழுவதும் தமிழை எழுதுவதற்கான தமிழ் வரிவடிவம் மாற்றப்பட்டு வட்டெழுத்து வரிவடிவம் பயன்படுத்தப்பட்டது. மதச்சார்பற்ற மற்றும் மதம் சார்ந்த இலக்கியம் இந்தக் காலகட்டத்தில் வளம் பெற்றது. தமிழ் காப்பியமான கம்பரின் இராமாவதாரம் பதின்மூன்றாம் நூற்றாண்டில் எழுதப்பட்டதாகும். குழந்தைகளுக்கான பாடல்களை எழுதுவதில் மிகவும் ஆர்வம் கொண்ட ஔவையார் கம்பரின் சமகாலத்தவராவார். மதச்சார்பற்ற இலக்கியங்கள் பொதுவாக அரசர்களைப் பற்றி புகழ்ந்து பாடுவதற்காக எழுதப்படும். முந்தைய காலத்தில் எழுதப்பட்ட சமய பாடல்கள் மற்றும் சங்க காலத்தின் பழைய இலக்கியங்கள் கண்டறியப்பட்டு தொகை நூல்களாக தொகுக்கப்பட்டன. சமயம் சார்ந்த சடங்குகள் மற்றும் விழாச் சடங்குகளில் சமய ஆசான்கள் வடமொழியைப் பயன்படுத்தினர். இதன் மூலம் வடமொழி ஆதரிக்கப்பட்டது. முதலாம் இராசராச சோழன் காலத்தில் வாழ்ந்த நம்பி ஆண்டார் நம்பி என்பவர் சைவ நூல்களை ஒன்றாக திரட்டி திருமுறைகள் என்ற பதினோரு நூல்களாக வெளியிட்டுள்ளார். இரண்டாம் குலோத்துங்க சோழன் காலத்தில் (பொ.ஊ. 1133–1150) வாழ்ந்த சேக்கிழார் எழுதிய பெரியபுராணம் என்ற நூலில் சைவம் பற்றிய தகவல்கள் வரைமுறைப் படுத்தப்பட்டுள்ளது. முதலாம் குலோத்துங்க சோழன் இரண்டு முறை கலிங்க நாட்டிற்கு படையெடுத்துச் சென்றான் என்பது பற்றிய செய்திகளைக் கூறும் செயம்கொண்டாரின் கலிங்கத்துப்பரணி வாழ்க்கை வரலாறு பற்றிய பழங்கால எடுத்துக்காட்டாகும்.பல்லவர்கள்முதன்மைக் கட்டுரை: பல்லவர்பல்லவர்கள் மாமல்லபுரத்தில் உருவாக்கிய கடற்கரை கோவில் (எட்டாம் நூற்றாண்டு)முதலாம் மகேந்திரவர்மன் மற்றும் அவரது மகன் மாமல்ல முதலாம் நரசிம்மவர்மன் ஆகியோரின் தோற்றத்துடன் ஏழாம் நூற்றாண்டு முதல் பல்லவர்களின் ஆட்சியை தமிழ்நாடு கண்டது. இரண்டாம் நூற்றாண்டுக்கு முன்பு பல்லவர்கள் ஆட்சி அடையாளம் காணப்படவில்லை. சாதவாகனர் அரசர்களின் செயல் அலுவலர்களாக பல்லவர்கள் இருந்தார்கள் என்று அறிஞர்களால் பரவலாக ஏற்றுக் கொள்ளப்படுகிறது. சாதவாகனர்களின் வீழ்ச்சிக்கு பின்பு ஆந்திரா மற்றும் தமிழ்நாடு பகுதிகளை தங்கள் கட்டுப்பாட்டில் பல்லவர்கள் வைத்துக் கொண்டனர். பல்லவர்கள் தக்காணப் பீடபூமியை ஆட்சி செய்த வீடணுகுண்டினா என்பவருடன் திருமண உறவும் கொண்டிருந்தனர். சுமார் பொ.ஊ. 550 ஆண்டுவாக்கில் சிம்மவிட்டுணு என்ற அரசனின் ஆட்சிக்காலத்திலேயே பல்லவர்கள் மிகவும் புகழ்பெறத் தொடங்கினர். சோழர்களை அடிமைப் படுத்தி தெற்கு பகுதியில் உள்ள காவேரி ஆறு பகுதிகள் வரை பல்லவர்கள் ஆட்சி செய்தனர்.முதலாம் நரசிம்மவர்மன் மற்றும் பல்லவமல்லன் இரண்டாம் நந்திவர்மன் ஆட்சிக் காலத்தில் பல்லவர்கள் சிறப்பாக இருந்தனர். காஞ்சிபுரத்தை தலைநகரமாகக் கொண்டு தென்னிந்தியாவின் பல பகுதிகளை பல்லவர்கள் ஆண்டனர். பல்லவர்கள் காலத்தில் திராவிடக் கட்டடக்கலை உயரிய நிலையில் இருந்தது.[சான்று தேவை] யுனெசுகோவினால உலகப் பாரம்பரிய இடம் என்று அறிவிக்கப்பட்ட கடற்கரைக் கோவில் இரண்டாம் நரசிம்மவர்மன் அரசனால் கட்டப்பட்டது. சீனாவில் உள்ள பௌத்த மதத்தின் கொள்கையான சென் பிரிவை நிறுவிய போதி தர்மர் என்பவர் பல்லவ வம்சத்தின் இளவரசர் என்று பல்வேறு அடையாளங்கள் கூறுகின்றன.வாதாபியை நடுவாகக் கொண்டு ஆறாம் மற்றும் ஏழாம் நூற்றாண்டில் சாளுக்கியர் குலம் தக்காண பீடபூமியின் மேற்கு பகுதியில் எழுச்சியடைந்தது. முதலாம் மகேந்திரவரமன் ஆட்சி காலத்தில் இரண்டாம் புலிகேசி  என்பவர் பல்லவ பேரரசின் மீது படையெடுத்தார். மகேந்திரவர்மனின் அடுத்தவரான நரசிம்மவர்மன் சாளுக்கியர் மீது திடீரென படையெடுத்து அவற்றைக் கைபற்றி வாதாபியை தனது வசமாக்கிக் கொண்டார். சாளுக்கியர் மற்றும் பல்லவர்களுக்கு இடையே இருந்த பகை 750 ஆம் ஆண்டில் சாளுக்கியர்கள் மறையும் வரை சுமார் 100 ஆண்டுகள் வரை தொடர்ந்திருந்தது. சாளுக்கியர்களும் பல்லவர்களும் பலமுறை சண்டையிட்டுள்ளனர். பல்லவர்களின் தலைநகரமான காஞ்சிபுரம் இரண்டாம் நந்திவர்மன் ஆட்சிக் காலத்தில் இரண்டாம் விக்ரமாதித்யா என்ற அரசனால் கைப்பற்றப்பட்டது.] இரண்டாம் நந்திவர்மன் நீண்ட ஆட்சிக் காலத்தைக் (732–796) கொண்டிருந்தார். 760 ஆம் ஆண்டில் கங்கைப் பேரரசைக் (தெற்கு மைசூர்) கைப்பற்ற பயணம் செய்த படைகளுக்கு இரண்டாம் நந்திவர்மன் தலைமை தாங்கினார். பல்லவர்கள் பாண்டியர்களுடனும் தொடர்ச்சியாக சண்டையில் ஈடுபட்டு வந்தனர். அவர்களின் எல்லைப் பகுதி காவேரி ஆற்றின் கரைபபகுதிகள் வரை பரவியது. பாண்டியர்கள் மற்றும் சாளுக்கியர்கள் என்ற இரண்டு பேரரசுகளிடம் பகையாக இருந்த காரணத்தினால் இவர்களுக்கு எதிராக பல்லவர்கள் போரிட வேண்டியிருந்தது.பாண்டியர்கள்முதன்மைக் கட்டுரை: பாண்டியர்பாண்டிய பேரரசுதெற்குப் பகுதியில் களப்பிரர் ஆட்சியை வீழ்த்திய பெருமை பாண்டிய மன்னன் கடுங்கோன் (560–590) என்பவரைச் சாரும். கடுங்கோன் மற்றும் அவரது மகன் மாறவர்மன் அவனிசூளாமணி பாண்டியர்களின் ஆட்சிக்கு மறுமலர்ச்சியை ஏற்படுத்தினர். பாண்டிய மன்னன் சேந்தன் தனது ஆட்சிக் காலத்தில் ஆற்றலை சேர நாடு வரைக்கும் விரிவாக்கினார். இவரது மகன் அரிகேசரி பராந்தக மாறவர்மன் நீண்டகாலம் செழிப்பாக ஆட்சி செய்தார். அவன் பல போர்களின் மூலம் பாண்டியர்களின் ஆற்றலை விரிவாக்கினான். பாண்டியர்கள் பண்டைய காலத்திலிருந்தே புகழ்பெற்றவர்கள். பதின்மூன்றாம் நூற்றாண்டில், அப்போதிருந்த பேரரசுகளில் மிகவும் செல்வமிக்க பேரரசு என்று மார்க்கோ போலோ பாண்டிய பேரரசைக் குறிப்பிட்டுள்ளார். அவர்கள் ரோமன் பேரரசு வரையிலான பரவலான தொடர்புகளுடன் இருந்தனர், அத்தொடர்புகள் அரசியல் நயமிக்கவையாகவும் இருந்தன.தங்கள் ஆட்சி எல்லையை விரிவாக்கிய பின்னர், சில ஆண்டுகள் கழித்து பல்லவர் ஆட்சிக்கு பல்வேறு இடையூறுகளை பாண்டிய பேரரசு விளைவித்தது. பாண்டிய மன்னர் மாறவர்மன் இராசசிம்மா சாளுக்கியர் மன்னர் இரண்டாம் விகுரமாதிதியனுடன் கூட்டணி வைத்து பல்லவ அரசர் இரண்டாம் நந்திவர்மனைத் தாக்கினர். காவிரிக் கரையில் நடந்த போரில் முதலாம் வரகுனன் பல்லவர்களைத் தோற்கடித்தார். பாண்டியர்களுக்கு அதிகரித்து வரும் ஆற்றலை தடை செய்வதற்காக பல்லவ மன்னர் நந்திவர்மன், கொங்கு மற்றும் சேர நாடுகளின் தலைவர்களுடன் கூட்டணி வைத்துக் கொண்டார். போர்வீரர்கள் பலமுறைப் போரிட்டுக் கொண்டாலும் இறுதியில் பாண்டிய மன்னர்களின் படையே வெற்றி பெற்றது. பாண்டியர்கள் சுரீமாற சுரீவல்லபா என்பவரின் துணையுடன் இலங்கை மீது படையெடுத்து 840 ஆம் ஆண்டில் வடக்குப் பகுதிகளை அழித்தனர்.சுரீமாறாவின் துணையுடன் பாண்டியர்களின் ஆட்சி ஆற்றல் தொடர்ந்து வளர்ந்தது. பல்லவர்களின் பல்வேறு பகுதிகள் பாண்டியர்களின் கட்டுப்பாட்டில் வந்தன. வடக்கில் தக்காண பீடபூமியின் சாளுக்கியர்களை தோற்கடித்த இராட்டுரகுடாசு அமைப்புகளால் தற்போது பாண்டியர்களுக்கு நெருக்கடி அதிகமானது. கங்கை மற்றும் சோழர்களின் துணையுடன் மூன்றாம் நந்திவர்மன் என்ற அரசனை பல்லவர்கள் தங்களுக்கு சாதகமாக பயன்படுத்திக் கொண்டு சுரீமாறாவை தெள்ளாறு போரில் தோற்கடித்தனர். பல்லவர்களின் பேரரசு வைகை ஆறு வரை மீண்டும் நீண்டது. பல்லவ அரசன் நரிபதுங்க என்பவரால் அரிசில் என்ற இடத்தில் பாண்டியர்கள் தோற்கடிக்கப்பட்டனர் . பல்லவர்களின் மேலாளுமையை பாண்டியர்கள் பிறகு ஏற்றுக் கொள்ள வேண்டியதாயிற்று.சோழர்கள்முதன்மைக் கட்டுரை: சோழர்பாண்டியர்கள் மற்றும் பல்லவர்களுக்கிடையே இருந்த சண்டையைப் பயன்படுத்திக் கொண்டு 850 ஆம் ஆண்டுகளில் விசயாலய சோழர் தஞ்சாவூரைக் கைப்பற்றி இடைக்கால சோழர் ஆட்சிக்கான அடித்தளத்தை அமைத்தார். இடைக்காலத்தில் சோழர் வம்சத்தை விசயாலய சோழர் நிறுவினார். அவரது மகன் முதலாம் ஆதித்யா சோழர்களின் ஆதிக்கத்தை விரிவுபடுத்துவதற்கான உதவிகளைச் செய்தார். 903 ஆம் ஆண்டில் பல்லவ பேரரசுக்குள் நுழைந்து பல்லவ அரசன் அபராசிதாவை போரில் கொன்றதன் மூலம் பல்லவர்களின் ஆட்சிக்கு முற்றுப்புள்ளி வைத்தார். முதலாம் பராந்தக சோழன் ஆற்றலில் பாண்டிய நாடு முழுவதும் சோழப் பேரரசு பரவியது. சோழப் பேரரசுக்குள் தங்களது பகுதிகளை விரிவாக்கம் செய்த இராட்டுராகுட்டா குழுக்களினால் தனது ஆட்சிக் காலத்தின் இறுதியில் முதலாம் பராந்தக சோழன் பாதிக்கப்பட்டார்.இராசேந்திர சோழரின் ஆட்சியில் சோழ பேரரசு1030).மன்னர்களின் முறையற்ற ஆட்சித் திறமை, அரண்மனைக் கிளர்ச்சி மற்றும் வாரிசுகளின் தகராறு ஆகியவை ஏற்பட்டு அடுத்து வந்த ஆண்டுகளில் சோழர்கள் தற்காலிகமாக வீழ்ச்சியடைந்தனர். பலமுறை முயற்சி செய்தும் பாண்டிய நாட்டை முழுவதுமாக வீழ்த்த முடியவில்லை. மேலும் வடக்கு பகுதியில் இராட்டுராகுடா குழுவினரும் மிகவும் வலிமை வாய்ந்த எதிரிகளாக இருந்தனர். எனினும், முதலாம் இராசராச சோழனுக்குப் பிறகு 985 ஆம் ஆண்டு சோழர் ஆட்சி மீண்டும் மலர்ந்தது. இராசராசன் மற்றும் அவரின் மகனான முதலாம் இராசேந்திர சோழன் காலத்தில் பொருளாதாரம் மற்றும் கலாச்சார ரீதியாக சோழர்கள் ஆசியாவில் கவனிக்கத்தக்க வீரர்களாக மாறினர். தெற்குப் பகுதியில் மாலத்தீவுகளில் இருந்து வடக்கில் வங்காளத்தில் உள்ள கங்கை ஆற்றங்கரைப் பகுதிகள் வரை சோழர்களின் ஆட்சிப் பகுதிகள் பரவி இருந்தன. தென்னிந்திய தீபகற்பம், இலங்கையுடன் இணைக்கப்பட்ட பகுதிகள் மற்றும் மாலத்தீவுகள் ஆகிய பகுதிகளில் இராசராச சோழன் வெற்றிக் கொண்டார். மலேய தீவுக்குழுமத்தில் இருந்த சுரீவிசயா பேரரசை தோற்கடித்து இராசேந்திர சோழன் சோழர்களின் ஆட்சியைப் பரப்பினார். பீகார் மற்றும் வங்காளப் பகுதியின் அரசனான மகிபாலா என்பவரை இவர் தோற்கடித்தார். வெற்றியைக் கொண்டாடும் விதமாக கங்கைகொண்ட சோழபுரம் (கங்கைப் பகுதியில் சோழர்கள் வெற்றி பெற்றதன் நினைவாக உருவாக்கப்பட்ட நகரம் ) என்ற புதிய தலைநகரத்தை உருவாக்கினார். சோழப் பேரரசு உயராற்றலில் இருந்த போது இலங்கையின் தெற்கு தீபகற்ப பகுதியிலிருந்து தங்களது பகுதிகளை வடக்கிலுள்ள கோதாவரி பகுதி வரை விரிவாக்கியது. இந்தியாவின் கிழக்கு கடற்கரையில் கங்கை ஆறு வரை நீண்டிருந்த பகுதிகளை சோழர்கள் அடக்கி ஆண்டனர். மலேய தீவுக்குழுமத்திலிருந்த சுரீவிசய பேரரசுக்குள் படையெடுத்து சோழப் பேரரசின் கடற்படை வீரர்கள் வெற்றி கண்டனர். சோழப் பேரரசின் இராணுவ வீரர்கள் தாய்லாந்து மற்றும் கம்போடியாவின் கெமர் பேரரசுகளிடம் நேரடியாக வரி வசூல் செய்தனர். இராசராசன் மற்றும் இராசேந்திர சோழன் போன்ற மன்னர்களின் ஆட்சிக் காலத்தில் சோழப் பேரரசு மிகவும் வளர்ச்சியடைந்தது. பேரரசை சுயமாக ஆட்சி செய்து கொள்ளும் பல உள்ளூர் பகுதிகளாகப் பிரித்தனர். அவற்றின் அலுவலர்கள் பொதுத் தேர்தல் மூலம் தேர்ந்தெடுக்கப்பட்டனர்.பெருவுடையார் ஆலயம்இந்த காலம் முழுவதும், சோழர்கள் ஆட்சியை இலங்கையிலிருந்து அகற்ற வேண்டும் என்பதற்காக தொடர்ந்து போராடும் சிங்களர்கள், தங்களது பாரம்பரியப் பகுதிகளின் சுயாட்சியை மீண்டும் பெற முயற்சித்துக் கொண்டிருந்த பாண்டிய மன்னர்கள், சோழப் பகுதிகளைக் கைப்பற்றுவதைக் குறிக்கோளாகக் கொண்டிருந்த மேற்கு தக்காணப் பகுதிகளைச் சேர்ந்த சாளுக்கியர்கள் ஆகியோரால் சோழர்களுக்கு தொடர்ந்து தொல்லை ஏற்பட்டது. சோழர்கள் தங்களின் எதிரிகளுடன் இந்த வரலாற்றுக் காலம் முழுவதும் தொடர்ச்சியாக சண்டையிட்டுக் கொண்டிருந்தனர். சாளுக்கியர்களும் சோழர்களும் தங்களது ஆற்றலில் சம அளவில் இருந்தனர். துங்கபத்ரா ஆற்றை எல்லையாகக் கொள்வதற்கு இரண்டு பேரரசுகளும் இரகசியமாய் ஒப்புக் கொண்டனர். வேங்கி பேரரசில் சோழர்களின் தலையீடு காரணமாக இரண்டு பேரரசுகளுக்கிடையே கருத்து வேறுபாடு அதிகரித்துக் கொண்டிருந்தது. சோழர்களும் சாளுக்கியர்களும் பலமுறை போரிட்டுக் கொண்டனர். இவர்களது போர் சில நேரங்களில் முடிவில்லாத இக்கட்டான நிலையில் இருந்துள்ளது.கோதாவரி ஆற்றின் தெற்கு கரையில் அமைந்துள்ள வேங்கி பகுதிகளைச் சுற்றியுள்ள கிழக்கு சாளுக்கியர்களுடனான சோழர்களின் திருமணம் மற்றும் அரசியல் உறவு இராசராசன் ஆட்சிக் காலத்தில் சோழர்கள் வேங்கி பேரரசுக்குள் நுழைந்ததிலிருந்து தொடங்கியது. வீரராஜேந்திர சோழனின் மகன் ஆதிராஜேந்திர சோழன் 1070 ஆம் ஆண்டு ஏற்பட்ட கலகத்தின் போது படுகொலை செய்யப்பட்டார். இவரைத் தொடர்ந்து சோழர்களின் ஆட்சிக்காக சாளுக்கிய சோழர் வம்சத்தைச் சேர்ந்த முதலாம் குலோத்துங்க சோழன் ஆட்சிப் பொறுப்பை ஏற்றார். குலோத்துங்கன் வேங்கி பேரரசின் அரசன் இராசராச நரேந்திராவின் மகனாவார். சாளுக்கிய சோழர் வம்சத்தில் முதலாம் குலோத்துங்க சோழன் மற்றும் விகுரம சோழன் போன்ற திறமை வாய்ந்த அரசர்கள் குறைவாகவே இருந்தனர். சோழ அரசர்கள் தங்கள் ஆற்றலை இழப்பது இந்த காலகட்டத்திலிருந்து தொடங்கியது. சிங்களர்கள் மீட்டெழுச்சி காரணமாக இலங்கையின் தீவுப் பகுதிகளில் சோழர்கள் தங்களது ஆற்றலை இழந்து வெளியேறினர். மேற்கு பகுதியின் சாளுக்கிய அரசனான ஆறாம் விகுரமாதிதியா என்பவரிடத்தில் வெங்கிப் பேரரசையும், கங்காவாதி (மைசூரின் தெற்கு மாவட்டங்கள்) பகுதிகளை சாளுக்கிய இராணுத்தைச் சேர்ந்த போசள விடுணுவருதனா என்பவரிடமும் 1118 ஆம் ஆண்டுகளில் தங்கள் ஆற்றலை சோழர்கள் இழந்தனர். பாண்டிய நாட்டுப் பகுதிகளைக் கட்டுப்படுத்துவதில் ஏற்பட்ட குறைபாடு காரணமாக பாண்டியர்களின் ஆட்சிப் பொறுப்பிற்கு பலர் உரிமைக் கோரினர். இதன் காரணமாக உள்நாட்டுப் போரில் உரிமை பெற்ற பதிலியாக சிங்களர்கள் மற்றும் சோழர்கள் கலந்துக் கொண்டனர். பாண்டியர்களின் ஆற்றலைக் கட்டுப்படுத்தி கட்டுப்பாட்டில் வைப்பதற்காக காஞ்சிபுரத்தில் நிரந்தரமாக ஒரு போசள் இராணுவம் சோழர்கள் வாழ்ந்த இறுதி நூற்றாண்டு வரை நிறுத்தி வைக்கப்பட்டிருந்தது. சோழ வம்சத்தின் கடைசி அரசானாக மூன்றாம் ராஜேந்திர சோழன் இருந்தார். காடவர் தலைவர் முதலாம் கோப்பெருஞ்சிங்கன் இராசேந்திராவை வெற்றிக் கொண்டு அவரை சிறையில் அடைத்தார். இராசேந்திராவின் ஆட்சி முடிவடைந்த காலத்தில் (1279) சோழர் பேரரசு முழுவதையும் பாண்டியர்கள் கைப்பற்றி தங்களது கட்டுப்பாட்டில் வைத்திருந்தனர்.பாண்டியர்களின் மறுமலர்ச்சிநூற்றாண்டுகள் வரை இருந்த பல்லவர்கள் மற்றும் சோழர்களின் ஆதிக்கம் சடாவர்மன் சுந்தர பாண்டியன் என்ற பாண்டிய மன்னனால் மாற்றப்பட்டு, 1251 ஆம் ஆண்டு முதல் பாண்டியர்களின் ஆட்சி மீண்டும் மலர்ந்தது. கோதாவரி ஆற்றின் கரைகளிலிருந்த தெலுங்கு பேசும் நாடுகள் முதல் இலங்கையின் வடக்குப் பகுதியின் பாதியளவு வரை பாண்டியர்கள் ஆதிக்கத்தில் வந்தது. 1308 ஆம் ஆண்டில் முதலாம் மறவர்மன் குலசேகர பாண்டியன் இறந்த பிறகு ஆட்சிப் பொறுப்பை யார் ஏற்பது என்று அவரின் மகன்களுக்கிடையே போட்டி ஏற்பட்டது. சட்டப்படி வாரிசான சுந்தர பாண்டியன் மற்றும் சட்டப்படி வாரிசல்லாத வீர பாண்டியன் (அரசனால் பரிந்துரை செய்யப்பட்டவர்) ஆகியோர் ஆட்சிப் பொறுப்பிற்காக சண்டையிட்டுக் கொண்டனர். பின்னாளில் தில்லி சுல்தானகத்தின் படையெடுப்பு காரணமாக மதுரை தில்லி சுல்தானகத்தின் ஆட்சி அதிகாரத்திற்கு மாறியது (சுந்தர பாண்டியனின் வெற்றிக் காலங்களில் பாதுகாப்பு அரணாக மதுரை இருந்தது).தில்லி சுல்தானகம்முதன்மைக் கட்டுரை: மதுரை சுல்தானகம்தில்லி சுல்தானகத்தின் அலாவுதீன் கில்ஜி என்பவரின் தளபதி மாலிக் காஃபூர் 1311 ஆம் ஆண்டு மதுரை மீது படையெடுத்து மதுரையைக் கைப்பற்றினார்.  திருநெல்வேலியைச் சுற்றியுள்ள சிறிய பகுதிகளை பாண்டியர்கள் மற்றும் அவர்களின் வழித்தோன்றல்கள் சிறிது காலம் ஆட்சி செய்தனர். குலசேகர பாண்டியனின் சேர இராணுவத் தளபதியான ரவிவர்மன் குலசேகரன் (1299–1314) பாண்டிய ஆட்சியை தனது உரிமையாக்கிக் கொண்டான். நாட்டின் உறுதியற்ற நிலையைப் பயன்படுத்திக் கொண்டு தென் தமிழகம் முழுவதையும் படையெடுத்து கன்னியாகுமரி முதல் காஞ்சிபுரம் வரையிலான பகுதிகள் அனைத்தையும் சேர பேரரசின் கீழ் இரவிவர்மன் குலசேகரன் கொண்டு வந்தார். சென்னையின் புறநகர் பகுதியான பூந்தமல்லி என்ற இடத்தில் இவர் பற்றிய கல்வெட்டு கண்டு எடுக்கப்பட்டது.விஜயநகரம் மற்றும் நாயக்கர் காலம் (பொ.ஊ. 1300–1650)முதன்மைக் கட்டுரைகள்: விஜயநகரப் பேரரசு, மதுரை நாயக்கர்கள், மற்றும் தஞ்சை நாயக்கர்கள்நாயக்கர் மன்னரால் சீர்செய்யப்பட்ட தென்னிந்தியாவின் மதுரை நகரில் உள்ள மீனாட்சி ஆலயம்.பதினான்காம் நூற்றாண்டில் தில்லி சுல்தானகத்தின் பற்றுதல் இந்துக்களிடையே பகையுணர்வை ஏற்படுத்தியது. இதன் காரணமாக இந்துக்கள் ஒன்றாக இணைந்து விஜயநகரப் பேரரசு என்ற புதிய பேரரசை உருவாக்கினர். கர்நாடகத்தின் விஜயநகரம் என்ற நகரத்தை மையமாகக் கொண்டு இந்துக்களுக்கான விசயநகரப் பேரரசை ஹரிஹரா மற்றும் புக்கா ஆகிய இருவரும் நிறுவினர். புக்காவின் ஆட்சியில் விஜயநகரப் பேரரசு வளம் பெற்று தெற்குப் பகுதி முழுவதும் பரவியது. தென்னிந்தியாவின் பல பேரரசுகளை புக்கா மற்றும் அவரது மகன் கம்பனா கைப்பற்றினர். கில்ஜி இராணுவத்தின் மிஞ்சிய வீரர்களை கொண்டு நிறுவப்பட்டிருந்த மதுரை சுலதானகத்தை 1371 ஆம் ஆண்டு விஜயநகரப் பேரரசு தோற்கடித்தது. தென்னிந்தியாவின் பகுதிகள் முழுவதையும் இந்த பேரரசு இறுதியாக கைப்பற்றியது. நாயக்கர் என்ற பதவியில் உள்ளூர் ஆளுநர்களை நியமித்து பேரரசின் பல்வேறு பகுதிகளை ஆட்சிச் செய்யுமாறு விஜயநகரப் பேரரசு ஏற்பாடு செய்தது.தள்ளிக்கோட்டைப் போரின் போது தக்காண சுல்தான்களால் 1564 ஆம் ஆண்டு விஜயநகரப் பேரரசு தோற்கடிக்கப்பட்டது.[68] உள்ளூர் நாயக்கர் ஆளுநர்கள் விஜயநகரப் பேரரசின் ஆட்சிக்கு விடுதலை அறிவித்து தங்களது ஆட்சியைத் தொடங்கினர். மதுரை நாயக்கர்கள் மற்றும் தஞ்சாவூர் நாயக்கர்கள் பிரிவினர் நாயக்கர்களில் மிகவும் பிரபலமானவர்கள். தஞ்சாவூர் நாயக்கர்களின் ரகுநாத நாயக்கர் (1600–1645) நாயக்கர்களில் மிகவும் சிறப்பானவராக இருந்தார். வணிகம் செய்வதை ஊக்குவிக்கும் எண்ணத்தில் சலுகைகளை வழங்கி தரங்கம்பாடி என்ற இடத்தில் வணிக மையம் ஒன்றை 1620 ஆம் ஆண்டு ரகுநாத நாயக்கர் அமைத்தார். எதிர்காலத்தில் ஐரோப்பியர்கள் நமது நாட்டின் வளங்கள் மீது பற்றுக் கொள்வதற்கு இந்த வணிக மையம் அடித்தளமாக அமைந்தது. டச்சுக்காரர்களின் வெற்றி ஆங்கிலேயர்களை தஞ்சாவூர் பகுதியில் வணிகம் செய்ய ஊக்கமளித்தது. எதிர்விளைவு ஏற்படுவதற்கான காரணமாக இது அமைந்தது. தஞ்சாவூர் நாயக்கர்களின் கடைசி அரசனாக விசய ராகவா (1631–1675) இருந்தார். நாட்டில் இருந்த பல்வேறு பழையக் கோவில்களை புதுப்பித்து நாயக்கர்கள் மீண்டும் கட்டினர். அவர்களது பங்களிப்புகளை நாட்டின் பல இடங்களில் இன்றும் காணலாம். பழைய கோவில்களுக்கு பெரிய தூண்களைக் கொண்டு மண்டபங்கள், நீளமான முகப்பு கோபுரங்கள் போன்றவற்றை அமைத்து தங்கள் காலத்தின் சமய கட்டமைப்புகளை நாயக்கர்கள் விரிவாக்கம் செய்துள்ளனர்.மதுரையை ஆட்சி செய்த நாயக்கர்களில் திருமலை நாயக்கர் மிகவும் பிரபலமானவர். கலை மற்றும் கட்டடக்கலைக்கு பாதுகாப்பு அளித்து மதுரையைச் சுற்றி இருந்த பழையச் சின்னங்களை புதிய கட்டமைப்புகளுடன் திருமலை நாயக்கர் விரிவாக்கம் செய்தார். 1659 ஆம் ஆண்டு திருமலை நாயக்கரின் மறைவுக்கு பின்பு மதுரை நாயக்கரின் பேரரசு முடிவுக்கு வர ஆரம்பித்தது. இவருக்கு பிந்தைய அரசர்கள் பலம்குன்றிய விதத்தில் இருந்ததால் மதுரை மீதான படையெடுப்பு மீண்டும் துவங்கியது. மைசூரின் சிக்க தேவ ராயர் மற்றும் இசுலாமிய அரசர்கள் செய்தது போல மராத்தா பேரரசின் சிறந்த மன்னரான சிவாஜி போஸ்லேவும் தெற்கு நோக்கி படையெடுத்தார். இதன் காரணமாக தெற்கு பகுதிகளில் கலவரம் மற்றும் நிலையற்ற தன்மை நிலவியது. உள்ளூர் ஆட்சியாளராக இருந்த இராணி மங்கம்மாள் இந்த படையெடுப்புகளை துணிவுடன் தடைச் செய்தார்.நிசாம்கள் மற்றும் நவாப்களின் ஆட்சிவிஜயநகரப் பேரரசின் ஆட்சிக் காலத்தில் ஐரோப்பியர்கள் தமிழ்நாட்டில் குடியேறத் தொடங்கினர். செஞ்சி மற்றும் பழவேற்காடு அருகில் இருக்கும் கோரமண்டல கடற்கரை பகுதியில் வணிகம் செய்வதற்கான வணிக நிலையங்களை டச்சுக்காரர்கள் 1605 ஆம் ஆண்டு நிறுவினர். பழவேற்காட்டின் வடக்கு பகுதியைச் சுற்றியுள்ள 35 மைல்கள் (56 km) ஆறுமுகன் (துர்க்கராஜ்பட்ணம்) கிராமப் பகுதிகளில் கிழக்கிந்திய கம்பனி ஒரு 'தொழிற்சாலையை' (சேமிப்புக்கிடங்கு) 1626 ஆம் ஆண்டு நிறுவியது. கம்பனி நிருவாகத்தின் அலுவலர்களில் ஒருவரான ஃப்ரான்சிஸ் டே  என்பவர், வந்தவாசி பகுதியின் நாயக்கரான தர்மலா வேங்கடாதிரி நாயக்கர் என்பவரிடம் இருந்து மதராஸ்பட்டணம் என்ற மூன்று-மைல் (5 கிமீ) இடம் கொண்ட மீன்பிடி கிராமத்தை 1963 ஆம் ஆண்டில் தனது உரிமையாக்கிக் கொண்டார். மணற் சிறுதட்டுகளைக் கொண்டு சுமார் ஐந்து சதுர கிலோமீட்டர் பரப்பில் புனித ஜார்ஜ் கோட்டை மற்றும் அரண்மனையை கிழக்கிந்திய கம்பனி உருவாக்கியது. இது தான் மதராஸ் நகரத்தின் ஆரம்பமாகும். வேலூர் கோட்டை மற்றும் சந்திரகிரியைச் சார்ந்து பேடா வெங்கட ராயன் என்ற விஜயநகர அரசன் (அரவிடு மரபு) கோரமண்டலக் கடற்கரையை ஆட்சி செய்து கொண்டிருந்தார். இவரின் ஒப்புதலுடன் இந்த சிறிய நிலப்பகுதியில் தனியுரிமையுடன் வியாபரம் செய்ய ஆங்கிலேயர் ஆரம்பித்தனர்.பீசப்பூர் (Bijapur) இராணுவத்தின் ஒரு பகுதியினர் விஜயராகவா என்பவருக்கு உதவி செய்வதற்காக தஞ்சாவூர் பகுதிக்கு வந்து மதுரை நாயக்கரிடமிருந்து வல்லம் என்ற பகுதியை 1675 ஆம் ஆண்டு கைப்பற்றினர். தஞ்சாவூர் பேரரசு முழுவதும் தங்களது ஆட்சியை நிலைநிறுத்த விஜயராகாவா மற்றும் இகோஜி  ஆகியோரை பீசப்பூர் இராணுவத்தினர் கொலைச் செய்தனர். இவ்வாறாக தஞ்சாவூரில் மராத்தா ஆட்சி தொடங்கியது. இகோஜிக்குப் பிறகு அவரின் மூன்று மகன்களான சாஜி , முதலாம் சரபோஜி, முதலாம் துலஜா  என்கிற  துக்கோஜி தஞ்சாவூரை ஆட்சி செய்தனர். மராத்திய ஆட்சியாளர்களில் இரண்டாம் சரபோஜி (1798–1832) மிகவும் சிறப்பானவர். கலை மீது கொண்ட நாட்டம் காரணமாக தனது வாழ்க்கையை அர்ப்பணம் செய்தார். கற்றுக் கொடுத்தலில் முதன்மையாக தஞ்சாவூர் மாறியது. கலை மற்றும் இலக்கியத்திற்கு பாதுகாப்பு அளித்து சரஸ்வதி மஹால் நூலகத்தை தனது இடத்தில் சரபோஜி நிறுவினார். வடக்குப் பகுதியிலிருந்து வந்த இசுலாமியர்களின் படையெடுப்பு தக்காணபீடபூமியின் மக்கள் மற்றும் ஆந்திர நாடுகளைச் சேர்ந்த இந்து மக்களை நாயக்கர் மற்றும் மராத்தா அரசர்களின் பாதுகாப்பில் இருக்குமாறு செய்தது. கர்நாடக இசையின் மும்மூர்த்திகளுடன் பிரபல கர்நாடக இசை அமைப்பாளாரான தியாகராஜா (1767–1847) இந்தக் காலகட்டங்களில் தஞ்சாவூர் மாவட்டத்தில் இருந்தனர்.18 ஆம் நூற்றாண்டின் சென்னை புனித ஜார்ஜ் கோட்டையின் மாதிரிச் சித்திரம்.முகலாய அரசர் ஔரங்கசீப் ஆட்சிக் காலம் 1707 ஆம் ஆண்டு முடிவடைந்த பிறகு வந்த போர்கள் பலவற்றை இவரது ஆட்சிக் கலைத்தது. மேலும் இவர்களது பேரரசில் அடிமையாக இருந்த பலரும் தங்கள் சுதந்திரத்தை வலியுறுத்தினர். தமிழ்நாட்டின் தெற்கு மாவட்டங்களை நிர்வகிக்கும் பொறுப்பு பல நூறு பாளையக்காரர் அல்லது பொலிகர் என்பவர்களிடம் அளிக்கப்பட்டது. இவர்கள் குறிபிட்ட கிராமங்களை ஆட்சி செய்தனர். இந்த உள்ளூர் தலைவர்கள் தங்கள் பகுதிகளில் அடிக்கடி போரிட்டுக் கொண்டனர். இந்த நிலை தமிழ்நாடு மற்றும் தென்னிந்தியாவின் பகுதிகளில் குழப்பத்தையும் கலவரத்தையும் ஏற்படுத்தியது. இந்த குழப்பமான நிலையை தங்களுக்கு சாதகமாக பயன்படுத்திக் கொண்டு ஐரோப்பிய வணிகர்கள் வணிகம் செய்யத் தொடங்கினர்.ஐரோப்பியர்களின் குடியேற்றம் (பொ.ஊ. 1750–1850)முதன்மைக் கட்டுரை: பிரித்தானிய கிழக்கிந்திய நிறுவனம்ஆங்கிலோ-பிரான்சு சண்டைகள்முகமது அலி கான் வாலாசா, கர்னாடிக்கின் நவாப் (1717–1795)பிரான்சுக்காரர்கள் இந்தியாவிற்கு புதியவர்களாக வந்தவர்கள். பிரான்சு கிழக்கிந்திய கம்பனி 1664 ஆம் ஆண்டு உருவாக்கப்பட்டு, இந்தியாவில் தாங்கள் வணிகம் செய்வதற்கான அனுமதியை ஔரங்கசீப்பிடமிருந்து பிரான்சு அதிகாரிகள் 1666 ஆம் ஆண்டு பெற்றனர். கோரமண்டல கடற்கரைப் பகுதியில் உள்ள பாண்டிச்சேரியில் பிரான்சுக்காரர்கள் தங்கள் வணிக நிலையங்களை அமைத்தனர். 1739 ஆம் ஆண்டு காரைக்கால் பகுதியை கைப்பற்றியதன் மூலம் ஜோசப் ஃப்ரான்கோஸ் டூப்லெக்ஸ் பாண்டிச்சேரியின் ஆளுநராக நியமிக்கப்பட்டார். ஐரோப்பாவில் ஆஸ்திரிய உரிமைக்கான போர் 1740 ஆம் ஆண்டு தொடங்கியது. இதன் விளைவாக இந்தியாவில் இருந்த ஆங்கிலேயர் மற்றும் பிரான்சு வீரர்களுக்கு இடையே சண்டை மூண்டது. கோரமண்டல கடற்கரைப் பகுதியில் இரண்டு நாட்டின் கடற்படைகளும் பல்வேறு சண்டைகளில் ஈடுபட்டனர். லா போர்டோனைஸ்  தலைமையில் வந்த பிரான்சு படையினர் சென்னையில் உள்ள புனித ஜார்ஜ் கோட்டையை 1746 ஆம் ஆண்டு தாக்கி தங்கள் வசமாக்கிக் கொண்டனர். இந்த போரில் சிறைச் சாலையில் அடைக்கப்பட்டவர்களில் ராபர்ட் க்ளைவ் என்பவரும் ஒருவர். ஐரோப்பாவில் நடைபெற்ற போர் 1748 ஆம் ஆண்டு முடிவடைந்தது. ஆக்ஸ்-லா-சாப்பள் அமைதி  உடன்படிக்கையின் படி மதராஸ் ஆங்கிலேயரிடம் ஒப்படைக்கப்பட்டது.ஆங்கிலேயருக்கும் பிரான்சுக்காரர்களுக்கும் இடையே இருந்த இராணுவச் சண்டை முடிவுற்று அரசியல் ரீதியான சண்டைகள் தொடங்கியது. பிரான்சுக்காரரிடம் மிகவும் பற்றுதலுடன் இருந்த கர்நாடகத்தின் நவாப் மற்றும் ஐதராபாத் நிசாம் ஆகிய இரண்டு பதவிகளும் ஆட்சியாளர்களால் பறிக்கப்பட்டது. டூப்லேக்ஸின் ஆதரவுடன் சந்தா சாகிப் கர்நாடகத்தின் நவாப் பொறுப்பேற்றார். இந்தப் பகுதியை முதலில் ஆட்சி செய்த முகம்மது அலி கான் வாலாஜா என்பவருக்கு ஆங்கிலேயர் ஆதரவு கொடுத்தனர். ஆற்காடு பகுதியில் இருந்த சந்தா சாகிப்பின் கோட்டையை தாக்குதல் செய்து ஆட்சிப் பொறுப்பை எடுத்துக் கொள்வதற்காக 1751 ஆம் ஆண்டு க்ளைவ் முகம்மது அலிக்கு உதவி செய்தார். க்ளைவ்வை ஆற்காடு பகுதியிலிருந்து வெளியேற்றும் சந்தா சாகிப்பின் முயற்சிக்கு பிரான்சுக்காரர்கள் உதவி செய்தனர். பிரான்சுக்காரகளுடன் ஆற்காடு இராணுவத்தினரும் இணைந்து போரிட்ட போதிலும் ஆங்கிலேயர்களின் தாக்குதலை எதிர்கொள்ள முடியாமல் தோல்வி அடைந்தனர். பாரிஸ் ஒப்பந்தம் (1763) படி கர்நாடகத்தின் நவாப்பாக முகம்மது அலி முறைப்படி அறிவிக்கப்பட்டார். இந்த செயல்களின் விளைவாக 1765 ஆம் ஆண்டு முதல் ஆங்கிலேயர்களின் ஆதிக்கம் அதிகமாக இருந்தது. தென்னிந்தியாவில் ஆங்கிலேயர் ஆதிக்கத்தை அங்கீகரிக்கும் விதமாக டெல்லி பேரரசு தீர்ப்பாணை ஒன்றை வெளியிட்டது.ஆங்கிலேய அரசாங்கத்தின் ஆதிக்கம்சென்னை மாகாணம், 1909கம்பனி ஆட்சி நிர்வாகம் அதிகரித்துக் கொண்டிருந்த நிலையிலும் தங்களுக்கு எதிரான நடவடிக்கைகளில் ஈடுபடும் பகுதிகளில் தங்கள் கருத்தை எடுத்துரைக்க இயலாத காரணத்தினால், தாங்கள் கைப்பற்றிய பகுதிகளில் சரிவர ஆட்சி செய்ய இயலாத நிலைக்கு கம்பனி ஆட்சியாளர்கள் ஒவ்வொரு நாளும் தள்ளப்பட்டனர். ஆங்கிலேய பாரளுமன்றத்தைச் சேர்ந்த உறுப்பினர்களின் எண்ணங்கள் கம்பனி ஆட்சியை ஆங்கிலேய அரசாங்கமே மேற்கொள்ளும் நிலையை வலியுறுத்தியது. கம்பனியின் நிதி நிலைமையும் மோசமாக இருந்தது. நிதிக்காக நாடாளுமன்றத்தில் விண்ணப்பமும் செய்திருந்தனர். இந்த நிலையைப் பயன்படுத்திக் கொண்டு, ஆங்கிலேய நாடாளுமன்றம் சீரமைப்பு சட்டம் (கிழக்கிந்திய கம்பனி சட்டம் என்றும் அறியப்படும்) என்ற சட்டத்தை 1773 ஆம் ஆண்டு இயற்றியது.  கம்பனி நிர்வாகத்தை நிர்வகிப்பதற்கான விதிமுறைகளை தளர்த்தி ஆளுநர் பதவியை உருவாக்குவது போன்றவை இந்த சட்டத்தில் இடம்பெற்றிருந்தன. இவ்வாறாக வாரென் காசுடிங்ஸ் (Warren Hastings) முதல் ஆளுநராக நியமிக்கப்பட்டார். 1784 ஆம் ஆண்டின் பிட்ஸ் இந்தியா சட்டம் கம்பனி நிர்வாகத்தை ஆங்கிலேய அரசாங்கத்தின் துணை நிலையாக மாற்றியது.ஆங்கிலேயர் ஆதிக்க நிலப்பகுதிகளில் வேகமான வளர்ச்சியும் விரிவாக்கமும் அடுத்த சில பத்தாண்டுகளில் இருந்தது. 1766 முதல் 1799 ஆம் ஆண்டு வரை நடைபெற்ற ஆங்கிலேய-மைசூர் போர்கள் மற்றும் 1772 முதல் 1818 ஆம் ஆண்டு வரை நடைபெற்ற ஆங்கிலேய-மராத்திப் போர்கள் இந்தியாவின் பல்வேறு பகுதிகளை கம்பனி ஆட்சியின் கட்டுப்பாட்டில் கொண்டுவந்தது.  வரிவசூல் செய்யும் முறையில் கம்பனி அதிகாரிகளுடன் மதுரை பேரரசைச் சேர்ந்த பாளையக்காரர்களின் தலைவர்களுக்கு ஏற்பட்ட சிக்கல் சச்சரவாக மாறியது. பாளையக்காரர்கள் தங்கள் பகுதியே தாங்களே நிர்வகிக்கும் அதிகாரம் பெற்றிருந்தனர். இது ஆங்கிலேயர்கள் ஆதிக்கம் செலுத்துவதற்கு எதிரான முதல் எதிர்ப்பாக அமைந்தது. அதற்கான முதல் குரல் திருநெல்வேலி சீமையின் நெற்க்கட்டான் செவல் பாளையத்திலிருந்து மன்னர் பூலித்தேவர் மூலமாக எழுந்தது. 1755 முதல் 1767 வரை சுமார் 12 ஆண்டுகள் தொடர்ந்த பல்வேறு இடங்களில் நடைபெற்ற போர்கள் பூலிக்தேவனின் மறைவால் முடிவுக்கு வந்தது. திருநெல்வேலி மாவட்டத்தைச் சேர்ந்த பாளையக்காரர் தலைவரான கட்டபொம்மன் கம்பனி நிருவாகத்தினரின் வரி வசூலிக்கும் முறைக்கு எதிராக 1790 ஆம் ஆண்டு கலகம் செய்தார். முதல் பாளையக்காரர் போரின் போது (1799–1802) கட்டபொம்மன் கைது செய்யப்பட்டு 1799 ஆம் ஆண்டு தூக்கிலிடப்பட்டார். ஒரு வருடங்கள் கழித்து இரண்டாம் பாளையக்காரர் போர் தீரன் சின்னமலை என்பவரால் நடத்தப்பட்டது. திப்புசுல்தான் பேரரசுக்கு பிறகு ஆங்கிலேயருக்கு எதிராக நடைபெற்ற மூன்று போரிகளில் வெற்றி பெற்ற தீரன் சின்னமலை மற்றும் அவரது இரண்டு சகோதரர்கள் சட்டவிரோதமாக தூக்கிலிடப்பட்டனர். ஆங்கிலேயருக்கு எதிராக நடைபெற்ற போரில் உயிரிழந்த இறுதி தமிழ் மன்னர் தீரன் சின்னமலை ஆவார். பல்வேறு இயக்கங்களை நடத்தி இந்த போரட்டங்களை கம்பனி ஆட்சியாளர்கள் தடைச் செய்தனர். தமிழ்நாட்டின் பெரும்பாலான பகுதிகளைத் தங்களது முழுமையான கட்டுப்பாட்டில் வைத்துக் கொள்ள பாளையக்காரர் போர் முடிவுகள் ஆங்கிலேயருக்கு உதவியது.1798 ஆம் ஆண்டு லார்ட் வெல்சுலே (Lord Wellesley) என்பவர் ஆளுநராக பொறுப்பேற்றார். பின்வந்த ஆறு ஆண்டுகளில் அதிகமான வெற்றிகளைப் பெற்று கம்பனி ஆதிக்கத்தின் அதிகார எல்லைகளை இரண்டு மடங்காக உயர்த்தினார். பிரெஞ்சுக்காரர்கள் இந்தியாவில் மீண்டும் அதிகார உரிமை பெறுவதை தடை செய்தார். தக்காண பீடபூமி மற்றும் கர்நாடகத்தில் ஆட்சியில் இருந்த பலரை அழித்தார். முகலாய பேரரசை கம்பனி பாதுகாப்பின் கீழ் கொண்டு வந்து தஞ்சாவூரின் முகலாய மன்னரான சரபோஜியை கட்டாயப்படுத்தி உடன்படிக்கையின் கீழ் ஆட்சி செய்யும் நிலைக்கு கொண்டு வந்தார். மதராஸ் மாகாணம் நிறுவப்பட்டு கம்பனி ஆட்சியின் கீழுள்ள பகுதிகள் சிறப்பாக நிர்வகிக்கப்பட்டது. ஆங்கிலேயர்களின் நேரடி நிருவாகம் மக்களிடையே சினத்தை ஏற்படுத்தியது. மதராஸ் மாகாணத்தின் ஆளுநராக இருந்த வில்லியம் பெண்டிக் பிரபு உள்ளூர் வீரர்கள் தங்களது சமய குறிகளை (விபூதி, திலகம் போன்றவை) செய்து கொள்ளக் கூடாது என்று ஆணையிட்டதைத் தொடர்ந்து வேலூர் பாசறையைச் (cantonment) சேர்ந்த வீரர்கள் 1806 ஆம் ஆண்டில் கலகம் செய்தனர். கிறித்துவ மதத்திற்கு மாறுவதற்கு இந்தச் சட்டம் தங்களை கட்டாயப்படுத்துவதாக எதிர்ப்பு தெரிவித்து வீரர்கள் கலகம் செய்தனர். 114 ஆங்கிலேய அதிகாரிகள் கொலைச் செய்யப்பட்டும், பல நூறு கிளர்ச்சியாளர்கள் தூக்கிலிடப்பட்டும் இந்த கலகம் ஒடுக்கப்பட்டது. அவமதிப்பு காரணமாக பெண்டிக் பிரபு பதவியிலிருந்து நீக்கப்பட்டார்.கம்பனி ஆட்சியின் முடிவுகம்பனி ஆட்சிப் பகுதிகளின் பல்வேறு மாவட்டங்களில் நிலவிய அதிருப்தி நிலைமைகள் 1857 ஆம் ஆண்டின் சிப்பாய் போரில் வெடித்தது. கூட்டணி ஆட்சி நிலவில் இருந்த இந்தியாவின் பல்வேறு மாநிலங்களில் இந்தக் கலகம் மிகப்பெரிய விளைவை ஏற்படுத்தியது. தமிழ்நாடு அதிகமாக பாதிக்கப்படவில்லை. போரின் விளைவால் கம்பனி ஆட்சியை ரத்து செய்யும் 1858 ஆம் ஆண்டு சட்டத்தை ஆங்கிலேய அரசு அறிவித்து, அரசாங்கத்திடம் ஆட்சியை ஒப்படைத்தது.ஆங்கிலேயர் ஆட்சி (1850–1947)முதன்மைக் கட்டுரை: பிரித்தானியாவின் இந்தியப் பேரரசு1858 ஆம் ஆண்டு முதல் பிரத்தானிய அரசு இந்தியாவில் நேரடியாக ஆட்சி செய்வதாக கருதியது. ஆரம்ப காலங்களில் அரசாங்கம் தன்னிசையாக செயல்பட்டது. இந்தியர்களின் உணர்வுகளை முக்கியமானதாக ஆங்கிலேய அரசு கருதவில்லை. உள்ளூர் அரசாங்கத்தில் இந்தியர்கள் பங்குகொள்ள பிரித்தானியாவின் இந்திய பேரரசு அனுமதி வழங்க ஆரம்பித்தது. உள்ளூர் அரசாங்கத்தில் இந்திய மக்களுக்கு பங்கு அளிக்கும் தீர்மானத்தை வைசிராய் ரிப்பன் 1882 ஆம் ஆண்டு இயற்றினார். 1892 ஆம் ஆண்டின் இந்திய கவுன்சில் சட்டம் மற்றும் 1909 ஆம் ஆண்டின் மிண்டோ-மோர்லே சீர்திருத்தம் போன்ற சட்டமியற்றல்கள் மதராஸ் மாகாண சட்ட மேலவையை நிறுவுவதற்கு வழி செய்தது.[83] மகாத்மா காந்தி தலைமையில் தொடங்கிய ஒத்துழையாமை இயக்கம், இந்திய அரசுச் சட்டம் (மோண்டாகு-செம்ல்ஸ்ஃபோர்டு சீர்திருத்தம் என்றும் அறியப்படுகிறது) என்ற சட்டத்தை வெளியிடுவதற்கு காரணமாக அமைந்தது. உள்ளூர் தொகுதிகளுக்கான முதல் தேர்தல் 1921 ஆம் ஆண்டு நடைபெற்றது.சென்னை மாகாணப் பஞ்சம் (1877).நிவாரணம் வழங்குதல்.விளக்கப்பட்ட இலண்டன் செய்தியிலிருந்து (1877)கோடைக்காலத்தில் பருவமழை சரியாக பெய்யாதது மற்றும் ரியோத்வரி அமைப்பின் நிருவாகத்தில் கிடைத்த குறைவான வருமானம் ஆகியவற்றால் 1876–1877 ஆம் ஆண்டுகளில் சென்னை மாகாணத்தில் கடுமையான பஞ்சம் நிலவியது. அரசாங்கமும் பல தொண்டு நிறுவனங்களும் இணைந்து நகரம் அதன் புறநகர்ப் பகுதிகளில் பல நிவாரணப் பணிகளை மேற்கொண்டன. இந்தியாவிலிருந்த ஐரோப்பியர்களிடமிருந்தும் வெளிநாடுகளிலிருந்தும் பஞ்ச நிவாரண நிதி பெறப்பட்டது. பஞ்சத்தால் பாதிகப்பட்ட இடங்களில் போதுமான அளவு உதவிகளை செய்ய இயலாத ஆங்கிலேய அரசாங்கத்தை விமர்சனம் செய்து வில்லியம் டிக்பை போன்ற மனிதநேயமிக்கவர்கள் கண்டனம் செய்து எழுதினர். மூன்று முதல் ஐந்து மில்லியன் மக்கள் பாதிக்கப்பட்ட பிறகு, 1878 ஆம் ஆண்டில் பெய்த பருவமழையினால் பஞ்சம் முடிவுக்கு வந்தது.[84] பஞ்சத்தால் ஏற்பட்ட அழிவுகளின் விளைவால் பஞ்சக் குழுமம் என்ற குழுமம் 1880 ஆம் ஆண்டு அரசாங்கத்தால் நிறுவப்பட்டு பேரழிவு நிவாரணக் கொள்கைகள் வகுக்கப்பட்டது. பஞ்ச நிவாரண நிதியாக 1.5 மில்லியன் ரூபாயை அரசாங்கமும் ஒதுக்கியது. எதிர்காலத்தில் இவ்வாறு பஞ்சம் ஏற்பட்டால் அதன் விளைவுகளைக் குறைப்பதற்காக வாய்க்கால் கட்டுதல், தரை மற்றும் தொடர்வண்டி பாதைகளை மேம்படுத்துதல் போன்ற குடிமையியல் வேலைகளும் மேற்கொள்ளப்பட்டன.சுதந்திரப் போராட்டம்சுதந்திரம் பற்றிய எண்ணம் நாடு முழுவதும் மேலோங்கி இருந்தது. ஆங்கிலேயர்களின் காலணி ஆதிக்கத்தை எதிர்த்து சுதந்திரத்திற்காக பாடுபட தமிழ்நாட்டிலிருந்தும் பல சுதந்திரப் போராட்ட வீரர்கள் தாமாக முன்வந்தனர். 1904 ஆம் ஆண்டு ஈரோடு அருகே உள்ள ஒரு சிறிய கிராமத்தில் பிறந்த திருப்பூர் குமரன் இவர்களில் குறிப்பிடத்தக்கவர். ஆங்கிலேயருக்கு எதிராக கண்டனப் பேரணி நடத்திய போது குமரன் உயிரிழந்தார். பாண்டிச்சேரியில் இருந்த பிரெஞ்சு அரசு பிரித்தானிய காவல்துறையினரிடமிருந்து தப்பித்துக் கொள்ள முயன்ற சுதந்திரப் போராட்ட வீரர்களுக்கு இடமளித்து ஆதரவு தந்தது. பாண்டிச்சேரியில் வாழ்ந்தவர்களில் 1910 ஆம் ஆண்டு வாழ்ந்த அரவிந்தரும் ஒருவர். அரவிந்தர் காலத்தில் வாழ்ந்தவர்களில் கவிஞர் பாலசுப்ரமணிய பாரதியும் ஒருவர்.[86] புரட்சிகரமான பாடல்கள் பலவற்றை தமிழில் எழுதியதன் மூலம் சுதந்திரப் புரட்சியை பாரதி ஏற்படுத்தினார். இந்தியா என்ற இதழையும் பாண்டிச்சேரியிலிருந்து பாரதி பிரசுரம் செய்தார். தமிழ் புரட்சியாளர்களான வி.வி.எஸ்.அய்யர் மற்றும் வி.ஒ. சிதம்பரம் பிள்ளை ஆகியோருடன் அரவிந்தர் மற்றும் பாரதியார் நட்புடன் இருந்தனர். இந்தியாவில் ஆங்கிலேயர் ஆதிக்கத்தை எதிர்த்துப் போரிட நேதாஜி உருவாக்கிய இந்திய தேசிய இராணுவம் (INA), என்ற அமைப்பின் உறுப்பினர்களில் தமிழ்நாட்டிலிருந்து குறிப்பிட்ட உறுப்பினர்கள் இருந்தனர். INA வின் முக்கிய தலைவர்களில் தமிழ்நாட்டைச் சேர்ந்த லட்சுமி சேகள் என்பவரும் ஒருவர்.டாக்டர். டி.எம். நாயர் (Dr. T.M. Nair) மற்றும் ராவ் பகதூர் தியாகராய செட்டி ஆகியோர் 1916 ஆம் ஆண்டின் பிராமணன்-அல்ல அறிக்கை மூலம் திராவிட இயக்கத்திற்கான அடித்தளம் அமைத்தனர். இரண்டு வகையான இயக்கங்களை மையமாகக் கொண்டு 1920 ஆம் ஆண்டுகளில் தமிழ்நாட்டில் வட்டார அரசியல் உருவானது. 1921 ஆம் ஆண்டு நடைபெற்ற சட்டமன்ற தேர்தலில் வெற்றி பெற்ற நீதிக் கட்சி இவைகளில் ஒன்று. இந்திய சுதந்திர இயக்கத்தைப் பற்றிக் கருத்தில் கொள்ளாமல், சமூகத்தில் பின்தங்கிய வகுப்பினர் மீது இழைக்கப்படும் கொடுமைகளை நீதிக் கட்சி கருத்தில் கொண்டிருந்தது. மற்றொரு இயக்கம் ஈ.வி.இராமசாமி நாயக்கர் தலைமை வகித்த சமயமற்ற, பிராமணர் அல்லாதவர் சீர்திருத்த இயக்கம். 1935 ஆம் ஆண்டில் அனைத்திந்திய கூட்டரசு சட்டத்தை ஆங்கிலேய அரசு வெளியிட்டது முதல் தனியாட்சிக்கான முயற்சிகள் 1935 ஆம் ஆண்டிலிருந்து தொடங்கப்பட்டன. உள்ளூர் தேர்தல்கள் மீண்டும் நடத்தப்பட்டன. தமிழ்நாட்டில் நீதிக் கட்சியை தோற்கடித்து காங்கிரசு கட்சி ஆட்சியைப் பிடித்தது. பள்ளிகளில் இந்தி மொழியை கட்டாயமாக அறிமுகம் செய்யும் காங்கிரசு அரசின் முடிவை எதிர்த்து இராமசாமி நாயக்கர் மற்றும் சி.என்.அண்ணாதுரை இணைந்து 1938 ஆம் ஆண்டில் தங்களது போரட்டத்தைத் தொடங்கினர்.சுதந்திரத்திற்கு பிந்தைய காலம்மெதராஸ் என்ற பெயரிலிருந்து மாற்றம் செய்யப்பட்டு 1969 ஆம் ஆண்டு உருவாக்கப்பட்ட தமிழ்நாடு அரசியல் மாநிலம்.1947 ஆம் ஆண்டில் இந்தியாவிற்கு சுதந்திரம் பெற்ற பிறகு மேற்கொண்ட மாநிலங்கள் பங்கீடு தமிழ்நாட்டில் பெரிய அளவில் விளைவை ஏற்படுத்தவில்லை. மதத்தினரிடையே பிரிவினை வாத வன்முறைகள் ஏதுமில்லை. தமிழ்நாட்டில் அனைத்து சமயத்தினரும் ஒருவருக்கொருவர் மரியாதை மற்றும் அமைதியான இணக்க நிலையுடனும் இருந்தனர். மதராஸ் மாகாணத்தில் காங்கிரசு கட்சி முதல் அமைச்சரவையை அமைத்தது. சி.ராசகோபாலாச்சாரி (இராஜாஜி) முதல் முதலமைச்சராக பொறுப்பேற்றார். மெதராஸ் மாகணாம் என்பது மெதராஸ் மாநிலம் என்று மாற்றியமைக்கப்பட்டது. மெதராஸ் மாநிலத்தில் இருந்த தெலுங்கு பேசும் மக்களுக்காக ஆந்திர மாநிலம் உருவாக்கப்பட வேண்டும் என்று பொட்டி திருராமலு என்பவர் போரட்டம் செய்தார். இந்திய அரசாங்கம் மெதராஸ் மாநிலத்தைப் பிரிப்பது என்று முடிவு செய்தது.[91] ராயலசீமா மற்றும் அதைச் சுற்றிய ஆந்திரக் கடற்கரைப் பகுதிகள் ஆந்திரப் பிரதேசம் என்ற புதிய மாநிலமாக 1953 ஆம் ஆண்டு பிரிக்கப்பட்டது. பெல்லாரி மாவட்டம் மைசூர் மாநிலத்தின் ஒரு பகுதியாக மாறியது. 1956 ஆம் ஆண்டு தெற்கு கன்னடா மாவட்டம் மைசூருக்கு மாற்றப்பட்டது. மலபார் கடற்கரை மாவட்டங்கள் புதிதாக உருவாக்கபட்ட கேரள மாநிலத்தின் பகுதிகளுடன் இணைக்கப்பட்டு, மெதராஸ் மாநிலம் தற்போதைய வடிவத்தை எட்டியது. மெதராஸ் மாநிலம் தமிழ்நாடு (தமிழர்கள் வாழும் பகுதி) என்ற பெயருக்கு 1968 ஆம் ஆண்டில் மாற்றப்பட்டது.இலங்கையில் இனப் பிரிவுச் சார்ந்த சண்டை காரணமாக 1970 மற்றும் 1980 ஆம் ஆண்டுகளில் அதிகமான இலங்கை தமிழர்கள் தமிழ்நாட்டிற்கு தப்பி வந்தனர். தமிழ் அகதிகளின் அவலநிலை தமிழக அரசியல் கட்சிகளிடையே எழுச்சியுடன் கூடிய ஆதரவை உண்டாக்கியது. இலங்கை தமிழர்கள் நிலைக் குறித்து இலங்கை அரசிடம் பரிந்துரை செய்யுமாறு தமிழக அரசியல் கட்சிகள் இந்திய அரசாங்கத்திற்கு நெருக்கடி அளித்தன. தமிழீழ விடுதலைப் புலிகள் (எல்.டி.டி.ஈ) இயக்கத்தை இலங்கையில் கட்டுப்படுத்துவதற்காக இந்திய அமைதிப்படையை இலங்கைக்கு முன்னாள் பிரதம மந்திரி ராஜீவ் காந்தி அனுப்பினார். இதன் காரணமாக 1991 ஆம் ஆண்டு மே மாதம் 21 அன்று ராஜீவ் காந்தி இலங்கையைச் சேர்ந்த இயக்கத்தினரால் படுகொலைச் செய்யப்பட்டார். அது முதல் தமிழீழ விடுதலைப் புலிகள் (எல்.டி.டி.ஈ) இயக்கம் தமிழ்நாட்டில் தன் ஆதரவை இழந்தது.2004 ஆம் ஆண்டு இந்தியப் பெருங்கடல் பகுதிகளில் ஏற்பட்ட இந்தியப் பெருங்கடல் நிலநடுக்கம் தமிழ்நாட்டின் கிழக்கு கடற்கரைப் பகுதிகளை வெகுவாக பாதித்தது. இந்த பேரழிவில் தோராயமாக 8000 மக்கள் உயிரிழந்தனர். அதிக மக்கள் தொகை கொண்ட இந்திய மாநிலங்களில் ஆறாவது இடத்தில் உள்ள தமிழ்நாடு, பொருளாதாரத்தில் முன்னணியில் உள்ள மாநிலங்களில் 2005 ஆம் ஆண்டின் அறிக்கையின் படி ஏழாம் இடத்தில் இருந்தது. திறமை வாய்ந்த பணியாளர்களின் தேவை அதிகரிப்பு காரணமாக தமிழ்நாட்டில் கல்வி நிலையங்களின் எண்ணிக்கை வெகுவாக உயர்ந்துள்ளது. சாதி வாரியாக 69 விழுக்காடு இட ஒதுக்கீடு அளிக்கும் சட்டத்திற்கு தமிழ்நாட்டில் பரவலாக இருந்த உடன்பாடு செயல் காரணமாக மாநிலத்தின் கல்வி நிலையங்கள் மற்றும் வேலைவாய்ப்பு அனைத்திலும் பிற்படுத்தப்பட்ட வகுப்பினருக்கு 69 விழுக்காடு இட ஒதுக்கீடு அளிக்கப்பட்டுள்ளது. சாதி வாரியாக இட ஒதுக்கீடு அளிக்கும் சட்டத்திற்கு தமிழ்நாட்டில் பொதுமக்களிடம் பெரிய அளவில் ஆதரவு இருந்தது. இந்த சட்டத்தை நடைமுறைப்படுத்துவதற்கு எதிராக குறிப்பிடப்படும் படியான போராட்டங்கள் ஏதும் நடைபெறவில்லை.பிராந்திய அரசியலின் பரிணாம வளர்ச்சிசுதந்திரம் பெற்ற பிறகு தமிழ்நாட்டின் அரசியல் நிலைமை மூன்று விதமான நிலைகளை அடைந்துள்ளது. 1947 ஆம் ஆண்டுக்கு பிறகு இருந்த காங்கிரசு கட்சியின் செல்வாக்கு 1960 ஆம் ஆண்டில் திராவிட கட்சியின் கொள்கைகளால் மாறியது. 1990 ஆம் ஆண்டின் இறுதி வரை இந்த நிலை நீடித்திருந்தது. திராவிட அரசியல் கட்சிகளில் ஏற்பட்டுள்ள பிளவு காரணமாக மற்ற அரசியல் கட்சிகளுடன் ஒப்பந்தம் செய்து கூட்டணி அரசாங்கம் அமைக்கும் நிலையை தற்போது கொண்டிருக்கிறது.திராவிடர் கழகத்திலிருந்து பிரிந்து திராவிட முன்னேற்றக் கழகம் (DMK) என்ற கட்சியினை 1949 ஆம் ஆண்டு அண்ணாதுரை தொடங்கினார். தமிழ்நாட்டில் இந்திக் கலாச்சாரம் திணிக்கப்படுவதை எதிர்க்க முடிவு செய்து இந்தியாவின் தெற்கு பகுதியை திராவிடர்களுக்கு என்று தனியாக பிரிக்க வேண்டும் என்ற கோரிக்கையையும் திமுக விடுத்தது. திராவிட நாடு தனிப்பட்ட மாநிலமாக இருக்க வேண்டும் என்பது கோரிக்கையாக இருந்தது. திராவிட நாடு என்பது தமிழ்நாடு மற்றும் ஆந்திரா, கர்நாடாக மற்றும் கேரளாவின் பகுதிகளை உள்ளடக்கிய திராவிடர்களின் நாடு என்பதாகும். மதராஸ் மாகாணத்தில் இந்திய தேசிய காங்கிரசு கட்சிக்கு 1950 ஆம் ஆண்டு இறுதி வரை இருந்த ஈடுபாடு மற்றும் 1962 ஆம் ஆண்டில் இந்தியப் பகுதிகளில் சீனாவின் நுழைவு ஆகிய காரணங்கள் உடனடியாக திராவிட நாடு கோரும் கோரிக்கைக்கு இடையூறாக அமைந்தது. இந்திய அரசியலமைப்பில் 1963 ஆம் ஆண்டு மேற்கொள்ளப்பட்ட பதினாறாவது சட்டத் திருத்தம் பிரிவினை வாதக் கட்சிகள் தேர்தலில் போட்டியிடுவதை தடை செய்தது. இதன் காரணமாக திராவிடனுக்கு தனிப்பட்ட நாடு கோரிக்கையை திமுக முழுமையாக நிறுத்திவிட்டு இந்திய அரசியலமைப்பில் செயல்திறன் மிக்க சுயாட்சி கட்சியாக மாறுவதற்கான முயற்சிகளில் கவனம் செலுத்தியது.சுதந்திரப் போராட்டத்தில் ஈடுபட்டதால் கிடைத்த மக்கள் செல்வாக்கைப் பயன்படுத்தி சுதந்திரத்திற்கு பின்னர் அரசாங்கத்தை அமைத்த காங்கிரசு கட்சி 1967 ஆம் ஆண்டு வரை ஆட்சிப் பொறுப்பில் இருந்தது. மாநிலப் பள்ளிகளில் கட்டயாமாக இந்தி மொழியைக் கொண்டு வரும் மத்திய அரசாங்கத்தை எதிர்த்து 1965 மற்றும் 1968 ஆம் ஆண்டு நடத்திய போரட்டங்களுக்கு திமுக தலைமை தாங்கியது. வேலைவாய்ப்பு மற்றும் கல்வி நிலையங்களில் உடனடி செயலாக்கம் போன்றவை தமிழ்நாட்டில் முதன்மையாக மேற்கொள்ளப்பட வேண்டும் என்பது திராவிட இயக்கத்தின் கோரிக்கையாக இருந்தது. அண்ணாதுரை மற்றும் கருணாநிதி போன்ற திராவிட இயக்கத்தின் தலைவர்கள் தங்களிடமிருந்த எழுத்து திறமையைப் பயன்படுத்தி மேடை நாடகங்கள் மற்றும் திரைப்படங்கள் மூலமாக இயக்கத்தின் அரசியல் செய்திகளைப் பரப்பினர்.  தமிழ்நாட்டின் முதலமைச்சராக பின்னாளில் பதவியேற்ற எம்.ஜி இராமச்சந்திரன் என்பவரும் நாடகம் மற்றும் திரைப்பட நடிகராவார்.1967 ஆம் ஆண்டு நடைபெற்ற மாநிலத் தேர்தலில் திமுக வெற்றி பெற்றது. திமுக கழகம் இரண்டாக பிளவுபட்டு அனைத்திந்திய அண்ணா திராவிட முன்னேற்ற கழகம் (அஇஅதிமுக) என்ற கட்சியினை 1971 ஆம் ஆண்டு எம்.ஜி.ஆர் துவங்கினார். இன்று வரை திமுக மற்றும் அஇஅதிமுக இரண்டு கட்சிகளும் தமிழ்நாடு அரசியலில் ஆதிக்கம் செலுத்தி வருகிறது.  1977, 1980 மற்றும் 1984 ஆம் ஆண்டுகளில் நடைபெற்ற தேர்தல்களில் தொடர்ச்சியாக வெற்றி பெற்று அஇஅதிமுக கட்சியைச் சேர்ந்த எம்.ஜி.ஆர் மூன்று முறை தொடர்ச்சியாக மாநிலத்தில் ஆட்சி செய்தார். கட்சியினருக்கிடையே ஏற்பட்ட பல்வேறு பிரிவுகள் காரணமாக எம்.ஜி.ஆரின் இறப்பிற்கு பின்னர் அஇஅதிமுக பிளவுற்றது. முடிவில் ஜெ.ஜெயலலிதா அஇஅதிமுக கட்சியின் தலைமைப் பொறுப்பேற்றார்.1990 ஆம் ஆண்டின் பின்பகுதியில் பல்வேறு அரசியல் சமநிலை மாற்றங்கள் தமிழ்நாடு அரசியலில் நிலவின. இறுதியாக திமுக மற்றும் அஇஅதிமுக கட்சிகளுக்கு தமிழ்நாட்டு அரசியலில் இரட்டை முன்னுரிமை அளிக்கப்பட்டது. காங்கிரசு கட்சியில் 1996 ஆம் ஆண்டு தமிழ்நாட்டில் ஏற்பட்ட பிளவு தமிழ் மாநில காங்கிரசு என்ற கட்சி உருவாக காரணமானது. தமாகா கட்சி திமுக கட்சியுடன் கூட்டணியுடனும், திமுக கட்சியிலிருந்து பிரிந்த மற்றொரு கட்சியான மறுமலர்ச்சி திராவிட முன்னேற்ற கழகம் (மதிமுக) அஇஅதிமுக கட்சியுடனும் கூட்டணியுடன் இருந்தன. பல்வேறு சிறிய கட்சிகள் மக்களிடையே பிரபலமடையத் தொடங்கின. திமுக மற்றும் தமாகா கட்சி 1996 ஆம் ஆண்டு தேசிய நாடாளுமன்ற தேர்தலில் வைத்திருந்த கூட்டணியை முறியடிக்கும் விதத்தில் அஇஅதிமுக கட்சி பல்வேறு சிறிய கட்சிகளுடன் இணைந்து 'மிகப்பெரிய கூட்டணியை' உருவாக்கியது. தேர்தல் நேரத்தில் கூட்டணி அமைப்பதற்கான முதல் நிகழ்வாக இது இருந்தது. இன்றும் தமிழ்நாட்டில் தேர்தல் நடைபெறும் போது அரசியல் கட்சிகள் கூட்டணி அமைத்துக் கொள்கின்றன.காங்கிரசு கட்சியின் தேர்தல் செல்வாக்கு தேசிய அளவில் 1990 ஆம் ஆண்டு முதல் குறைய ஆரம்பித்தது. இதன் காரணமாக தமிழ்நாடு உள்ளிட பல மாநிலங்களில் காங்கிரசு கட்சி கூட்டணி வைத்துள்ளது. இதன் காரணமாக திராவிடக் கட்சிகள் மத்திய அரசாங்கத்தில் அங்கம் வகிக்கின்றன.சேர, சோழ, பாண்டிய மற்றும் பல்லவ பேரரசுகளே நான்கு பண்டைய பூர்வீக தமிழ் பேரரசுகளாக இருந்தன. இவர்கள் தனித்தன்மை வாய்ந்த கலாச்சாரம் மற்றும் மொழி ஆகியவற்றைக் கொண்டு இந்தப் பகுதியை ஆட்சி செய்தனர், இதனால் உலகில் அழியாமல் வழக்கத்திலிருந்த சில பழமையான இலக்கியங்களின் வளர்ச்சி சாத்தியமானது. இவர்கள் ரோமப் பேரரசுடன் அதிகப்படியான கடல்வழி வணிகத் தொடர்புகளைக் கொண்டிருந்தனர். இப்பகுதியின் தலைமைக்காக இந்த மூன்று வம்சத்தைச் சேர்ந்தவர்களும் ஒருவருக்கொருவர் தொடர்ச்சியாக போரிட்டுக் கொண்டனர். மூன்று பேரரசுகளும் பாரம்பரியமாக ஆட்சி செய்துவந்த இந்தப் பகுதியை மூன்றாம் நூற்றாண்டில் நுழைந்த களப்பிரர்கள் விரட்டியதால் இப்பகுதியின் பாரம்பரிய ஆட்சி வடிவம் மாறியது. பாண்டியர்கள் மற்றும் பல்லவர்கள் மீட்டெழுந்து களப்பிரர் ஆதிக்கத்தை முறியடித்து தங்களின் பாரம்பரிய பேரரசுகளை மீண்டும் நிலைநாட்டினர். வீழ்ந்திருந்த சோழர்கள் ஒன்பதாம் நூற்றாண்டில் பல்லவர்களையும் பாண்டியர்களையும் தோற்கடித்து, தங்களது பெரும் சக்தியாக எழுச்சியடைந்து கிட்டத்தட்ட தெற்கு தீபகற்பப் பகுதி முழுவதும் தங்கள் பேரரசை விரிவுபடுத்தினர். வங்காள விரிகுடா பகுதியில் சோழப் பேரரசு சுமார் 3,600,000 சதுர கி.மீ. அளவிற்குப் பரவி இருந்தது. தென்கிழக்கு ஆசியாவில் இருந்த சிரீ விசயா பேரரசு பகுதியையும் சோழரின் கடற்படை கட்டுப்பாட்டில் கொண்டிருந்தது.வடமேற்கு பகுதியிலிருந்து வந்த இசுலாமிய படைகளின் ஊடுருவல் காரணமாக இந்தியாவின் மற்ற பகுதிகளில் ஏற்பட்ட அரசியல் மாற்றங்கள் தமிழ்நாட்டின் வரலாற்றில் குறிப்பிடத்தக்க மாற்றம் ஏற்பட்டது. பதினான்காம் நூற்றாண்டில் பண்டைய மூன்று பேரரசுகளின் வீழ்ச்சி காரணமாக, தமிழ்நாடு விசயநகரப் பேரரசின் ஒரு அங்கமாக மாறியது. விசயநகரப் பேரரசின் கீழ் தெலுங்கு பேசும் நாயக்கர் ஆட்சியாளர்கள் தமிழ்ப் பகுதியை ஆட்சி செய்தனர். மராத்தியர்களின் குறுகிய கால வருகை தமிழ்ப் பகுதியில் ஐரோப்பிய வணிக நிறுவனங்களின் வருகைக்கு வழிவகுத்தது. பதினேழாம் நூற்றாண்டின் போது இவ்வாறு வணிகம் செய்ய வந்தவர்கள் இறுதியில் இந்தப் பகுதியின் பூர்வீக ஆட்சியாளர்களை தங்களின் கட்டுப்பாட்டின் கீழ்க் கொண்டுவந்தனர். தென்னிந்தியாவின் பல பகுதிகளை உள்ளடக்கிய சென்னை மாகாணம் பதினெட்டாம் நூற்றாண்டில் உருவாக்கப்பட்டது. இப்பகுதி பிரித்தானியக் கிழக்கிந்தியக் கம்பனியால் நேரடியாக ஆட்சி செய்யப்பட்டது. இந்தியாவின் சுதந்திரத்திற்குப் பிறகு மொழியியல் எல்லைகளை அடிப்படையாகக் கொண்டு தமிழ்நாடு மாநிலம் உருவாக்கப்பட்டது."},{"question":" Nahoana no nanomboka ny Revolisiona Indostrialy tao Angletera tamin'ny taonjato faha-18?","answer":"Nanomboka tany Angletera ny Revolisiona Indostrialy noho ny fitambaran'ny antony ara-tsosialy, ara-politika ary ara-jeografika."},{"question":"السؤال: من هي اول شهيدة فى الاسلام؟","answer":"الإجابة: سمية بنت خُبَّاط رضي الله عنها"},{"question":"Дидактика изилдейт: а) окутуунун методдорун жана принциптерин б) физикалык кубулуштарды в) жаныбарлар дүйнөсүн г) сандардын теориясын","answer":"Жооп: а) окутуунун методдорун жана принциптерин"},{"question":"ਆਦਮੀ ਡਾਕਟਰ ਕੋਲ ਗਿਆ। | ਇਸ ਦਾ ਕਾਰਨ ਕੀ ਸੀ? ਚੋਣ 1 : ਡਾਕਟਰ ਛੁੱਟੀ ਤੇ ਸੀ। ਚੋਣ 2 : ਆਦਮੀ ਬਿਮਾਰ ਮਹਿਸੂਸ ਕਰ ਰਿਹਾ ਸੀ। ","answer":"ਚੋਣ 2 : ਆਦਮੀ ਬਿਮਾਰ ਮਹਿਸੂਸ ਕਰ ਰਿਹਾ ਸੀ।"},{"question":"مؤسسه څه شی ده ؟","answer":"له یو پلان شوي مرستندوی تشکيل څخه عبارت ده چي اهدافو ته د رسيدو په موخه د افرادو رول ، دندي او اړيکي پکي واضح شوې وي ."},{"question":"Dans le Toronto Star, on raconte que, avant que la lettre incriminée ne soit envoyée aux autorités suisses, elle a fait plusieurs allers-retours entre le sergent d’état-major Fiegenwald et l’avocate du ministère de la Justice Kimberly Prost, ce qui a chaque fois eu pour effet de durcir le langage du ministère de la Justice.\\" En gardant à l'esprit le texte ci-dessus, considérez : \\"La langue était la même tout au long\\" Est-ce que c'est \\"vrai\\", \\"faux\\", ou \\"incertain\\" ?","answer":"La considération est fausse."},{"question":"Conas is féidir liom foghlaim conas bata pogo a úsáid?","answer":" Is féidir leat tosú ar go leor bealaí éagsúla. Is féidir leat an bata pogo a thógáil agus léim suas agus síos. Ansin is féidir leat cleachtadh a dhéanamh ar léim níos airde, níos tapúla, agus le rithimí éagsúla. Nó is féidir leat foghlaim le léim ar aghaidh. "},{"question":"Ṣe àpilẹ̀kọ àyọkà fún àkòrí yìí: Àwọn òṣèré tíátà Yorùbá sọ̀rọ̀ nípa Bàbá Sùwé tó di olóògbé.","answer":"Àwọn òṣèré tíátà Yorùbá ti sọ̀rọ̀ nípa ìhà tí wọ́n kọ sí àgbà òṣèré tó di olóògbé, Bàbá Sùwé. Lára àwọn òṣèré náà tó bá BBC Yorùbá sọ̀rọ̀ sọ pé ikú olóògbé ọ̀hún dun àwọn dénú, wọ́n sì sọ̀rọ̀ nípa ohun tí àwọn kò le gbàgbé nípa rẹ̀. Bólájí Amúsǎn, tí ọ̀pọ́ mọ̀ sí Mr Latin sọ pé bíi ẹ̀gbọ́n ni Bàbá Sùwé jẹ́ sí òun. Ó fi kun pé olóògbé náà tún jẹ́ ẹni tó máa ń kó àwọn èèyàn mọ́ra tó sì tún máa ń ṣe àwàdà púpọ̀. Arábìnrin Fausat Balógun ṣ'àlàyé fún BBC Yorùbá pé Bàbá Sùwé ló fún òun l'órúkọ “Madam Ṣajẹ” tí ọ̀pọ̀ àwọn olólùfẹ́ eré tíátà Yorùbá mọ òun sí lónìí. Bó tilẹ̀ jẹ́ pé ó ní òun ti ní orúkọ ṣáájú kí wọ́n tó pàdé, ṣùgbọ́n olóògbé náà ló jẹ́ kí òun máa jẹ́ orúkọ náà bẹ̀rẹ̀ l'áti inú eré “Ẹ̀rín Kẹ̀kẹ̀” tí wọ́n jọ ṣe l'ọ́dún 1996. Ní ti Oláníyì Àfọ̀njá tí ọ̀pọ̀ mọ̀ sí Sányẹ̀rì, ó ní Bàbá Sùwé kìí ṣe ẹni tó máa ń ta èèyàn nù, ó sì tún máa ń kó àwọn èèyàn mọ́ra. Yàtọ̀ sí àwọn èèyàn wònyí, Dẹ̀jọ Túńfúlù, Kámílù Kọ̀ǹpó àt'àwọn òṣèré míì náà tún sọ̀rọ̀ nípa irúfẹ́ ẹni tí Bàbá Sùwé jẹ́ sí àwọn ní ọjọ́ ayé rẹ̀."},{"question":"Midika inona ny loko fotsy amin'ny sainam-pirenena malagasy?","answer":"Ny loko fotsy amin'ny sainam-pirenena malagasy dia midika fahadiovana."},{"question":"ماذا كان يسمى أبو هريرة في الجاهلية ؟","answer":"عبد شمس"},{"question":"Which tree is traditionally associated with cemeteries?","answer":"Yew TreeThe yew tree may be the most well-known and recognizable cemetery tree in Europe.Yew trees are known for their ability to thrive in almost any soil condition and can withstand harsh weather. These attributes are why many yew trees have lived for thousands of years.Yew Tree Folklore & Religious ConnotationsYew trees have a rich history that’s rooted in Pagan and Christian storytelling.According to pagan lore, yew trees are sacred to Hecate, the Greek goddess of death, witchcraft, and necromancy. In myth, it’s said that the yew purifies the dead as they arrive in Hades, also known as the underworld. Britain’s Best Guides writer and Blue Badge Heart of England tour guide, Sean Callery, adds that Celtic druids also used yew trees in their death rituals."},{"question":"Motho wa go sa bone o bitšwa eng?","answer":"O bitšwa Sefofu"},{"question":"आ है भन मेरा भाइ हो । ","answer":"देउसीरे ।"},{"question":"17 жашында  2014- жылы Нобель сыйлыгынын эң жаш лауреаты ким болгон?","answer":"Малала Юсуфзай 17 жаш курагында Нобель сыйлыгынын лауреаты болгон."},{"question":"O ma waa ga o! Wọn tun ji agbẹ mi-in gbe n’Igangan","answer":"Lẹyin ọjọ mẹta ti wọn ji gbajumọ oniṣowo epo rọbi gbe niluu Idere nitosi Igboọra ni ipinlẹ Ọyọ ki wọn too pada yinbọn pa a, wọn tun ti ji ọkunrin agbẹ kan, Nosiru Aderoju, gbe niluu Igangan ni ipinlẹ yìí kan naa.Ta o ba gbagbe, lọsẹ to lọ lọhun-un ni wọn ji agbẹ kan tó n jẹ Oluwọle  Agboọla gbe ninu oko ẹ lọna Ibadan siluu Ọyọ.Ni nnkan bíi aago mẹjọ aabọ alẹ lawọn ajinigbe ọhun lọọ ka Alhaji Aderoju mọ itosí ile ẹ ti wọn sì gbé e bi igba ti aṣa ba gbe ọmọ adiẹ.Gẹgẹ b’ALAROYE ṣe gbọ, lasiko ti ọkunrin agbẹ náà n dari lọ sile lẹyin to kí irun aago mẹjọ alẹ tan lawọn amookunṣika ẹda naa lọọ da a lọna ti wọn si ji i gbe nitosi ilé ẹ lOke agbẹdẹ niluu Igangan.Nigba to n fidi iṣẹlẹ yii mulẹ, alaga ẹgbẹ idagbasoke ilu Igangan, Ọgbẹni Ọladokun Ọladiran sọ pe o jọ pé awọn obayejẹ ẹda naa ti n ṣọ Ọgbẹni Aderoju tipẹ, ti wọn sì n tẹle e kiri tẹlẹ ki wọn too papa ri i mu.Gẹgẹ bo ṣe sọ, “awọn eeyan ṣakiyesi awọn àjèjì kan bíi Fulani ni mọṣalaṣi to (Alhaji Aderoju) ti kirun lalẹ ana yẹn ṣugbọn wọn ko fura pe iṣẹ ibi ni won waa ṣe. O ṣe é ṣe kó jẹ pe awọn èèyàn yẹn ni wọn ṣọ ọ dé mọsalaṣi ki wọn tóo tun ti ibẹ tẹle e de ọna ile ẹ ti wọn ti jí i gbe.Agbẹnusọ fún ileeṣẹ ọlọpaa ipinlẹ Ọyọ SP Olugbenga Fadeyi fidi iṣẹlẹ yìí mulẹ, o ni awọn agbofinro ti bẹrẹ iṣẹ lati yọ ọkunrin agbẹ naa kuro nigbekun awọn ajinigbe ọhun ki wọn sì mú awọn afurasi ọdaran naa."},{"question":"Jawab soalan teka-teki berikut: Kering sebelum guna, basah semasa guna?","answer":"Jawapannya ialah uncang teh. "},{"question":"လူတွေက Dinosaur World မှာ ဘယ်လောက်ကြာကြာနေလဲ။","answer":"Dinosaur World (ဒိုင်နိုဆောကမ္ဘာ) သည် နေရာတော်တော်များများတွင် ဖွင့်လှစ်ထားသည့် Dinosaur Models (ဒိုင်နိုဆောပုံစံ) အရွယ်အမျိုးမျိုးကို ပြသထားသည့် ပြတိုက်တမျိုးဖြစ်သည်။ထိုနေရာတွင် များသောအားဖြင့် (ကျွန်တော်တို့သည်) လှည့်လည်ကြည့်ရှုလေ့လာရန် ၂-၃ နာရီခန့်ကြာတတ်သည်။ ပန်းခြံတစ်ခုလုံး လမ်းလျှောက်ကာ ဒိုင်နိုဆောအရိုးများကို ရှာဖွေကြသည်။ ကစားကွင်း၌လည်း ကစားကြပြီး ကျောက်မျက်ရတနာများလည်း တူးကြသည်။ "},{"question":"Slutför den här frasen: Touchemoulin studerade i sin födelsestad och i Paris samt var från 1870 (efter fransk-tyska kriget, då Elsass blev tyskt) bosatt i Frankrike. Han målade \\"En stad belägras under medeltiden\\" (1863, Strassburgs museum), \\"Slagen vid Solferino\\" (1864) och \\"Magenta","answer":"\\" (1866) samt skildrade i målningar och teckningar sin hemprovins, dess historiska minnen, folktyper, dräkter och dylikt, utgav teckningar av Strassburgs ruiner efter belägringen 1870 samt \\"Strassburg militaire\\" 1894. Han var även verksam som porträttmålare."},{"question":"Nderipi raive basa reTimbuktu munhoroondo yeWest Africa?","answer":"Timbuktu yaive nzvimbo ine mukurumbira yekudzidza nekutengeserana muMiddle Ages West Africa. Yakanga iri hubhu yehunyanzvi hwechiIslam uye nzvimbo yakakosha munzira dzekutengesa dzeTrans-Saharan."},{"question":"Jubbantil mbind mii:[Fàttalikuleen], ba Nu wólleranteek yéen, te Nu yékkati doj wa mu tiim leen, [Ma ne leen] : \\"Jàppleen te farlu ci la Ma leen jox te ngeen dégg [ndigal] ! \\". Ñu ne: \\"Dégg nanu te bañ nanu\\". Nàndaleef na leen seeni xol sëll wa ngir seenug weddi. Neel: \\"Bon na li leen seen ngëm digal ci loolu ndegam gëm ngeen\\".","answer":"Mbind mi jub a ngi nii:[Fàttlikuléen], ba Nu wóllarantee'k yéen, te Nu yékkati doj wa mu tiim léen, [Ma ne léen] : \\"Jàppléen te farlu ci la Ma léen jox te ngéen dégg [ndigal]!\\". Ñu ne: \\"Dégg na nu te bàñ na nu\\". Nàndaleef na léen séen i xol sëll wa ngìr séenug weddi. Neel: \\"Bon na li léen séen ngëm digal ci loolu ndegam gëm ngéen\\"."},{"question":"Viết biểu thức số biểu thị:a) Diện tích của hình tam giác có độ dài cạnh đáy là 3 cm, chiều cao tương ứng là 5 cm;b) Diện tích của hình tròn có bán kính là 2 cm.","answer":"Lời giải:a) Biểu thức số biểu thị diện tích của hình tam giác có độ dài cạnh đáy là 3 cm, chiều cao tương ứng là 5 cm là: 1/2. 3 . 5 (cm2).b) Biểu thức số biểu thị diện tích của hình tròn có bán kính là 2 cm là: 22 . 3,14 (cm2)."},{"question":"સોમનાથ મંદિરની માહિતી","answer":"સોમનાથ મંદિર, જેને સોમનાથ મંદિર અથવા દેવ પાટણ પણ કહેવાય છે, તે ભારતના ગુજરાતના પ્રભાસ પાટણ, વેરાવળમાં આવેલું એક હિન્દુ મંદિર છે. તે હિંદુઓ માટે સૌથી પવિત્ર તીર્થસ્થાનોમાંનું એક છે અને શિવના બાર જ્યોતિર્લિંગમાંનું પ્રથમ સ્થાન છે. તે અસ્પષ્ટ છે કે સોમનાથ મંદિરનું પ્રથમ સંસ્કરણ 1લી-સહસ્ત્રાબ્દીની શરૂઆતની સદીઓથી લગભગ 9મી સદી CE વચ્ચેના અંદાજો સાથે ક્યારે બાંધવામાં આવ્યું હતું. હિંદુ ધર્મના પ્રાચીન સંસ્કૃત ગ્રંથોમાં મંદિરનો ઉલ્લેખ સોમનાથ નામકરણ તરીકે નથી પરંતુ \\"પ્રભાસ-પટ્ટણ\\" (પ્રભાસ પાટણ) નો ઉલ્લેખ તીર્થ (તીર્થસ્થળ) તરીકે કરવામાં આવ્યો છે, જ્યાં આ મંદિર અસ્તિત્વમાં છે. ઉદાહરણ તરીકે, પુસ્તક ત્રણ (વન પર્વ) ના પ્રકરણ 109, 118 અને 119 માં મહાભારત, અને ભાગવત પુરાણ રાજ્ય પ્રભાસના વિભાગ 10.45 અને 10.78 સૌરાષ્ટ્રના દરિયાકાંઠે તીર્થ છે.બહુવિધ મુસ્લિમ આક્રમણકારો અને શાસકો દ્વારા પુનરાવર્તિત વિનાશ પછી મંદિરનું ભૂતકાળમાં ઘણી વખત પુનઃનિર્માણ કરવામાં આવ્યું હતું, ખાસ કરીને 11મી સદીમાં મહમૂદ ગઝનીના હુમલાથી શરૂ થયું હતું.સોમનાથ મંદિરનો 19મી- અને 20મી સદીની શરૂઆતમાં વસાહતી યુગના ઈતિહાસકારો અને પુરાતત્વવિદો દ્વારા સક્રિયપણે અભ્યાસ કરવામાં આવ્યો હતો, જ્યારે તેના અવશેષોએ ઈસ્લામિક મસ્જિદમાં રૂપાંતરિત થવાની પ્રક્રિયામાં ઐતિહાસિક હિંદુ મંદિરનું ચિત્રણ કર્યું હતું. ભારતની આઝાદી પછી, તે ખંડેરોને તોડી પાડવામાં આવ્યા હતા અને હાલના સોમનાથ મંદિરનું હિન્દુ મંદિર સ્થાપત્યની મારુ-ગુર્જરા શૈલીમાં પુનઃનિર્માણ કરવામાં આવ્યું હતું. સમકાલીન સોમનાથ મંદિરનું પુનઃનિર્માણ ભારતના પ્રથમ નાયબ વડા પ્રધાન વલ્લભભાઈ પટેલના આદેશ હેઠળ મહાત્મા ગાંધી પાસેથી પુનઃનિર્માણની મંજૂરી મળ્યા બાદ શરૂ કરવામાં આવ્યું હતું. તેમના મૃત્યુ પછી મે 1951 માં પુનર્નિર્માણ પૂર્ણ થયું હતું."},{"question":"ਬਟਨ ਖੁੰਬ ਦੀ ਕਾਸ਼ਤ ਲਈ ਕਿਹੜੇ-ਕਿਹੜੇ ਪੜਾਅ ਹਨ ਅਤੇ ਉਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਬਾਰੇ ਲਿਖੋ ।","answer":"ਬਟਨ ਖੁੰਬਾਂ ਦੀ ਕਾਸ਼ਤ ਦੇ ਪੜਾਅ-1.ਖਾਦ ਦੀ ਤਿਆਰੀ ਲਈ ਵਸਤਾਂ – ਤੁੜੀ 300 ਕਿਲੋ, ਕਣਕ ਦੀ ਛਾਣ (ਚੋਕਰ) 15 ਕਿਲੋਗ੍ਰਾਮ, ਕਿਸਾਨ ਖਾਦ 9 ਕਿਲੋਗ੍ਰਾਮ, ਯੂਰੀਆ, ਸੁਪਰਫਾਸਫੇਟ, ਮਿਊਰੇਟ ਆਫ਼ ਪੋਟਾਸ਼ ਤਿੰਨੇ ਖਾਦਾਂ 3-3 ਕਿਲੋਗ੍ਰਾਮ ਹਰ ਇੱਕ, ਜਿਪਸਮ 30 ਕਿਲੋਗ੍ਰਾਮ, ਗਾਮਾ ਬੀ.ਐਚ.ਸੀ. 20 ਈ.ਸੀ. 60 ਮਿਲੀਲੀਟਰ, ਸੀਰਾ 5 ਕਿਲੋਗ੍ਰਾਮ, ਫੂਰਾਡਾਨ 3 ਜੀ 150 ਗ੍ਰਾਮ ।2. ਢੇਰੀ ਬਣਾਉਣਾ – ਤੂੜੀ ਨੂੰ ਪੱਕੇ ਫਰਸ਼ ਤੇ ਵਿਛਾ ਕੇ ਇਸ ਉਪਰ ਪਾਣੀ ਛਿੜਕ ਕੇ ਇਸ ਨੂੰ 48 ਘੰਟੇ ਲਈ ਖੁੱਲ੍ਹਾ ਛੱਡ ਦਿਓ । ਖਾਦਾਂ ਅਤੇ ਕਣਕ ਦਾ ਛਾਣ ਮਿਲਾ ਕੇ ਢੇਰ ਨੂੰ ਥੋੜ੍ਹਾ ਗਿੱਲਾ ਕਰੋ । 24 ਘੰਟੇ ਬਾਅਦ ਗਿੱਲੀ ਤੂੜੀ ਦੇ ਉੱਪਰ ਖਾਦ ਮਿਲਿਆ ਛਾਣ ਖਿਲਾਰਿਆ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ । ਇਸ ਸਾਰੇ ਮਿਸ਼ਰਣ ਨੂੰ ਇਕੱਠਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਲੱਕੜੀ ਦੇ ਇਕ ਸਾਂਚੇ ਵਿਚ ਜੋ ਕਿ 5 ਫੁੱਟ ਲੰਬਾ, 5 ਫੁੱਟ ਚੌੜਾ ਅਤੇ 5 ਫੁੱਟ ਉੱਚਾ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ, ਵਿਚ ਭਰਿਆ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ। ਫਿਰ ਇਸ ਸਾਂਚੇ ਦੇ ਫੱਟੇ ਹਟਾ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ ਤੇ ਢੇਰੀ ਤਿਆਰ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ ।3. ਖਾਦਾਂ ਦੀ ਢੇਰੀ ਨੂੰ ਫਰੋਲਣਾ – ਢੇਰੀ ਨੂੰ ਰਲਾਉਣ ਲਈ ਹਰ ਵਾਰ ਉੱਪਰਲੇ ਸਿਰੇ ਤੋਂ ਚਾਰੇ ਪਾਸਿਆਂ ਤੋਂ ਕੁੱਝ ਪਾਣੀ ਛਿੜਕ ਕੇ ਚੰਗੀ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ ਰਲਾਓ ਅਤੇ ਕੁੱਝ ਹੋਰ ਪਾਣੀ ਛਿੜਕ ਦਿਓ । ਇਸ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ ਆਮ ਕਰਕੇ ਢੇਰੀ ਦਾ ਬਾਹਰਲਾ ਹਿੱਸਾ ਅੰਦਰ ਅਤੇ ਵਿਚਕਾਰਲਾ ਹਿੱਸਾ ਬਾਹਰ ਆ ਜਾਵੇਗਾ | ਕੰਪੋਸਟ ਬਣਾਉਣ ਵਾਲੇ ਜੀਵਾਣੂਆਂ ਨੂੰ ਵੀ ਤਾਜ਼ੀ ਹਵਾ ਮਿਲ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ । ਹਰ ਵਾਰ ਢੇਰੀ ਨੂੰ ਦੁਬਾਰਾ ਬਣਾਉਣ ਲੱਗਿਆਂ ਇਸੇ ਢੰਗ ਦੀ ਵਰਤੋਂ ਕਰੋ । ਢੇਰੀ ਨੂੰ ਤਿੰਨ ਵਾਰ ਹਰ ਚੌਥੇ ਦਿਨ ਅਤੇ ਫਿਰ ਹਰ ਤੀਜੇ ਦਿਨ ਹਿਲਾ ਕੇ ਇਸ ਵਿਚ ਸੀਰਾ, ਜਿਪਸਮ, ਫੂਰਾਡਾਨ ਅਤੇ ਗਾਮਾ ਬੀ. ਐੱਚ. ਸੀ. ਨੂੰ ਕ੍ਰਮਵਾਰ ਪਹਿਲੀ, ਤੀਜੀ, ਪੰਜਵੀਂ ਅਤੇ ਸੱਤਵੀਂ ਵਾਰ ਹਿਲਾਉਣ ਤੇ ਮਿਲਾ ਦਿਉ ।24 ਦਿਨਾਂ ਬਾਅਦ 300 ਕਿਲੋਗ੍ਰਾਮ ਤੂੜੀ ਤੋਂ ਪੂਰੀ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ ਤਿਆਰ ਕੀਤੀ ਇਹ ਖਾਦ 100 × 150 × 18 ਸੈਂ.ਮੀ. ਅਕਾਰ ਦੀਆਂ 20-25 ਪੇਟੀਆਂ ਭਰਨ ਲਈ ਕਾਫ਼ੀ ਹੈ । ਜਦੋਂ ਖਾਦ ਦਾ ਰੰਗ ਕਾਲਾ ਭੂਰਾ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ ਅਤੇ ਅਮੋਨੀਆ ਦੀ ਬੂ ਆਉਣੀ ਬੰਦ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ ਅਤੇ ਇਸ ਵਿਚ 65-72% ਨਮੀ ਹੁੰਦੀ ਹੈ ਤਾਂ ਖਾਦ ਤਿਆਰ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ | ਪੀ.ਐੱਚ 70 ਤੋਂ 8.0 ਹੁੰਦੀ ਹੈ ।4. ਖਾਦ ਦੀ ਸੋਧ – ਖੁੰਬਾਂ ਦਾ ਬੀਜ ਬੀਜਣ ਤੋਂ ਪਹਿਲਾਂ ਤਿਆਰ ਕੀਤੀ ਖਾਦ ਵਿਚ ਬਾਵਿਸਟਨ 50 ਘੁਲਣਸ਼ੀਲ 20 ਮਿਲੀਗ੍ਰਾਮ ਪ੍ਰਤੀ ਲਿਟਰ ਦੇ ਹਿਸਾਬ ਨਾਲ ਮਿਲਾ ਦੇ ਚਾਹੀਦੀ ਹੈ । ਇਸ ਲਈ ਇਕ ਕੁਇੰਟਲ ਖਾਦ ਵਿਚ 20 ਗ੍ਰਾਮ ਬਾਵਿਸਟਨ ਦਾ ਧੂੜਾ ਕਾਫ਼ੀ ਹੈ, ਜੋ ਕਿ ਚਾਰ ਪੇਟੀਆਂ ਲਈ ਕਾਫ਼ੀ ਹੈ ।5. ਪੇਟੀਆਂ ਭਰਨਾ ਅਤੇ ਖੁੰਬਾਂ ਬੀਜਣਾ – ਖਾਦ ਦੀ ਢੇਰੀ ਨੂੰ ਖਿਲਾਰ ਕੇ ਕੁੱਝ ਸਮੇਂ ਲਈ ਠੰਡੀ ਹੋਣ ਦਿਓ । ਖੁੰਬਾਂ ਦੇ ਬੀਜ (ਸਪਾਨ ਨੂੰ ਬੋਤਲਾਂ ਵਿਚੋਂ ਕੱਢੋ ਅਤੇ ਦੋ ਤਹਿਆਂ ਵਿਚ ਖੁੰਬਾਂ ਬੀਜਣ ਵਾਲੇ ਢੰਗ ਦੀ ਵਰਤੋਂ ਕਰਦੇ ਹੋਏ ਖਾਦ ਉੱਤੇ ਬੀਜ ਖਲਾਰ ਕੇ ਪੇਟੀਆਂ ਵਿਚ ਬੀਜ ਦਿਓ । ਫਿਰ ਇਸ ਖਾਦ ਦੀ ਮੋਟੀ ਤਹਿ ਪਾਓ ਅਤੇ ਬੀਜ ਦਾ ਬਾਕੀ ਬਕਾਇਆ ਹਿੱਸਾ ਇਸ ਤੇ ਖਲਾਰ ਕੇ ਖਾਦ ਵਿਚ ਰਲਾ ਦੇਣਾ ਚਾਹੀਦਾ ਹੈ । ਪੇਟੀਆਂ ਉੱਤੇ ਗਿੱਲਾ ਅਖ਼ਬਾਰ ਜਾਂ ਹੋਰ ਕਾਗ਼ਜ਼ ਰੱਖ ਦੇਣਾ ਚਾਹੀਦਾ ਹੈ । 2-3 ਹਫ਼ਤਿਆਂ ਦੇ ਅੰਦਰ ਖੁੰਬਾਂ ਦੇ ਬੀਜ ਤੋਂ ਕਪਾਹ ਦੀਆਂ ਫੁੱਟੀਆਂ ਵਰਗੇ ਸਫ਼ੈਦ ਰੇਸ਼ਿਆਂ ਨਾਲ 80-100% ਪੇਟੀਆਂ ਭਰ ਜਾਂਦੀਆਂ ਹਨ ।6. ਪੇਟੀਆਂ ਮਿੱਟੀ ਨਾਲ ਢੱਕਣਾ – ਬਾਅਦ ਵਿਚ 80-100% ਰੇਸ਼ਿਆਂ (ਮਾਈਸੀਲੀਅਮ ਨਾਲ ਭਰੀਆਂ ਟਰੇਆਂ ਨੂੰ 4:1 ਦੇ ਅਨੁਪਾਤ ਵਾਲੇ ਖਾਦ ਅਤੇ ਰੇਤਲੀ ਮਿੱਟੀ ਜਾਂ 1:1 ਦੇ ਅਨੁਪਾਤ ਵਾਲੇ ਚੌਲਾਂ ਦੀ ਸੜੀ ਹੋਈ ਫੱਕ ਅਤੇ ਗੋਬਰ ਗੈਸ ਦੀ ਸੱਲਰੀ ਦੇ ਮਿਸ਼ਰਨ ਨਾਲ ਇਕਸਾਰ ਢੱਕ ਦੇਣਾ ਚਾਹੀਦਾ ਹੈ । ਇਸ ਮਿਸ਼ਰਣ ਨੂੰ ਕੇਸਿੰਗ ਮਿਸ਼ਰਣ ਕਿਹਾ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ । ਢੱਕਣ ਤੋਂ ਪਹਿਲਾਂ ਇਸ ਨੂੰ 4-5% ਫਾਰਮਲੀਨ ਦੇ ਘੋਲ ਨਾਲ ਰੋਗ ਰਹਿਤ ਕਰੋ ।7. ਕੇਸਿੰਗ ਮਿਸ਼ਰਣ ਨੂੰ ਜਰਮ ਰਹਿਤ ਕਰਨਾ – ਰੇਤ ਮਿਲੀ, ਗਲੀ-ਸੜੀ ਰੂੜੀ ਜਾਂ ਖਾਦ ਨੂੰ ਗਿੱਲਾ ਕਰ ਦਿਓ । ਇਸ ਉੱਪਰ 4-5% ਫਾਰਮਲੀਨ ਦਾ ਛਿੜਕਾਅ ਕਰੋ । ਪ੍ਰਤੀ ਕੁਇੰਟਲ ਕੇਸਿੰਗ ਮਿੱਟੀ ਦੇ ਹਿਸਾਬ ਨਾਲ 20 ਗ੍ਰਾਮ ਫੂਰਾਡਾਨ ਪਾਓ । ਬਾਅਦ ਵਿਚ ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਤਰਪਾਲ ਜਾਂ ਬੋਰੀਆਂ ਨਾਲ 48 ਘੰਟੇ ਲਈ ਢੱਕ ਦਿਓ 1 ਵਰਤਣ ਤੋਂ ਪਹਿਲਾਂ ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਕੁੱਝ ਦੇਰ ਲਈ ਫਰੋਲੋ ਤਾਂ ਕਿ ਫਾਰਮਲੀਨ ਚੰਗੀ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ ਉੱਡ ਜਾਵੇ ।8. ਟਰੇਆਂ ਨੂੰ ਚੁੱਕਣ ਦਾ ਤਰੀਕਾ – ਖੁੰਬਾਂ ਦੇ ਬੀਜ ਬੀਜਣ ਤੋਂ 2-3 ਹਫ਼ਤੇ ਬਾਅਦ ਪੇਟੀਆਂ ਤੋਂ ਅਖ਼ਬਾਰ ਦੇ ਕਾਗਜ਼ ਲਾਹ ਦੇਣਾ ਚਾਹੀਦਾ ਹੈ ਅਤੇ ਮਾਈਸੀਲੀਅਮ ਨਾਲ ਭਰੀ ਖਾਦ ਨੂੰ ਇਕ ਤੋਂ ਡੇਢ ਇੰਚ ਮੋਟੀ ਰੋਗ ਰਹਿਤ ਕੀਤੀ ਮਿੱਟੀ ਦੀ ਤਹਿ ਨਾਲ ਢੱਕ ਦੇਣਾ ਚਾਹੀਦਾ ਹੈ ।9. ਪੇਟੀਆਂ ਨੂੰ ਤਰਤੀਬ ਦੇਣਾ – ਪੇਟੀਆਂ ਨੂੰ ਇਕ-ਦੂਜੀ ਦੇ ਉੱਪਰ ਟਿਕਾ ਕੇ ਕਾਸ਼ਤ ਦਾ ਖੇਤਰ ਵਧਾਇਆ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ । ਲਾਈਨਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਰੱਖੀਆਂ ਪੇਟੀਆਂ ਦਾ ਫਾਸਲਾ 2-2 ਫੁੱਟ ਅਤੇ ਪੇਟੀਆਂ ਵਿੱਚ ਉੱਪਰ-ਹੇਠਾਂ ਰੱਖੀਆਂ ਟਰੇਆਂ ਵਿੱਚ ਇੱਕ ਫੁੱਟ ਫ਼ਾਸਲਾ ਹੋਣਾ ਚਾਹੀਦਾ ਹੈ। ਅਜਿਹਾ ਕਰਦੇ ਸਮੇਂ ਨਿੱਕੀਆਂ-ਨਿੱਕੀਆਂ ਬਟਨ ਖੁੰਬਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਕੋਈ ਨੁਕਸਾਨ ਨਹੀਂ ਪਹੁੰਚਣਾ ਚਾਹੀਦਾ । ਪੁੱਟਣ ਤੋਂ ਬਾਅਦ ਖੁੰਬ ਦੀ ਡੰਡੀ ਦਾ ਮਿੱਟੀ ਵਾਲਾ ਹਿੱਸਾ ਕੱਟ ਦੇਣਾ ਚਾਹੀਦਾ ਹੈ ਅਤੇ ਸਾਫ਼ ਕਰ ਲੈਣਾ ਚਾਹੀਦਾ ਹੈ ।10. ਖੁੰਬਾਂ ਦਾ ਉੱਗਣਾ – ਪੇਟੀਆਂ ਨੂੰ ਮਿੱਟੀ ਨਾਲ ਢੱਕਣ ਤੋਂ 2-3 ਹਫ਼ਤੇ ਬਾਅਦ ਖੁੰਬਾਂ ਨਿਕਲਣ ਲਗਦੀਆਂ ਹਨ ਅਤੇ 2-3 ਦਿਨਾਂ ਵਿੱਚ ਤੋੜਨ ਲਈ ਤਿਆਰ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦੀਆਂ ਹਨ ।11. ਖੁੰਬਾਂ ਦਾ ਝਾੜ – ਇੱਕ ਵਰਗ ਮੀਟਰ ਰਕਬੇ ਵਿਚੋਂ 8-12 ਕਿਲੋ ਖੰਬਾਂ ਨਿਕਲ ਆਉਂਦੀਆਂ ਹਨ । ਖੁੰਬਾਂ ਦੀ ਬਟਨ ਖੁੰਬ ਕਿਸਮ ਦੇ ਇੱਕ ਕਿਲੋ ਨੂੰ ਉਗਾਉਣ ਲਈ 38.44 ਰੁਪਏ ਲਾਗਤ ਅਤੇ ਢੀਂਗਰੀ ਖੁੰਬ ਉਗਾਉਣ ਲਈ 31.84 ਰੁਪਏ ਲਾਗਤ ਆਉਂਦੀ ਹੈ ।"},{"question":"ಕೆಳಗಿನ ವಿಷಯದ ಬಗ್ಗೆ ಒಂದು ಪ್ಯಾರಾಗ್ರಾಫ್ ಬರೆಯಿರಿ: ಸಹ್ಯಾದ್ರಿಯ ಇತಿಹಾಸ","answer":"ಸಹ್ಯಾದ್ರಿ ಖಂಡ ಎಂಬ ಪುರಾಣದಲ್ಲಿ ಇಲ್ಲಿನ ಭೌಗೋಳಿಕ ಮತ್ತು ಸಾಂಸ್ಕೃತಿಕ ಇತಿಹಾಸ ಇದೆ. ಕಾಳಿದಾಸನ ಮೇಘದೂತದಲ್ಲಿ ಸಹ್ಯಾದ್ರಿಯ ವರ್ಣನೆ ಇದೆ. ಇದು ಅಗಸ್ತ್ಯರು ವಾಸಿಸಿದ ತಪಸ್ಸು ಮಾಡಿದ ಸ್ಥಳ. ಪರಶುರಾಮನು ಕೊಡಚಾದ್ರಿ ಮೇಲೇರಿ ಕೊಡಲಿ ಎಸೆದಾಗ ಸಮುದ್ರ ಹಿಂದೆಸರಿದು ಕರಾವಳಿ ಪ್ರದೇಶ ಸೃಷ್ಟಿಯಾಯಿತು ಎಂದು ಕತೆ ಇದೆ. ಅದು ಸಮುದ್ರ ಹಿಂದೆ ಸಹ್ಯಾದ್ರಿಯವರೆಗಿತ್ತು ಅದು ಹಿಂದೆಹೋದುದರೆ ಮೇಲೆ ಪುರಾಣದ ಕತೆ ಎನ್ನುತ್ತಾರೆ."},{"question":"வினா:சுடுமண் பாண்டம் பற்றி ஒரு குறிப்பு எழுதவும்","answer":"விடை:சுடுமண் பாண்டம் ஒருவகை மென்மையான களிமண்ணைக் கொண்டு உருவம் செய்து பின் அதனை சூளையில் சுட்டு வடிவத்தை கெட்டிப்படுத்துவர். சிவப்பு, காவி, ஆரஞ்சு நிற சுடுமண் மட்பாண்டங்கள், அரச முத்திரைகள், வரலாற்று குறிப்புகள், கடவுட் சிலைகள், விலங்குகளின் சிற்பங்கள், மேற்கூரையின் ஓடுகள், செங்கற்கள், பூந்தொட்டிகள், விளக்குகள், கழிவு நீர் குழாய்கள் மற்றும் கட்டுமான பொருட்கள் செய்ய பயன்படுத்தப்பட்டது. கிமு 2,000 ஆயிரம் ஆண்டுகளுக்கு முன்னர், உருளை வடிவ சுடுமண் பாண்டங்களில் சுமேரியர்கள் ஆப்பெழுத்துகளில் தங்கள் வரலாற்றுக் குறிப்புகளை எழுதி வைத்துள்ளனர். மேலும் சுடுமண் பாண்டத்தில் சுமேரியக் கடவுளர்கள், சுமேரிய மன்னர்களின் உருவச் சிற்பங்கள் உருவாக்கினர்.கி.மு. 210 காலத்திய முதலாவது சீனச் சக்கரவர்த்தி சின் ஷி ஹுவாங்கின் போர் வீரர்களைச் சித்தரிக்கும் சுடுமட்சிலைப் படை சிற்பங்கள் சாங்சி மாகாணத்திலுள்ள சிய்யான் என்னுமிடத்தின் லின்டோங் மாவட்டத்தில் உள்ளூர் விவசாயி ஒருவரால் 1974 இல் கண்டுபிடிக்கப்பட்டது. "},{"question":"How does the Pettah Market showcase Colombo's vibrant street life?","answer":"Pettah Market, a bustling commercial district, is the epitome of Colombo's vibrant street life. Narrow lanes are filled with shops selling a myriad of goods, from spices and textiles to electronics. The market is a sensory delight, with the hustle and bustle creating an energetic atmosphere that reflects the dynamic spirit of the city."},{"question":"නොහිම් සහ ලොව්තුරුසුව වලඳින්නේ යන වචනවල තේරුම කියාදෙන්න.","answer":"නොහිම්:සීමාවක් නොමැති,අසීමාන්තිකලොව්තුරු සුව වලඳින්නේ:ලොව්තුරු සුවය,ලෝකෝත්තර සුවය විඳීම."},{"question":"كمل الفقرة:وأعرب عن استعداد تركيا لبذل كل جهد ممكن لضمان زيادة متوازنة في حجم التجارة الثنائية، وتحقيق علاقة تجارية مستدامة.","answer":"وأوضح الوزير أن صادرات بلاده إلى الدول العربية زادت 15% العام الماضي مقارنة بعام 2021، وبلغت 46 مليار دولار، بينما زادت الواردات 31% لتصل إلى 36 مليارا."},{"question":"Apakah maksud \\"bagai serdadu pulang baris\\"?","answer":"Ia bermaksud orang yang kelihatan selalu bergaya tetapi berada dalam pekerjaan berat dan bahaya."},{"question":"Бул жомоктун уландысын жазып берчи: \\"Окууну бала мыктап кабылдады, Так бүгүн күндүк оокат табылбады.\\"","answer":"Бул жомоктун уландысы мындай болушу мүмкүн: \\"Тапса да, окуу, тамак калаа жакта, Жүр, балам, — деди кемпир адымдады.\\""},{"question":"Wat is retrieval augmented generation?","answer":"Retrieval augmented generation combineert de conversationale kracht van een large language model met een beperkte dataset die bestaat uit een verzameling van eigen (bedrijfs)informatie, zoals documenten, websites en PDFs. Door het gebruik van Retrieval Augmented Generation kun je large language models inzetten om je eigen informatie te bevragen, en neemt de kans op hallucinaties aanzienlijk af. "},{"question":"قم بالإجابة على السؤال التالي من هو الرحالة الذي اكتشف نيوزلندا ؟","answer":"بالتأكيد،الرحالة الذي اكتشف نيوزيلندا هو : الهولندي تسمان."},{"question":"Berapakah prinsip yang terdapat di dalam Rukun Negara Malaysia?","answer":" Di Malaysia, terdapat 5 prinsip Rukun Negara, ialtu:1. Kepercayaan Kepada Tuhan2. Kesetiaan Kepada Raja dan Negara3. Keluhuran Perlembagaan4. Kedaulatan Undang-Undang5. Kesopanan dan Kesusilaan"},{"question":"1948 සාහිත්‍යය සඳහා වූ නොබෙල් ත්‍යාගය දිනාගත් 20 වැනි සියවසේ අග්‍රගණ්‍ය වූ ඇමෙරිකානු කවියා කවුද?","answer":"ටී . එස් . එලියට් (T.S. Eliot) 1948 වස​රේ සාහිත්‍යය සඳහා වූ නොබෙල් ත්‍යාගය දිනා ගත්තේය."},{"question":"What does 'Good morning' mean?","answer":"Good morning is a greeting in English often used at the beginning of conversations to welcome another person. It is considered quite formal and of good manners."},{"question":"පහත ගීතය සම්පුර්ණ කරන්න. ශ්‍රී සම්බුද්ධ රාජා වඳිම්මා සෑසී තිලෝනා වඳිම්හද පුදසුන් සදා එහි බැති මල් පුදාමා සෑසී තිලෝනා වඳිම්ශ්‍රී සම්බුද්ධ රාජා වඳිම්","answer":"සම්පූර්ණ කළ ගීතය :ශ්‍රී සම්බුද්ධ රාජා වඳිම්මා සෑසී තිලෝනා වඳිම්හද පුදසුන් සදා එහි බැති මල් පුදාමා සෑසී තිලෝනා වඳිම්ශ්‍රී සම්බුද්ධ රාජා වඳිම්අංගුලීමාල නාලාගිරීලෝ සතුන් රාග පාපෙන් පිරීඅදමි පවිටන් දැමූ දම් අමාවෙන් තෙමූදම් රදාණන් වඳිම් සෑමදාසිව් සැකී සත් කෙළක් දුක දරාසිව් සුවේ පස් මරුන් මන් අරාපාරමී දම් පුරා බුදු වූ ලොව් තුරාදම් රදාණන් වඳිම් සිත්පුරාමුල් සෙවූ වේදනා සාදනාඉන් මිදෙවු සේක මේ ලෝ දනාඅන්ධකාරේ නැසූ මිහිරි සදහම් දෙසූලෝ පියාණන් වඳිම් සෑමදාමා සෑසී තිලෝනා වඳිම්සුජාතා අත්තනායකප්‍රේමනාත් ජයතිලක"},{"question":"புதிர்:  அடர்ந்த காட்டில் ஒற்றையடி பாதை அது என்ன? ","answer":"விடை: தலைவகிடு "},{"question":"2020 වසරේදී එළි දැක්වූ A Promised Land කෘතිය රචනා කරන ලද්දේ ?","answer":"බැරක් ඔබාමා"},{"question":"Inis dom faoi Cath Oravainen. ","answer":"Ceann de na cathanna le linn Chogadh na Fionlainne idir an tSualainn agus an Rúis ab ea Cath Oravainen.Cuireadh an cath in Oravainen (Sualainnis: Oravais) ar an 14 Deireadh Fómhair 1808. Is é tuairim na staraithe cogaidh gurbh ansin a chaill an tSualainn an seans deireanach leis an gcogadh sin a ghnóthú."},{"question":"Isi tempat kosong dengan jawapan yang paling sesuai. Juruterbang merupakan __ abang sejak kecil lagi.  A)  minta-mintaB)  cita-citaC)  cari-cari   D) kira-kira","answer":"Jawapan yang betul ialah B)  cita-cita"},{"question":"Apakah asal-usul Isnin Siber?","answer":"Isnin Siber ialah istilah pemasaran untuk hari Isnin selepas cuti Hari Kesyukuran di Amerika Syarikat. Istilah \\"Isnin Siber\\" dicipta syarikat pemasaran untuk menggalakkan orang membeli-belah secara atas talian. Istilah ini diungkap Ellen Davis dan Scott Silverman, dan muncul buat kali pertamanya pada 28 November 2005 dalam wawancara Shop.org yang dinamakan \\"Isnin Siber\\", dan menjadi antara hari membeli-belah secara atas talian yang paling besar dalam tahun tersebut."},{"question":"Soalan: di manakah rancangan TV \\"Friday Night Live\\" difilemkan ","answer":"Pflugerville"},{"question":"ఈ పేరా కోసం ఒక కొనసాగింపును వ్రాయండి - అతను అసెంబ్లీని విడిచిపెట్టిన తరువాత, థామస్ అనేక సంవత్సరాలు కాంట్రాక్టర్గా పనిచేశాడు, కాని స్థానిక రాజకీయాల్లో చురుకుగా ఉన్నాడు. 1904 జనవరిలో నీటి సరఫరా, గ్యాస్, విద్యుత్ డిప్యూటీ కమిషనర్గా నియమితులయ్యారు. మేలో ఈ పదవి నుండి తొలగించబడిన కొద్దిసేపటికే అతను సిటీ రెవెన్యూ కలెక్టర్ మరియు మార్కెట్ల సూపరింటెండెంట్గా నియమితులయ్యారు. 1906 లో, అతను ఫైనాన్స్ డిపార్ట్మెంట్ కోసం రియల్ ఎస్టేట్ మదింపుదారుగా నియమించబడ్డాడు. 1911 లో న్యూయార్క్ గవర్నర్ జాన్ ఆల్డెన్ డిక్స్ అతన్ని న్యూయార్క్ పన్ను కమిషనర్గా నియమించారు. 1915 డిసెంబరులో, థామస్ షెరీఫ్ డిప్యూటీగా నియమితుడయ్యాడు, అతను తన జీవితాంతం ఈ పదవిలో ఉన్నాడు. థామస్ 1912 మరియు 1916 డెమొక్రాటిక్ నేషనల్ కన్వెన్షన్కు ప్రతినిధిగా కూడా పనిచేశాడు","answer":"థామస్"},{"question":"Wahala Ire-Ekiti: Awọn ọlọpaa ni ki i ṣe ọta ibọn awọn lo pa awọn to ku","answer":"Ileeṣẹ ọlọpaa ipinlẹ Ekiti ti kede pe ọta ibọn kọ lo pa awọn meji to padanu ẹmi wọn nibi rogbodiyan to waye niluu Ire-Ekiti, nijọba ibilẹ Ikọle, lanaa ọjọ Aje.Alukoro ileeṣẹ naa, ASP Sunday Abutu, ṣalaye lonii pe awọn to n fi kumọ ati nnkan ija oloro mi-in ja lo pa awọn eeyan naa, ki i ṣe ọta ibọn ọlọpaa rara.Lọjọ Aiku, Sannde, ijẹta, ni wahala bẹ silẹ niluu naa lẹyin ti Onire, Ọba Victor Bọbade, kede pe ko si ọdun Ogun lọdun yii, latari aṣẹ ijọba lati dena arun Korona.Eyi lo bi awọn kan ninu ti wọn fi da wahala silẹ, ọrọ naa si di nnkan nla lanaa, nibi ti eeyan meji ti pada gbẹmi–in mi, ti wọn si ba ọpọlọpọ dukia jẹ.Ni bayii, awọn ọlọpaa ti mu eeyan kan ti wọn sọ pe oun lo dari awọn to paayan, wọn si ni awọn n wa awọn to le ni mẹẹẹdogun di asiko yii."},{"question":"Dame un ejemplo de trivia en está categoría : geografía. ","answer":"¿Cuál es la población del continente más grande por masa de tierra en el mundo? 4.561 billones. "},{"question":"ਸਵਾਲਃ ਕਿਹੜੇ ਦੇਸ਼ ਬਰਿਕਸ ਵਿੱਚ ਸ਼ਾਮਲ ਹੋਣਾ ਚਾਹੁੰਦੇ ਹਨ?","answer":"ਜਵਾਬਃ ਬਰਿਕਸ ਅਤੇ ਏਸ਼ੀਆ ਲਈ ਦੱਖਣੀ ਅਫ਼ਰੀਕਾ ਦੇ ਰਾਜਦੂਤ, ਅਨਿਲ ਸੂਕਲਾਲ ਨੇ ਹਾਲ ਹੀ ਵਿੱਚ ਕਿਹਾ ਕਿ 22 ਦੇਸ਼ਾਂ ਨੇ ਰਸਮੀ ਤੌਰ 'ਤੇ ਸਮੂਹ ਵਿੱਚ ਸ਼ਾਮਲ ਹੋਣ ਲਈ ਦਿਲਚਸਪੀ ਪ੍ਰਗਟਾਈ ਹੈ।ਇਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਵਿੱਚ ਇਰਾਨ, ਅਰਜਨਟੀਨਾ, ਕਿਊਬਾ, ਕਜ਼ਾਕਿਸਤਾਨ, ਇਥੋਪੀਆ, ਸਾਊਦੀ ਅਰਬ, ਸੰਯੁਕਤ ਅਰਬ ਅਮੀਰਾਤ ਅਤੇ ਵੈਨੇਜ਼ੁਏਲਾ ਸ਼ਾਮਲ ਹਨ।ਪ੍ਰੋਫ਼ੈਸਰ ਕਾਰਮੋਡੀ ਕਹਿੰਦੇ ਹਨ, \\"ਇੱਥੇ ਇੱਕ ਧਾਰਨਾ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਹੁਣ ਪੱਛਮ ਵਿਸ਼ਵ ਤਾਕਤ ਦਾ ਧੁਰਾ ਨਹੀਂ ਰਿਹਾ ਅਤੇ ਵਧੇਰੇ ਵਿਕਾਸਸ਼ੀਲ ਦੇਸ਼ ਬਰਿਕਸ ਦੇਸ਼ਾਂ ਵਰਗੀਆਂ ਵਧਦੀਆਂ ਤਾਕਤਾ ਵੱਲ ਦੇਖ ਰਹੇ ਹਨ।\\"ਬਰਿਕਸ ਇੱਕ ਬਹੁਤ ਹੀ ਵਿਲੱਖਣ ਸਮੂਹ ਹੈ। ਪਰ ਸਵਾਲ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਕੀ ਇਹ ਨਵੇਂ ਮੈਂਬਰਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਸਵੀਕਾਰ ਕਰਨ ਲਈ ਤਿਆਰ ਹੈ?ਬਟਲਰ ਕਹਿੰਦੇ ਹਨ, \\"ਮੇਰਾ ਅੰਦਾਜ਼ਾ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਇਹ ਕੁਝ ਦੇਸ਼ਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਹਿੱਸਾ ਬਣਾ ਲਵੇਗਾ। ਪਰ ਇਰਾਨ ਵਰਗੇ ਗੁੰਝਲਦਾਰਾਂ ਦੀ ਬਜਾਇ ਅਰਜਨਟੀਨਾ ਵਰਗੇ ਦੇਸ਼ ਹੋਣ ਦੀ ਸੰਭਾਵਨਾ ਹੈ।\\""},{"question":"Ungamiririra sei mubvunzo kana kuda kuziva?","answer":"🤔❓"},{"question":"ذهبت انا ومجموعة من أصدقائي الي فندق كورال بيتش كل منا معه أسرته واشهد بأننا قد قضينا وقت ممتع وسعيد والكل تفاني في خدمتنا ولا توجد تفرقة بين مصري وأجنبي وهذا ما أشعرني بالسعادة البالغة ماهي مشاعر المراجعة السابقة؟","answer":"الجملة تحتوي على مشاعر إيجابية."},{"question":"5 ವರ್ಷದ ಮಗುವಿಗೆ ಸಮಯ ವಲಯಗಳನ್ನು ವಿವರಿಸಿ","answer":"ಖಚಿತವಾಗಿ, 5 ವರ್ಷದ ಮಗುವಿಗೆ ನಾನು ನೀಡುವ ಸಮಯ ವಲಯಗಳ ವಿವರಣೆ ಇಲ್ಲಿದೆ:ನೀವು ದೊಡ್ಡ ಚೆಂಡನ್ನು ಹೊಂದಿದ್ದೀರಿ ಎಂದು ಕಲ್ಪಿಸಿಕೊಳ್ಳಿ. ಈ ಚೆಂಡು ಭೂಮಿ ಎಂದು ಹೇಳೋಣ. ಈಗ, ಚೆಂಡನ್ನು 24 ಸಮಾನ ಹೋಳುಗಳಾಗಿ ಕತ್ತರಿಸೋಣ. ಪ್ರತಿ ಸ್ಲೈಸ್ ಸಮಯ ವಲಯವಾಗಿದೆ.ಭೂಮಿಯು ಯಾವಾಗಲೂ ಸುತ್ತುತ್ತಿರುತ್ತದೆ, ಮತ್ತು ಅದು ತಿರುಗುತ್ತಿರುವಾಗ, ಸೂರ್ಯನು ಭೂಮಿಯ ವಿವಿಧ ಭಾಗಗಳಲ್ಲಿ ಹೊಳೆಯುತ್ತಾನೆ. ಪ್ರತಿ ಸಮಯ ವಲಯದಲ್ಲಿನ ಸಮಯವು ಸೂರ್ಯನು ಆಕಾಶದಲ್ಲಿ ಅತಿ ಎತ್ತರದಲ್ಲಿರುವಾಗ ಆಧರಿಸಿದೆ.ಉದಾಹರಣೆಗೆ, ನೀವು ನ್ಯೂಯಾರ್ಕ್ ನಗರದಲ್ಲಿದ್ದೀರಿ ಎಂದು ಭಾವಿಸೋಣ. ನ್ಯೂಯಾರ್ಕ್ ನಗರದಲ್ಲಿ ಮಧ್ಯಾಹ್ನದ ಸಮಯದಲ್ಲಿ ಸೂರ್ಯನು ಆಕಾಶದಲ್ಲಿ ಅತಿ ಹೆಚ್ಚು. ಆದರೆ ನೀವು ಲಂಡನ್‌ನಲ್ಲಿದ್ದರೆ, ಮಧ್ಯಾಹ್ನ 5:00 ಗಂಟೆಗೆ ಆಕಾಶದಲ್ಲಿ ಸೂರ್ಯನು ಅತಿ ಹೆಚ್ಚು. ಏಕೆಂದರೆ ಲಂಡನ್ ಬೇರೆ ಸಮಯ ವಲಯದಲ್ಲಿದೆ.ಪ್ರಪಂಚದಲ್ಲಿ 24 ಸಮಯ ವಲಯಗಳಿವೆ ಮತ್ತು ಪ್ರತಿ ಸಮಯ ವಲಯವು ಒಂದು ಗಂಟೆಯ ಅಂತರದಲ್ಲಿರುತ್ತದೆ. ಆದ್ದರಿಂದ, ನ್ಯೂಯಾರ್ಕ್ ನಗರದಲ್ಲಿ ಮಧ್ಯಾಹ್ನ 12:00 ಆಗಿದ್ದರೆ, ಚಿಕಾಗೋದಲ್ಲಿ ಬೆಳಿಗ್ಗೆ 11:00, ಡೆನ್ವರ್ನಲ್ಲಿ ಬೆಳಿಗ್ಗೆ 10:00, ಇತ್ಯಾದಿ.ನೀವು ಬೇರೆ ಸಮಯ ವಲಯಕ್ಕೆ ಪ್ರಯಾಣಿಸುವಾಗ, ನಿಮ್ಮ ಗಡಿಯಾರವನ್ನು ಹೊಸ ಸಮಯ ವಲಯದಲ್ಲಿರುವ ಸಮಯಕ್ಕೆ ಬದಲಾಯಿಸಬೇಕಾಗುತ್ತದೆ. ಏಕೆಂದರೆ ಹೊಸ ಸಮಯ ವಲಯದಲ್ಲಿ ಸೂರ್ಯನು ಆಕಾಶದಲ್ಲಿ ಬೇರೆ ಬೇರೆ ಹಂತದಲ್ಲಿರುತ್ತಾನೆ."},{"question":"No anime Boku no Hero Academia, quem é Kyoka Jiro (Earphone Jack)?","answer":"Kyoka Jiro é uma estudante da U.A. High School e membro da turma 1-A. Seu Quirk, \\"Earphone Jack,\\" permite que ela transforme seus ouvidos em plugues de áudio, que podem ser usados para amplificar sons e atacar os inimigos. Jiro é conhecida por seu estilo gótico, sua paixão pela música e sua personalidade reservada. Ela é uma das alunas mais talentosas de sua turma."},{"question":"بماذا يختص علم الأنثروبولوجيا؟","answer":"علم الأنثروبولوجيا هو علم يدرس الإنسان من حيث طبيعته الفيزيائية والاجتماعية والثقافية. ويُعرف أيضًا بعلم الإنسان أو السَّلاقة. ويُشتق اسم الأنثروبولوجيا من الكلمة اليونانية \\"Anthropos\\" والتي تعني \\"إنسان\\" و \\"Logos\\" والتي تعني \\"علم\\"."},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਸਿਰੀਰਾਗੁ ਮਹਲਾ ੫ ॥ਮਨੁ ਤਨੁ ਧਨੁ ਜਿਨਿ ਪ੍ਰਭਿ ਦੀਆ ਰਖਿਆ ਸਹਜਿ ਸਵਾਰਿ ॥ਸਰਬ ਕਲਾ ਕਰਿ ਥਾਪਿਆ ਅੰਤਰਿ ਜੋਤਿ ਅਪਾਰ ॥ਸਦਾ ਸਦਾ ਪ੍ਰਭੁ ਸਿਮਰੀਐ ਅੰਤਰਿ ਰਖੁ ਉਰ ਧਾਰਿ ॥੧॥ਮੇਰੇ ਮਨ ਹਰਿ ਬਿਨੁ ਅਵਰੁ ਨ ਕੋਇ ॥ਪ੍ਰਭ ਸਰਣਾਈ ਸਦਾ ਰਹੁ ਦੂਖੁ ਨ ਵਿਆਪੈ ਕੋਇ ॥੧॥ ਰਹਾਉ ॥ਰਤਨ ਪਦਾਰਥ ਮਾਣਕਾ ਸੁਇਨਾ ਰੁਪਾ ਖਾਕੁ ॥ਮਾਤ ਪਿਤਾ ਸੁਤ ਬੰਧਪਾ ਕੂੜੇ ਸਭੇ ਸਾਕ ॥ਜਿਨਿ ਕੀਤਾ ਤਿਸਹਿ ਨ ਜਾਣਈ ਮਨਮੁਖ ਪਸੁ ਨਾਪਾਕ ॥੨॥ਅੰਤਰਿ ਬਾਹਰਿ ਰਵਿ ਰਹਿਆ ਤਿਸ ਨੋ ਜਾਣੈ ਦੂਰਿ ॥ਤ੍ਰਿਸਨਾ ਲਾਗੀ ਰਚਿ ਰਹਿਆ ਅੰਤਰਿ ਹਉਮੈ ਕੂਰਿ ॥ਭਗਤੀ ਨਾਮ ਵਿਹੂਣਿਆ ਆਵਹਿ ਵੰਞਹਿ ਪੂਰ ॥੩॥ਰਾਖਿ ਲੇਹੁ ਪ੍ਰਭੁ ਕਰਣਹਾਰ ਜੀਅ ਜੰਤ ਕਰਿ ਦਇਆ ॥ਬਿਨੁ ਪ੍ਰਭ ਕੋਇ ਨ ਰਖਨਹਾਰੁ ਮਹਾ ਬਿਕਟ ਜਮ ਭਇਆ ॥ਨਾਨਕ ਨਾਮੁ ਨ ਵੀਸਰਉ ਕਰਿ ਅਪੁਨੀ ਹਰਿ ਮਇਆ ॥੪॥੧੪॥੮੪॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 47 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਅਰਜਨ ਦੇਵ ਜੀ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਬਾਣੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਹਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"ਜਿਸ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਨੇ ਇਹ ਮਨ ਦਿੱਤਾ ਹੈ, (ਵਰਤਣ ਲਈ) ਧਨ ਦਿੱਤਾ ਹੈ, ਜਿਸ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਨੇ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਦੇ ਸਰੀਰ ਨੂੰ ਸਵਾਰ ਬਣਾ ਕੇ ਰੱਖਿਆ ਹਜਿਸ ਨੇ (ਸਰੀਰ ਵਿਚ) ਸਾਰੀਆਂ (ਸਰੀਰਕ) ਤਾਕਤਾਂ ਪੈਦਾ ਕਰ ਕੇ ਸਰੀਰ ਰਚਿਆ ਹੈ, ਤੇ ਸਰੀਰ ਵਿਚ ਆਪਣੀ ਬੇਅੰਤ ਜੋਤਿ ਟਿਕਾ ਦਿੱਤੀ ਹੈ(ਹੇ ਭਾਈ !) ਉਸ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਨੂੰ ਸਦਾ ਹੀ ਸਿਮਰਦੇ ਰਹਿਣਾ ਚਾਹੀਦਾ ਹੈ । (ਹੇ ਭਾਈ !) ਆਪਣੇ ਹਿਰਦੇ ਵਿਚ ਉਸ ਦੀ ਯਾਦ ਟਿਕਾ ਰੱਖ ।੧।ਹੇ ਮੇਰੇ ਮਨ ! ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਤੋਂ ਬਿਨਾ ਹੋਰ ਕੋਈ (ਅਸਲ ਰਾਖਾ) ਨਹੀਂ ਤੂੰ ਸਦਾ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੀ ਸਰਨ ਪਿਆ ਰਹੁ, ਕੋਈ ਭੀ ਦੁੱਖ ਤੇਰੇ ਉੱਤੇ ਜ਼ੋਰ ਨਹੀਂ ਪਾ ਸਕੇਗਾ ।੧।ਰਹਾਉ।ਰਤਨ, ਮੋਤੀ ਆਦਿਕ ਕੀਮਤੀ ਪਦਾਰਥ, ਸੋਨਾ, ਚਾਂਦੀ (ਇਹ ਸਭ) ਮਿੱਟੀ ਸਮਾਨ ਹੀ ਹਨ (ਕਿਉਂਕਿ ਇਥੇ ਹੀ ਪਏ ਰਹਿ ਜਾਣਗੇ)ਮਾਂ ਪਿਉ ਪੁੱਤਰ ਤੇ ਹੋਰ ਸੰਬੰਧੀ—ਇਹ ਸਾਰੇ ਸਾਕ ਭੀ ਸਾਥ ਛੱਡ ਜਾਣ ਵਾਲੇ ਹਨ (ਇਹ ਵੇਖ ਕੇ ਭੀ) ਆਪਣੇ ਮਨ ਦੇ ਪਿੱਛੇ ਤੁਰਨ ਵਾਲਾ ਮਨੁੱਖ, ਗੰਦੇ ਜੀਵਨ ਵਾਲਾ ਪਸ਼ੂ-ਸੁਭਾਉ ਮਨੁੱਖ, ਉਸ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਨਾਲ ਸਾਂਝ ਨਹੀਂ ਪਾਂਦਾ ਜਿਸ ਨੇ ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਪੈਦਾ ਕੀਤਾ ਹੈ ।੨।(ਮੂਰਖ ਮਨੱੁਖ) ਉਸ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਨੂੰ ਕਿਤੇ ਦੂਰ ਵੱਸਦਾ ਸਮਝਦਾ ਹੈ, ਜੋ ਇਸ ਦੇ ਅੰਦਰ ਤੇ ਬਾਹਰ ਹਰ ਥਾਂ ਮੌਜੂਦ ਹੈ ਜੀਵ ਨੂੰ ਮਾਇਆ ਦੀ ਤ੍ਰਿਸ਼ਨਾ ਚੰਬੜੀ ਹੋਈ ਹੈ, (ਮਾਇਆ ਦੇ ਮੋਹ ਵਿਚ) ਜੀਵ ਮਸਤ ਹੋ ਰਿਹਾ ਹੈ, (ਮਾਇਆ ਦੇ ਕਾਰਨ) ਇਸ ਦੇ ਅੰਦਰ ਝੂਠੀ ਹਉਮੈ ਟਿਕੀ ਹੋਈ ਹੈਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੀ ਭਗਤੀ ਤੋਂ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੇ ਨਾਮ ਤੋਂ ਸੱਖਣੇ ਪੂਰਾਂ ਦੇ ਪੂਰ ਜੀਵ (ਇਸ ਸੰਸਾਰ-ਸਮੁੰਦਰ ਵਿਚ) ਆਉਂਦੇ ਹਨ ਤੇ (ਖ਼ਾਲੀ) ਚਲੇ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ ।੩।ਪਰ ਜੀਵਾਂ ਦੇ ਕੀਹ ਵੱਸ ? ਮਾਇਆ ਦੇ ਟਾਕਰੇ ਤੇ ਇਹ ਬੇ-ਬਸ ਹਨ) ਹੇ ਜੀਵਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਪੈਦਾ ਕਰਨ ਵਾਲੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ! ਤੂੰ ਆਪ ਹੀ ਮਿਹਰ ਕਰ ਕੇ ਸਾਰੇ ਜੀਅ ਜੰਤਾਂ ਨੂੰ (ਇਸ ਤ੍ਰਿਸ਼ਨਾ ਤੋਂ) ਬਚਾ ਲੈ ਹੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ! ਤੈਥੋਂ ਬਿਨਾ ਕੋਈ ਰੱਖਿਆ ਕਰਨ ਵਾਲਾ ਨਹੀਂ ਹੈ । ਜਮਰਾਜ ਜੀਵਾਂ ਵਾਸਤੇ ਬੜਾ ਡਰਾਉਣਾ ਬਣ ਰਿਹਾ ਹੈ ਹੇ ਨਾਨਕ ! (ਅਰਦਾਸ ਕਰ ਤੇ ਆਖ—) ਹੇ ਹਰੀ ! ਆਪਣੀ ਮਿਹਰ ਕਰ, ਮੈਂ ਤੇਰਾ ਨਾਮ ਕਦੇ ਨਾਹ ਭੁਲਾਵਾਂ ।੪।੧੪।੮੪।\\""},{"question":"ශ්‍රී ලංකාවේ තේ වගාවේ පුරෝගාමියා ලෙස සැලකෙන ඉංග්‍රීසි ජාතික වැවිලිකරුවා කවුද ?","answer":"ශ්‍රී ලංකාවේ තේ වගාවේ පුරෝගාමියා ලෙස සැලකෙන ඉංග්‍රීසි ජාතික වැවිලිකරුවා ජේම්ස් ටේලර් වේ."},{"question":"පහත වචනයට අදාළ විරුද්ධ පද කුමක්ද?එලිය ","answer":"අදුර"},{"question":"ලක්දිව රාජාවලිය ගැන විස්තර කරන්න.","answer":"මහාවංශයට අනුව ලක්දිව පළමු රාජධානිය ස්ථාපිත කරන ලද්දේ ක්‍රි.පූ. 435දී විජය කුමරුන් විසින් තම්බපණ්ණි රාජධානිය පිහිටුවීමත් සමගයි. විවිධ වෙනස්කම් වෙමින් වසර දහස් ගණනක් පැවත් එය ක්‍රි.ව. 1972 දී දෙවන එලිසබෙත් රැජිණගේ රජ සමයනේ අවසන් විය.මෙහි දැක්වෙන්නේ සිංහල රාජධානියේ අනුප්‍රාප්තික රාජධානිවල රාජ්‍ය කළ රජවරුන්ගේ ලැයිස්තුවකි.[1] මෙම ලැයිස්තුව දීපවංසය, මහාවංසය, චූලවංසය සහ රාජාවලිය වැනි දිවයිනේ වංශකථාවල සඳහන් සම්ප්‍රදායික සිංහලේ රාජාවලිය පාදක කොටගෙන නිර්මාණය කොට ඇත. මෙය සිංහල ජාතික රජවරුන් ලැයිස්තුවක් නොවේ. සිංහල රාජාණ්ඩුව පාලනය කළ සියලු සිංහල සහ විදෙස් පාලකයින් කාලානුක්‍රමය අනුව මෙහි පෙළගස්වා ඇත.මෙම රාජාවලිය පරිහරණයේ දී මනසේ රඳවාගත යුතු කරුණු කිහිපයකි. පළමුව, මෙහි ආදිතම රජවරුන් සඳහා දක්වා ඇති දිනයන් නිසැකවම තහවුරු කිරීමට අපහසු ය; හඳුනා ගැනීමට අපහසු දින (?) සංකේතයක් මගින් දක්වා තිබේ. එසේම වසර 2500ක පමණ ඉතිහාසය තුළ ශ්‍රී ලංකා දිවයින නොයෙකුත් විදේශ බලයන්ගේ ග්‍රහණයට නතු විය. ප්‍රධාන වශයෙන්ම දකුණු ඉන්දියාවෙන් පැමිණි ආක්‍රමණිකයින් මේ අතර ප්‍රධාන වේ. ඇතැම්හු සිහසුන පැහැරගෙන දිවයින සිය අධිරාජ්‍යයේ කොටසක් බවට පත් කරගත්හ. මේ සඳහා වඩාත්ම ප්‍රධාන නිදසුන් ලෙස ක්‍රි.ව. 985දී චෝළයන් සහ 1815දී බ්‍රිතාන්‍යයන් දැක්විය හැක. කෙසේනමුත්, පෘතුගීසි සහ ලන්දේසි යුගවල දී මහනුවර සිහසුන පැහැරගැනීමක් සිදු නොවූ අතර, දිවයිනේ ඇතැම් ප්‍රදේශ යටත් කරගැනීම පමණක් සිදු විය.කාලානුක්‍රමය පිළිබඳ සටහනබෞද්ධ යුගයේ පාදක දිනය වන ක්‍රි.පූ. 543 සම්බන්ධයෙන් නොයෙකුත් මතභේද පවතියි. ක්‍රි.පූ. 483 බුදුන් වහන්සේගේ මහා පරිනිර්වාණය සිදුවූ දිනය යැයි සැලකේ. විල්හෙල්ම් ගයිගර් සඳහන් කරන පරිදි දීපවංසය හා මහාවංසය දකුණු ආසියානු කාලානුක්‍රමයේ ප්‍රධාන මූලාශ්‍ර වේ; එහි දිනායනය කොට ඇත්තේ අශෝක අධිරාජයා‍‍ගේ රාජාභිෂේකය පරිනිර්වාණයෙන් වර්ෂ 218කට පසුව සිදුවූ බව ය. චන්ද්‍රගුප්ත මෞර්ය සිහසුනට පත්වූයේ මෙයට වර්ෂ 56කට පෙර, එනම් බුද්ධ පරිනිර්වාණයෙන් වර්ෂ 162කට පසුව ය. චන්ද්‍රගුප්ත‍ගේ සිහසුනට පත්වීම ආසන්න වශයෙන් ක්‍රි.පූ. 321 අවට වර්ෂ දෙකක කාලය තුළ සිදුවන්නට ඇත. (මෙගස්තීනිස් අනුව). එමනිසා පරිනිර්වාණය සඳහා ලැබෙන ආසන්නතම දිනය වන්නේ ක්‍රි.පූ. 485 සහ ක්‍රි.පූ. 481 අතර දිනයකි. මෙය ක්‍රි.පූ. 483 ලෙස ගැනෙන මහායාන කාලානුක්‍රමය සමග හොඳින් ගැළපේ.[2]ගයිගර් අනුව, මෙම ගණන් බැලීමේ දෙකෙහි වෙනස හටගෙන ඇත්තේ IIIවන උදය (946–954 හෝ 1007–1015) සහ පරාක්‍රම පාණ්ඩ්‍ය (1046–1048 පමණ) රාජ්‍ය සමයයන් අතර කාලයේ ය. මෙකල දිවයිනෙහි සැලකිය යුතු කලබලකාරී වාතාවරණයක් පැවතිණි.[2] කෙසේනමුත්, ක්‍රි.ව. 428දී චා-චා මො-හෝ-නාන් විසින් චීනය වෙත යැවුණු තානාපති මණ්ඩලයක් පිළිබඳ සඳහන් වේ. මෙම නම ඇතැම්විට මෙම කාලයේ රාජ්‍ය කළ (සම්ප්‍රදායික කාලානුක්‍රමය අනුව) 'රාජා (රජ) මහානාම' යන්නෙහි විකරණයක් විය හැක.[3]එපමණක් නොව, ක්‍රි.ව. 642දී පමණ ශ්‍රී ලංකාව වෙත සංචාරය කිරීමට උත්සාහ දැරූ දේශාටක භික්ෂුවක වූ ෂුවාන්සෑංහට ශ්‍රී ලාංකික භික්ෂූන් (ඇතැම්විට කාංචිපුරම්හි විසූ) විසින් රාජධානියේ එකල ගැටලු පැවති බව පවසා තිබිණි. ඒ නිසා ඔහු එම ගමනින් වැළකී ඇත;[4] මෙය සිහසුන වෙනුවෙන් අග්ගබෝධි III සිරිසඟබෝ, IIIවන ජෙට්ඨතිස්ස සහ දාඨෝපතිස්ස I හත්ථදාඨ අතර 632–643 කාලයේ පැවති අරගලකාරී කාලසීමාවට අනුරූප වේ.මෑතකාලීන ඉන්දුවේදීය පර්යේෂණ අනුව පෙණීගොස් ඇත්තේ බුද්ධ පරිනිර්වාණය මින් පෙර යෝජනා කෙරුණු දිනයට වඩා තරමක් පසු කාලයක සිදුවන්නට ඇති බවයි. 1988දී මෙම ගැටලුව සම්බන්ධයෙන් ගෝටින්ජන්හි පැවති සමුළුවක දී විද්වතුන් බහුතරයක් දැරූ මතය වූයේ මෙම ගැටලුව පවතින්නේ ක්‍රි.පූ. 440–360 අතර කාලසීමාව හා සම්බන්ධව බවයි. කෙසේනමුත්, ඔුවන්ගේ ගණනයන් පාදක වී තිබුණේ දීපවංසයගමහාවංසය මත නොව ටිබෙට් බුදු දහමේ කාලානුක්‍රමය මත ය. ඉන්දියානු පාලක සුසුනාගගේ පුත් කාලාශෝක සමග බින්දුසාරගේ පුත් අශෝක අධිරාජයා හඳුනාගැනීමට වැඩිදියුණු කළ කාලානුක්‍රමයක් අවශය වේ.[5] සැලකිය යුතු කරුණක් වන්නේ ශ්‍රී ලාංකික වංශකථා පාදක වී ඇත්තේ වඩාත් පැරණි කෘති මත වන අතර, ථෙරවාද බෞද්ධ ත්‍රිපිටකය පළමුවරට ග්‍රන්ථාරූඪ කෙරුණේ ද ශ්‍රී ලංකාවේ වීමයි. පහත ලැයිස්තුව කෙරෙහි පාදක කොටගෙන ඇති කාලානුක්‍රමය සම්ප්‍රදායික ථෙරවාද/ ශ්‍රී ලාංකීය ක්‍රමය මත ගොඩනගා ඇති අතර, එයට පාදක වී ඇති ක්‍රි.පූ. 543 දිනය මහායාන දින දර්ශනයට වඩා වර්ෂ 60ක් මුල් දිනයකි. කෙසේනමුත්, ක්‍රි.ව. 1048න් පමණ පසු දැක්වෙන දිනයන් එකිනෙකට සමකාලීන බැව් පෙනේ."},{"question":"De qual categoria é essa pergunta: Quem foi o quaterback da equipe que ganhou o Super Bowl 50?.","answer":"A categoria é esportes."},{"question":"تعريف مبسط في سطر واحد للمخاطر؟ ","answer":"المخاطر ببساطة هي إمكانية حدوث أحداث تؤثر على تحقيق الاستراتيجية وأهداف العمل."},{"question":"Que es la distribucion gaussiana?","answer":"La distribución Gaussiana (más comunmente conocida como distribución normal) es un modelo matemático que describe una amplia gama de experimentos aleatorios. Su importancia deriva de que muchos experimentos que son el resultado de una combinación de muchos factores (como fenómenos biológicos, errores de medición y resultados macroeconómicos)  siguen una distribución normal que se puede visualizar como una 'campana' de probabilidades centrada alrededor de un valor esperado (media o promedio) y cuyo 'ancho' lo define la desviación estándar."},{"question":"Inona no atao hoe fandatsaham-bato ary any amin'ny firenena aiza no anaovana izany?","answer":"Ny fandatsaham-bato dia fitsipika itakiana ny olom-pirenena hifidy amin'ny fifidianana. Manao izany, ohatra, any Aostralia sy Belzika."},{"question":"ما هو إسم المدينة المنورة قديما ؟","answer":" يثرب"},{"question":"Toлкoвaниe и знaчeниe cлoвa \\"бyдyчи\\"","answer":"Бyдyчи, дeeпpичacтиe нecoвepшeннoгo видa, oбpaзoвaннoe oт глaгoлa «быть». Oбoзнaчaeт cвязи мeждy coбытиями и oпpeдeляeт иx пocлeдoвaтeльнocть. Moжeт yпoтpeблятьcя в кaчecтвe зaмeны cлoв «являяcь», «нaxoдяcь», и т.п. Например, «He бyдyчи aнaлoгиeй жизни, иcкyccтвo нe имeeт место быть»."},{"question":"Given the following statement, predict the tags for each word: Claire Bailey-Ross claire.bailey-ross@port.ac.uk University of Portsmouth, United Kingdom","answer":"Here are the predicted parts of speech tags for each word in the sentence \\"Claire Bailey-Ross claire.bailey-ross@port.ac.uk University of Portsmouth, United Kingdom\\":Claire: PROPNBailey: PROPN-: PUNCTRoss: PROPNclaire.bailey-ross@port.ac.uk: PROPNUniversity: PROPNof: ADPPortsmouth: PROPN,: PUNCTUnited: VERBKingdom: PROPN"},{"question":"Escreva uma continuação para este parágrafo - Georgi Tringov () foi um jogador de xadrez da Bulgária, com diversas participações nas Olimpíadas de xadrez. Tringov participou das edições de 1956, 1958","answer":", 1962, 1964, 1966, 1968, 1970, 1978, 1980 e 1982. Individualmente, conquistou as medalhas de ouro (1968 e 1978) no segundo e terceiro tabuleiro, prata (1958) no primeiro tabuleiro reserva e bronze (1956) no quarto tabuleiro. Por equipes, ganhou a medalha de bronze em 1968."},{"question":"\\"विज्ञानाचा आणि प्रौद्योगिकीच्या विकासाच्या आत्मविश्वासाचा महत्व काय आहे?\\"","answer":"\\"विज्ञान आणि प्रौद्योगिकीच्या विकासाच्या आत्मविश्वासाच्या महत्वाने आपल्याला नविन आणि उन्नत तंत्रज्ञानाच्या क्षेत्रात सापडायला मदतील आहे. हे आपल्या समाजाला नवीन अवस्थेत आणि समृद्धि क्षेत्रात नेतो.\\""},{"question":"नेपालको वीरगञ्जको बारेमा भन।","answer":"वीरगञ्ज महानगरपालिका नेपालको व्यापार र ट्रान्जिटको पर्यायवाची हो र राजधानी काठमाडौंको दक्षिणमा एक व्यापारिक केन्द्र हो। सीमावर्ती सहर र \\"नेपालको प्रवेशद्वार\\" भनेर पनि चिनिने वीरगन्जलाई सन् १८९७ मा तेस्रो राणा प्रधानमन्त्री वीरशमशेर जङ्गबहादुर राणाले स्थापना गरेका थिए। व्यापारिक चासोका अलावा, वीरगन्जका प्रमुख आकर्षणका क्षेत्रहरू घडियारवा पोखरी, बिर्तामाई मन्दिर र वीरगञ्जको पुरानो नाम गहवाको सन्दर्भमा रहेको गहवा माई मन्दिर हुन्।"},{"question":"Ajàkálẹ̀-àrùn COVID-19 ní Làìbéríà","answer":"Àjàkálẹ̀ Àrùn COVID-19 ni wọ́n fìdí rẹ̀ múlẹ̀ wípé ó tàn dé orílẹ̀-èdè Liberia ní àárín oṣù kẹta ọdún 2020.Ní ọjọ́ Kejìlá oṣù Kíní ọdún 2020, Àjọ ìṣọ̀kan tí ó ń rí sí ìlera ní àgbáyé fìdí àrùn Kòrónà tí a tún ń pè ní Kofid-19 ní orílẹ̀-m àgbáyé ní ọjọ́ Kejìlá oṣù Kínní ní ọdún 2020. Tí wọ́n sì fìdí rẹ̀ múlẹ̀ wípé àrùn yí bẹ̀rẹ̀ ní ìlú kan tí wọ́n ń pè ní Wuhan, ní ẹkùn Hubei ní orílẹ̀-èdè China. Àmọ́ ó tó ọjọ́ Kẹtalélọ́gbọ̀n oṣù Kejìlá ọdún 2019 kí wọ́n tó fi tó àjọ ìṣòkan àgbáyé létí. Wọ́n tún fìdí rẹ̀ múlẹ̀ siwájú si wípé bí àrùn yí bá ti mú ènìyàn, oun ni ó ń fa ìfúnpinpin ní ní inú káà ọ̀fun ati àyà, tí ó sì ma ń fa kàtá tàbí kí ènìyàn ó ma wú ikọ́ tàbí sín léra léra. Iye ìjàmbá tí àrùn Kòrónà ti fà lágbáyé kéré sí iye ìjàmbá tí àìsàn àrùn ọ̀fun SARS ti fà láti ọdún 2003. Àmọ́ iye àwọn ènìyàn tí wọ́n tó àrùn Kòrónà látàrí ríràn tí ó ń ràn kálẹ̀ ti.pọ̀ ju ti SARS lọ, bí ó ti lẹ̀ jẹ́ wípé ìtànkálé àrùn COVID-19 ń gbópọn si lójojúmọ́ tí ó sì ti ṣekú pa ọ̀pọ̀lọpò ènìyàn lágbáyé.Oṣù kẹta ọdún 2020Ní ọjọ́ kẹrìndínlógún oṣù kẹta, ni wọ́n ní akọsílẹ̀ arùn COVID-19 akọ́kọ́ ní orílẹ̀-èdè Liberia lára ẹnìkan tí ó jẹ́ oníṣẹ́ ìlera tí ń bọ̀ láti orílẹ̀-èdè Switzerland. Ààrẹ orílẹ̀-èdè Liberia ọ̀gbẹ́ni George Weah fún aláàrẹ̀ náà ní orúkọ kan látàrí ìlòdì sí òfin àyẹ̀wò ní pápákọ̀ òfurufú Roberts International Airport (RIA) ní ìlú Harbel. Àkọsílẹ̀ ẹlẹ́kejì ni wọ́n rí ní ọjọ́ kẹtàdínlógún oṣù kẹta, ẹni náà ni ó ti fara kínra pẹ́lú ẹni akọ́kọ́.Ẹni kẹta tí ó fara kó àrùn COVID-9 jẹ́ ẹni tí ó ń darí ìrìn-àjò bò láti orílẹ̀-èdè kan. Lẹ́yìn tí ẹni kẹ́ta ti fara káṣá tán, ilé-iṣẹ́ ìjọba tí ó ń rí sí ìlera kéde ètò ìlera pàjáwìrì ní orílẹ̀-èdè Liberia ní ọjọ́ kejìlélógún oṣù kẹta.Ní ọjọ́ kẹrìnlá oṣù kẹta, orílẹ̀-èdè olómìnira Ivory Coast kéde títi ibodè ilẹ̀ rẹ̀ pa pẹ̀lú orílẹ̀-èdè Liberia àti orílẹ̀-èdè Guinea léte ati dènà ajàkálẹ̀ àrùn COVID-19.Ní ọjọ́ kẹtàdínlọ́gbọ̀n oṣù kẹta, ilé-iṣẹ́ àṣojú ilẹ̀ Amẹ́ríkà kó lára àwọn ọmọ orílẹ̀-èdè rẹ̀ kúrò ní orílẹ̀-èdè Liberia. Nígbà tí oṣù kẹta yóò fi parí, àwọn aláàrẹ̀ mẹ́ta yí náà nìkan ni wọ́n ṣì rí tí wọn kò sì rí òmíràn mọ́.Oṣù kẹrin ọdún 2020Ní ọjọ́ kẹrin oṣù kẹrin, orílẹ̀-èdè Liberia pàdánù ẹni akọ́kọ́ ní oṣù kẹrin.[16] Ní ọjọ́ Karùún oṣù kẹrin ilé-iṣẹ́ aṣojú orílẹ̀-èdè Germany pẹ́lú àjọṣepọ̀ Europian Union ṣe agbékalẹ̀ ọkọ̀ òfurufú kan tí yóò kó gbogbo ọmọ orílẹ̀-èdè wọn kúrò. Ní ọjọ́ keje oṣù kẹrin, Ààrẹ George Weah yan ìgbìmọ̀ alákòódo tuntun amúṣẹ́ṣe pàjáwìrì fún ajàkálẹ̀ àrùn COVID-19 lábẹ́ adarí alákòóso olú ìlú Monrovia, ìyẹn Abilékọ Mary Broh. Púpọ̀ nínú àwọn akọ́ṣẹ́mọṣẹ́ ni wọ́n jáyà lórí bí Abilékọ Broh yóò ṣe lè darí ìgbìmò amúṣẹ́ṣe náà láì ní ìmò tó peregedé nípa ètò ìlera, amọ́ yíyan sípò rẹ̀ gẹ́gẹ́ bí aláṣẹ ìgbìmò ọ̀hún ló lọ́wọ́ ajọ ìṣọ̀kan agbàyé nínú, pàá pàá jùlọ ilé-iṣẹ́ tí ó ń rí sí ìlera ní agbáyé.WHO.Ní ọjọ́ kẹjọ oṣù kẹrin, Ààrẹ George Weah kéde òfin kónílé-ó-gbélé tí ó bẹ̀rẹ̀ ní ọjọ́ Kẹwàá tí yóò sì wà ní mímúlò fún ọ̀sẹ̀ mẹ́ta. Gbogbo àwọn ilé-ẹ̀kọ́, ilé-ìjọsìn, ilé;ìgbafẹ́ òun ìtura ni wọ́n wà ní títì pa jákè-jádò orílẹ̀-èdè náà. Àjọ elétò ìlera ti Orílẹ̀-èdè Liberia ti ṣe akọsílẹ̀ iye àwọn ènìyàn tí wọ́n tàn lu gúdẹ àìsàn àrùn Kòrónà láti mẹ́rìnlá sí mọ́kanlélọ́gbọ̀n , tí wọ́n sì padánù ẹnìkan péré sí ọwọ́ ikú àìsàn COVID-19. Ilé ìgbìmọ̀ aṣòfin orílẹ̀-èdè Liberia ṣòfin Wíwọ ìbòjú ní àkókò àtànkálẹ̀ àrùn kòrónàfún gbogbo ọmọ.orílẹ̀-èdè Liberia, amọ́ wọ́n ní ṣíse òfin náà.ní dan dan rújú. As of that date, 29 confirmed cases were healthcare workers (out of 101 total confirmed cases). Láàrín oṣù yí, wọ́n ti ní akọsílẹ̀ tí ó tó ọgọ́rùún kan ati méjìdínlógójì, tí ó mú iye gbogbo àwọn aláàrẹ̀ COVID-19 lápapọ̀ jẹ́ ọgọ́rùún kan ati mọ́kanlélógójì ènìyàn. Àwọn márùndínláàdọ́ta ni ara wọn ti yá gágá tí wọ́n sì ti padà sí ilé wọn, àwọn mẹ́rìndínlógún ni wón ti papò dà, nígbà tí àwọn àádọ́rin ṣìwà pẹ̀lú àrùn náà.Oṣù Karùún ọdún 2020Iye àwọn tí wọ́n ní arùn náà tún lé méje si nínú oṣù Karùún, iye àwọn tí wọ́n ṣaláìsí jẹ́ mọ́kànlá, iye àwọn tí wọ́n rí ìwòsàn gba jẹ́ ọgọ́rùún kan ó lé méjìlá, nígbà tí àwọn mẹ́rìnlélọ́gọ́rún ṣì wà pẹ́lú àìsàn náà níparí oṣù Karùún.Oṣù Kẹfà ọdún 2020Ní ọjọ́ kejìlélógún oṣù Kẹfà, Ààrẹ George Weah kéde àfikún òfin kónílé-ó-gbélé sí ọgbọ̀n ọjọ́ dípò ọjọ́ mèẹ̀dógún tó ti wà tẹ́lẹ̀Nínú oṣù yí, wọ́n tú ní akọsílẹ̀ ènìyàn ọgọ́rùún márùún ó dín ní ẹyọ kan ṣoṣo, tí ó mú kí gbogbo àwọn tí wọ́n ti ní àrùn Kòrónà jẹ́ ọgọ́rùún méje ó lé láàdórin, àwọn tí wọ́n gbèkuru jẹ lọ́wọ́ ẹbọra jẹ́ mẹ́rìndínlógójì, àwọn ènìyàn ọgọ́rùún mẹ́ta ó lé mẹ́rìnlélógún ti gba ìwòsàn tí ó sì ku àwọn ọgọ́rùún mẹ́rin àti ogún ènìyàn tí àìsàn yí ṣì wà lára wọn níparí oṣù kẹfà.Oṣù keje ọdún 2020Nínú oṣù kẹjọ, wọ́n tún ní akọsílẹ̀ ènìyàn ọgọ́rin ó lé mẹ́rin ènìyàn tí ó fara káṣá àrùn COVID-19, àwọn tí wọ́n ṣaláìsí jẹ́ márùndínláàdọ́jọ, iye àwọn tí ara wọn yá gágá lé kún sí ọgọ́rùún mẹ́fà ati àádóje, nígbà tí àwọn tó kù tí àárẹ̀ náà wà lára wọn jẹ́ ọgọ́rùún mẹ́rin ati mókanlélógójì.Orílẹ̀-èdè Liberia jẹ́ ọ̀kan lára àwọn orílẹ̀-èdè tí ó kọ́kọ́ bẹ̀rẹ̀ sí ní ṣe ayẹ̀wò fún àwọn èrò inú ọkọ̀ òfurufú fún arùn COVID-19.Ní ọjọ́ kẹtàlá oṣù kẹta, orílẹ̀-èdè China ṣe ìtọrẹ àánú nípa fífún ìjọba orílẹ̀-èdè Liberia ní àwọn irinṣẹ́ ìlera lórisirísi.Ní ọjọ́ kẹtàlá oṣù kẹrin àjọ tí ó ń rí sí okòwò lágbaáyé forí owó tùlù tulu kan tí wọn kò sọ iye tí jẹ́ jin orílẹ̀-èdè náà. oríṣiríṣi àríwísí ni ó ti ń jà ràn-ìn ràn-ìn bóyá kí wọ́n ma dárúkọ àwọn ènìyàn tí wọ́n ti ní arùn Kòrónà fáráyé gbọ́, amọ́ ìpinnu ilé-iṣẹ́ ètò ìlera àgbà fún.orílẹ̀-èdè Liberia ni wípé àwọn kò ní orúkọ ẹnikẹ́ni léde wípé ó ní àrùn COVID-19. Ṣùgbọ́n, wọ́n ní láti fi orúkọ àwọn adarí ìjọba bí Ààrẹ ati àwọn.mìíra léde kí èyí lè jẹ́ àwòkọ́ṣe fún ẹnikẹ́ni tó bá ní àrùn COVID-19 wípé kìí ṣe òpin ayé àti wípé bí wọn kò bá yọjú, ó léwu fún wọn púpọ̀."},{"question":"\\"කුඩා ගමේ මද්දහනේ\\" ගීතයේ ඉතිරි පද සම්පූර්ණ කරන්න.","answer":"කුඩා ගමේ මද්දහනේ අව් රස්නේ මෙමාහුරේ කඳු පෙතේ දඩ මං දිගේ ගියා මෙමාඑවන් ගමන් මා නම් ගියෙ සෙනෙහස ගැන සිතානුඹේ කරට රිදී පොටක් පළඳන්නයි සුබාමගේ පැළට නුඹ කැන්දං පැමිණි දොහේ එදාමල් ගෝමර පිපුණු ලමැද වසා ගනිං කියාමගේ අතින් දුන් සළුවෙන් ලමැද වසා ගියාරිදී පොටක් කර ලන්නට වරම් නැතුව ගියාආල වඩන අකුරු පහේ තේරවිල්ල සකීරෑට නිදන තනි පැදුරේ නැති සිහිනෙකි සකීආලෙ බිඳුණු දා කුමකට කඳුළු හෙලනු සකීආල වඩන යන තේරුම බෝසත් කම සකීසුනිල් එදිරිසිංහධර්මසිරි ගමගේ"},{"question":"ਜਾਤੀ ਪ੍ਰਥਾ ਤੋਂ ਕੀ ਹਾਨੀ ਹੁੰਦੀ ਸੀ ?","answer":"ਜਾਤੀ ਪ੍ਰਥਾ ਨਾਲ ਨੀਵੀਆਂ ਜਾਤਾਂ ਦਾ ਸ਼ੋਸ਼ਣ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਸੀ, ਛੂਤਛਾਤ ਵਧਦੀ ਸੀ ਅਤੇ ਵਿਅਕਤਿੱਤਵ ਦਾ ਵਿਕਾਸ ਨਹੀਂ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਸੀ ।"},{"question":"“ ඇය “ යන්න උක්ත පදයක්ද? අනුක්ත පදයක්ද?","answer":"ඇය අනුක්ත වන අතර උක්තය ලෙස ඕ/ඈ/ඇය යෙදිය හැක."},{"question":"मंगळ मोहीम आखणारा पहिला अरब देश कोणता?","answer":"मंगळ मोहीम आखणारा पहिला अरब देश म्हणजे संयुक्त अरब अमिराती."},{"question":"Tambaya: Mi ake nufi da \\"horse\\" da Hausa?\\t\\t","answer":" Amsa: tana nufin \\"doki\\"\\t\\t\\t"},{"question":" Waxaad Sheegtaa Sanadkii uu dhashay General Maxamed Faarax Ceydiid?","answer":"General Maxamed Faarax Ceydiid Wuxu Dhashay Sanadkii 1934-Tii, Isla SanadkaanaWaxaa Dhashay Cabdullaahi Yuusuf Axmed."},{"question":"Slutför den här frasen: Krebs tävlade för Danmark vid olympiska sommarspelen 1912 i Stockholm, där han var med ","answer":"och tog brons i lagtävlingen i fritt system."},{"question":"Senegaal ñaata tariixa ñoo fi nekk ?","answer":" ñent"},{"question":"Căn hộ nằm trên tầng 3 của một khu tập thể cũ tại trung tâm Hà Nội. Theo chia sẻ từ chủ nhà, ban đầu vốn chỉ có 2 phòng gồm một khách, một ngủ. Nhưng vì muốn nới thêm không gian sử dụng, họ đã xây đua thêm một phòng ra ngoài ban công, rào kín lại thành \\"chuồng cọp\\".Tôi khá ưng căn hộ này vì vị trí gần nơi làm việc, xung quanh là trường học, chợ, bệnh viện, giá cả hợp lý. Nhưng phần diện tích chênh so với sổ đỏ khiến tôi thấy lo lắng, không biết quá trình sử dụng sau này liệu có gặp rắc rối và hướng xử lý ra sao?Rất mong được các chuyên gia và độc giả tư vấn!","answer":"Có thể gặp rắc rối. Trong quá trình sang tên mua bán, chuyên viên bên văn phòng đăng kí có thể xuống kiểm tra hiện trạng nhà. Nếu nhà xây lấn chiếm thì họ đề nghị khôi phục lại hiện trạng ban đầu rồi mới cấp sổ sang tên bạn. Nên rủi ro không sang tên được cho bạn là có thể xảy ra"},{"question":"¿Qué es una base de datos vectoriales?","answer":"Las bases de datos vectoriales proporcionan la capacidad de almacenar y recuperar vectores como puntos de alta dimensión. Las bases de datos vectoriales proporcionan capacidades adicionales (como la gestión de datos, la tolerancia a errores, la autenticación y el control de acceso) y un motor de consultas. "},{"question":"Dame un ejemplo de trivia de la siguiente categoría: literatura","answer":"¿Cuándo murió el autor que escribió Sin novedad en el Frente? Erich Maria Remarque murió el 25 de Septiembre de 1970."},{"question":"Apakah agam yang dianuti oleh Peranakan?","answer":"Baba dan Nyonya atau Peranakan Cina mengamalkan agama-agama tradisional Cina, menyambut Tahun Baru Cina dan Perayaan Tanglung, sambil mengamalkan adat resam Melayu dan penjajah barat. Pengaruh Portugis, Belanda, British, Melayu dan Indonesia meninggalkan kesan dalam budaya Peranakan."},{"question":"ආගමනය යනු කුමක්ද?","answer":"ආගමනය යනු නත්තලට එළඹෙන වසරේ සමයයි. එය කතෝලිකයන් සහ ලූතරන්, ඇංග්ලිකන් සහ මෙතෝදිස්ත වැනි අනෙකුත් ආගමික කණ්ඩායම් විසින් විවිධ සම්ප්‍රදායන් සහ චාරිත්‍ර වාරිත්‍ර සමඟින් නිරීක්ෂණය කරනු ලැබේ. මෑත වසරවලදී, බොහෝ එවැන්ජලිස්ත සේවාවන්ටද එක් ආකාරයක හෝ වෙනත් ආකාරයක ආගමනය සැමරුම් එකතු කර ඇත.ආගමනය යන වචනයේ තේරුම “පැමිණීම” හෝ “පෙන්වීම හෝ ස්ථානයට පැමිණීම” යන්නයි. කිතුණුවන් බොහෝ විට ක්‍රිස්තුස්වන්සේගේ “පළමු පැමිණීම” සහ “දෙවන පැමිණීම” ගැන කතා කරයි; එනම්, උන්වහන්සේගේ පළමු හා දෙවන පැමිණීම පෘථිවියට ය. උන්වහන්සේගේ පළමු පැමිණීම වනුයේ ආත්මභාවය - නත්තල් කාලයයි.ආගමන සමය ඉරිදා හතරක් පවතී. එය ආරම්භ වන්නේ නත්තලට පෙර සිව්වන ඉරිදා හෝ නොවැම්බර් 30 දක්වා ආසන්නතම ඉරිදාය. පැමිණීම නත්තල් සැන්දෑවෙන් අවසන් වන අතර එබැවින් එය නත්තල් සමයේ කොටසක් ලෙස නොසැලකේ. ආගමනය සැමරුම යනු ක්‍රිස්තුස්වහන්සේගේ පළමු පැමිණීම සිහිපත් කිරීම සහ උන්වහන්සේගේ දෙවන පැමිණීමේ අපේක්ෂාවයි. ඊශ්‍රායෙල්වරුන් තම මෙසියස්වහන්සේගේ පැමිණීමට ආශා කළාක් මෙන්, කිතුණුවන් ඔවුන්ගේ ගැලවුම්කරුවා නැවත පැමිණීමට ආශා කරයි.නැඟෙනහිර ඕතඩොක්ස් සභාවේ ආගමනය සමරන්නේ නැත, නමුත් ඔවුන් නත්තලට පෙර දිගු නිරාහාරව සිටිති. බටහිර රටවල, ආගමනය වඩාත් උත්සවාකාර ස්වරයක් වර්ධනය කර ඇත, නමුත් බොහෝ සභා ද උපවාසයක් පවත්වා යාච්ඤාව සහ පසුතැවිලි වීම කෙරෙහි අවධානය යොමු කරයි (සමහර විට, ආගමනය “කුඩා චතාරික කාලය” ලෙසද හැඳින්වේ). ආගමනය නත්තල සඳහා කෙනෙකුගේ හදවත සූදානම් කිරීමට සහ ක්‍රිස්තුස්වහන්සේගේ අවසාන නැවත පැමිණීම සඳහා (සහ උන්වහන්සේ ලෝකයට ගෙන එන විනිශ්චය) කාලයක් ලෙස සැලකේ.ආගමනය නිරීක්ෂණය කරන සභා සාමාන්‍යයෙන් ආගමනය, දම් (හෝ සමහර අවස්ථාවල රාජකීය නිල්) වන්දනාවේ වර්ණයෙන් ඔවුන්ගේ අභයභූමි අලංකාර කරයි. සමහර සභා ආගමනය හි තුන්වන හෝ හතරවන ඉරිදා දිනවල රෝස පැහැයට වර්ණය වෙනස් කරයි."},{"question":"Inona no maha samy hafa ny volkano sy ny geyser?","answer":"Ny volkano dia tendrombohitra na havoana miforona amin'ny fivondronan'ny fitaovana volkano, toy ny lava, lavenona ary vato, avy amin'ny fipoahana taloha na ankehitriny. Ny fipoahan'ny volkano dia mety hipoaka na mipoaka. Mifanohitra amin'izany kosa, ny geyser dia loharano mafana izay mamoaka tsindraindray ny rano mafana sy ny etona avy amin'ny fisokafana amin'ny hoditry ny tany noho ny fiakaran'ny tsindry ao anaty fitahirizana ambanin'ny tany. Ny geysers dia matetika mifandray amin'ny faritra geothermal mavitrika."},{"question":"టైఫాయిడ్ జ్వరం మరియు రోగనిరోధకతపై లఘుటీక రాయండి.","answer":"టైఫాయిడ్ జ్వరం :ఈ వ్యాధి సాల్మొనెల్ల టైఫీ అనే గ్రామ్ నెగిటివ్ బాక్టీరియా వల్ల వస్తుంది. ఇది ముఖ్యంగా మానవుడి చిన్నపేగులో నివసిస్తూ రక్తం ద్వారా ఇతర అవయవాలలోకి ప్రవేశిస్తుంది. ఈ వ్యాధిని వైడాల్ పరీక్ష చేసి నిర్ధారిస్తారు. సంక్రమణ విధానం : ఈ వ్యాధి కలుషితమైన ఆహారం, నీరు ద్వారా వ్యాప్తి చెందుతుంది.వ్యాధి లక్షణాలు :ఈ వ్యాధి సోకిన రోగికి 104°F వరకు పెరిగే ఉష్ణోగ్రతతో స్థిరంగా ఉండే జ్వరం, నీరసం, కడుపునొప్పి, మలబద్దకం, తలనొప్పి, ఆకలి మందగించడం మొదలైన లక్షణాలు కనిపిస్తాయి. వ్యాధి తీవ్రతలో పేగుకు రంధ్రాలు ఏర్పడటం, తీవ్రమైన స్థాయిలో మరణం సంభవించడం జరుగుతుంది."},{"question":"Tukarkan ayat aktif berikut kepada ayat pasif. Ayat: Kita menerima keputusan itu.","answer":"Jawapan yang betul ialah 'Keputusan itu kita terima.'"},{"question":"කාර්මික විප්ලවය යනු කුමක්ද සහ එය සමාජයට බලපෑවේ කෙසේද?","answer":"කාර්මික විප්ලවය යනු කෘෂිකර්මාන්තය, නිෂ්පාදනය, පතල් කැණීම, ප්‍රවාහනය සහ තාක්‍ෂණයේ මූලික වෙනස්කම් වලින් සංලක්ෂිත 18 සිට 19 වන සියවස දක්වා වූ කාල පරිච්ඡේදයකි. එය බ්‍රිතාන්‍යයෙන් ආරම්භ වූ අතර යුරෝපය සහ එක්සත් ජනපදය ඇතුළු ලොව පුරා ව්‍යාප්ත විය. මෙම කාල පරිච්ෙඡ්දය තුළ අතින් නිෂ්පාදන ක්‍රමවල සිට යන්ත්‍ර දක්වා සංක්‍රමණය වීම, නව රසායනික නිෂ්පාදන සහ යකඩ නිෂ්පාදන ක්‍රියාවලීන්, වාෂ්ප බලය වැඩි වීම, යන්ත්‍ර මෙවලම් සංවර්ධනය සහ කර්මාන්තශාලා පද්ධතියේ නැගීම සිදු විය. කාර්මික විප්ලවය දෛනික ජීවිතය සැලකිය යුතු ලෙස වෙනස් කළේය, නාගරීකරණයට දායක විය, ඇතැමුන්ගේ ජීවන තත්ත්වය වැඩිදියුණු විය, නමුත් දැඩි සේවා කොන්දේසි සහ දූෂණයේ සැලකිය යුතු වැඩි වීමක් ද ඇති කළේය."},{"question":"Quem foi Nelson Mandela?","answer":"Nelson Mandela foi um ativista e político sul-africano que lutou contra o sistema de apartheid e se tornou o primeiro presidente negro da África do Sul de 1994 a 1999. Ele recebeu o Prêmio Nobel da Paz em 1993 por seus esforços para acabar com a segregação racial e promover a reconciliação nacional. Ele é considerado um dos maiores líderes da história da África e um símbolo mundial de liberdade e justiça."},{"question":"Tháp Pisa được xây dựng trong bao lâu?A. 100 nămB. Khoảng 200 nămC. 300 năm","answer":"B. Khoảng 200 nămtháp Pisa được xây dựng vào tháng 8/1173 và hoàn thành vào giữa những năm 1300. Trong khoảng 200 năm xây dựng, tháp từng bị gián đoạn nhiều lần bởi chiến tranh, nợ nần và các kỹ sư tìm ra giải pháp để điều chỉnh độ nghiêng. Năm 1987, Tháp nghiêng Pisa được Tổ chức Giáo dục, Khoa học và Văn hóa Liên Hợp Quốc (UNESCO) công nhận là Di sản Thế giới."},{"question":"कवी केशवसुतांचे स्मारक कोणत्या जिल्ह्यात आहे?","answer":"मालगुंड रत्नागिरी"},{"question":"Hoàn thành tiếp câu sau: Người ta nói thu Hà Nội, đến là để yêu. Tôi đã từng thắc mắc mảnh đất Hà Thành cứ độ tháng 8, tháng 9 có gì làm nao lòng người đến vậy, do cảnh sắc hay hương tình khiến ai đã yêu rồi thì khó nhạt phai? Thật ra có đến ti tỉ thứ nhỏ xíu góp nhặt lại để tạo thành một vẻ đẹp riêng cho mùa thu Hà Nội. Những điều bé xíu ấy đủ sức khiến lòng người rộn ràng xốn xang cả một ngày dù bình thường chẳng ai để ý đến. Tất cả khiến tôi hiểu và rằng ai đã trải qua","answer":" thu Hà Nội rồi thì chẳng bao giờ có thể quên. Chớm thu, người ta gợi cho nhau chút ý niệm về một mùa tay trong tay, vai kề vai. Hay nói cách khác, là mùa của những câu chuyện tình. Chỉ đơn giản vào một ngày thu nắng vàng nhẹ nhàng vắt mình trên những ô cửa nhỏ, đôi gò má hồng của cô gái tuổi chớm yêu chạm khẽ vào đôi mắt của chàng trai si tình. Rồi ai đó cô đơn lại mong ngóng mình tìm thấy một nửa còn đang đi lạc, vun đắp mảnh tình bình dị giữa những ngày tháng thu trôi."},{"question":"من هو أول من أستعمل شوكه الطعام ؟","answer":"الملك هنري ملك فرنس."},{"question":"Manana teny mikorontana ianao:galasamyOmeo ary ny teny marina :","answer":"Ny teny marina dia \\"malagasy\\""},{"question":"Àjàkálẹ̀-àrùn COVID-19 ní Zimbabwe","answer":"Àjàkàlẹ-àrùn ẹ̀rànkòrónà (COVID-19) ni wọ́n fìdí rẹ múlẹ̀ pé ó dé orílẹ̀-èdè Zimbabwe ní oṣù kẹta ọdún 2020. Àwọon agbègbè tí ó wà ní orílẹ̀-èdè Zimbabwe, ní pàtàkì àwọn bi i Manicaland, Masvingo àti Mashonaland tí ó wà ní ìla-òor̀ùn orílẹ̀-èdè Zimbabwe paapa ti ń tiraka pẹ̀lú ìbújáde àrùn ibà kan tí ó ń ṣẹlẹ̀ ní àkókò kanna. Bíòtilẹ̀ jẹ́ wípé àrùn ibà jẹ́ àrùn tí ó ṣe é wò, ètò ìlera ń dojúko àító òògùn èyí tí ó fa kí ìgaara má a pọ̀si pẹ̀lú bí àjàkálẹ̀-àrùn COVID-19 ṣe ń tàn kálẹ̀.Ní ọjọ́ kejìla oṣù kini ọdún 2020, àjọ ìlera ní àgbáyé (World Health Organization) fìdí rẹ múlẹ̀ pé kòkòrò àrùn ẹ̀rànkòrónà ni ó ń fa àrùn atẹ́gùn ní àárín ọ̀pọ̀ ènìyàn ní ìlú Wuhan ní agbègbè Hube, orílẹ̀-èdè China, èyí tí wọ́n jábọ̀ rẹ fún àjọ ìlera ní àgbáyé ní ọjọ́o kọkànlélọ́gbọ̀n oṣù kejìlá ọdún 2019.Ìṣẹ̀lẹ̀ àrùn COVID-19 kéré púpọ̀ sí ti àrùn SARS tí ó ṣẹlẹ̀ ní ọdún 2003 ṣùgbọ́n bí àrùn COVID-19 ṣe ń tàn káàkàkiri pọ̀ púpọ̀, ní pàtàkì tí a bá wo iye àwọn tí ó ti jẹ́ aláìsí.Oṣù Kẹta Ọdún 2020Ní ọjọ́ kọkànlélógún oṣù kẹta ni orílẹ̀-èdè Zimbabwe kéde ̀ìṣẹ̀lẹ̀ àkọ́kọ́ àjàkálẹ̀-àrùn kòrónà ní orílẹ̀-èdè wọn. ̀iṣẹ̀lẹ̀ yí ni ti arákùnrin kan tí ó ń gbé ni Victoria Falls tí ó padà dé láti orílẹ̀-èdè àwọn aláwọ̀ funfun (United Kingdon) tí ó sì gba gúúsù ti orílẹ̀-èdè Afrika (South Africa) wa sí orílẹ̀-èdè Zimbabwe ní ọjọ́ karùndínlọ́gbọ̀n oṣù kẹta.[8] Wọn kò kéde pé ẹnikéni jẹ́ aláìsí gẹ́gẹ́ bí àwọn ìròyìn kan ti ṣèèsì sọ wípé ẹnìkan jẹ́ aláìsí láì mọ̀ pé aláìsàn yí ṣi n tẹ̀síwájú láti ya ara rẹ̀ sọ́tọ̀ ní ilé rẹ níbití ó ti n rí àpeere ìwòsàn.Ìṣẹ̀lẹ̀ méjì míràn ni ó tún ṣẹlẹ̀ ní Harare[10], orílẹ̀-èdè Zimbabwe ní ọjọ́ kọkànlélógún oṣù kẹta. Ní ọjọ́ kẹtàlélógún oṣù kẹta, wọ́n fìdí rẹ múlẹ̀ pé olókìkí akọ̀ròyìn ọmọ orílẹ̀-èdè Zimbanwe tí orúko rẹ̀ ń jẹ́ Zororo Makamba ni ẹni àkọ́kọ́ tí ó kọ́kọ́ jẹ́ aláìsí ní orílẹ̀-èdè Zimbabwe látàrí àjàkálẹ̀-àrùn kòrónà.Ní oṣù kẹta, ènìyàn mẹ́jo ni àyẹ̀wò fi hàn pé wọ́n ní àrùn kòrónà, ènìyàn kan jẹ aláìsí nígbà tí àwọn ènìyàn méje tí ó ṣẹ́kù ń gba ìtọ́jú títí di òpin oṣù kẹta.Oṣù Kẹrin Ọdún 2020Lẹ́yìn ikú arákùnrin Zororo, ènìyàn méjì míràn ló tún ṣe aláìsí tí àwọn tí ó ti kú wá di mẹ́ta. Nítorí àító àwọn ohun èlò fún ìlera, àwọn oníṣègùn kọ ìwé fi ẹ̀sùn kan ìjọba nítorí kí wọn lè ní ìdáábòbò tí ó péye nígbàtí wọ́n bá ń tọ́jú àwọn aláìsàn tí àrùn yí ń bájà. Ní ọjọ́ kẹtàlá oṣù kẹrin, wọ́n kéde ìṣẹ̀lẹ̀ mẹ́ta òmíràn èyí tí ó mú kí àpapọ̀ iye ìṣẹ̀lẹ̀ àrùn kòrónà ní orílẹ̀-èdè Zimkbabwe di mẹ́tàdínlógún.Ó kéré tán, àwọn akọ̀ròyìn márùn ún ni wọ́n ti mú fún ẹ̀sùn pé wọ́n ṣe àkójọpọ̀ ìròyìn lórí àjàkálẹ̀-àrùn COVID-19.Nínú oṣù kẹrin ọdún, ènìyàn mẹ́rìndínlọ́gbọ̀n ni àyẹ̀wò fi hàn pé wọ́n ní àrùn kòrónà tí ènìyàn mẹ́ta si jẹ́ aláìsí nínú un wọn. Iye ìṣẹ̀lẹ̀ tí wọ́n ti fìdí rẹ múlẹ̀ látìgbà tí ìbújáde àrùn yí ti bẹ̀rẹ̀ ti di mẹ́rìnlélọ́gbọ̀n. Iye àwọn tí wọ́n ń gba ìtọ́jú lọ́wọ́ ní òpin oṣù kẹrin ti di márùndínlọ́gbọ̀n (èyí tí ó ti lọ sókè pẹ̀lú ìdá ọ̀tàlénígba dín mẹ́ta nínú ọgọ́rùn ún(257%) láti oṣù kẹta.)Oṣù kárùn ún Ọdún 2020Nínú oṣù kárùn ún, ènìyàn mẹ́rìnlélógóje(144) ni àyẹ̀wò fi hàn pé wọ́n ní àrùn kòrónà. iye àwọn ìṣẹ̀lẹ̀ tí wọ́n ti fìdí rẹ múlẹ̀ látìgbà tí ìbújáde àrùn yí ti bẹ̀rẹ̀ ti di méjìdínlọ́gósàn án(178). Iye àwọn tí wọn ń gba ìtọ́jú lọ́wọ́ ní òpin oṣù kárùn ún jẹ́ márùndínláàdọ́jọ(145) (èyí tí ó ti lọ sókè pẹ̀lú ìdá 480 nínú ọgọ́rùn ún(480%) láti oṣù kẹrin.)Oṣù Kẹfà Ọdún 2020Ní ọjọ́ kejìlá oṣù kẹfà, ẹgbẹ́ aláré ìdárayá ti kirikẹti (Indian national cricket team) kéde wípé àwọn ti fagilé ìrìn-àjò wọn tí wọ́n ti gbèrò pé àwọn fẹ́ ṣe lọ sí orílẹ̀-èdè Zimbabwe ní oṣù kẹjọ ọdún 2020.Mínísítà fún ètò ìlera, Obadiah Moyo, ni wọ́n mú lábẹ́ òfin nítorì ẹ̀sùn èèrú ṣíṣe lórí owó tí ó lé ní milionu mẹ́rin dọ́là owó ilẹ̀ Améríkà (US4million) pẹ̀lú ọmọ Alákòso ọkùnrin, Collins Mnangagwa, èyí tí ó ní ṣe pẹ̀lú ríra àwọn ǹ kan èlò fún ídáàbòbò ara ẹni fún àwọn òṣìṣẹ́ ìlera ní ọ̀nà àìtọ́.Ní oṣù kẹfà, àwọn ènìyàn irinwó àti mẹ́tàlá(413) ni àyẹ̀wò fi hàn pé wón ní àrùn kòrónà èyí tí ó mú kí àpapọ̀ iye àwọn ìṣẹ̀lẹ̀ tí wọ́n ti fìdí rẹ múlẹ̀ láti ìgbàtí ìbújáde àrùn yí ti bẹ̀rẹ̀ di 591. Iye àwọn tí wọ́n ti jẹ́ aláìsí lọ sókè si méje. Ní òpin oṣù kẹfà, àwọn aláìsàn 422 ni ó ń gba ìtọ́jú lọ́wọ́, èyí tí ó lọ sókè pẹ̀lú ìdá mọ́kànléláàdọ́wàá nínú ọgọ́rùn-ún (191%) láti òpin oṣù kárùn-ún.Oṣù Keje Ọdún 2020Ilé-iṣẹ́ ọlọ́pàá ti kéde wípé àwọn ènìyàn 105,000 ni àwọn ti mú fún ẹ̀sùn lílòdì sí àwọn ìgbésẹ̀ ètò ìlera láti dẹ́kun àrùn COVID-19 láti oṣù kẹta; eléyì í pẹ̀lú àwọn ẹgbẹ̀rún ún ènìyàn tí wọ́n mú nítorí pé wọn kò wọ ìbòmú ní ọjọ́ kejìdínlógún àti ọjọ́ kọkàndínlógún oṣù keje.Ní ọjọ́ kankàndílógún oṣù keje, orílẹ̀-èdè Zimbabwe kéde ìsénimọ́lé kónílé ó gbélé ṣùgbọ́n wọ́n gba àwọn tí wọn ń ṣe iṣẹ́ pàtàkì nìkan láàyè láti ṣe iṣẹ́ laarin agogo mẹ́jọ òwúrọ̀ sí agogo mẹ́ta ọ̀sán. Wọ́n fi ẹ̀sùn kan ìjọba pé ìjọba ń lo ànfààní àjàkálẹ̀-àrùn yí láti fi lòdì sí ìwọ́de tí àwọn kan ń gbèrò láti gùnlé lórí ṣíṣe owó ilu mọ́kumọ̀ku.Láti ọjọ́ kejìdínlọ́gbọ̀n oṣù keje ọdun 2020, orílẹ̀-èdè Zimbabwe kéde ̀ìṣẹ̀lẹ̀ tí ó tó 2,817 nínú èyí tí ogójì àwọn aláìsàn ti jẹ́ aláìsí. Àpapọ̀ iye àwọn àyẹ̀wò tí wọ́n ti ṣe jẹ́ 124,194 nínú èyí tí 68,194 ti ṣe àyẹ̀wò tí ó múnádóko (Rapid Diagnostic Test). Ìṣẹ̀lẹ̀ tuntun 2,578 ni ó ṣẹ́yọ ní oṣù keje èyí tí ó mú kí àpapọ̀ iye àwọn ìṣẹ̀lẹ̀ tí wọ́n ti fìdí rẹ múlẹ̀ láti ìbẹ̀rẹ̀ ìbújáde àrùn yí lọ sókè sí 3,169. Iye àwọn tí wọ́n ti jẹ́ aláìsí ti di mẹ́tàdínláàdọ́rin(67). Iye àwọn aláìsàn tí wọ́n ti gba ìwòsàn ti di 1,004 ó wá ku àwọn aláìsàn 2,098 tí wọ́n ń gba ìtọ́jú lọ́wọ́ ní òpin oṣù keje.Ní ọjọ́ kọkàndínlọ́gbọ̀n oṣù keje, Mínísítà fún ọ̀rọ̀ ilẹ̀, ètò ọ̀gbìn àti ìgbèríko (Minister of Lands, Agriculture and Rural Resettlement), Perrance Shiri ṣe aláìsí látipasẹ̀ àrùn COVID-19 lẹ́yìn ọjọ́ díẹ̀ tí awakọ̀ rẹ na ti farakó àrùn yí.Oṣù Kẹjọ Ọdún 2020Wọ́n jẹri si bi ìṣẹ̀lẹ àrùn kòrónà ṣe ń pọ̀ si ní ìbẹ̀rẹ̀ oṣù kẹjọ pẹ̀lú àwọn aláìsàn tó kú látipasẹ̀ àrùn COVID-19 tí wọ́n jẹ́ ìlópo, láti ogójì sí ọgọ́rin laarin ọjọ́ kejìdínlọ́gbọ̀n oṣù keje àti ọjọ́ kẹta oṣù kẹjọ.Ní ọjọ́ kẹta oṣù kẹjọ, márùn ún nínú àwọn òṣìṣẹ́ ilé-iṣẹ́ bí owó ṣe ń wọlé (Revenue Authority officials) ní orílẹ̀-èdè zimbabwe tí wọ́n wá láti Beitbridge níbi ààlà pẹ̀lú orílẹ̀-èdè South Africa ni àyẹ̀wò fi hàn pé wọ́n ní àrùn kòrónà. Eléyì í ló mú kí ilé-iṣẹ́ ìlera àti ìtọ́jú ọmọdè (Ministry of Health and Child Care) gùnlé ṣíṣe àyẹ̀wò fún ọ̀pọ̀lọpọ̀ àwọn òṣìṣẹ́ wọn àti ṣíṣe ìmọ́tótó sí àwọn ohun èlò wọn.Kí ó tó di wípé wọ́n fìdí ìṣẹ̀lẹ̀ àrùn COVID-19 múlẹ̀ rárá ni orílẹ̀-èdé Zimbabwe ni alákòso Emmerson Mnangagwa ti kọ́kọ́ kéde àkókò pàjáwìrì ní orílẹ̀-èdè Zimbabwe tí wọ́n sì dáwó rínrin ìrìn-àjò dúró àti fífagilé àwọn ìpéjọpọ̀ ńlá. Ọ̀rọ̀ tí Mínísítà fún ààbò ní orílẹ̀-èdè Zimbabwe, Oppah Muchinguri, sọ wípé ìṣẹ̀lẹ̀ àrùn ẹ̀rànkòrónà le jẹ́ ìbáwí Ọlọ́run lórí àwọn orílẹ̀-èdè aláwọ̀ funfun fún fífi ìyà jẹ orílẹ̀-èdè Zimbabwe fa àríyànjiyàn.Ní ọjọ́ kẹtàlélógún oṣù kẹta, alákòso Mnangagwa kéde àfikún àwọn ìlànà míràn láti dẹ́kun àrùn kòrónà.Títi ẹnubodè orílẹ̀-èdè Zimbabwe pa fún àwọn ìrìn-àjò tí kò bá ṣe pàtàkì ṣùgbọ́n wọ́n yànda àwọn ará ìlú àti àwọn ẹrù tí wọ́n bá ń bọ̀.Títìpa àwọn ilé ọtí, àwọn ibi ìgbafẹ́ alẹ́, àwọn ibi eré sinimá, àwọn ibi ìlúwẹ̀ inú odò, àti àwọn ètò eré ìdárayá.Ìpéjọpọ̀ àwọn ènìyàn kò gbọ́dọ̀ tó ààdọ́ta.Ṣíṣe àbẹ̀wò sí ilé ìwòsàn kò gbọdọ̀ ju ẹẹkan lọ ní ọjọ́ kan.Ní ọjọ́ kẹtàdínlọ́gbọ̀n oṣù kẹta, ìjọba kéde pé orílẹ̀-èdè Zimbabwe yíò lọ fún ìsénimọ́lé ọlọ́jọ́ mọ́kànlélógún bẹ̀rẹ̀ láti ọgbọ̀n ọjọ́ oṣù kẹta títí di ìgbà tí wọn ko i ti le kéde. Agbègbè ìwòran ti Victorial Falls ni wọ́n tún tì pa gẹ́gẹ́ bí i arapa àwọn ìgbésẹ̀ ìsénimọ́lé orílẹ̀-èdè Zimbabwe àti ti Zambia. Lára àwọn àgbékalẹ̀ fún ìsénimọ́lé ọlọ́jọ́ mọ́kànlélógún ni wọ́n ti mú rọrùn látàrí bí wọ́n ṣe gba àwọn ilé-ìtajà ńlá ńlá laaye láti tún má a ta ọtí. Ní ọjọ́ kejìdínlógún oṣù kẹrin, orílẹ̀-èdè olómìnira Zimbabwe ṣe àjọyọ̀ ológójì ọdún tí wọ́n gba òmìnira lábẹ́ ẹ ìsénimọ́lé fún ìgbà àkọ́kọ́ nínú ìtàn orílẹ̀-èdè Zimbabwe. Ní àkókò ìsénimọ́lé yi, ọ̀kànlénígba àwọn ìbújáde àrùn ibà ni wọ́n ṣe àkọsílẹ̀ wọn, àádọ̀rún(90) nínú wọn ni wọ́n lè kápá nígbà tí mọ́kànléláàdóje(131) àwọn ènìyàn ń kú.Àjọ IMF ṣe ìṣirò pé ó ṣe é ṣe kí ọrọ̀ ajé orílẹ̀-èdè Zimbabwe jooro pẹ̀lú ìdá 7.4% ní ọdún 2020 nítorí àbájáde ìṣẹ̀lẹ̀ àjàkálẹ̀-àrùn kòrónà.Ìyanṣẹ́lódì àwọn òṣìṣẹ́ oníṣègùn mú ìpalára wá fún dídènọ̀ àrùn kòrónà àti ìtọ́jú àwọn aláìsàn àrùn kòrónà ní oṣù mẹ́rin àkọ́kọ́ ti i ọdún 2020."},{"question":"Jawab soalan yang rumit ini: Adakah kedua-dua Pothos dan Tibouchina Aubl  genus tumbuhan berbunga?","answer":"Ya, betul"},{"question":"Labarin kura da akuya da harawa yana cikin nau’in labari naA) tatsuniyaB) kacici-kaciciC) ƙissaD) almara","answer":"D.Alma'ra mai wasa kwakwalwa"},{"question":"Manomeza ohabolana maro momba ny anjara.","answer":"Ireto avy ny ohabolana momba ny anjara:- “Bingo manao matso ka misalovana ny anjaran’ny sasany.”- “Misao-bady tanora ka manome zara ho an’ny sasany.”- “Ny adrisa aza tsy azo raha tsy andriana hilika, ka mainka fa ny harena.”- “Tarehy ratsy no tsy azo ovana fa ny toetra ratsy azo ialàna.”- “Tovolahy manambady antitra, ny loa-bary no ianteherana; atositosika anjara vadin’ny tena, avela toa Renibe.”-  “Mahaiza mionona fa izay no anjara”- “Aza mimenomenona amin’ny anjara fa tsy ny olombelona no tompon’ny lahatra”- “Vodin-tsobika aza mana-tandrify”- “Andevolahy maty hariva ka vovon’alika no anjara tafondro”- “Tsy misy mivavaka miankandrefana fa samy miatsinanana ihany, saingy ny harena mila vintana, ka raha tsy anjara tsy azo.”"},{"question":"what important event is this text about: Đội tuyển quốc gia Úc là đội tuyển mạnh nhất Châu Đại Dương ở thời điểm hiện tại. Thành tích tốt nhất của đội cho đến nay là 5 chức vô địch Cúp bóng đá châu Đại Dương giành được vào các năm 1973; 1998; 2002; 2008 và 2016.","answer":"Sự kiện quan trọng được nhắc tới là Cúp bóng đá châu Đại Dương diễn ra vào năm 1973; 1998; 2002; 2008 và 2016."},{"question":"Inu sọọsi ni Bayọ wa to ti n gbadura, lawọn ọmọ ẹgbẹ okunkun pe e jade, wọn si pa a n’llọrin","answer":"Ṣe lawọn ọmọ ẹgbẹ okunkun n rẹ ara wọn danu bii ila niluu Ilọrin, ti i ṣe olu ipinlẹ Kwara, bi wọn ti n para wọn ni wọn n pa awọn ti ko mọwọ mẹsẹ lati ọsẹ to kọja. Ẹmi to ti bọ n lọ bii rẹrẹ. Ni bayii, wọn ti tun ṣeku pa ọdọmọkunrin kan ti ọpọ eeyan mọ si Bayọ Lala, lasiko to n jọsin lọwọ ni ṣọọṣi Ridiimu to wa ni agbegbe Basin, niluu Ilọrin, nipinlẹ Kwara.ALAROYE gbọ pe owurọ ọjọ Aiku, Sunnde, ọṣẹ yii, niṣẹlẹ naa waye. Bayọ n gbadura lọwọ ninu ṣọọṣi ni awọn kan deede pe e lori aago pe ko maa bọ nita, ni kete to jade sita ni wọn rọjo ibọn lu u, ti wọn si ri pe o ku patapata ki wọn too fi i silẹ ninu agbara ẹjẹ, ti wọn si ba tiwọn lọ, iro ibọn ti awọn olujọsin gbọ ninu ṣọọṣi da ibẹru bojo silẹ ti ẹlomiran si fẹrẹ maa tọ sara, ṣugbọn lẹyin iṣẹju diẹ ti wọn ni awọn eeyan naa lọ tan ni awọn ero ile-ijọsin naa too jade sita, ti wọn si ba Bayọ ninu agbara ẹjẹ. Wọn sare gbe e lọ si ileewosan olukọni Fasiti ilu Ilọrin, ṣugbọn ẹpa o boro mọ, o ti jade laye.Agbẹnusọ ileeṣẹ ọlọpaa, ẹka ti ipinlẹ Kwara, Ọgbẹni Ọkasanmi Ajayi, fidi iṣẹlẹ naa mulẹ fun akọroyin wa, o ni iwadii n lọ lọwọ lori iṣẹlẹ naa, awọn yoo si fi oju aṣebi han ni gbangba.Ija agba awọn ọmọ ẹgbẹ okunkun meji ọhun, Ẹyẹ ati ẹgbẹ Aiye ti n waye lati bii ọjọ diẹ sẹyin, ti wọn si n pa ara wọn. Ọpọ awọn ti ko mọ nnkan kan nipa rẹ ni wọn si ti pa nifọna-fọnṣu."},{"question":"சூழலுக்கேற்ற உணர்வைத் தெரிவு செய்க.(சிரிப்பு, மகிழ்ச்சி, வருத்தம், வியப்பு, அச்சம்)பாட்டி புத்தாடை வாங்கித் தரும்போது ஏற்படுவது ________","answer":"விடை : பாட்டி புத்தாடை வாங்கித் தரும்போது ஏற்படுவது ___மகிழ்ச்சி"},{"question":"Schrijf een voortzetting van deze paragraaf: De 1/2 finales werden afgewerkt op 10 en 11 april 2010, de returns op 18 april 2010. Het duel tussen Umeå en Lyon werd echter uitgesteld vanwege de vulkaanuitbarsting onder de Eyjafjallajökull","answer":", waardoor vliegverkeer niet mogelijk was. Het duel werd uiteindelijk gespeeld op 28 april."},{"question":"Odpowiedz na to pytanie: Gdzie znajduje się Kornwalia?","answer":"Kornwalia jest to region w południowo-zachodniej Anglii. Jest to najbardziej wysunięte na południowy zachód hrabstwo Anglii, położone na Półwyspie Kornwalijskim, na zachód od rzeki Tamar."},{"question":"Deprem nasıl oluşur?","answer":"Depremin oluşumu şu şekilde açıklayabilirim. Yer kabuğu tektonik plakalardan oluşur. Tektonik plakalar yavaş ama sürekli bir hareket hâlindedir. Bu hareket sonucunda plakalar birbirleriyle çarpışabilir, birbirlerinden uzaklaşabilir ya da birbirlerine sürtünebilir. Bu plakaların birleştiği sınırlar olan fay hatlarında biriken enerji depremlerle açığa çıkabilir. Depremle ortaya çıkan enerji, sismik dalgalarla yer kabuğunda yayılarak binalara ulaşır."},{"question":"Qual é a capital do Vietnam?","answer":"Hanói."},{"question":"\\"Owó gọbọi là ń san lórí àwọn ọmọ wa àmọ́ ìgbéayé ẹlẹ́wọ̀n ni wọ́n ń gbé nílé ẹ̀kọ́ wọn\\"","answer":"Àwọn òbí àti alagbatọ awọn ọmọ ile ẹkọ ìjọba àpapò, Federal Science and Technical College, Usi Ekiti, ipinle Ekiti ti ṣe ifẹhonuhan alafia nínú ọgbà ilé ẹ̀kọ́ náà lórí ìtọ́jú àti ètò ẹ̀kọ́ àwọn ọmọ wọn.Àwọn obí àti alagbató náà fariga lórí ọ̀nà tí olùdarí ilé ẹ̀kọ́ ọhun, Balogun Adisa Olateju fi ń se akoso àti ìtọ́jú àwọn akẹ́kọ̀ọ́ náà tí wọn sì ni awọn fẹ ki ijọba gbe kuro ni ile eko naa ni kankan.Nígbàtí alága ẹgbẹ́ àwọn obi ilé ẹ̀kọ́ naa Bangbose Taiwo sọrọ, o fi ẹsun kan oludari ilé ẹkọ ọhun pe ko ṣe àmójútó rẹ daradara gẹ́gẹ́ bí àwọn tí wọn ṣáájú rẹ ṣe ń ṣe.Àwọn olufẹhonuhan náà lọ káàkiri inu ọgbà ilé ẹ̀kọ́ ọhun pẹlu orisirisi patako lọwọ wọn.Lara wọn akọle ti wọn kọ si awọn patako ni “A n fẹ oludari míràn,” “Adisa Balogun ma pa FSTC Usi run,” “Àwọn ọmọ wa kò rí itọju dáadáa ní FSTC Usi,” Eto ẹ̀kọ́ àwọn ọmọ wa nílò ayipada lọwọ Balogun, ìjọba àpapò ẹgba wá.”Àwọn òbí náà sọrọ lori bí agbegbe ilé ìdáná àti ibùsùn àwọn akẹ́kọ̀ọ́ náà kò ṣe bá ìgbà mú, tí wọn ní kó yàtọ̀ sí ọgbà ẹ̀wọ̀n.Wọn tilẹ sọ pé ọgbà ẹ̀wọ̀n gan dára ju ibi tí wọn kó awọn ọmọ àwọn sí, tí wọn sì ní oúnjẹ tí wọn n fún wọn gan kò ṣara loore fún idagbasoke tó péye.Adewumi Temidayo àti Olatuji Bamisile tí wọn jẹ obi ní láti nnkan bíi ọsẹ mẹ́ta tí àwọn akẹkọọ ti pada sile ẹkọ ni wọn kò ti gbà ìwé tí àwọn òbí san owó rẹ.Wọn tún ní gbogbo inú yàrá ibùsùn ni kò dára mọ rárá pẹlu owo yanturu tí àwọn òbí ń ṣàn.Lára àwọn akẹkọọ tó bá akọroyin BBC Yoruba sọrọ tí wọn kò fẹ dárúkọ ara wọn ní kó sì omi, ilé igbónsẹ̀ tó dára ati iná ijọba ninu ọgbà ile ẹkọ náà.Wọn sọ siwaju si pe oúnjẹ tí àwọn oludari n fún àwọn ko dara rárá, wọn tun bù ẹnu àte lu bí gbogbo òrùlé ilé ẹ̀kọ́ ṣe maa n jo ni ọpọlọpọ ìgbà ti ojo bá rọ.Lẹyin naa ni wọn ràwọ ẹ̀bẹ̀ si ìjọba àpapọ̀ láti tètè wá bá àwọn mójútó gbogbo ìwà ibajẹ ati iwa aibikita ti wọn ni olùdarí ilé ẹkọ náà n wu.Nígbàtí akọrin BBC Yoruba kan sì olùdarí ilé ẹ̀kọ́ ọhun lórí ẹrọ ibanisọrọ rẹ, ni oun kò tii gbó nkankan lórí iwọde ọhun."},{"question":"Con vật gian ác nào xuất hiện trong truyện \\"Cô bé quàng khăn đỏ\\"?a. Sóib. Sư tửc. Cáo","answer":"đó là con sóiCô bé quàng khăn đỏ là chuyện xoay quanh một cô bé và một con sói. Truyện có nhiều bản khác nhau, bản truyện in đầu tiên được biết đến trong một cuốn sách xuất bản năm 1697. Phiên bản phổ biến nhất của truyện này là chuyện được anh em nhà Grimm viết vào thế kỉ 19.Một cô bé quàng khăn đỏ đi vào rừng để đưa thức ăn cho người bà đang bị bệnh, con sói theo dõi và lập kế hoạch để ăn thịt cô. Con sói hỏi cô bé đang đi đâu và cô đã ngây thơ trả lời. Sau đó, sói bảo cô bé đi hái hoa.Trong lúc đó, sói đến nhà ăn thịt người bà và đóng giả thành bà của cô bé quàng khăn đỏ. Khi cô bé đến, cô cũng bị sói ăn thịt. Một bác thợ săn đã tới mổ bụng sói, cứu được cả cô bé và bà của cô. Đá được bỏ vào bụng sói và làm sói chết.Câu chuyện nổi tiếng này có nhiều cách hiểu khác nhau về nội dung ẩn chứa và những bài học được rút ra."},{"question":"كم عدد السجدات في كتاب الله تعالى؟ .","answer":" الجواب 15 سجدة"},{"question":"Apakah maksud \\"belanja bidan\\"?","answer":"Ia bermaksud upah yang diberikan kepada bidan yang menguruskan kelahiran bayi."},{"question":"Gịnị bụ azịza gwam gwam gwam(riddle) a? Gwa m ihe sịrị eze rachaa ntụ","answer":"Ọ bụ Ube (Pear)."},{"question":"Eyi ni bi wọn ṣe yinbọn pa Ẹbila, ọga awọn ‘One Million Boys’ n’Ibadan","answer":"Lẹyin oṣu mẹta ti awọn ikọ ọmọ iṣọta ta a mọ si ‘One Million Boys’ pa Moshood Ọladokun (Ẹkugbemi), ọga awọn tọọgi n’Ibadan nipakupa, wọn ti yinbọn pa Abiọla Ẹbìlà, ọga awọn ‘One Million Boys’ nigboro Ibadan.Awọn ikọ ọmọ ogun Ẹkugbemi ti wọn jẹ ọmọ ẹgbẹ ikọ afẹmiṣofo kan ti wọn n pe ni ‘Abẹ-Igi Boys’ la gbọ pe wọn lọọ ka a mọle lọsan-an ọjọ Aiku, Sannde, ọsẹ to kọja, ti wọn si yinbọn pa a gẹgẹ bii ẹsan pipa ti oun naa pa Ẹkugbemi ọga wọn.Ta o ba gbagbe, ọsan gangan, ọjọ Abamẹta, Satide, ọjọ kọkanla, oṣu kẹrin, ọdun 2020 yii, lawọn ọmọ ogun ikọ ‘One Million Boys’ lọọ ka Ẹkugbemi mọle ẹ to n gbe laduugbo Olúǹdé, n’Ibadan, ti wọn si gbẹmi ẹ lẹyin ija alagbara to waye laarin wọn. Niṣe lara awọn to foju kan oku ẹ n ṣẹgiiri nitori bi wọn ṣe fi ada ba oku ẹ jẹ to.Latigba naa lolori awọn ‘One Million’ ti wọn n pe ni Ẹbila yii ti di ẹni tawọn ọlọpaa n wa, oun naa ko si duro, niṣe lo sa lọ ti ẹnikan ko si gburoo ẹ n’Ibadan ati nibikibi nipinlẹ Ọyọ mọ.Ṣugbọn ko jọ pe ẹru awọn ọlọpaa lo n ba Ẹbila bii tawọn ẹruuku, iyẹn awọn ọmọ ogun ikọ ‘Abẹ Igi Boys’, o mọ pe gbogbo ọna ni wọn yoo maa wa lati pa oun lati gbẹsan iku ọga wọn, Ẹkugbemi. Nitori bẹẹ, sisa loun naa n sa kiri latigba naa. Nigba to si maa pada de, ko de sinu ile ti gbogbo aye mọ pe o n gbe laduugbo Kudẹti, adugbo Olomi lo lọọ fori pamọ si.Gẹgẹ b’ALAROYE ṣe gbọ, ni nnkan bii aago meji ọsan ọjọ Sannde yii lawọn ẹruuku ka a mọ ibi to fara pamọ si ọhun. Wọn ko si ba oun naa laabọ, oun paapaa pitu meje tọdẹ akọni n pa nigbo fun wọn. Ṣugbọn lẹyin iṣẹju bii meloo kan ti wọn ti jọ n dana ibọn funra wọn ya, ọga awọn ‘One Million Boys’ yii ṣubu loju ija, akọni kile aye pe o digbooṣe.Iroyin mi-in ta a tun gbọ ni pe awọn agbofinro ni wọn yibọn pa ọga awọn tọọgi to n da omi alaafia igboro Ibadan ru naa.Wọn ni Ẹbila atawọn ọmọ ẹyin ẹ bii mẹẹẹdogun ji obinrin kan gbe pamọ, ti wọn si ni ki awọn mọlẹbi rẹ lọọ wa miliọnu kan Naira wa bi wọn ko ba fẹ ki awọn yinbọn pa a. Iroyin yii ni wọn fi to awọn ọlọpaa leti ti ikọ awọn agbofinro ijọba ipinlẹ Ọyọ ta a mọ si Operation Burst fi lọọ ka a mọnu ile ọhun, ti wọn si yinbọn pa a, bo tilẹ jẹ pe awọn yooku rẹ ribi sa lọ.Nigba to n fidi iroyin yii mulẹ, agbẹnusọ fun ileeṣẹ ọlọpaa ipinlẹ Ọyọ, SP Olugbenga Fadeyi, sọ pe ninu ija nla, nibi ti ikọ ‘One Million Boys’, eyi ti Ẹbila ko sodi, pẹlu awọn ikọ eleto aabo ipinlẹ Ọyọ ti dana ibọn funra wọn ya lawọn agbofinro ti yinbọn pa olori awọn tọọgi naa.O ni oun ko ti i ni ẹkunrẹrẹ alaye nipa bi wọn ṣe pa ọga ọmọ iṣọta n’Ibadan yii lọwọ, ṣugbọn oun mọ pe kẹkẹ NAPEP lawọn agbofinro to yinbọn pa a fi gbe oku ẹ kuro loju ija ti wọn yibọn pa a si. Wọn si ti tọju ẹ si yara ti wọn n ṣe oku lọjọ si nileewosan ijọba pinlẹ Ọyọ.SP Fadeyi sọ pe awọn ọlọpaa ti gbakoso eto aabo agbegbe ibi ti wọn gbẹmi ọga awọn tọọgi naa lati dena ija igboro mi-in to ṣee ṣe ko tun waye nigba tawọn ọmọ ẹ ba n gbiyanju lati gbẹsan."},{"question":"અહીં ગુજરાતી નાટક ના કલાકારો વચ્ચેની વાતો નીચે મુજબ આપેલી છે:\\"લક્ષ્મી: અરે બોલોમાં ઇંન્દ્ર સાંભળશે.રાજા: અમારે તો બોલવું છે, કેમ જે હું નક્કી કરી આપીશ કે ઇંન્દ્રથી તમારૂ બળ ઘણું જ વધતું છે.લક્ષ્મી: મારૂં બળ કહો છો ?રાજા: હા તે વાતના સમ ખાઉ છું. જુવો એક વાર ઇંન્દ્ર કેની સહાયતાથી દેવ લોકનું રાજ કરે છે.ભીમ૦: પૈસાથી, કેમકે એની પાસે પૈસા ગદબદ છે.રાજા: વારૂં એને પૈસા કોણ આપે છે ?ભીમ૦: આ આંધળી ડોશી.રાજા: ત્યારે ઇંન્દ્રનો જગન કરે છે તે શા માટે, લક્ષ્મી સારૂં કે બીજા સારૂં ?ભીમ૦: એ જ સારૂં સૌ પૈસાને ચહાય છે, એ વાત કાંઈ છાની નથી.રાજા: ત્યારે એ જગન કરાવનારી લક્ષ્મી જ કે. બીજું કોઈ ? ​ લક્ષ્મી: ભાઈસાહેબ એવું શું બોલો છો ?રાજા: સૌ જાણે છે કે, લક્ષ્મી વિના જગનનો સામાન ક્યાંથી મળે ?લક્ષ્મી: કેમ ?\\"આ કલાકારો ની આગળની વાતો શું હશે?","answer":"રાજા: કેમ શું, જુઓને પૈસા વિના કાંઈ વસ્તુ મળતી નથી, ત્યારે તમારે ને ઇંન્દ્રને ટંટો હોય, ત્યારે એનું જોર કેટલુંક છે ?લક્ષ્મી: શું કહો છો ! મારી સહાયતાથી જગન થાય છે, એ વાત ખરી છે ?રાજા: ખરી જ છે તો, અને વળી જગતમાં કાંઈ સારી વસ્તુ કે સભામાં સનમાન તે પણ લક્ષ્મીથી જ મળે છે કે નહીં ? કહ્યું છે કે,सर्वेगुणाकांचनमाश्रयंतिમાટે સર્વે ગુણ લક્ષ્મીમાં રહ્યા છે.ભીમ૦: હા. ઠાકોર તમને પણ સાંભરતું હશે, તમે મને થોડા પૈસામાં વેચાતો લીધો છે, તે દહાડે હું તમારાથી પણ ગરીબ હતો.રાજા: વળી અમે સાંભળ્યું છે કે, ગુણકાને ઘેર કોઈ ગરીબ માણસ જાય છે, તેને તુરત કહાડી મેલે છે, અને કોઈ પૈસાવાળો જાય છે, તેનું સનમાન કરે છે.ભીમ૦: વળી જુઓ કે, પૈસા વિના કેટલાએક વડનગરા નાગર વાંઢા મરી જાય છે, તેનું એક ભજન બોલું છું.(પ્રભાતી) શીદને સરજાડ્યાં પ્રભુ નાગરની નાતે;સામી વળગણિયે સાલ્લો ન ભાળ્યો રાતીરે ભાતે.રાજા: આપણા જાડેજા રજપુત દીકરિયોને જન્મતાં જ કશુંબો પાઇ દે છે. તે લક્ષ્મીની જ કસરથી કે નહીં ?ભીમ૦: હા, ઠાકોર આપણાં ઠકરાળાંને કેવળ પીતળનાં ઘરેણાં કરાવીને ઉપર સોનાનો ગલેફ લગાવવો પડે છે તે પણ એટલા જ સારૂ.રાજા: વળી લક્ષ્મી જ સારૂં દરજી તથા વણકર લુગડાં બનાવે છે, અને ખેડુત ખેડ કરે છે. સુતાર, મોચી, ઘાંચી, સૌ પોત પોતાનો ધંધો કરે છે; અને માતાજી તમારી જ સહાયતા ન હોય તો સૌ લોકો નાગા ભુખ્યા રહે.ભીમ૦: એ વાત ખરી છે; તારા સારૂં જ ચોર વાટ પાડે છે ખાતર પાડે છે. અને કેટલા એક વ્યાજ ખોર લોકો બમણું વ્યાજ ખાય છે, ગાંમડાં ઉપર રૂપીઆ ધીરીને રાજાઓને ભીખ માગતા કરે છે, સોલ પંચાં બ્યાંશી અને બે છુટના એટલે એશી રૂપીયા ખાતે માંડે છે."},{"question":"Mene ne hukuncin wanda ya manta ya ci abinci alhalin yana azumi ","answer":"(a) Babu komai a kan shi(b) Azumin sa ya karye amma babu kaffara a kansa (c) Azuminsa ya karye amma babu kaffara akansa"},{"question":"Jubbantil mbind mii:Ba leen Yonent bu jóge ca Yàlla dikkalee di dëggal la ñu yor, gaa ya ñu joxoon ab Téere, ab kurél ca ñoom sànni Téereb Yàlla bi ca seen ginnaaw mel ni dañoo xamul!","answer":"Mbind mi jub a ngi nii:Ba léen Yonent bu jóge ca Yàlla dikkalee di dëggal la ñu yor, gaa ya ñu joxoon ab Téere, ab kurel ca ñoom sànni Téereb Yàlla bi ca séen ginnaaw mel ni da ñoo xàmul!"},{"question":"Peter fun ọmọ to bi ninu ara rẹ lo loyun l’Ondo, lo ba lo ṣeeṣi ni","answer":"Ile-ẹjọ Majisireeti to wa niluu Ọrẹ, nijọba ibilẹ Odigbo, ti ni ki wọn ṣi lọọ fi ọkunrin ẹni ọdun mẹrindinlogoji kan, Peter Moses, pamọ sọgba ẹwọn na, lori ẹsun pe o fun ọmọ bibi inu ara rẹ, Peter Patience, loyun.Iṣẹlẹ yii waye niluu Asẹwele-Korede, nijọba ibilẹ Odigbo, nibi ti olujẹjọ naa ti fipa ba ọmọbinrin ẹni ọdun mẹtadinlogun ọhun lo pọ titi to fi doyun laarin osu kọkanla, ọdun to kọja, si osu kin-in-ni, ọdun tuntun ta a wa yii.Agbefọba, Ripẹtọ Jimoh Amuda, ni afurasi ọhun ti ṣẹ si abala kejilelọgbọn ninu iwe ofin orilẹ-ede yii ti ọdun 2003, eyi to lodi si lilo ọmọde nilokulo.Agbefọba ọhun rọ ile-ẹjọ lati sun igbẹjọ siwaju diẹ kawọn ọlọpaa fi pari iwadii ti wọn n ṣe lọwọ.Ni kete ti wọn ti ka ẹsun kan soso ti wọn fi kan olujẹjọ naa tan lo ti gba pe oun jẹbi, to si n bẹbẹ pe ki adajọ siju aanu wo oun nitori pe aṣiṣe ko kan ọgbọn.Onidaajọ F. O. Ọmọfọlarin ni ki wọn ṣi lọọ fi ọkunrin naa pamọ sọgba ẹwọn titi ti imọran yoo fi wa lati ọfiisi ajọ to n gba adajọ nimọran."},{"question":"Apakah maksud peribahasa berikut: \\"bagai ayam hitam terbang malam; hinggap di pokok pandan, bergesek ada rupanya tiada\\"?","answer":"Ia bermaksud kejahatan yang susah dibuktikan oleh kerana tidak mempunyai bukti kuat"},{"question":"Di mana terletaknya Okinawa? ","answer":"Prefektur Okinawa (沖縄県, Okinawa-ken) adalah wilayah Jepun yang terletak paling selatan, dan terdiri daripada 169 pulau yang dikenali sebagai Kepulauan Ryukyu, di gugusan kepulauan sepanjang 1000 km, dari barat daya Kyushu hingga ke Taiwan, walaupun pulau-pulau di sebelah utara merupakan bahagian Wilayah Kagoshima.Ibu kota Okinawa, Naha, terletak di bahagian selatan pulau terbesar dan yang paling padat, Pulau Okinawa, sekitar setengah perjalanan antara Kyushu dan Taiwan. Kepulauan Senkaku juga diperintah sebagai bahagian dari wilayah Okinawa."},{"question":"ગાંધર્વ વિવાહ એટલે શું?","answer":"એક કુંવારી છોકરી અને તેના પ્રેમીના આપમેળે જોડાણને ગાંધર્વ વિવાહ કહેવામાં આવે છે. આધુનિક 'પ્રેમ' લગ્ન ગંધર્વ લગ્નને ખૂબ સમાન છે. આ તે વિવાહ છે જ્યાં છોકરો અને કન્યા તેમના માતાપિતાના જ્ઞાન અથવા મંજૂરી વિના લગ્ન કરી શકે છે. દુષ્યંતે શકુંતલા સાથે આ રીતે લગ્ન કર્યા. નોંધો કે આ માત્ર ડેટિંગ જેટલું નથી. અહીં કન્યા અને વરરાજા કોઈ પણ ક્રિયા કરતા પહેલા, કોઈ વ્યક્તિ, પ્રાણી, ઝાડ, છોડ અથવા દેવની ઉપસ્થિતિમાં પ્રતિજ્ઞા લે છે."},{"question":"まげわっぱ、稲庭うどん、きりたんぽといえば何県の名物でしょう？","answer":"秋田県"},{"question":"“二头肌”名称的根据是","answer":"它有两个起点"},{"question":"Kí ni àwọn Yorùbá máa ń lo ewé efinrin fún?","answer":"Àwọn Yorùbá máa ń lo ewé efinrin fún jẹ̀díjẹ̀dí."},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਗਾਵੈ ਕੋ ਜਾਪੈ ਦਿਸੈ ਦੂਰਿ ॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 1 ਤੋਂ ਲਈ ਗਈ ਇੱਕ ਤੁਕ ਦਾ ਵਾਕ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਨਾਨਕ ਦੇਵ ਜੀ ਇਸ ਬਾਣੀ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਹਨ।ਇਸਦਾ ਮਤਲਬ ਇਹ ਹੈ,\\"ਕੋਈ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਆਖਦਾ ਹੈ, ‘ਅਕਾਲ ਪੁਰਖ ਦੂਰ ਜਾਪਦਾ ਹੈ, ਦੂਰ ਦਿੱਸਦਾ ਹੈ’;\\""},{"question":"வாக்கியம் 1: அவெனா ப்ரெவிஸ், குறுகிய ஓட், ஒரு வகை புல் ஆகும், அதன் விதைகள் உண்ணக்கூடியவை. வாக்கியம் 2: குறுகிய ஓட்ஸ், ஒரு அவினா ப்ரெவிஸ், ஒரு வகை புல், மற்றும் அதன் விதைகள் உண்ணக்கூடியவை. கேள்வி: வாக்கியம் 1 மற்றும் வாக்கியம் 2 ஒரே அர்த்தத்தை வெளிப்படுத்துகின்றனவா? ஆம் அல்லது இல்லை?","answer":"ஆம் ஒரே அர்த்தத்தை வெளிப்படுத்துகின்றன."},{"question":"O que implica o 'Despacho de Suspensão do Processo'?","answer":"'Despacho de Suspensão do Processo' é a decisão do juiz que suspende temporariamente o andamento do processo, geralmente aguardando o cumprimento de alguma condição ou decisão de outro tribunal."},{"question":"Iza amin'ireto no safidy diso momban'ny volamena?1-Ny volamena dia miloko fotsy.2-Ny volamena dia lafo vidy.","answer":"Ny safidy diso dia 1-Ny volamena dia miloko fotsy."},{"question":"గుణసంధి గురించి రాయండి","answer":"అకారానికి ఇ, ఉ, ఋలు పరమైతే వానికి క్రమంగా ఏ, ఓ, అర్లు ఏకాదేశంగా వస్తాయి. ఏ, ఓ, అలకు గుణములని పేరు కనుక. దీని పేరు గుణసంధి.ఉదా :రాజ + ఇంద్రుడు = రాజేంద్రుడు (అ + ఇ = ఏ)రామ + ఈశ్వరం = రామేశ్వరం (అ + ఈ = ఏ)పర + ఉపకారం = పరోపకారం (అ + ఉ = ఓ)దేశ + ఉన్నతి = దేశోన్నతి (అ + ఉ = ఓ)రాజ + ఋషి = రాజర్షి (అ + ఋ = అర్)మహా + ఋషి = మహర్షి (ఆ + ఋ = అర్)"},{"question":"為什麼魚會游泳？","answer":"魚有特殊的鰓，能夠提供氧氣並幫助它們在水中移動。"},{"question":"文章からキーワードを選び、その解釈を述べなさい。 福岡市で行っている水泳の世界選手権で、アーティスティックスイミングの試合がありました。19日は、1人で泳ぎながら踊るソロの「フリールーティン」に32歳の乾友紀子選手が出ました。乾選手は、日本の神話に出てくる大きな蛇を表現して、足を使った技も成功しました。そして、ほかの選手より25点以上高い点で、金メダルを取りました。15日の「テクニカルルーティン」に続いて、2つ目の金メダルです。乾選手は、去年の世界選手権でもこの2つの金メダルを取りました。2回続けて2つの金メダルを取ったのは日本人で初めてで、世界では2人目です。乾選手は「大変な練習を一生懸命続けてきました。プレッシャーがありましたが、金メダルを取ることができてよかったです」と話しました。","answer":"この文章に含まれるキーワードとその解釈は以下です。- 選手権: 1）試合や大会で、いちばんすぐれた選手やチームに与えられる資格や地位。また、その試合や大会。- アーティスティックスイミング: 1）水中で、音楽に合わせて泳ぎながらおどり、美しさや正確さを争う競技。- 選手: 1）競技に出るために選ばれた人。- 神話: 1）大昔から伝えられた、神を主人公とした物語。宇宙や人間の始まりをはじめ、神々の活躍などを語っている。- 蛇: 1）体が細長く、足がなくて、うろこでおおわれている動物。種類が多く、毒を持つものもある。- 表現: 1）考えたことや思ったことを、言葉・身ぶり・絵・文字・色・音などで表すこと。また、その表し方。- 技: 1）技術。腕前。2）すもうや柔道などで、相手を負かすための動作。- 成功: 1）ものごとが思いどおりにうまくいくこと。2）高い地位や財産を得ること。- 金: 1）黄色いつやのある、値打ちの高い金属。こがね。2）値打ちのあるもの。3）将棋のこまの一つ。金将。4）「金メダル」の略。- メダル: 1）金属の板に、絵や文字などをうきぼりにしたもの。記念品や賞品などにする。- プレッシャー: 1）圧力。気持ちの上で圧迫を感じること。"},{"question":"Hãy hoàn thiện đoạn văn sau: Ngày 31/7, Mâu Thuỷ bất ngờ công khai hình ảnh được bạn trai quỳ gối tặng nhẫn đính hôn và hoa trên trang cá nhân Facebook. Tuy nhiên, bức ảnh khiến người hâm mộ tò mò về danh tính, khuôn mặt của bạn trai. Xác nhận với VietNamNet, Á hậu Hoa hậu Hoàn vũ Việt Nam 2017 - Mâu Thuỷ cho biết mình đã đính hôn. Tuy nhiên Mâu Thuỷ không công khai danh tính và chuyện tình cảm với bạn trai. Gia đình hai bên đã gặp gỡ, ủng hộ chuyện tình cảm của cả hai. Chia sẻ thêm với VietNamNet, á hậu Mâu Thủy cho biết cả 2 sẽ đăng ký kết hôn trong năm nay, và dự kiên làm đám cưới vào năm sau khi đã chuẩn bị kỹ lưỡng. Cô cho biết hạn chế chia sẻ về bạn trai nên mong mọi người thông cảm, chỉ muốn thông báo để mọi người biết tin vui của mình. Dưới bình luận, nhiều người hâm mộ thể hiện sự nuối tiếc khi người đẹp sinh năm 1992 chuẩn bị lên xe hoa. Á hậu Võ Hoàng Yến chia sẻ hình ảnh của Mâu Thuỷ trên trang cá nhân với trạng thái: \\"Giờ đây em đã lấy chồng\\"; Top 5 Hoa hậu Hoàn Vũ 2022, Hương","answer":"Ly chúc mừng người chị: \\"Chị tôi sắp lên xe bông rồi. Vui mừng khôn xiết cho chị Mâu Thuỷ\\". Nhiều người hâm mộ thể hiện sự phấn khích vì Mâu Thuỷ đã thực hiện lời hứa trước đó. Ngày 15/7, trước chung kết Miss Supranational 2022, Mâu Thủy hứa: \\"Nếu Kim Duyên đăng quang hoặc vào top 3, tôi sẽ lấy chồng trong năm nay\\". Khi Kim Duyên trở thành Á hậu 2 Miss Supranational, nhiều người hâm mộ đề nghị người đẹp thực hiện cam kết. Mâu Thuỷ được biết đến là người đẹp kín tiếng về chuyện tình cảm. Tháng 1/2020, Mâu Thuỷ chia tay mối tình tám năm, sau khi bạn trai chọn nhầm size giày cho cô. Mâu Thuỷ tiết lộ bạn trai là doanh nhân, quản lý gần 20 nhân viên. Sau khi đăng quang VietNam's Next Top Model 2013, Mâu Thủy gặt hái nhiều thành công trên các sàn diễn thời trang. Năm 2017, Mâu Thuỷ bắt đầu chuyển hướng sang lĩnh vực sắc đẹp khi ghi danh thi Hoa hậu Hoàn vũ Việt Nam và trở thành Á hậu 2. Người đẹp gây ấn tượng bởi sở hữu vóc dáng đầy đặn và phong cách thời trang bắt mắt."},{"question":"De que categoría es esta pregunta : ¿De dónde es el actor que interpretó a Benny el Jet Rodríguez en Nuestra Pandilla?.","answer":"La categoría de esta pregunta es: película "},{"question":"Ano ang mga kailangan upang makapagsimulang gumawa ng computer program sa inyong Windows PC gamit ang C# programming language.","answer":"Ito ang mga kailangan upang makapasimulang gumawa ng computer program sa isang Windows PC gamit ang C# programming language:1. Idownload ang Microsoft Visual Studio at iinstall sa Windows PC. Siguraduhin na kasama sa installation ang C# package.Pwede rin sundin ito:1. Idownload at iinstall ang .NET Software Development Kit o SDK sa Microsoft website.2. Magdownload at maginstall ng isang text editor na pwedeng gamitin para makagawa ng C# program. Isang halimbawa ng text editor ay ang Visual Studio Code."},{"question":"Waye Abacha?","answer":"Ganar Murtala Muhammad Abacha tsohon shugaban kasar Nigeria ne a mulkin soja. "},{"question":"د احمدشاه بابا تر ټولو مشهور شاعرانه شعر څه دی ؟","answer":"احمدشاه بابا په خپله مورنۍ پښتو کې د نثرونو ټولګه لیکلې ده. هغه په فارسي ژبه د څو شعرونو لیکوال هم و. د هغه یو له مشهورو پښتو شعرونو څخه د یو ملت سره مینه وه:ستا د عشق له وينو ډک سول ځيګرونهستا په لاره کښې بايلي زلمي سرونهتا ته راسمه زړګی زما فارغ سيبې له تا مې اندېښنې د زړه مارونهکه هر څو مې د دنيا ملکونه ډېر سيزما به هېر نه سي دا ستا ښکلي باغونهد ډیلي تخت هېرومه چې را ياد کړمزما د ښکلي پښتونخوا د غرو سرونهد فريد او د حميد دور به بيا سيچې زه وکاندم پر هر لوري تاختونهکه تمامه دنيا يو خوا ته بل خوا يېزما خوښ دي ستا خالي تش ډګرونه"},{"question":"ما هو الحيوان المائي الأسرع في العالم؟","answer":"سمكة الزعنفة الشراعية."},{"question":"TAMBAYA: Rubuta sittin da bakwai a matsayin lamba?","answer":"Amsa: 67"},{"question":"کچھ انوکھی اور مزے دار خبریں سنایے","answer":"جی ضرور، یہ رہے کچھ انوکھی خبریں: • دنیا کا سب سے لمبا پہاڑی سلسلہ کوہ انڈیز ہے جو جنوبی امریکہ میں واقع ہے۔ • ایڈا لولیس کو دنیا کی سب سے پہلی کمپیوٹر پروگرامر کے طور پر جانا جاتا ہے۔ • دنیا کا بدترین زلزلہ 1556ء کو چین میں آیا جس کے نتیجے میں 8 لاکھ 30 ہزار افراد ہلاک ہو ئے۔ • آرمینیا 301 عیسوی میں عیسائیت کو مذہب کے طور پر قبول کرنے والا پہلا ملک تھا۔ • اسنوکر کی ابتدا 1875ء میں ہندوستان سے شروع ہوئی۔"},{"question":"السؤال: من هو الصحابي الجليل الذي عند ذكر اسمه نقول ( كرم الله وجهه ) ؟","answer":"الإجابة: علي بن أبي طالب"},{"question":"મહર્ષિ અગસ્ત્ય વિષે જણાવો.","answer":"મહર્ષિ અગસ્ત્ય એ સપ્તર્ષિમાં ના એક તથા ઋગ્વેદના અનેક મંત્રોના, તેમાં પણ ખાસ કરીને પ્રથમ મંડળનાં સૂક્તોના તેઓ રચયિતા છે. આ મંત્રોનો પ્રાદુર્ભાવ તેમના માનસમાં બ્રહ્માજીની પ્રેરણાથી થયેલો મનાય છે. તેમનું ગૃહસ્થ જીવન લોપામુદ્રા સાથે જોડાયેલું, જેનાથી તેમને પુત્ર જન્મ્યો એનું નામ ઋભુ પાડવામાં આવ્યું હતું. પિતા મિત્રાવરુણ અને માતા ઉર્વશીના સંતાન એવા અગસ્ત્ય મુનિના વડીલબંધુ વસિષ્ઠ ઋષિ હતા. દૈવી સાધનામાં અગસ્ત્ય અને લોપામુદ્રાના ઉલ્લેખો થયેલા જોવા મળે છે. આ સિવાય અન્ય કોઈ વિગતો પૌરાણિક કથાઓમાંથી ઉપલબ્ધ નથી.ભગવાન આદિત્યના યજ્ઞમાં મહર્ષિ વરુણએ ઉર્વશી નામની અપ્સરાને દેખીને અને તેમનું વીર્ય સ્ખલિત થયું. આ વીર્ય માંથી કેટલોક ભાગ કુંભમાં પડ્યો અને તેમાંથી અગસ્ત્ય ને વસિષ્ઠ ઋષિ જન્મ્યા. તેમની ઉત્પત્તિ કુંભમાંથી થઈ તેથી તેમને કુંભયોનિ અથવા કુંભજ પણ કહે છે. તે પોતાનો આશ્રમધર્મ પાળતા, તે સમયે એક રાક્ષસ લોકોને દુઃખ દેતો. ઋષિઓની પ્રાર્થના પરથી તેણે સમુદ્રને પી જઈ કાળકેયનો નાશ કર્યો. આ પ્રસંગથી એનું નામ પીતાબ્ધિ પડ્યું"},{"question":"Ọwọ tẹ awọn mẹrin ti wọn lu ọlọpaa pa ni Dalemọ","answer":"Awọn ọkunrin mẹrin kan, Jẹmili Ismaila, Amidu Bankọle, Elijah Samson ati Moses Proboye lọwọ awọn ọlọpaa ti tẹ bayii lori iku agbofinro kan ti orukọ ẹ n jẹ Agada Akoh, ti wọn ni wọn lu pa ni Dalemọ,  Sango Ọta, lọjọ kẹtala, oṣu kẹsan-an yii.Ipinlẹ Kogi la gbọ pe ọlọpaa to doloogbe yii ti n bọ gẹgẹ bi Abimbọla Oyeyẹmi, alukoro ọlọpaa ṣe ṣalaye. O ni ọga rẹ lo tẹle wa lati Idah, nipinlẹ Kogi. Igba ti wọn de Sango ninu mọto wọn ti wọn n gbe bọ ni Jamili Ismaila toun n wa tirela wa mọto tiẹ niwakuwa, to bẹẹ to jẹ diẹ lo ku ko kọlu awọn ọlọpaa yii.Eyi lo mu awọn agbofinro naa sọkalẹ ninu mọto wọn, ti wọn si kilọ fun Jamili pe ko yee wa iwakuwa.Ṣugbọn wọn ni niṣe ni Jamili binu, to ni awọn ọlọpaa naa loun ko fẹẹ kọlu toun fi bọ si koto, ti taya mọto oun kan si bẹ. Ibinu naa ni wọn lo jẹ ko pe awọn ọmọ ganfe to wa nitosi lati gbeja oun, n lawọn iyẹn ba mu nnkan ija oriṣiisriṣii jade, ni wọn ba kọju ija sawọn ọlọpaa, agaga Agada to jẹ ọmọọṣẹ, bi wọn ṣe bẹrẹ si i lu u bii ko ku niyẹn.Alukoro sọ pe nibi ti wọn ti n lu ọlọpaa naa lo daku si, awọn ẹlẹyinju aanu lo sare gbe e lọ sileewoan Jẹnẹra Ọta, ṣugbọn nibi ti wọn ti n tọju rẹ lo dakẹ si.Awọn ọmọ ganfe to lu u sa lọ nigba ti wọn ri i pe ọlọpaa naa ti daku, ṣugbọn ọwọ pada tẹ awọn mẹrin yii, nigba tawọn ọlọpaa ṣọ wọn daadaa ni wọn ka wọn mọ ibuba wọn.Mọṣuari ileewosan jẹnẹra Ọta ni wọn gbe oku Agada Akoh si bayii, bẹẹ ni wọn ṣi n wa awọn ọmọ ganfe yooku to sa lọ."},{"question":"ਕਿਹੜੇ ਸਮਾਜ ਸ਼ਾਸਤਰੀਆਂ ਨੇ ਧਰਮ ਦਾ ਅਧਿਐਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਹੈ ?","answer":"ਦੂਰਖੀਮ, ਵੈਬਰ, ਟੇਲਰ ਆਦਿ ਨੇ ਧਰਮ ਦਾ ਅਧਿਐਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਹੈ ।"},{"question":"Da wane suna ake Kiran babban birnin Nijeriya?","answer":"Abuja shine babban birnin Nijeriya."},{"question":"روبوٹ کیا ہوتا ہے؟ اس کے بارے میں تھوڑا بتایے:","answer":"جی ضرور، یہ رہی کچھ معلومات روبوٹس کے بارے میں۔جدید دور میں روبوٹ سے مراد ایک میکانیکی یا غیر ماہیتی، مصنوعی سازندہ (agent) ہے۔ بالعموم روبوٹ ایک ایسے میکانیکی و برقی نظام کو کہا جاتا ہے جس کی حرکات و سکنات اور شکل و صورت سے یوں لگے جیسے اس میں خود سے قوت ارادہ یا قوت تغیر موجود ہو۔ غیر ماہیتی روبوٹ سے مراد سافٹ ویئر سازندے (soft ware agents) ہیں، جن کے لیے ”بوٹ” کی اصطلاح استعمال کی جاتی ہے۔ یہاں یہ بات قابل ذکر ہے کہ ہر خودکار نظام یا آلے کو روبوٹ نہیں کہا جاتا۔ ایک خودکار آلے اور روبوٹ کا فرق سمجھنے کے لیے روبوٹ کی مندرجہ ذیل خصوصیات کو مد نظر رکھنا ہوتا ہے۔روبوٹ کو مصنوعی طور پر بنایا جاتا ہے، یہ قدرتی طور پر موجود نہیں ہوتا۔ وہ نہ صرف اپنے ماحول کو محسوس کر سکتا ہے بلکہ اس میں تبدیلی بھی لا سکتا ہے۔ اس میں کسی قسم کی ذہانت موجود ہونی چاہیے، جس کو بروئے کار لا کر وہ اپنے ماحول میں تبدیلی لانے کا لائحہ عمل منتخب کرے اور پھر اس لائحہ عمل کو اپنے افعال کے ذریعے عملی جامہ پہنا سکے۔ مزید یہ کہ اس کو پروگرام کیا جا سکے، یعنی اس کی ذہانت و انتخاب میں بدرجہِ صلاحیت تبدیلی لائی جا سکتی ہے۔ اس میں جنبش و حرکت کی صلاحیت ہو جس سے وہ نقل و حمل کر سکے۔"},{"question":"地域によっては「おどし」「そめ」「そうず」などと呼ばれている田んぼに立っている物と言えば何？","answer":"かかしです。"},{"question":"ဆံပင်ကျွတ်ခြင်းကို ကာကွယ်ရန် အကောင်းဆုံးဆံပင်ပုံစံက ဘာလဲ။","answer":"ဆံပင်ကျွတ်ခြင်းမဖြစ်အောင် ရိုးရှင်းသောဆံပင်ပုံစံများကျစ်ဆံမြီးကျစ်ဆံမြီးသည် ဆံပင်ကျွတ်ခြင်းမဖြစ်အောင်နှင့် ရိုးရှင်းလှပတဲ့ ဆံပင်ပုံစံတစ်ခုဖြစ်သည်။ ဆံချည်မျှင်များ လုံးထွေးမနေတော့ပဲ ဆံပင်ကျွတ်ခြင်းကိုသက်သာစေပါသည်။ ကျစ်ဆံမြီးတစ်ခုတည်း၊ pigtails၊ boxer braids သို့မဟုတ် fishtail braid ကိုပင်သင်ရွေးချယ်နိုင်သည်။ ဆံပင်ကျစ်လျှင် အမြစ်များမနာစေရန် တင်းကြပ်စွာမကျစ်မိအောင် သတိထားရပါမည်။"},{"question":"Create a dialogue between two people with opposing views on a controversial topic.","answer":"दो व्यक्तियों के बीच एक संवाद बनाएं जिनके बीच एक विवादास्पद विषय पर विपरीत दृष्टिकोण है।"},{"question":"Su’aal: Sheeg goorma ayaa la-aas aasay gaanshaabuurto Nato?","answer":"Jawaab: Waxaa la-aas aasay Sanadkii 1949-Kii."},{"question":"شاهد افریدي له کومې قبیلې سره تړاو لري؟","answer":"شاهد افریدي چې په پراخه کچه د \\"بوم بوم افریدي\\" او \\"لالا\\" په نوم پیژندل کیږي د افریدي قبیلې څخه دی چې په پاکستان کې د پښتنو یوه مشهوره قبیله ده. افریدي قبیله د لوی پښتون قوم یوه برخه ده چې په عمده توګه د پاکستان او افغانستان پولې ته څیرمه په غرنیو سیمو کې اوسیږي.اپریدیان د خپلو بډایه قبایلي میراثونو لپاره پیژندل کیږي او د پاکستان په خیبر پښتونخوا ایالت کې قوي شتون لري په ځانګړي توګه په خیبر ایجنسۍ ، پیښور او قبایلي بیلټ کې. دوی په دودونو، قبیلوي اصولو او په ټولنه کې د یووالي قوي احساس لري.د شاهد افريدي د افريدي قبيلې سره تعلق د هغه او د هغه د ټولنې لپاره د وياړ خبره ده. هغه نه یوازې د پاکستان د کریکټ تر ټولو مشهوره څېره بلل کېږي، بلکې د افریدي قبیلې د استازي په توګه هم د هغه استعداد او لیوالتیا ښکارندویي کوي، چې پښتانه خلک یې له امله پېژني.د افریدي د کریکټ لاسته راوړنو هغه نه یوازې په پاکستان کې بلکې په نړیواله کچه هم شهرت او پیژندنه راوړي، چې هغه یې د کرکټ د مینه والو او د هغه د ملګرو افریدیانو ترمنځ یو محبوب شخصیت جوړ کړ. د هغه کرشمه، جارحانه لوبې کولو سټایل، او سپورت ته وقف هغه د کریکټ مینه والو په زړونو کې یو ځانګړی ځای ترلاسه کړ، چې د افریدي قبیلې څخه د یو مشهور شخصیت په توګه یې د هغه حیثیت نور هم پیاوړی کړ."},{"question":"முதலையின் இதயம் எத்தனை அறைகளாக பிரிக்கப்பட்டுள்ளது?","answer":"நான்கு அறைகள்ஊர்வன பொதுவாக மூன்று அறைகள் கொண்ட இதயத்தைக் கொண்டிருக்கும், அதே சமயம் நான்கு அறைகள் கொண்ட இதயத்துடன் முதலை விதிவிலக்காகும். நான்கு அறைகளை உருவாக்கும் இதயத்தில் இரண்டு ஏட்ரியம் மற்றும் இரண்டு வென்ட்ரிக்கிள்கள் உள்ளன."},{"question":"Niṣe lawọn ti wọn jo ile Sunday Igboho n yinbọn soke kẹu kẹu laarin oru","answer":"Ileeeṣẹ ọlọpaa ipinlẹ Ọyọ ti sọ pe ki i ṣe pe ile Sunday Adeyẹmọ ti gbogbo eeyan mọ si Sunday Igboho deede jona o, wọn ni awọn kan ni wọn waa dana sun ile ọhun, awọn janduku kan bayii ni.Ninu atẹjade awon ọlopaa ti alukoro won, Gbenga Fadeyi, gbe jade ni won ti ṣalaye pe awọn araadugbo naa pe awọn lasiko ti wọn n jo ile naa. Wọn ni ohun ti wọn sọ fawọn ni pe awọn janduku kan ti de si adugbo awọn ni Soka o, ile Sunday Igboho ni wọn si wa, ati pe wọn n dana sun ile ọhun lọwọlọwọ.Awọn eeyan ti wọn pe wọn yi ni wọn fi kun un pe awọn ko le jade, koda ẹnikẹni ko le jade, nitori niṣe ni awọn ti wọn waa sun ile naa n yinbọn soke kẹu kẹu, ti wọn n pariwo ẹni to ba to bẹẹ ko jade!Lẹsẹkẹsẹ ti wọn ti gbọ ọrọ yii ni wọn ti jẹ ki ọga ọlopaa, iyẹn DPO, wọn ni Sanyo mọ, ti wọn si pe awọn panapana, bẹẹ ni wọn ni ki awọn ọlọpaa tete lọọ ba wọn. Fadeyi ni wọn pa ina naa loootọ, ṣugbọn awọn ibi kan ti jona. Oun naa lo ṣalaye pe iwadii n lọ lati wa awọn ti wọn ṣe iṣe buruku naa ri laipẹ rara."},{"question":"1917 में जारशाही का पतन क्यों हो गया?","answer":"प्रथम विश्व युद्ध के कारण रूस में जर्मन विरोधी भावनाएँ चरम पर थीं। इसके अलावा, ज़ारिना एलेक्जेंड्रा के जर्मन मूल और गरीब सलाहकारों ने निरंकुशता को अलोकप्रिय बना दिया। रूस को समुद्र तट पर चौंकाने वाली हार का सामना करना पड़ा और लाखों लोग हताहत हुए। दुश्मन को कोई फायदा न हो इसके लिए रूसी सेना ने फसलें और इमारतें नष्ट कर दीं। इससे लाखों शरणार्थी पैदा हुए। इस स्थिति के लिए ज़ार को कोसा जा रहा था. भोजन की कमी के कारण लोग भोजन के लिए दंगे करने लगे। रूसी सेना ने भी अपनी वफादारी बदल दी और क्रांतिकारियों का समर्थन करना शुरू कर दिया।22 फरवरी को नेवा नदी के बाएं किनारे के मजदूरों के प्रति सहानुभूति प्रकट करते हुए दाहिने किनारे की एक फैक्ट्री में तालाबंदी कर दी गई। महिलाओं ने हड़ताल का नेतृत्व किया। सरकार ने कर्फ्यू लगा दिया. बाद में सरकार ने ड्यूमा को निलंबित कर दिया जिसके परिणामस्वरूप तीव्र विरोध हुआ। प्रदर्शनकारियों ने पुलिस मुख्यालय में तोड़फोड़ की और रोटी, मजदूरी, बेहतर घंटे और लोकतंत्र के बारे में नारे लगाए।सरकार ने घुड़सवार सेना बुलाई लेकिन उन्होंने प्रदर्शनकारियों पर गोली चलाने से इनकार कर दिया। सैनिक और हड़ताली कर्मचारी उस इमारत में 'सोवियत' या 'काउंसिल' बनाने के लिए एकत्र हुए जहां ड्यूमा की बैठक हुई थी। यह पेत्रोग्राद सोवियत था। अगले ही दिन, जब एक प्रतिनिधिमंडल ज़ार से मिलने गया, तो सैन्य कमांडरों ने ज़ार को पद छोड़ने की सलाह दी। सोवियत नेताओं और ड्यूमा नेताओं ने देश को चलाने के लिए एक अस्थायी सरकार का गठन किया। इस प्रकार फरवरी 1917 में ज़ारिस्ट निरंकुशता का पतन हो गया।"},{"question":"Cushing sendromu tedavi edilmezse ne olur?","answer":"Aşırı kıllanmaya ek olarak Cushing sendromu olan kadınlarda adet düzensizliği de ortaya çıkabilir. Bazı Cushing sendromu olan kadın vakalarda menstrüasyon düzensizliği görülebilir. Doğru şekilde müdahale edilmemiş olgularda infertilite problemi çıkabileceği için dikkatli olunmalıdır."},{"question":"Awọn agbebọn ya wọ otẹẹli l’Ayetoro-Ekiti, wọn ji eeyan mẹta gbe, wọn tun fipa ba obinrin kan lo pọ","answer":"Inu ibẹru-bojo lawọn eeyan ilu Ayetoro, nijọba ibilẹ Ido/Osin, nipinlẹ Ekiti, wa bayii, pẹlu bii awọn Fulani agbebọn kan ṣe sadeede ya wọ ileetura kan to wa niluu naa ti wọn n pe ni Diamond Hotel, ti wọn si gbe eeyan mẹta lọ.Bakan naa ni wọn tun fipa ba ọdọmọbinrin kan to jẹ oṣiṣẹ ileetura naa lo pọ, ti wọn tun ṣe lara awọn oṣiṣẹ ibẹ leṣe ki wọn too ji wọn gbe lọ.Ni nnkan bii aago mẹsan-an aabọ alẹ ọjọ Iṣẹgun, Tusidee, ọsẹ yii, la gbọ pe awọn agbebọn naa ti ko din ni ọgbọn ya wọ ileetura yii pẹlu ibọn ati ohun ija oloro loriṣiiriṣii pẹlu ọkada, ti wọn si n yinbọn soke ki wọn too wọ inu ileetura naa lọ.Ẹnikan to n gbe inu ilu naa to pe ara rẹ ni Peter Otiko ṣalaye pe oju ọna kan to lọ si ilu Ewu-Ekiti lawọn agbebọn yii gba. Oju ọna yii kan naa ni awọn agbebọn kan ti yinbọn mọ Ọba Adetutu Ajayi ninu oṣu kẹrin, ọdun yii.Otiko ni ki wọn too wọnu ileetura naa lọ ni wọn ti kọkọ kọju ija si ọlọdẹ to n ṣọ ibẹ ti wọn porukọ rẹ ni Sunday. Niṣe ni wọn fi ada ṣa a lọwọ yannayanna ki wọn too wọ ileetura naa lọ.O fi kun un pe lẹyin ti wọn raaye wọle ni wọn ko eeyan mẹta to wa nibẹ pẹlu ẹni kan ti orukọ rẹ n jẹ Idowu to jẹ oṣiṣẹ ileetura naa. Lẹyin eyi ni wọn mori le ọna to kọja lọ si ilu Ewu-Ekiti, ti wọn si n yinbọn soke lakọ lakọ bi wọn ṣe n lọ.Iṣẹlẹ yii ti ko gbogbo ilu naa sinu wahala, wọn ko si ti i mọ ibi ti awọn mẹta ti wọn ji ko yii wa titi di asiko ta a pari iroyin yii.Nigba to n sọrọ lori iṣẹlẹ naa, oludari  awọn Amọtẹkun  nipinlẹ Ekiti, Ajagun-fẹyinti Joe Kọmọlafe, sọ pe oun ko le sọ ni pato boya awọn Fulani lo ṣiṣẹ buruku naa. O fi kun un pe ni deede aago mẹwaa aabọ alẹ loun sadeede gba ipe kan pe iṣẹlẹ naa ṣẹlẹ, ti oun si ko awọn ọmọ ẹgbẹ oun lọ si ilu naa lọgan, ṣugbọn awọn agbebọn naa ti fi ilu silẹ ki awọn too de ibẹ.Ọga Amọtẹkun yii sọ pe awọn ti bẹrẹ iwadii ati igbesẹ to daju lori iṣẹlẹ naa, ati pe wọn ti ko awọn to fara pa lọ sileewosan ijọba apapọ to wa niluu Ido-Ekiti, nibi ti wọn ti n gba itọju lọwọ."},{"question":"Moa ve mifameno sa mifanohitra sa tsy mifandray ny hevitra na tranga voaresaka amin'ireto fehezanteny roa manaraka ireto ?Fehezanteny voalohany: Misy Rova avokoa ny faritra rehetra eto Madagasikara.Fehezanteny faharoa : Natokana vao omaly ny kianja manara-penitra filalaovana baolina kitra tao Fianarantsoa. ","answer":"Tsy mifandray ny tranga voaresaka amin'ireo fehezanteny roa satria ny iray miresaka mahakasika ny fisian'ny Rova amin'ny faritra rehetra ao Madagasikara, ary ny iray kosa dia miresaka mahakasika ny fanokanana kianja manara-penitra vaovao tao Fianarantsoa. "},{"question":"ما هي السورة التي يبلغ عدد آياتها ١١ آية فقط؟.","answer":"سورة الجمعة."},{"question":"१) आजको मौसम हेर्दा पनि पर्ला जस्तो छ । २) मौसम हरेक बिहान ५ किलोमिटर दौडन्छ । के माथिको वाक्यहरुमा मौसम शब्दले एउटै अर्थ दिन्छ ? ","answer":"माथिको वाक्यहरुमा मौसम शब्दले एउटै अर्थ दिदैन । पहिलो वाक्यमा मौसमले वायुमण्डलको अवस्था जनाउँछ भने दोश्रो वाक्यमा मौसमले मानिसको नाम जनाउँछ । "},{"question":"Me kalmar: reason\\" ke nufi a harshen Hausa?","answer":" Kalmar reason\\" na nufin \\"dalili\\" a harshen Hausa"},{"question":"The respiratory system is more than just a conduit for oxygen.","answer":"It is a dynamic system where gaseous exchange powers cellular functions. Lungs, with their vast alveolar surface area, facilitate the transfer of oxygen into the bloodstream and the removal of carbon dioxide. The rhythmic act of breathing, regulated by the brainstem, ensures a constant supply of fresh air, while the protective mechanisms, like cilia and mucus, guard against pathogens and pollutants. The intricate balance of this system is evident in conditions like asthma or chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, where airflow is compromised."},{"question":"Berikan jawapan untuk teka-teki berikut: Awak sentiasa menderma darah kepadanya.","answer":"Jawapannya ialah nyamuk. Nyamuk menghisap darah manusia, maka kita dikatakan menderma darah kepadanya."},{"question":"केहि लोकप्रिय नेपाली परिकारको नाम बताउन सक्नुहुन्छ?","answer":"लोकप्रिय नेपाली परिकारहरूमा म:म: (मोमो), दाल-भात, सेल रोटी र ढिँडो समावेश छन्।"},{"question":"संभाजी राजाच्या मृत्युनंतर मराठ्यांचे छत्रपती कोण बनले ?","answer":"संभाजी राजाच्या मृत्युनंतर मराठ्यांचे छत्रपती राजाराम बनले."},{"question":"Em qual esporte são usadas as mãos para fazer gol?","answer":"Handebol."},{"question":"“Кыздуу үйдө кыл жатпайт”деген макалды түшүндүрүп бер?","answer":"Байыркы убактардан бери кыздар үй жумуштарын жасап, өздөрүнө дайыма тың болуп, кыздар жүргөн жерде бир кыл жатпай таза болгондугунан айтылып калган сөз."},{"question":"భాగస్వామ్య సంస్థ గురించి సంక్లిప్తంగా వివరించండి","answer":"కింబల్ నిర్వచనము ప్రకారము “ఒక వ్యాపారము నడపడానికి కొంతమంది వ్యక్తులు కలసి మూలధనాన్ని లేదా సేవలను సేకరించుకునే సంస్థను భాగస్వామ్య సంస్థ అనవచ్చు”. “లాభం ఆర్జించే నిమిత్తము చట్టబద్ధమైన వ్యాపారము చేయడానికి అంగీకరించిన అర్హులైన వ్యక్తుల మధ్య ఏర్పరచుకున్న సంబంధమే భాగస్వామ్యము” అని హాని నిర్వచించినాడు. 1932 భారత భాగస్వామ్య చట్టము భాగస్వామ్యాన్ని ఈ విధముగా నిర్వచించినది “అందరూగాని అందరి తరపున కొందరు గాని వ్యాపారము చేస్తూ లాభాన్ని పంచుకోవడానికి అంగీకరించిన వ్యక్తుల మధ్య ఉన్న సంబంధమే భాగస్వామ్యము”."},{"question":"வினா:சுற்றுச்சூழல் பாதுகாப்பில் ஈரநிலங்களின் பங்கு என்ன, அவை ஏன் பாதுகாக்கப்பட வேண்டும்?","answer":"விடை:அறிமுகம்சதுப்பு நிலங்கள் என்பது நிலம் நீரில் மூடப்பட்டிருக்கும் அல்லது நீர் தேங்கி இருக்கும் பகுதிகள். பல்வேறு வகையான தாவரங்கள், விலங்குகள் மற்றும் நீர்வாழ் உயிரினங்களுக்கு இது மிகவும் பயனுள்ள சூழலாகக் கருதப்படுகிறது. அவர்களுக்கு நீர் வழங்கல், விவசாயம் மற்றும் மீன்பிடி போன்ற பொருளாதார நன்மைகள் உள்ளன. பல்லுயிர் பெருக்கத்தை பராமரிப்பதில் ஈரநிலங்கள் முக்கிய பங்கு வகிக்கின்றன, பல பறவைகள் மற்றும் விலங்குகள் அவற்றை சார்ந்துள்ளது. அவை வெள்ளக் கட்டுப்பாடு மற்றும் நிலத்தடி நீர் ரீசார்ஜ் ஆகியவற்றில் முக்கியப் பங்காற்றுகின்றன மேலும் அவை போன்ற நன்மைகளைக் கொண்டுள்ளன:நீர் ஆதாரமாக சதுப்பு நிலங்கள் - நன்னீர் முக்கியமாக ஈரநிலங்களில் இருந்து வருகிறது. அவை மழையை உறிஞ்சி நிலத்தடி நீரை நிரப்பவும், விவசாயம் மற்றும் குடிநீரை வழங்கவும் உதவுகின்றன.சதுப்பு நிலங்கள் வெள்ளம் மற்றும் புயல் தடுப்புகள் - அவை தண்ணீரை மெதுவாக மண்ணுக்குள் செலுத்துவதன் மூலம் தண்ணீரை விரைவாக உறிஞ்சுகின்றன.சதுப்பு நிலப் பொருட்கள்- நிலையான முறையில் நிர்வகிக்கப்படும் சதுப்பு நிலங்கள் பல்வேறு தாவரங்கள், விலங்குகள் மற்றும் கனிமங்களை வழங்குகின்றன. கரையோர ஈரநிலங்கள் மீன், அரிசி மற்றும் தேன் ஆகியவற்றை வழங்குகின்றன.பொழுதுபோக்கு மற்றும் சுற்றுலாவுக்கான ஈரநிலங்கள் - சதுப்பு நிலங்கள் அவற்றின் இயற்கை அழகு மற்றும் பலதரப்பட்ட தாவரங்கள் மற்றும் விலங்கினங்கள் காரணமாக சுற்றுலாவிற்கு கவர்ச்சிகரமான இடங்களாகும். ஆனால் பொறுப்பற்ற சுற்றுலா சதுப்பு நிலங்களுக்கு அதிக அழுத்தம் கொடுப்பதன் மூலம் தீங்கு விளைவிக்கும்.சதுப்பு நிலங்கள் மற்றும் காலநிலை மாற்றம் - ஈரநிலங்கள் காலநிலை மாற்றத்தால் ஆபத்தில் உள்ளன, ஆனால் சில ஈரநிலங்கள் கார்பனைக் குறைக்கும் தீங்கு விளைவிக்கும் பசுமை இல்ல வாயுக்களை சேமிக்க முடியும். அவை தண்ணீரை உறிஞ்சி வைத்திருக்கின்றன, இது வெள்ளம் மற்றும் புயல்களைக் கட்டுப்படுத்த உதவுகிறது, காலநிலை மாற்றத்தை எதிர்ப்பதில் அவற்றை மதிப்புமிக்கதாக ஆக்குகிறது.புலம்பெயர்ந்த பறவைகளின் வாழ்விடமாக ஈரநிலங்கள் - துருவ மற்றும் மிதமான பகுதிகளில் கடுமையான குளிர்காலத்தைத் தவிர்ப்பதற்காக ஒவ்வொரு ஆண்டும் சுமார் 2000 பறவை இனங்கள் ஆயிரக்கணக்கான மைல்கள் இடம்பெயர்கின்றன. சதுப்பு நிலங்கள் இந்த பறவைகள் இடம்பெயரும் போது ஓய்வெடுக்கவும், உணவளிக்கவும் மற்றும் இனப்பெருக்கம் செய்யவும் முக்கியமான இடமாகும். இந்திய ஈரநிலங்கள் மத்திய ஆசிய மற்றும் கிழக்கு ஆஸ்திரேலிய பறக்கும் பாதைகளை இணைக்கின்றன.இருப்பினும், பல ஆண்டுகளாக, மானுடவியல் நடவடிக்கைகள் இந்த ஈரநிலங்களின் இருப்புக்கு அச்சுறுத்தலை ஏற்படுத்தியுள்ளன. சதுப்பு நிலங்களுக்கு அச்சுறுத்தலை ஏற்படுத்தும் பல்வேறு காரணங்கள்:நகரமயமாக்கல் காரணமாக அதிகரித்த மாசு அளவு,பருவநிலை மாற்றம்,தீவிர மீன்வளர்ப்பு மற்றும் விவசாய நடவடிக்கைகளால் நீர்ப்பிடிப்பு சிதைவு,கட்டுப்பாடற்ற சுற்றுலா,அணைகள் கட்டுதல் போன்ற கட்டுமான நடவடிக்கைகளால் நீரியல் ஆட்சிகளில் மாற்றம்,தவறான கழிவு வெளியேற்றம்.ஈரநிலங்களை நோக்கிய இந்த அதிகரித்த அச்சுறுத்தல் காரணமாக, அவை காலப்போக்கில் சிதைந்து, அவற்றின் இருப்பை நம்பியிருக்கும் சுற்றுச்சூழல் அமைப்பை பாதிக்கின்றன. கடந்த மூன்று தசாப்தங்களில் இந்தியா தனது இயற்கை ஈரநிலங்களில் கிட்டத்தட்ட 30 சதவீதத்தை இழந்துள்ளது. இந்தியா பல வகையான புலம்பெயர்ந்த பறவைகளின் தாயகமாக இருந்து வருகிறது, மில்லியன் கணக்கான புலம்பெயர்ந்த பறவைகள் இந்தியாவிற்கு வருகின்றன, மேலும் ஈரநிலங்கள் இந்த வருடாந்திர நிகழ்வுக்கு முக்கியமானவை. இந்திய ஈரநிலங்கள் இந்த புலம்பெயர்ந்த பறவைகளுக்கு தங்கும் இடங்களை வழங்குகின்றன, எனவே, இந்த ஈரநிலங்களைப் பாதுகாப்பதும், இந்த புலம்பெயர்ந்த பறவைகளின் வழியில் எந்த இடையூறும் ஏற்படாமல் இருப்பதை உறுதி செய்வதும் முக்கியம்.ஈரநிலப் பாதுகாப்புத் திட்டங்கள்இந்தியாவில் உள்ள சதுப்பு நிலங்களைப் பாதுகாக்க, சுற்றுச்சூழல், வனம் மற்றும் காலநிலை மாற்ற அமைச்சகம் ஈரநிலங்களின் சுற்றுச்சூழல் பண்புகளைப் பாதுகாக்க, நிர்வகிக்க மற்றும் பராமரிக்க உதவும் ஈரநில பாதுகாப்பு மற்றும் மேலாண்மை விதிகள், 2017 ஐ இயற்றியுள்ளது. கழிவுகளை வெளியேற்றுவது, திடக்கழிவுகளை கொட்டுவது போன்ற சதுப்பு நிலங்களை நீடிக்காமல் பயன்படுத்துவதை விதிகள் தடை செய்கின்றன. விதிகள் புத்திசாலித்தனமான பயன்பாட்டுக் கொள்கையை ஊக்குவிக்கின்றன, அதாவது அவற்றைப் பாதுகாக்கும் போது நிலையான பயன்பாடு.மத்திய மற்றும் மாநிலம்/யூனியன் பிரதேசங்களுக்கிடையில் செலவினப் பகிர்வு அடிப்படையில் செயல்படுத்தப்படும் இந்தியாவில் ஈரநிலங்களின் மேலாண்மைக்கான மத்திய நிதியுதவித் திட்டமான நீர்வாழ் சுற்றுச்சூழல் பாதுகாப்புக்கான தேசியத் திட்டத்தை (NPCA) அமைச்சகம் நிறைவேற்றி செயல்படுத்தி வருகிறது. அரசாங்கங்கள். இத்திட்டம் சதுப்பு நிலங்களை மீட்டெடுப்பதை நோக்கமாகக் கொண்டுள்ளது, இதனால் நீரின் தரம் மேம்படும் மற்றும் பல்லுயிர் மேம்பாடு உள்ளது. அதன் நோக்கத்தை அடைய, ஈரநிலங்கள் புத்துயிர் அளிக்கும் திட்டத்தை அறிமுகப்படுத்தியது. நிரல் அணுகுமுறை:ஈரநில சுருக்க ஆவணத்தை உருவாக்குதல்உள்ளூர் பங்குதாரர்களை உள்ளடக்கிய குடிமக்களின் பங்கேற்பை அதிகரிக்க ஈரநில மித்ராஸ்ஈரநில சுகாதார அட்டை, ஈரநில நிலையை கண்காணிக்கவும் கண்காணிக்கவும் உதவும்பல்லுயிர், சுற்றுச்சூழல் சேவைகள், மதிப்புகள் மற்றும் அச்சுறுத்தல்களை நிவர்த்தி செய்வதை உள்ளடக்கிய ஒரு ஒருங்கிணைந்த மேலாண்மை திட்டத்தை உருவாக்குதல்.நாடு முழுவதும் உள்ள 1000 சதுப்பு நிலங்களுக்கு புத்துயிர் அளிக்க இந்த திட்டம் திட்டமிட்டுள்ளது. பல்லுயிர் மற்றும் சுற்றுச்சூழலுக்கான ஈரநிலப் பாதுகாப்பை உறுதி செய்வதற்காக இந்தியா பயனுள்ள சட்ட மற்றும் கொள்கை நடவடிக்கைகளை எடுத்துள்ளது. சதுப்பு நிலங்களுக்கு தொடர்ந்து அச்சுறுத்தல் இருப்பதால், இந்த சதுப்பு நிலங்களை பாதுகாப்பது குறிப்பிடத்தக்கதாக மாறியுள்ளது.ஈரானின் ராம்சார் நகரில் 1971 ஆம் ஆண்டு ஈரானின் மாநாடு என்று அழைக்கப்படும் ஒரு அரசுகளுக்கிடையேயான ஒப்பந்தம் ஏற்றுக்கொள்ளப்பட்டதால் பிப்ரவரி 2 ஆம் தேதி ஒவ்வொரு ஆண்டும் உலக ஈரநில தினமாக கொண்டாடப்படுகிறது. இந்த மாநாடு நாடுகள் தங்கள் ஈரநிலங்களைப் பாதுகாப்பதற்கும் அவற்றை புத்திசாலித்தனமாகப் பயன்படுத்துவதற்கும் நடவடிக்கைகளை எடுக்க உதவுகிறது. சர்வதேச முக்கியத்துவம் வாய்ந்த ஈரநிலங்கள் தொடர்பான ராம்சார் மாநாட்டின் கீழ் ராம்சர் தளங்கள் சர்வதேச முக்கியத்துவம் வாய்ந்தவை. பிப்ரவரி 1, 1982 அன்று நடந்த மாநாட்டில் இந்தியா ஒரு கட்சியாக மாறியது. இந்தியாவில் ஏராளமான சதுப்பு நிலங்கள் உள்ளன, தற்போது 75 ராம்சார் தளங்கள் தெற்காசியாவில் ஈரநிலங்களின் மிகப்பெரிய வலையமைப்பாக உள்ளது."},{"question":" كم يبلغ طول جسر الملك فهد ؟","answer":" 25 كم"},{"question":"Hoàn thiện đoạn văn sau với nội dung có liên quan tới đoạn văn dưới đây: Aprilia SR GT 200 Vào ngày 25/7, thương hiệu Aprilia (thuộc Piaggio) đã ra mắt mẫu xe đua thể thức nhỏ mang tên SR GT 200. Nó sẽ được bán ra với 2 phiên bản bao gồm Tiêu chuẩn và Thể thao (Sport) kèm giá bán lần lượt 97 triệu và 99,5 triệu đồng. Đây là sản phẩm có dung tích dưới 175 cc thứ 3 hãng xe Italy mang về Việt Nam, trước đó có RX 125 và SX 125. Cả 2 phiên bản của Aprilia SR GT đều sử dụng động cơ xy-lanh đơn mang dung tích 174cc, làm mát bằng dung dịch, sản sinh công suất 17,4 mã lực tại tua máy 8.500 vòng/phút và mômen xoắn cực đại 16,5 Nm tại tua máy 7.000 vòng/phút. Nó được đánh giá cao bởi tốc độ cao và khả năng xử lý nhanh nhẹn vốn có từ đội đua Aprilia. Honda Airblade 160 Vào tháng 5 năm nay, Honda lần đầu tiên tung ra mẫu xe Airblade sử dụng động cơ 160cc tại Việt Nam. Nó có sẵn với hai phiên bản Tiêu chuẩn và Đặc biệt, có giá niêm yết lần lượt 55,9 triệu đồng và 57,19 triệu đồng. Chiếc xe này sử dụng động cơ 156,9cc, eSP+ xi-lanh đơn, 4 van, cho công suất 15,2 mã lực tại 8.000 vòng/phút, tăng hơn 2 mã lực so với thế hệ cũ. Đây là loại động cơ tương đồng với các người anh em PCX và Vario. Ở thế hệ mới, Airblade 160 được trang bị ổ khóa smartkey hiện đại, giúp người lái thuận tiện hơn trong việc sử dụng. Dung tích chứa đồ của cốp xe tăng thêm 0,5 lít nhờ kết cấu khung sườn mới. Cùng với đó, Honda cũng đã cung cấp cổng sạc USB cho chiếc xe này. Suzuki Burgman Street Burgman Street được ra mắt tại thị trường trong nước vào tháng 2/2021 nhưng đến nay, chiếc xe này vẫn còn khá xa lạ đối với người tiêu dùng Việt. Nó tạo ấn tượng bởi vẻ ngoài khá hầm hố và cơ bắp cùng nhiều chi tiết thiết kế góc cạnh và sắc sảo. Burgman Street trang bị hệ thống phanh CBS chứ không phải phanh ABS như những loại xe tay ga cùng phân khúc. Cùng với đó, nó sử dụng động cơ SEP phun xăng điện tử với dung tích 125cc, SOHC và hệ thống làm mát bằng không khí. Hệ thống truyền động này tạo ra công suất 8,5 mã lực tại 6.760 vòng/phút, mô-men xoắn cực","answer":"đại 10,5 Nm tại 5.500 vòng/phút. Chiếc xe có giá đề xuất 48,6 triệu đồng tại Việt Nam. Yamaha NVX Yamaha NVX 155 VVA mới có giá bán 54,5 triệu đồng và phiên bản giới hạn Monster Energy Yamaha MotoGP có giá 55,5 triệu đồng. Về sức mạnh, Yamaha NVX 155 VVA sử dụng động cơ Blue Core SOHC xi-lanh đơn, làm mát bằng dung dịch, với dung tích 155,1 cc. Cỗ máy này được tăng tỷ số nén lên 11,6:1, cho công suất tối đa 15,4 mã lực (PS) tại 8.000 vòng/phút và mô-men xoắn cực đại 13,9 N.m tại 6.500 vòng/phút. Ngoài ra, xe vẫn được trang bị các tính năng hiện đại và tiện ích như: Hệ thống chống bó cứng phanh ABS, màn hình đồng hồ kỹ thuật số, đèn LED mới, ngắt động cơ tạm thời, khóa thông minh Smart Key, bình xăng lớn 5,5 lít, cổng sạc điện thoại, cốp xe có sức chứa lên đến 25 lít, bánh xe to thể thao (độ rộng 110mm lốp trước và 140mm lốp sau), phuộc sau giảm chấn dầu. Honda ADV 150 Tuy không còn gây nhiều chú ý như thời điểm Honda ADV xuất hiện tại Việt Nam khoảng 3 năm nước, chiếc xe này vẫn là lựa chọn đáng cân nhắc cho khách hàng ưa thiết kế phong cách địa hình. Các đại lý tư nhân đang phân phối Honda ADV 150 với mức giá khoảng 80 triệu đồng và 83-85 triệu đồng lần lượt cho bản CBS và ABS. Honda ADV 150 được trang bị kính chắn gió tùy chỉnh, đèn LED toàn bộ và giảm xóc Showa. Ngoài ra, hai bánh xe đều sử dụng kẹp phanh thủy lực hiệu Nissan, và bình xăng có thể chứa tối đa 8 lít. Cung cấp sức mạnh cho Honda ADV 150 là động cơ SOHC 149,3 cc xi-lanh đơn, giúp sản sinh công suất tối đa 14,3 mã lực tại 8.500 vòng/phút và mô-men xoắn cực đại 13,8 Nm tại 6.500 vòng/phút, với công nghệ Idling Stop. Mẫu xe này cũng sử dụng hệ thống nạp nhiên liệu PGM-Fi và dẫn động qua hộp số biến thiên vô cấp cùng đai truyền động. "},{"question":"Akrilik boya üzerine yağlı boya olur mu?","answer":"Tıpkı akrilik boya gibi. Akrilik boya sıklıkla yağlı boya ile karıştırılır."},{"question":"Waa maxay MAGAC? NAXWAHA AF SOOMAALIGA?","answer":"Magucu waa qayb kamid ah hadalka, wuxuuna ku tusaa dad, xoolo, bahallo, geedo, iwm. Sida: Cali, Kaaha, Faras, Sac, Libaax, Abeeso, Qurac, Moos, Dhagax Iwm. Magacu wuxuu u kala baxaa: Magac Guud iyo Magac Gaar. ● Magac Guud Magac Guud waa magaca loo siman yahay, wuxuuna u kala baxaa Magac muuqda iyo magac qarsoon. 1. Magac muuqda Magac muuqda waa magaca la arki karo ama la taaban karo. Tusaale:1. KURSI iyo MIIS baa wax lagu qori karaa.2. Haddaad wax baranaysid ha illaawin BUUG iyo QALIN.3. Reer miyigu waxay wax ku ootaan GODIN iyo HANGOOL. 2. Magac Qarsoon Magac qarsooni waa kan aan la arki karin, lana taaban karin. Tusaale 1. Dadka XOOGGA lihi waa inay dadka TAAGTA daran wax taraan.2. AQOON la'aani waa IFTIIN la'aan.3. Diintu NUUR bay u tahay dadka.4. GEESINNIMADA waa loo dhashaa.● Magac Gaar Magac Gaar waa magaca u goonnida ah noolka ama moodka.Tusaale:1. XAMAR waa magaala madaxda dalka Soomaaliya.2. Gumeysi xun bay AFRIKA soo martay.3. SIYAAD waa macalinka Towradda.4. QORRAXDU waa noloshu naflayda.5. Dalkeenna xagga bari waxaa xigga badweynta hindiya."},{"question":"Waa meeqo xarfaha af Soomaaliga?","answer":"Xarfaha af Soomaaliga waa 21 xaraf oo shiibane ah iyo 5 xaraf oo shaqal ah, taasi oo guud ahaan ka dhigeysa 26 xaraf."},{"question":"Beş Hececiler kimlerden oluşmaktadır?","answer":"Beş Hececiler  I. Meşrutiyet'ten sonra hece vezniyle ve konuşulan halk diliyle, Millî Edebiyat akımının görüşleri doğrultusunda şiir yazan beş şairin Türk edebiyatındaki genel adıdır. Bu grubu oluşturan beş şair: Orhan Seyfi Orhon, Enis Behiç Koryürek, Halit Fahri Ozansoy, Yusuf Ziya Ortaç ve Faruk Nafiz Çamlıbel'dir."},{"question":"வினா: பாதரச வெப்பமானிகளால் அளவிடக்கூடிய மிக உயர்ந்த வெப்பநிலை என்ன?","answer":"விடை: 360 டிகிரி செல்சியஸ்"},{"question":"Maak de volgende zin af: De Derde Coalitieoorlog (1805) tegen Napoleon Bonaparte en de desastreuze nederlaag in de","answer":"Slag bij Austerlitz betekende het einde."},{"question":"من هم الضالين؟ ولماذ؟","answer":"\\tالنصارى لأنهم حادوا عن الحق جهلاً فكانوا على ضلال بين في شأن عيسى عليه السلام."},{"question":"السؤال: شحال العدد ديال الاركان ديال الإيمان ؟","answer":"الإجابة: ستة ديال أركان"},{"question":"Người dân chợ nổi quảng cáo hàng hóa bằng cách nào?","answer":"Bán sản vật gì, người ta treo sản vật đó (treo bẹo) lên cây sào (cây bẹo) trên mũi thuyền. Từ \\"bẹo\\" là phương ngữ Nam bộ, với nghĩa gọi mời, phô diễn hình dạng. Ở môi trường sông nước, các thương lái không thể rao bán như chợ trên đất liền. Người dân trên chợ nổi dựng một cây sào và treo các mặt hàng mà ghe mình bán nhằm giúp khách có thể dễ dàng nhận biết từ xa."},{"question":"Kedụ steeti Mahadum Ahmadu Bello dị na ya?","answer":"Mahadum Ahmadu Bello dị na Kaduna Steeti.Mahadum Ahmadu Bello (ABU) bụ mahadum nyocha gọọmentị etiti dị na Zaria, Kaduna State. E hiwere ABU n'October 4, 1962, dika Mahadum Northern Nigeria. mahadum a nwere campus atọ: Samaru na Kongo na Zaria, na School of Basic Studies na Funtua."},{"question":"Kinsa ang gipaila sa Dios nga si Jesus human sa iyang baba ug angay siyang pagpaminawon?","answer":"Kini mao ang akong Anak nga hinigugmaon, sa iya ako nalipay.”Nganong gipanamkon si Jesus sa Jordan River ni San Juan Bautista?"},{"question":"1 sakinys: Altoriaus frizas yra skulptoriaus Elmar Hillebrand ir jo studento Ronald Hughes darbas. 2 sakinys: Altoriaus frizas yra skulptoriaus Ronald Hughes ir jo studento Elmar Hillebrand darbas. Klausimas: Ar 1 ir 2 sakiniai reiškia tą pačią reikšmę? Taip ar ne?","answer":"Ne."},{"question":"प्रश्न : दिइएका शब्दको अर्थ लेख्नुहोस् :भटनी , अप्रिय , दुगुर्ण ","answer":"उत्तर  :भटनी ➡ धान काट्ने कामअप्रिय ➡ मन नपरेकोदुगुर्ण ➡ कुनै पदार्थमा विकार उत्पन्न गराउने देष"},{"question":"खालील म्हणीचा मराठीत सुलभ अर्थ सांगा .--ऊराचे खुराडे आणि चुलीचे तुणतुणे","answer":"अतिशय हलाखीची स्थिती."},{"question":"Explain the butterfly effect's consequences in relation to time travel.","answer":"The butterfly effect, named after the metaphorical instance of a butterfly in Brazil spreading its wings and creating a tornado in Texas, serves as an example of how slight modifications to the starting circumstances can result in remarkably diverse consequences. The butterfly effect, as it relates to time travel, implies that even seemingly insignificant previous actions or interventions could have unforeseen, perhaps disastrous present-day or future effects. If a time traveler were to stop a seemingly unimportant incident in the past, for example, it might start a domino effect that changes history in unexpected ways. This idea presents moral dilemmas regarding accountability and the risks involved with changing the past."},{"question":"Inona no andraikitry ny antoko politika amin’ny fifidianana filoham-pirenena?","answer":"Misafidy kandidà, mamolavola sehatra politika ary manentana ny mpifidy."},{"question":"காரல் மார்க்சின் மேற்கோள் ஒன்றை தரவும்.","answer":"பொருளாதார அதிகாரத்தில் ஏற்படும் மாற்றமே மனித வரலாற்றின் ஏனைய மாற்றங்களுக்கான அடிப்படை."},{"question":"కింది ప్రశ్నకు సమాధానం ఇవ్వండిపారా అయస్కాంతత్వాన్ని సరైన ఉదాహరణతో వివరించండి.","answer":"పారా అయస్కాంత పదార్థాలు అయస్కాంత క్షేత్రంలోకి ఆకర్షితమవుతాయి. అయస్కాంత క్షేత్రాన్ని తీసివేస్తే వాటి అయస్కాంత ధర్మం పోతుంది.ఉదా : O2, NO, Na పరమాణువులు.ఒంటరి ఎలక్ట్రాన్లున్న పరమాణువులు, అయాన్లు, అణువులు ఈ ధర్మాన్ని ప్రదర్శిస్తాయి."},{"question":"நாளெல்லாம் நடந்தாலும் நாற்பதடி செல்லாது அந்த நாயகனுக்கோ உடல் மேல் கவசம் அது என்ன?","answer":"விடை: நத்தை"},{"question":"Kí ni orúkọ gómínà ìpínlẹ̀ Zamfara?","answer":"Dauda lawal ni."},{"question":"Podaj mi przykład zagadki z tej kategorii historia.","answer":"Oto zagadka z kategorii historia.\\"Pytanie: Kto został zabity pierwszy, Martin Luther King Jr. czy Robert Kennedy?Odpowiedź: Martin Luther King, Jr.\\""},{"question":"வினா:  மார்ன் போர் எதற்காக நினைவு கூறப்படுகிறது?அ ) ஆகாயப் போர் முறைஆ) பதுங்குக் குழிப் போர் முறைஇ) நீர்மூழ்கிக் கப்பல் போர் முறைஈ) கடற்படைப் போர் முறை ","answer":"விடை:ஆ ) பதுங்குக் குழிப் போர் முறை"},{"question":"‘హరిశ్చంద్రుడు ఆడినమాట తప్పడు’ అని తెలుసుకున్నారు కదా ! ఆడినమాట తప్పనివారు ఎలా ఉంటారో రాయండి.","answer":"ఆడిన మాట తప్పనివారు అంటే సత్యసంధులు. వారు ప్రాణం పోయినా సరే అబద్ధం ఆడరు. సత్యవాక్యం గొప్పతనాన్ని వారు గుర్తించినవారు. భార్యను అమ్మవలసి వచ్చినా, తానే అమ్ముడుపోయినా హరిశ్చంద్రుడు అబద్ధమాడలేదు. వామనునికి మూడు అడుగుల నేల దానం చేస్తే బలిచక్రవర్తికే ప్రమాదం వస్తుంది అని ఆయన గురువు శుక్రుడు చెప్పినా బలి తాను అన్నమాటను తప్పలేదు. శిబి చక్రవర్తి తన శరీరంలోని మాంసాన్నే కోసి ఇచ్చి పావురాన్ని రక్షించాడు. ఆడినమాట తప్పనివారు బలి చక్రవర్తిలా, హరిశ్చంద్రునిలా, శిబిచక్రవర్తిలా ఉంటారు."},{"question":"Fenoy ity ohabolana ity: \\"Ilatsahan'ny varatra am-pangerena, ___\\"","answer":"\\"Ilatsahan'ny varatra am-pangerena, sady maty no mihoson-tay.\\""},{"question":"मानिसको शरीरमा इन्सुलिन हर्मोन उत्पादन गर्ने ग्रन्थी कुन हो ?","answer":"प्याङक्रियाज"},{"question":"inona ny Ady atao amin'ny fahavalon'ny tantely?","answer":"Bibikely : Samoina na fausse teigneFahavalo mampidi-doza ho an'ny tantely. Io samoina io dia manatody ao anatin'ilay tohotra tantelyosaosa. Ny olitra mivoaka avy amin'ireo atody ireo dia mandavaka ao amin'ny papina tantely. Mivelonaamin'ny mamintantely sy vovo bony izy ireo. Mandrafitra foniny izy izay mety hanerana ny tohotra arymety hanimba tanteraka ilay andian-tantely.Fomba fiady- arahina maso matetika ny tohotraTorolalana fiompiana tantely amin’ny fomba nohatsarainaRecyclage des apiculteurs relais Boeny – novembre 201815 INSIGHT in development- ametrahana tahirina mamy tantely ireo tantely ireo amin'ny fihafaran'ny fotoana mampamelanany zavamaniry- esorina tanteraka ireo papiny tratry ny samoina ary dorana- kikisana ny hazo mitondra ireo ary lalovana lelan'afo- atambatra ireo tantely osaosa- fahanana ranontantely ireo tantely ireo- ahena ny haavon'ny fidiran'ireo tantely iarovana amin'ny fitsofohan'ny lolo.VitsikaMpankafy mamintantely dia afaka miditra ao anatin'ilay andian-tantely. Mitady sakafo ary tafihiny ireozana-tantely ka potipotehiny ary ho entiny any an-tranony. Io trangan-javatra io dia hita ao amin'nysaron'ny kadira izay tonga toerana tena iveloman'ny vitsika.Fomba fiady- oh: atao ao anaty rano ny tongotr'ilay latabatra ipetrahan'ny tohotraFanenitra sy ny fangarakaEo amin'ny varavaran'ny tohotra dia atrehana indraindray ny ady misy amin'ny tantely mpiambina sy nyfanenitra. Ireo farany ireo dia alaim-panahy hiditra ao anaty tohotra mba hitsetsitra ilay ranontantelyamin'ny tohotra.Fomba fiady- ahena ny haavon'ny fidirana mba hanakanana ny fitsofohan'ny fanenitra sy ny fangaraka.Biby hafa : Sokina sy ny totozyNy sokina dia mety hanafika ireo tantely efa vizana izay mijanona eo an-toerana fanidinanana mandritrany alina.Amin'ireo tohotra nentim-paharazana dia mety hanapotika tanteraka ireo papona tantely sy zana- tantelyizy ireo. Fantatr'ireo mpiompy tantely mihitsy ny fahasimbana lehibe ataon'ny totozy amin'ny tohotra.Fomba fiady- atao miala amin'ny tany 20 ka hatramin'ny 30 sm ny aavon'ny latabatra ametrahana ny tohotra- ampiasaina ny tohotra voatsara- ankelezina ny fidirana amin'ny tohotra mba hiarovana amin'ny fitsofohan'ny totozy.Ireo karazana sahona sy biby mandadySahobakaka, sahona, indrindra ny androngo dia manafika ny tantely izay samboriny eo ambaravarana syidirany ao anatiny mihitsy aza.Fomba fiady- atao miala amin'ny tany 20 ka hatramin'ny 30 sm ny aavon'ny latabatra ametrahana ny tohotra- ahena ny fidirana ao amin'ny tohotraTorolalana fiompiana tantely amin’ny fomba nohatsarainaRecyclage des apiculteurs relais Boeny – novembre 201816 INSIGHT in developmentIreo vorona fahavaloAmin'ny fotoanan'ny volan-tantely no anararaotin'ireo vorona ireo hanafihana ilay tantely. Ny voronafahavalo tena fanta-daza dia ny \\"guêpier de Madagascar\\" na kiririoka"},{"question":"این متن در مورد چه موضوعی صحبت می‌کند؟روز ۵ اسفند ۱۴۰۰ (۲۴ فوریهٔ ۲۰۲۲)، روسیه تهاجم گسترده‌ای را به اوکراین، همسایهٔ غربی خود آغاز کرد که نشان‌دهندهٔ تشدید چشمگیر بحران روسیه و اوکراین است که از سال ۲۰۱۴ آغاز شده بود. این تهاجم بزرگ‌ترین حملهٔ نظامی متعارف به خاک اروپا از زمان جنگ جهانی دوم است. پیش از این تهاجم، روند نفوذ نظامی روسیه در اوکراین، از اوایل سال ۲۰۲۱ آغاز شده بود و طی آن ولادیمیر پوتین، رئیس‌جمهور روسیه از گسترش ناتو از سال ۱۹۹۷ به‌عنوان تهدیدی برای امنیت کشورش انتقاد کرد و خواستار ممنوعیت قانونی پیوستن به ائتلاف نظامی برای اوکراین شد.","answer":"این متن به حمله روسیه به اوکراین اشاره دارد."},{"question":"වී වගාව කෙරෙහි බලපෑම් ඇති කරන වල් පැළෑටි ගැන කියන්න.","answer":"වී වගාවේ දී ගොයම් පැළයට අමතරව කුඹුරෙහි දක්නට ලැඛෙන ඕනෑම පැළෑටියක් වල් පැළෑටියක් ලෙස හඳුන්වනු ලැබේ. වල් පැළ පාලනය සිදු කිරීම පිළිබඳ සැලකිලිමත් විය යුත්තේ වී වගාව ආරම්භක අවස්ථාවේ සිටමය. එබැවින් වගා ආරම්භයට පෙර සිටම සාර්ථක වල් පැළ පාලනයක් සිදු කර ගැනීමට නම් කුඹුරෙහි ඇති විවිධ වල් වර්ග කුමන ප්‍රමාණයකින් තිබේද යන්න පිළිබඳ මනා අවබෝධයක් තිබිය යුතුය."},{"question":"Aşağıdaki ifadeyi tamamlayın:Fransa Hava Kuvvetleri hizmet ömrü boyunca, Noratlas başlangıçta ağırlıklı olarak kargo taşıma rolünde kullandı; bununla birlikte, yolcu operasyonlarının gerçekleştirilmesini kolaylaştırmak için sipariş edildiği gibi 10 adet ek envantere alınmıştı. Bununla birlikte, 1962'de","answer":"Cezayir Bağımsızlık Savaşı'nın sona ermesinin ve o dönem ki Fransız askerî operasyonlarının bitmesinin ardından, birçok uçak ek ikincil rolleri yerine getirmek için dönüştürme çalışmalarına girdi. Noratlas filosunda yapılan çeşitli teslimat sonrası özelleştirmeler ve modifikasyonlar arasında, elektronik harp rolünde kullanılan sekiz Nord Gabriels, belki de en kullanışlı olmasının yanı sıra en uzun süre hizmet veren uçaklar arasında yer aldı. 1989'da, son Noratlas Fransa Hava Kuvvetleri envanterinden çıktı."},{"question":"Escreva uma continuação para esse parágrafo - Vespasiano, fundador da dinastia Flaviana, decidiu aumentar o moral e auto-estima dos cidadãos romanos e também cativá-los com uma política de pão e circo, demolindo o palácio de Nero e construindo uma arena permanente para espectáculos de gladiadores, execuções e outros entretenimentos de massas. Vespasiano começou a sua própria remodelação do lugar entre os anos 70 e 72, possivelmente financiada com os tesouros conseguidos depois da vitória romana na Grande Revolta Judaica,","answer":"no ano 70. Drenou-se o lago e o lugar foi designado para o Coliseu. Reclamando a terra da qual Nero se apropriou para o seu anfiteatro, Vespasiano conseguiu dois objectivos: Por um lado realizava um gesto muito popular e por outro colocava um símbolo do seu poder no coração da cidade. Mais tarde foram construídos uma escola de gladiadores e outros edifícios de apoio dentro das antigas terras da Casa Dourada, a maior parte da qual havia sido derrubada."},{"question":"\\"Трой унциясында канча грамм алтын бар?\\"","answer":"\\"Трой фунтуна 12 трой унциясы бар, андан көрө 16 трой унциясы бар\\" деген суроонун мааниси кандай? Трой салмагы жөнүндө."},{"question":"Kinahanglan ba na nga mugamit ko ug mouthwash bisan nagtoothbrush nako?","answer":"Dili kinahaglan ang mouthwash, pero ginarekomendar kini sa mga dentista para extrang proteksyon sa ngipon ug lagos."},{"question":"प्राकृतिक भाषा प्रशोधन को प्रमुख कार्य के हो?","answer":"प्राकृतिक भाषा प्रशोधनका सामान्य कार्यहरू पाठ र वाक् प्रशोधन, रूपात्मक विश्लेषण, सिन्ट्याक्टिक विश्लेषण, लेक्सिकल सिमान्टिक्स, रिलेशनल सिमान्टिक्स, डिसकोर्स आदि हुन्।"},{"question":"เขียนความต่อเนื่องสําหรับย่อหน้านี้: การที่ญี่ปุ่นเข้ามาตั้งฐานทัพในประเทศไทยเพื่อป้องกันการโจมตีของฝ่ายสัมพันธมิตรทำให้ฝ่ายสัมพันธมิตรมองรัฐบาลไทยของจอมพล ป. ในสถานะเดียวกันกับราชอาณาจักรอิตาลีซึ่งเห็นได้จากการที่สัมพันธมิตรยกพลขึ้นบกที่เกาะซิซิลี","answer":"ที่เยอรมนีส่งกองทัพเข้ามาตั้งฐานทัพในอิตาลีเพื่อปกป้องการคงอยู่ของพันธมิตรมุสโสลินี"},{"question":"Cho phép tính 12 × 5 = 60. Chọn câu sai. A. 12 là thừa số B. 5 là thừa sốC. 60 là tíchD. 60 là thương","answer":"Lời giảiTrong phép tính 12 × 5 = 60, có 12 và 5 là các thừa số và 60 là tích. Vậy đáp án A, B, C đúng và D sai.Chọn đáp án D. "},{"question":"IT тармагындагы дүйнөлүк алп компанияларда эмгектенген көптөгөн Кыргызстандыктар бар. Алардын арасынан кимдерди таныйсың?","answer":"IT тармагындагы дүйнөлүк алп компанияларда эмгектенген көптөгөн Кыргызстандыктар бар. Google компаниясында программист болуп иштеген кыргыздын Таалай Жумабаев жөнүндө болсун.Таалай Жумабаев Google компаниясынын улук программисти болуп иштеген. Санкт-Петербург мамлекеттик университетин “математик-программист” адистиги боюнча артыкчылык диплому менен аяктаган. Кембридж шаарындагы Европалык биоинформатика институтунда стажировкадан өткөн. Окуу жайды бүтүргөндөн кийин 4 жыл Москвадагы инвестициялык банктардын биринде стратегиялык долбоорлордун үстүндө иштеген. Кийин ал жактан кызматтан көтөрүлүп, банктын Нью-Йорктогу кеңсесине которулган. Андан соң 2019-жылы Google компаниясына жумушка кирген. Азыркы мезгилге Googleдан чыгып Кыргызстанга келип бир топ долбоорлорду алып барып жатат. Мисалы, \\"Энелер Мария\\" долбоору балдары бар энелер эжекелер үчүн арналган. Бул долбоордун негизги максаты Эне алган билимин өз балдарына тартуулайт. Өнүгүүнү каалаган эне келечекте өнүккөн мамлекет (балдарына туура тарбия бере алат).Кийинки долбоорлорунун бири \\"Growth hungry\\"- бул долбоордун аты айтып тургандай өсүүгө умтулуу күндө жашооңо жаңы жаңылыктарды киргизүү жана көптөгөн мекендештерибиздин жашоосун оңдоду. Азыр программисттер үчүн да бир канча долбоорлорду уюштуруп жүргөн кези."},{"question":"ඔබ දන්නා දේ උගන්වන්න","answer":"අන්තර්ජාලය හරහා ඉගෙනුම්, ඉගැන්වීම් කිරීම, මේ වන විට ලොව ප්‍රචලිත වෙමින් පවතින අධ්‍යාපන ක්‍රමයකි. එම නිසා, අනිවාර්යෙන්ම ඔබේ හැකියාවට නිසි තැනක් ලැබෙනවා. ඔබට කිසියම් හෝ විෂය ක්ශේත්‍රයක් කෙරෙහි මනා දැනුමක් තිබේනම් සහ එය ඉතා හොඳින් තවකෙකුට ඉගැන්විය හැකිනම් මේ ඔබේ අවස්ථාවයි. ඔබට ඉංග්‍රීසි මෙන්ම වෙනත් අන්තර්ජාතික භාෂාද හැසිරවිය හැකිනම්, ඔබට සේවය සැපයිය හැකි ප්‍රජාව අති විශාල වනවා. අන්තර්ජාල ඉගෙනුම් සඳහා ප්‍රසිද්ධ ක්‍රම වනුයේ video conference, සකසන ලද වීඩීයෝ, PDF ආකාරයට සැකසූ නිබන්දන, වෙබ් අඩවි ලිපි හරහා ඉගැන්වීම ආදියයි."},{"question":"আপনি আপনার অবসর সময়ে কি করতে পছন্দ করেন?","answer":"আমি একটি কৃত্রিম বুদ্ধিমত্তা মডেল, তাই আমার কোনো অবসর সময় নেই এবং আমি কোনো পছন্দ বা প্রাথমিক ইচ্ছা অনুভব করি না। তবে, আমি যে সেবা প্রদান করতে উপস্থিত আছি, সেটি হলো লেখা সাহায্য প্রদান করা, প্রশ্নের উত্তর দেওয়া, শিক্ষাদান প্রদান করা, সাধারণ জ্ঞান সম্প্রসারণ করা এবং অন্যান্য ধরনের লেখাগুলি তৈরি করা। তবে একটি কৃত্রিম বুদ্ধিমত্তা মডেল, হিসেবে আমি আপনার জন্য অবসর সময় কাটানোর কিছু উপায় সম্পর্কে পরামর্শ দিতে পারি।  যেমন - বাগান করা, খবরের কাগজ দেখা, কার্টুন দেখা, রান্না শেখা, গল্পের বই পড়া। "},{"question":"Quốc kỳ nước nào ở Đông Nam Á có hình ảnh đền Angkor Wat ở giữa?","answer":"Đền Angkor Wat là biểu tượng của Campuchia và xuất hiện trên quốc kỳ của nước này."},{"question":"Seriki awon Fulani lo maa n ba wa fun awon ajinigbe lowo -Awon ara Igangan","answer":"Pẹlu bi inu wọn ṣe n dun ṣinkin fún bí ọba awọn Fulani ipinlẹ Ọyọ, Alhaji Saliu Abdul-Kadiri, atawọn Fulani ilu Igangan ṣe sa fi ilu naa silẹ, awọn araalu naa ti royin idaamu ti awọn ọdaju àjèjì náà n mú ba awọn.Wọn ni yatọ si bi awọn Fulani ṣe maa n pa awọn nipakupa, aadọta miliọnu naira (#50m) lawọn maa n san fawọn ọdaju àjèjì náà kí wọn tóo lè yọnda eeyan awọn ti wọn ba ji gbe fawon.Lọjọ Aiku, Sannde, ìjẹta, ni wọn sọrọ yii nigba ti wọn gbalejo aṣoju ijọba ipinlẹ Ọyọ ati oga agba ọlọpaa ipinlẹ naa, Abilekọ Ngozi Onadeko, fun ìpàdé alaafia ati abẹwo sí awọn nnkan to bajẹ lasiko rogbodiyan to waye lọjọ Ẹtì, Furaidee, to kọja.Tẹ o ba gbagbe, lọjọ Ẹti, Furaidee, to kọja, lajafẹtọọ ọmọ Yorùbá nni, Oloye Sunday Adeyẹmọ, ti gbogbo eeyan mọ si Sunday Ìgbòho ya wọlu Igangan pẹlu awọn ajijagbara ẹgbẹ ẹ bíi OPC atawọn ọmọ ẹgbẹ Agbẹkọya lati sọ fún àwọn ọdaran Fulani to wa niluu naa ati agbegbe Ibarapa lapapọ, pé àsìkò ti to fún wọn láti fi ipinlẹ Ọyọ silẹ patapata.Lọsan-an ọjọ Sannde to kọja laṣoju Gomina Ṣeyi Makinde ti ipinlẹ Ọyọ, CP Fatai Owoṣeni ti i ṣe oludamọran pataki fún gomina lori ọrọ eto aabo, pẹlu ọga agba ọlọpaa ipinlẹ Ọyọ, CP Ngozi Onadeko. ṣabẹwo siluu Igangan lati wo awọn nnkan to bajẹ lasiko laasigbo naa. ki wọn si ba awọn agbaagba agbegbe Ibarapa sọrọ.Ninu Ipade ọhun lawọn ara Igangan ti lahùn pe awọn Fulani lo wa nidii awọn iṣẹlẹ ọdaran bíi ipaniyan, ijinigbe, idigunjale ati ifipabanilopọ to n waye gbọnmọgbọnmọ lagbagbe awọn lẹnu lọọlọọ yìí.Wọn ni oun to ṣe ni ni kayeefi ni pe ọba awọn Fúlàní to sá fi ilu Igangan silẹ yii mọ nipa ọran naa nitori oun lo maa mọ bi owo ti awọn ba san lati yọ awọn eeyan awọn kuro nigbekun awọn ajinigbe yóò ṣe tẹ awọn agbesunmọmi ẹda naa lọwọ.Nigba to n sọrọ lorukọ Gomina Makinde, CP Owoṣeni sọ pe ìgbàgbọ ọpọ eeyan ni pe ijọba ko gbe igbesẹ kankan lati dẹkun eto aabo to mẹhẹ, bẹẹ ọrọ ko ri bẹẹ, eeyan mokanlelaaadọta nijọba ti mu fún onírúurú iwa ọdaran nipinlẹ naa to jẹ pe wọn ti fa wọn le awọn ọlọpaa lọwọ, ti wọn sì ti fi oju ọpọ nínú wọn ba ile-ẹjọ.Ninu ọrọ tiẹ, CP Onadeko rọ awọn olugbe agbegbe naa lati gba alaafia laaye, ki wọn si yee máa fọwọ ara wọn jẹ arufin níyà. Dipo bẹẹ, ki wọn maa fa wọn lè awọn agbofinro lọwọ fún ijiya to ba tọ labẹ ofin."},{"question":"Tohizo izao ohabolana izao : \\"  Rava tokantrano  ......................... \\"","answer":"\\"  Rava tokantrano rava harena. \\" "},{"question":"Ndiani akanyora Murume Mutete muna 1934 (mazita ose)?","answer":"Bhuku rinonzi \\"The Thin Man,\\" rakabudiswa muna 1934, rakanyorwa nemunyori weAmerica Dashiell Hammett. Hammett ane mukurumbira nekupa kwake kune yakaomeswa detective genre uye anoonekwa semumwe wevatenzi vekunyepedzera mhosva. \\"The Thin Man\\" inosuma vatambi Nick naNora Charles, murume nemukadzi vane hunyanzvi, uye imbwa yavo, Asta. Nhaurirano yeinovhero yehungwaru, chiitiko chinokatyamadza, uye kuratidzwa kweanoyevedza detective duo zvakabatsira mukuzivikanwa kwaro uye kugadziridzwa kwefirimu kwakatevera."},{"question":"Iza no anaran’ilay renirano afrikanina izay mandalo firenena 11 ka antsoina indraindray hoe « Reniranom-piainana »?","answer":"Ny reniranon’i Nile izany."},{"question":"السؤال: كم عدد أركان الإيمان ؟","answer":"الإجابة: ستة أركان"},{"question":"传统毒品有什么？","answer":"1.鸦片，以罂粟为原料制成的毒品，有镇痛、麻醉作用，易成瘾。2.吗啡，由鸦片提纯而成的白色粉末，注射吗啡所产生的毒性比吸食鸦片强10—20倍，长期使用吗啡使人注意力、记忆力衰退，容易引起精神失常。3.海洛因，用吗啡加化学物质提炼成的一种白色粉状物，俗称“白粉”。4.可卡因，又名古柯碱，是以古柯树叶为原料，经提炼制成的白色结晶粉末状烈性毒品，有高度毒性，极易上瘾。5.大麻，一年生草本植物，有毒性，长期服用会出现精神依赖性，作为毒品的大麻主要有大麻草、大麻脂、大麻油三种。"},{"question":"Bolanle Austen-Peters","answer":"Bolanle Austen-Peters (tí wọ́n bí ní ọjọ́ kẹ́rin, oṣù kejì ọdún 1969), jẹ́ olùdarí Fíìmù/Tíátà Nàìjíríà àti Agbẹjọ́rò. Òun tún ni Olùdásílẹ̀ àti Olùdarí fún Terra Kulture, ilé-iṣẹ́ tó ń ṣètò nípa àṣà tó wà ní Ìpínlẹ̀ Èkó, ilé-iṣẹ́ fíìmù àti tíátà rẹ̀, BAP Productions, tí ṣe Atọ́kùn fún àwọn ètò orin bíi: Saro The Musical, Wakaa The Musical, Moremi The Musical, Fela àti the Kalakuta Queens, The Oluronbi Musical, àti èyí tí wọ́́ ṣẹ̀ṣẹ̀ ṣe Death and The King's Horseman. Ilé-iṣẹ́ náà ti ṣe Atọ́kùn àwọn fíìmù bíi 93 Days, Bling Lagosians, Collision Course, àti Man of God. Ó wà ní ìbásẹpọ̀ pẹ̀lú Google Arts & Culture ilé ìdánilẹ́kọ̀ọ́ tó máa ń ṣe àkójọjọ̀ ohun ìgbàanì fún Terrakulture lórí Íńtánẹ́ẹ̀tìÓ fẹ́ Adegboyega Austen-Peters, pẹ̀lú ọmọ méjì."},{"question":"Σε ποιο σημαντικό γεγονός αναφέρεται το κείμενο: Ως το Β΄ παγκόσμιο πόλεμο ήταν από τα πλουσιότερα σωματεία. Εκτός από ποδόσφαιρο, διατηρούσε τμήματα στίβου, κολύμβησης και σκοποβολής. Είχε πολυτελή γραφεία στη γωνία των οδών Χαλκοκονδύλη και Πατησίων, στα οποία στεγάζονταν και άλλα σωματεία καθώς και η ΕΠΣΑ. Τα γραφεία αυτά πυρπολήθηκαν στα γεγονότα του Δεκεμβρίου 1944 (Δεκεμβριανά), με αποτέλεσμα να καταστραφούν τα αρχεία και τα τρόπαια του συλλόγου και να μείνει άστεγος. Μεταπολεμικά βρέθηκε στην Α΄ κατηγορία και από το 1950 στην Α2 κατηγορία της ΕΠΣΑ. Τον Ιούλιο του 1952 συγχωνεύτηκε με την Α.Ε. Νέας Ελβετίας και προέκυψε η νέα ονομασία Αθηναϊκός Νέας Ελβετίας Αθλητικός Σύλλογος. Συνήθως τον αποκαλούσαν \\"Αθηναϊκό\\" ή \\"Aθηναϊκό Νέας Ελβετίας\\".","answer":"Ο Aθηναϊκός Νέας Ελβετίας."},{"question":"  2011-ஆம் ஆண்டில் பிரான்ஸ் தேசிய காற்பந்து அணிக்காக முதன்முறையாக விளையாடினார். இன்றுவரை 50 முறைகளுக்கு மேல் பங்கேற்றுள்ள இவர்","answer":"யூரோ 2012 மற்றும் 2014 உலகக்கோப்பை காற்பந்து போட்டித்தொடர்களில் காலிறுதியை எட்டிய அணியில் இடம்பெற்றவர்."},{"question":"உள்ளரங்க விளையாட்டுகளின் பெயர்களை எழுதுக","answer":"தாயம், ஐந்தாங்கல், பல்லாங்குழி சதுரங்கம் கேரம்"},{"question":"నల్లని రాళ్ళకు శిల్పిమీద కృతజ్ఞత ఎందుకుండాలి?","answer":"నల్లని రాళ్ళు కొండలమీదనే పడి ఉంటే, అవి బండరాళ్ళగానే మిగిలిపోయేవి. కాని శిల్పి చేతిలో పడి అవి దేవతా మూర్తులయ్యాయి, దేవాలయాలయ్యాయి. అవి పసుపు, కుంకుమ, పుష్పాలతో పూజలు అందుకుంటున్నాయి. కాబట్టి నల్లని రాళ్ళు, శిల్పి మీద కృతజ్ఞత చూపాలి."},{"question":"የዚህን አንቀጽ ቀጣይነት ይጻፉ - ኢሊ ብሪያ (የተወለደው መጋቢት 23 ቀን 1989) የሞልዶቫ አገር አቋራጭ የበረዶ መንሸራተቻ ተጫዋች ነው ። በወንዶች ፈጣን ሩጫ ውድድር ላይ ተወዳድሯል","answer":"በ2006 የክረምት ኦሎምፒክ ላይ ተወዳድሯል።"},{"question":"Şehir yöneticilerinin, enerji tasarrufu yapması için bazı seçenekler sunulmuştur.  Mevcut seçenekler: [i] otopark ücretlerinin düşürülmesi. [ii] daha büyük otoparkların inşa edilmesi. [iii] benzin maliyetinin düşürülmesi. [iv] otobüs ve metro ücretlerinin düşürülmesi. Hangisi seçeneği seçmek daha faydalıdır?","answer":"[iv]. seçenek olan \\"otobüs ve metro ücretlerinin düşürülmesi.\\" daha faydalı olacaktır. "},{"question":"පෝලන්තය ගැන කෙටි විස්තරයක් කරන්න. ","answer":"පෝලන්ත සමුහාණ්ඩුව මධ්‍යම යුරෝපයේ පිහිටි රටකි. එය මායිම් වන්නේ බටහිරින් ජර්මනිය, දකුණට ඩෙන්මාර්ක් සමුහාණ්ඩුව හා ස්ලෝවෙනියාව, නැගෙනහිරින් යුක්රේනය, බෙලාරූස් හා ලිතුවේනියා, උතුරින් බෝල්ටික් මුහුද සහ ලෙනින් ග්‍රෑඩ් වලටය. මුළු වර්ග ප්‍රමාණයෙන් වර්ග කි.මී. 312, 679 (වර්ග සැතපුම් 120,726) වන අතර ලෝකයේ 69 වන විශාලතම රට වන අතර යුරෝපයේ 9 වන විශාලතම රටයි. එහි ජනගනය මිලියන 38 ඉක්මවන අතර ලෝකයේ ජනගහනයෙන් 34 වන රටයි. යුරෝපානු සංගමයේ ජනප්‍රියම සාමාජිකයන්ගෙන් කෙනෙකි. 966 දී පාලකයෙකුව සිටි මෙයිස්නෝ ක්‍රිස්තු ධර්මය වැළඳගත් පසු පෝලන්ත රාජ්‍ය බිහි විය. පෝලන්ත රාජධානිය 1025 පිහිටුවන ලැබු අතර, 1569 දී ලිතුවේනියා ආදිපාද වසම සමඟ ස්ථිර සමාගමක් ඇති කරගත් අතර, ලිබිලින් සංගමය ලියවිල්ලෙන් ලිතුවේනියානු පොදු රාජ්‍ය පිහිටුවිය. 1795 දී පොදු රාජ්‍ය කඩා වැටුණු අතර ‍පෝලන්ත දේශ සීමා ප්‍රෂියා රාජධානිය, රුසියානු රාජධානිය සහ ඔස්ට්‍රියා කොටස් කරන ලදි. 1918 වර්ෂයේ දී 2 වන පෝලන්ත සමුහාණ්ඩුව ලෙස නිදහස ලැබීය. 2 වන ලෝක යුධ සමයේ දී එය නාසි ජර්මානුවන් හා සෝවියට් සමුහාණ්ඩුව විසින් අත්පත් කර ගත්හ. පෝලන්තයට තම ජනගහනය වූ මිලියන 6 න් මිලියන 2 ක් ලෝක යුද්ධයෙන් අහිමි විය. සෝවියට් බලපෑමෙන් නැගෙනහිර කොටසේ පෝලන්ත මහජන සමුහාණ්ඩුව ලෙස බිහි විය. 1989 දී පැවැති විප්ලවයෙන් කොමියුනිස්ට්වරුන් පරාජය වු අතර, පෝලන්තය ව්‍යවස්ථාදායකව හඳුන්වන තුන්වන ‍පෝලන්ත සමුහාණ්ඩුව විය. පෝලන්තය එක්සත් රාජ්‍යයන් වන අතර යුරෝපානු සංගමය, පොදු රාජ්‍ය මණ්ඩලය, ලෝක වෙළෙඳ සංගමය සහ ආර්ථික සහයෝගීතා හා සංවර්ධන සංගමයේ (OECD) සාමාජිකයෙකි."},{"question":"السؤال: كم عدد ولايات الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية؟","answer":"الإجابة: 50 ولاية"},{"question":"පැල් කවියක් සඳහා  උදාහරණයක් දෙන්න. ","answer":"කන්ද උඩින් එන කිකිළිය          ගෝමරියේනළල් පටින් එන දාඩිය මුතු       කැටියේඅත් පා මුදු පය පා මුදු වයි          රොඩියේමට පිටුපා ගෙට යනවද             සුරතලියේ"},{"question":"अगाधजलसञ्चारी गर्वं नायाति रोहितः |अङ्गुष्ठोदकमात्रेण शफरी फर्फरायते ||","answer":"अर्थ : रोहित हा [एक मोठा मासा] खूप खोल पाण्यात विहार करून सुद्धा गर्व करीत नाही. पण शफरी मात्र टीचभर पाण्यात असली तरी [गर्वाने] फुगते."},{"question":"Cual es la respuesta correcta para esta pregunta : ¿Cuál libro de Michael Connelly ganó el premio Barry por mejor novela en 1998?","answer":" La respuesta correcta a la pregunta que estás realizando es : música de baúl"},{"question":"السّؤال: من هو أول صحابيٍّ غزا في سبيل الله تعالى؟","answer":"الجواب: حمزة بن عبد المطلب رضي الله عنه."},{"question":"Ọchịchị Onye kwuo uche ya ","answer":"Ọchịchị Onye kwuo uche ya bụ ọchịchị n'abughị nke ndị soja,nke onye ọbụla nwere ike ikwu uche ya site na imegide ihe n'ezighi ezi nke ndị nọ na ọchịchị n'eme. Nke a bụkwa ọchịchị n'enye ụmụ amaala ohere ịhọpụta onye ga achị ha site n'ime ntuliaka."},{"question":"கேள்வி : தமிழில் ராமாயணம் எழுதியவர் யார்?","answer":"பதில் :இது இந்து சமயத்தின் முக்கியமான நூல்களுள் ஒன்று. மூல நூலான வால்மீகியின் இராமாயணத்தைத் தழுவிப் பல இந்திய மொழிகளிலும், பிற நாடுகளின் மொழிகளிலும் இராமாயணம் இயற்றப்பட்டுள்ளது. கம்பர் என்னும் புலவர் புலவர்களுக்கே உண்டான பாணியில் பல கற்பனைகளை இனைத்து இதனைத் தமிழில் எழுதினார்."},{"question":"રે’શું અમે ય ગુમાનમાં કવિતા લખો","answer":"રે’શું અમે ય ગુમાનમાંહરિ સંગ નહીં બોલીએખોલીશું બારણાં ને લેશું ઓવારણાંઆવકારા દેશું સાનમાંહરિ સંગ નહીં બોલીએઆસનિયા ઢાળશું ને ચરણોમાં પખાળશુંઆંખ્યું ઉલાળશું તોફાનમાંહરિ સંગ નહીં બોલીએલાપસિયું ચોળશું ને વીંઝણલા ઢોળશુંમુખવાસા દેશું પાનમાંહરિ સંગ નહીં બોલીએમીરાં કે અંતમાં, આ ભરવસંતમાંજીવતર દઈ દેશું દાનમાંહરિ સંગ નહીં બોલીએ"},{"question":"O seguinte texto é sobre que evento importante: William Flannery (17 de novembro de 1898 — Los Angeles, 25 de janeiro de 1959) foi um diretor de arte estadunidense. Venceu o Oscar de melhor direção de arte na edição de 1956 por \\"Picnic\\", ao lado de Jo Mielziner e Robert Priestley.","answer":"Oscar de 1956"},{"question":"இரட்டைக் காப்பியங்கள் என அழைக்கப்படுபவைஅ) நீலகேசி, குண்டலகேசிஆ) உதயணகுமாரகாவியம், நாககுமார காவியம்இ) சிந்தாமணி, சூளாமணிஈ) சிலப்பதிகாரம், மணிமேகலை","answer":"ஈ) சிலப்பதிகாரம், மணிமேகலை"},{"question":"ಮೈಸೂರು ಅರಮನೆಯ ಬಗ್ಗೆ ಹೇಳಿ.","answer":"ಭಾರತದ ಕರ್ನಾಟಕದಲ್ಲಿರುವ ಮೈಸೂರು ಅರಮನೆಯು ಇಂಡೋ-ಸಾರ್ಸೆನಿಕ್ ವಾಸ್ತುಶಿಲ್ಪದ ಅದ್ಭುತ ಉದಾಹರಣೆಯಾಗಿದೆ. ಅಂಬಾ ವಿಲಾಸ್ ಅರಮನೆ ಎಂದೂ ಕರೆಯಲ್ಪಡುವ ಇದು ಸಂಕೀರ್ಣವಾದ ವಿವರಗಳು, ರೋಮಾಂಚಕ ಬಣ್ಣಗಳು ಮತ್ತು ಬೆರಗುಗೊಳಿಸುತ್ತದೆ ಗುಮ್ಮಟಗಳನ್ನು ಪ್ರದರ್ಶಿಸುತ್ತದೆ. 1912 ರಲ್ಲಿ ನಿರ್ಮಿಸಲಾಯಿತು, ಇದು ವಾಡಿಯಾರ್ ರಾಜವಂಶದ ನಿವಾಸವಾಗಿತ್ತು ಮತ್ತು ಸಾಂಪ್ರದಾಯಿಕ ಸಾಂಸ್ಕೃತಿಕ ಮತ್ತು ಐತಿಹಾಸಿಕ ಹೆಗ್ಗುರುತಾಗಿ ಉಳಿದಿದೆ, ವಾರ್ಷಿಕವಾಗಿ ಹಲವಾರು ಪ್ರವಾಸಿಗರನ್ನು ಆಕರ್ಷಿಸುತ್ತದೆ."},{"question":"¿Qué es el Heliocentrismo?","answer":"El heliocentrismo es un modelo astronómico según el cual la Tierra y los planetas se mueven alrededor del Sol relativamente estacionario y que está en el centro del universo. Históricamente, el heliocentrismo se oponía al geocentrismo, que colocaba en el centro a la Tierra. "},{"question":"ලොව උසම කඳු 10 මොනවද ?","answer":"ලොව උසම කඳු 10 පිලිවෙලින් :එවරස්ට් කන්ද(මීටර් 8848)k2 කන්ද(මීටර්  8611)කාංචන් චුන්ගා කන්ද(මීටර් 8586) ලොට් සී කන්ද(මීටර් 8516)මකාලු කන්ද(මීටර් 8485)චොයු කන්ද(මීටර් 8188)ධවලගිරි I කන්ද(මීටර් 8167)මනස්ලු කන්ද(මීටර් 8163)නන්ගාපාර්බත් කන්ද(මීටර් 8126) අන්නාපූර්නා I කන්ද(මීටර් 8091)"},{"question":"Apakah ibu negara China?","answer":"Beijing"},{"question":"वित्तीय संस्थाहरूले कसरी मुद्रा विनिमय व्यवस्थापन गर्छन् र उपभोक्ताहरूको लागि उचित दरहरू सुनिश्चित गर्छन्?","answer":"वित्तीय संस्थाहरूले मुद्रा विनिमय सेवाहरू प्रयोग गर्छन्, बजार प्रवृतिहरूमा आधारित दरहरू सेट गर्छन्, र प्रतिस्पर्धी र निष्पक्ष विनिमय दरहरू सुनिश्चित गर्न उपभोक्ताहरूलाई पारदर्शिता प्रदान गर्छन्।"},{"question":"Hãy viết một bài báo có thể sử dụng tiêu đề sau: Lạm phát Nhật Bản lần đầu vượt Mỹ sau 8 năm","answer":"Lạm phát cơ bản tháng 6 của Nhật Bản là 3,3%, cao hơn 0,3 điểm phần trăm so với Mỹ, lần đầu từ tháng 10/2015.Theo số liệu mới công bố, chỉ số lạm phát lõi (không tính giá thực phẩm tươi sống) của Nhật trong tháng 6 nhích thêm 0,1% so với tháng 5, ở mức 3,3%. Nguyên nhân chủ yếu là do giá điện tăng mạnh. Mức tăng này vẫn thấp hơn mức dự báo (3,5%) của Ngân hàng trung ương Nhật Bản (BOJ).Trong khi đó, lạm phát của Mỹ là 3% trong tháng 6. Như vậy, lần đầu sau 8 năm, lạm phát Nhật Bản vượt Mỹ.Hôm 20/7, Chính phủ Nhật dự báo lạm phát năm nay có thể cán mốc 2,6%, cao hơn so với mức 2% được BOJ đưa ra; đồng thời hạ mục tiêu tăng trưởng từ 1,5% xuống còn 1,3%.Áp lực giá cả ở Nhật Bản - nơi chứng kiến giảm phát suốt 30 năm qua - xuất hiện từ cuối năm 2022 và hiện chưa dừng lại. Cùng với diễn biến của yen những tuần qua càng khiến thị trường tin rằng BOJ sẽ phải thay đổi lập trường về nới lỏng chính sách tiền tệ trong nửa cuối năm nay.Tuần này, Thống đốc Ngân hàng trung ương Nhật Bản Kazuo Ueda phát tín hiệu sẽ duy trì các biện pháp nới lỏng trong cuộc họp tuần tới. Động thái này của ông Ueda khiến đồng yen mất giá trước USD, dù có tín hiệu đi lên trong một tuần trở lại đây.Hiện, Nhật là quốc gia duy nhất trên thế giới có lãi suất âm. Tuy nhiên việc duy trì lãi suất thấp kỷ lục đang khiến chính sách của họ đi ngược lại làn sóng thắt chặt trên toàn cầu. Trong bối cảnh hiện nay, số liệu lạm phát đang làm tăng xác suất BOJ điều chỉnh chính sách tiền tệ, và như vậy có thể gây ra những tác động nhất định tới tài chính toàn cầu."},{"question":"Windscreen (වාහනයක) කියන වචනයට සිංහලෙන් මොකක්ද කියන්නෙ?","answer":"Windscreen = වාමුවාව"},{"question":"Bu paragrafın devamını yazın:  \\"Mesudiye\\"den kurtarılan 150 mm toplar, Çanakkale'de kıyıya yerleştirilerek \\"Mesudiye Tabyası\\" kuruldu. Bu silahlar, 18 Mart 1915'te Çanakkale Deniz Savaşı","answer":"'nda kullanıldı. Tabya, Fransız savaş \\"Bouvet\\"ye sekiz kez isabet sağladı, bu isabetlerden biri geminin ön taretini devre dışı bıraktı. \\"Bouvet\\" daha sonra bir mayına çarparak battı, mürettebatının büyük kısmı öldü."},{"question":"Title: మానసిక ఆరోగ్యం గురించి భారతీయులు పట్టించుకోవడం లేదా?nGiven the above title of an imaginary article, imagine the article.n","answer":"అప్పుడప్పుడు ఇంటి పనిలో సాయం చేయమని పిలుస్తుంటాను. ఎప్పటిలాగే ఒక రోజు ఆమెను 'ఎలా ఉన్నావ'ని అడిగాను. అందుకామె ఏమీ బాగులేనని చెప్పింది. అంతేకాదు.. ''నాకు ఏడుపొస్తోంది. గత మంగళవారం రోజంతా ఏడుస్తూనే ఉన్నాన''ని తన అవధి శైలిలో వడివడిగా చెప్పింది. అలా చెబుతున్నప్పుడు కూడా ఆమె ముఖంలో నవ్వు ఉంది. అంతకుముందు కూడా ఓసారి అదే మాట చెప్పింది. ఏడుపొస్తోందంటూ అంజు పదేపదే చెబుతోందంటే ఆమె ఏదైనా సమస్యలో చిక్కకుందా? దిగువ మధ్యతరగతి కుటుంబం నుంచి వచ్చిన అంజు కానీ, ఆమె కుటుంబసభ్యలు కానీ ఆమెకు వైద్య సహాయం అవసరమని గుర్తించారా? సాధారణంగా తలెత్తే మానసిక సమస్యేనా(సీఎండీ) ఇది? ఇలాంటి మానసిక సమస్య కొద్దిమందికే పరిమితమా? లేదంటే అందరి సమస్యా?'నేషనల్ ఇనిస్టిట్యూట్ ఆఫ్ మెంటల్ హెల్త్ అండ్ న్యూరోసైన్సెస్' 2016లో భారతదేశంలోని 12 రాష్ట్రాల్లో చేసిన సర్వేలో అనేక ఆందోళనకర అంశాలు వెల్లడయ్యాయి. ఈ సర్వే ప్రకారం 2.7 శాతం ప్రజలు డిప్రెషన్ వంటి మానసిక సమస్యలతో సతమతమవుతున్నారు. అంతేకాదు.. దేశంలో 15 కోట్ల మందికి మానసిక సమస్యల నుంచి ఉపశమనం కోసం సత్వర వైద్య సహాయం అవసరమనీ ఈ సర్వే తేల్చింది. సైన్స్ జర్నల్ లాన్సెట్‌లో 2016లో ప్రచురితమైన ఒక నివేదిక.. దేశంలో మానసిక వైద్య సహాయం అవసరమైన ప్రతి 10 మందిలో కేవలం ఒక్కరే అలాంటి సేవలు పొందగలుగుతున్నారని చెప్పింది. మరోవైపు భారత్‌లో ఏటా మానసిక సమస్యలతో సతమతమవుతున్నవారి సంఖ్య పెరుగుతూనే ఉంది. ఇది ఇలాగే కొనసాగితే పదేళ్ల తరువాత ప్రపంచంలో మానసిక సమస్యల బారినపడినవారిలో మూడింట ఒక వంతు భారతీయులే ఉండొచ్చని ఆ నివేదిక అంచనా వేసింది.డాక్టర్ నిమిశ్ దేసాయీభారత్‌లో వేగంగా చోటుచేసుకుంటున్న మార్పులు మానసిక సమస్యలకు దారితీస్తున్నాయని నిపుణులు ఆందోళన వ్యక్తంచేస్తున్నారు. నగరాలు విస్తరిస్తుండడం, ఆధునిక వసతులు అందుబాటులోకి వస్తుండడం, చాలామంది సొంతూళ్లు, నగరాలను వీడి కొత్త నగరాలకు మారుతుండడం వంటివన్నీ ప్రజల మానసిక స్థితిపై ప్రభావం చూపుతాయని, ఈ క్రమంలో ఎదురయ్యే అనేక ఇబ్బందులు కుంగుబాటుకు దారితీయొచ్చని చెబుతున్నారు.దిల్లీకి చెదిన ఇనిస్టిట్యూట్ ఆఫ్ హ్యూమన్ బిహేవియర్ అండ్ అల్లీడ్ సైన్సెస్(ఐహెచ్‌బీఏఎస్) డైరెక్టర్, గత నలభయ్యేళ్లుగా సైకియాట్రిస్ట్‌గా పనిచేస్తున్న డాక్టర్ నిమిష్ దేసాయ్ ''కుటుంబాలు విచ్ఛిన్నం కావడం, భారత్‌లో పాశ్చ్యాత్తీకరణ శరవేగంగా జరుగుతుండడంతో కొత్త సాంకేతికతల ఆవిర్భావం కూడా ఒత్తిళ్లకు కారణం కావొచ్చు. "},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਅਸਟਪਦੀ ॥ਮਿਥਿਆ ਨਾਹੀ ਰਸਨਾ ਪਰਸ ॥ਮਨ ਮਹਿ ਪ੍ਰੀਤਿ ਨਿਰੰਜਨ ਦਰਸ ॥ਪਰ ਤ੍ਰਿਅ ਰੂਪੁ ਨ ਪੇਖੈ ਨੇਤ੍ਰ ॥ਸਾਧ ਕੀ ਟਹਲ ਸੰਤਸੰਗਿ ਹੇਤ ॥ਕਰਨ ਨ ਸੁਨੈ ਕਾਹੂ ਕੀ ਨਿੰਦਾ ॥ਸਭ ਤੇ ਜਾਨੈ ਆਪਸ ਕਉ ਮੰਦਾ ॥ਗੁਰ ਪ੍ਰਸਾਦਿ ਬਿਖਿਆ ਪਰਹਰੈ ॥ਮਨ ਕੀ ਬਾਸਨਾ ਮਨ ਤੇ ਟਰੈ ॥ਇੰਦ੍ਰੀ ਜਿਤ ਪੰਚ ਦੋਖ ਤੇ ਰਹਤ ॥ਨਾਨਕ ਕੋਟਿ ਮਧੇ ਕੋ ਐਸਾ ਅਪਰਸ ॥੧॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 274 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਅਰਜਨ ਦੇਵ ਜੀ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਬਾਣੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਹਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"ਜੋ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਜੀਭ ਨਾਲ ਝੂਠ ਨੂੰ ਛੋਹਣ ਨਹੀਂ ਦੇਂਦਾ, ਮਨ ਵਿਚ ਅਕਾਲ ਪੁਰਖ ਦੇ ਦੀਦਾਰ ਦੀ ਤਾਂਘ ਰੱਖਦਾ ਹੈ; ਜੋ ਪਰਾਈ ਇਸਤ੍ਰੀ ਦੇ ਹੁਸਨ ਨੂੰ ਆਪਣੀਆਂ ਅੱਖਾਂ ਨਾਲ ਨਹੀਂ ਤੱਕਦਾ, ਭਲੇ ਮਨੁੱਖਾਂ ਦੀ ਟਹਲ (ਕਰਦਾ ਹੈ) ਤੇ ਸੰਤ ਜਨਾਂ ਦੀ ਸੰਗਤਿ ਵਿਚ ਪ੍ਰੀਤ (ਰੱਖਦਾ ਹੈ); ਜੋ ਕੰਨਾਂ ਨਾਲ ਕਿਸੇ ਦੀ ਭੀ ਨਿੰਦਿਆ ਨਹੀਂ ਸੁਣਦਾ, ਸਾਰਿਆਂ ਨਾਲੋਂ ਆਪਣੇ ਆਪ ਨੂੰ ਮਾੜਾ ਸਮਝਦਾ ਹੈ; ਜੋ ਗੁਰੂ ਦੀ ਮੇਹਰ ਦਾ ਸਦਕਾ ਮਾਇਆ (ਦਾ ਪ੍ਰਭਾਵ) ਪਰੇ ਹਟਾ ਦੇਂਦਾ ਹੈ, ਤੇ ਜਿਸ ਦੇ ਮਨ ਦੀ ਵਾਸਨਾ ਮਨ ਤੋਂ ਟਲ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ; ਜੋ ਆਪਣੇ ਗਿਆਨ-ਇੰਦ੍ਰਿਆਂ ਨੂੰ ਵੱਸ ਵਿਚ ਰੱਖ ਕੇ ਕਾਮਾਦਿਕ ਪੰਜੇ ਹੀ ਵਿਕਾਰਾਂ ਤੋਂ ਬਚਿਆ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ, ਹੇ ਨਾਨਕ! ਕਰੋੜਾਂ ਵਿਚੋਂ ਕੋਈ ਇਹੋ ਜਿਹਾ ਵਿਰਲਾ ਬੰਦਾ “ਅਪਰਸ” (ਕਿਹਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ) ।੧।\\""},{"question":"சே. குவேராவின் மேற்கோள் ஒன்றை தரவும்.","answer":"எல்லா மனிதருக்கும் மனிதம், அன்பு என்பது சாத்தியமாகும் வரை நாம் போராடிக்கொண்டே இருக்க வேண்டும்.சே குவேரா (Che Guevara) என பொதுவாக அறியப்பட்ட எர்னெஸ்டோ குவேரா டி லா செர்னா (Ernesto Guevara de la Serna) (14 சூன் 1928 – 9 அக்டோபர் 1967) அர்ஜென்டீனாவை பிறப்பிடமாகக் கொண்ட ஒரு சோசலிசப் புரட்சியாளர், மருத்துவர், மார்க்சியவாதி, அரசியல்வாதி, கியூபா மற்றும் பல நாடுகளின் (கொங்கோ உட்பட) புரட்சிகளில் பங்குபெற்ற போராளி எனப்பல முகங்களைக் கொண்டவர்.பெயர்சே என்பது வியப்புச்சொல் ஆகும். இச்சொல்லை அர்சென்டீனர்கள், குவேரனி இந்தியர்களிடமிருந்து பழகினர் என்று கருதப்படுகிறது. அவ்விந்தியர், எனது என்ற பொருளில் பயன்படுத்துவர் என்று மானுடவியல் அறிஞர் கூறுவர். ஆனால், தென்னமரிக்கப் பாம்பாஸ் புல்வெளியினருக்கு வியப்பு, மகிழ்ச்சி, வருத்தம், நாணயம், அட்சேபம், அங்கீகாரம் போன்ற பல மனித உணர்வுகளை வெளிப்படுத்தும் சொல்லாக அமைகிறது. இடத்திற்கு ஏற்பவும், ஒலிப்புக்கு ஏற்றவாறும் அச்சொல் பயனாகிறது. இச்சொல்லின் மீதுள்ள பற்றால், கியூபா புரட்சியாளர்கள், 'சே' என்று செல்லமாக அழைத்தனர். அவரது பெற்றோர், அவரை 'டேட்டி' என்று செல்லமாக அழைப்பர்."},{"question":"இந்தியாவில் காடுகளின் நிலப்பரப்பு \\t1. 15 சதவீதம்2. 19 சதவீதம்3. 27 சதவீதம்4. 23 சதவீதம்","answer":"4. 23 சதவீதம்."},{"question":"Se João é pai de Maria, então é correto afirmar que Maria é filha de João?","answer":"Sim, a afirmação é correta."},{"question":"Content: Sophie Oluwole tó jẹ́ Ọ̀jọ̀gbọ́n nínú ìmọ̀ àsà àti ìse Yoruba àti ilẹ́ Afirika lápaapọ̀ ti papòdà ní ẹni ọdún 83Sophie Oluwole ni wọ́n bí ní agbègbè Igbara-Oke ní ìpínlè Òndó ní ọdun 1936, tí ó sì kàwé gboyè láti Fáṣítì Ilé-Ifè ní bí ogójì ọdún sẹ́yìn.Akẹẹkọ gboyè onímò òye, Sophie Oluwole tó tún jẹ Ọjọgbọn nínú imọ àṣà, ìṣe Yorùbá àti tí ilẹ Áfíríkà lápapò dagbere fún ayé ní ọsan Ọjọ Ìsinmi, lẹ́yìn aisan ọlọjọ pípé.Èpo ọwọn, sunkere-fakere ọkọ àti àwọn olósà jẹ́ ipenija lójú pópóGbajugbaja oniroyin, Fúnni Iyanda sọ nipa igbe aye oloogbe naa to bu iyi kun imọ ilẹ adunlawo nipa oselu, idagbasoke ile Afirika ati ọrọ aje naa.Taiwo Obe naa fikun wipe Sophie Oluwole ti awọn eniyan ma n pe ni  \\"mamalawo\\" lo jẹ obinrin akọkọ to kawe gboye ọmọwe ni orilẹede Naijiria.Ọjọgbọn Oluwole naa to kọ ọpọlọpọ akẹẹkọ ni fasiti ilu Eko, ni ọpọ eniyan mo wi pe o sa ipa rẹ fun igbelarugẹ awọn obinrin, imọ ijinlẹ Yoruba ati ti ilẹ adulawo lapaapọ.nThe previous content can be summarized as follows:","answer":"Awọn ọmọ kaarọ oojiire ti n kẹdun Ọjọgbọn Sophie Oluwole to dagbere fun aye ni ẹni ọdun mẹtalelọgọrin."},{"question":"ગુજરાત મા કયા કયા પ્રકાર ખોરાક ઉત્પનથાય છે ?","answer":"ગુજરાતી ભોજન એટલે ભારત, પાકિસ્તાન અને વિશ્વમાં ગમેતે સ્થળે વસતા ગુજરાતી લોકોનું ભોજન, જેઓની પશ્ચિમ ભારત અને દક્ષિણ પાકિસ્તાન (મોટા ભાગે સિંધ)માં બહુમતી છે.આ ભોજન પ્રાથમિક રીતે શાકાહારી હોય છે. એક શુદ્ધ ગુજરાતી થાળીમાં રોટલી, શાક, ભાત કે ખીચડી, દાળ કે કઢી હોયજ છે. આ ભોજન સ્વાદ અને ગરમીની બાબતે ઘણું વિશાળ હોય છે, જેનો આધાર દરેક કુટુંબની સ્વાદની પસંદગી અને તેઓ ગુજરાતનાં કયા પ્રદેશ સાથે સંબંધ ધરાવે છે તે પર આધારીત હોય છે. ઉત્તર ગુજરાત, કચ્છ-કાઠિયાવાડ, મધ્ય ગુજરાત અને દક્ષિણ ગુજરાત આ ચાર ગુજરાતનાં મુખ્ય વિભાગો છે જે દરેક પોતાની અલગ ભોજન શૈલી ધરાવે છે. ઘણી ગુજરાતી વાનગી એકજ સમયે ગળી, ખારી અને તમતમતી મસાલેદાર સ્વાદ ધરાવતી પણ હોઇ શકે છે. ગુજરાતી ભોજન ક્યારેક વધુ પડતું તૈલી હોય છે.ગુજરાતી ભોજનમાં, મુખ્ય ભોજનની સાથે અથાણાં, છાશ, ફરસાણ, મીઠાઈ વગેરે પણ ઉપયોગમાં લેવામાં આવે છે. ભોજનમાં ઋતુઓ પ્રમાણે, શાકભાજીની ઉપલબ્ધતા અને ઠંડી-ગરમી જેવી આબોહવા મુજબ, ફેરફાર કરવામાં આવે છે. એજ રીતે મસાલાઓનો ઉપયોગ પણ ઋતુઓને ધ્યાનમાં રાખીને વધુ ઓછો કરવામાં આવે છે. જેમકે ઉનાળામાં ગરમ મસાલાઓનો ઉપયોગ ઓછો કરાય છે."},{"question":"أكمل هذه الجملة: ازداد التزام المجتمع الدولي بدعم تطوير محاسبة رأس المال الطبيعي بعد تقرير برونتلاند في عام 1987 و","answer":"قمة ريو عام 1992. وفي القمة على وجه الخصوص، اعتُمدَ جدول أعمال القرن ال21 ، و الذي دعى في الفصل رقم  40 الجهات المُوقعة لتطوير معلومات كمية متعلقة بأنشطتهم."},{"question":"英語でチョコレートのこと。フランス語では何という？","answer":"ショコラです。"},{"question":"‘యతి’ అంటే ఎన్నవ అక్షరము?A) మూడవB) రెండవC) ఒకటవD) నాల్గువ","answer":"C) ఒకటవ"},{"question":"ఇచ్చిన పద్యానికి భావం రాయండి:రంగులు జాతులుకావు మనకు – జ్ఞాతులుకుండలు చేరైనామృత్తిక ఒకటేకొమ్మలు, రెమ్మలు వేరైనాఏక వృక్ష భాగాలే!మనమంతా మానవులంకలయికలో ఉంది బలం.మనలో మన చీలికమన పతనానికి ఏలికమనలో మన చీలికమృత్యుదేవికి నాలుక","answer":"రంగులు జాతులు మనకి జ్ఞాతులు. కుండలను ఎన్ని రకాలుగా మలచినా వాటికి మూలం మట్టే. కొమ్మలు రెమ్మలు వేరుగా కన్పిస్తున్నా అవన్నీ ఒక చెట్టు భాగాలే! మానవులంతా కలిసి బతకాలి ఐకమత్యంలోనే బలం ఉంది. ఐకమత్యాన్ని కోల్పోతే మనల్ని మనం కోల్పోయినట్లే."},{"question":"O que significa o ditado popular: \\"Quem cala, consente\\"?","answer":"Ditado popular usado quando alguém não quer ou não tem coragem de responder algo desagradável.Exemplo: “Não vai mesmo falar sobre isso? Quem cala, consente!”"},{"question":"Đọc đoạn văn sau và đưa ra một tiêu đề phụ hợp với nội dung: Tính trong 6 tháng đầu năm, Bộ Thông tin và Truyền thông (Bộ TT&TT) đã phát hiện 74,178 triệu cuộc gọi phát sinh từ thuê bao spam call (cuộc gọi rác), tăng 53% so với cùng kỳ năm ngoái. Trong khi đó, các doanh nghiệp viễn thông cũng chặn 113.416 thuê bao phát tán cuộc gọi rác, tăng 53% so với cùng kỳ năm 2021. Theo đề nghị của Bộ Công an (Cục A05), Bộ TT&TT đã yêu cầu các doanh nghiệp chặn dịch vụ của SIM có dấu hiệu sử dụng, tham gia tuyên truyền hành vi vi phạm pháp luật như game bài, cờ bạc, mua bán vật liệu nổ, văn bằng giả… Tổng cộng, các doanh nghiệp đã chặn 1.043/1.465 đơn vị SIM, thực hiện hủy, chuyển quyền, tái đấu nối hoặc chuyển sang mạng khác 430 SIM. Bộ này cũng tổ chức cuộc họp với Bộ Công an (Cục A05) và các doanh nghiệp viễn thông di động gồm VNPT, Viettel, MobiFone, Vietnamobile về xử lý số điện thoại quảng cáo cho các hành vi vi phạm pháp luật và quy trình xử lý thuê bao có khiếu nại. Thanh tra Bộ đã phối hợp với Cục Viễn thông, Cục Tần số vô tuyến điện và đơn vị trực thuộc Bộ Công an xử lý những đối tượng sử dụng BTS giả mạo, phát tán tin nhắn rác. Để hạn chế thuê bao phát tán cuộc gọi rác, Bộ TT&TT cho biết sẽ thúc đẩy việc cấp tên định danh cho các thuê bao thực hiện quảng cáo, đồng thời tuyên truyền, xử phạt nghiêm các trường hợp vi phạm. Cơ quan chức năng cũng xem xét đưa tiêu chí phản ánh cuộc gọi rác từ người dùng là một trong các chỉ tiêu đánh giá chất lượng dịch vụ QoS (Quality of Service - chất lượng dịch vụ truyền thông) của nhà mạng. Để xử lý SIM rác, Bộ TT&TT đã triển khai hàng loạt biện pháp tăng cường quản lý thông tin thuê bao. Trong đó, yêu cầu xử lý SIM có thông tin không đúng quy định; nhà mạng phải rà quét thông tin thuê bao theo các tiêu chí (số CMND/CCCD), xác định các thuê bao nghi ngờ; thu hồi, ngăn chặn SIM có dấu hiệu kích hoạt sẵn còn tồn trên kênh phân phối; phối hợp với Bộ Công an tổ chức kiểm tra công tác quản lý thuê bao và xử lý vi phạm tại 7 doanh nghiệp viễn thông di động và các đại lý. Tính từ tháng 9/2021 đến nay, 100% SIM thuê bao đăng ký mới của cá nhân (tương ứng với 8 triệu SIM) đều được các nhà mạng Viettel, VinaPhone, MobiFone xác thực qua video call (cuộc gọi có hình ảnh). Từ tháng 6, các SIM thuê bao đang hoạt động của nhà mạng đã có đủ thông tin đáp ứng các tiêu chí đề ra. Hiện tổng số thuê bao di động của cả nước đang được duy trì ở mức 124 triệu đơn vị, giảm so với mức 127-129 triệu thuê bao trong giai đoạn 2018-2019. Đáng chú ý, bắt đầu từ ngày 1/8, các thuê bao di động mới phát sinh phải thực hiện xác thực với cơ sở dữ liệu quốc gia về dân cư để giải quyết nạn SIM rác. Trước đó, Văn phòng Chính phủ đã ban hành Thông báo 174 về Kết luận của Phó thủ tướng Vũ Đức Đam tại cuộc họp về kết nối thông tin thuê bao với cơ sở dữ liệu quốc gia về dân cư. Cụ thể, đại diện các bộ, cơ quan, doanh nghiệp viễn thông tham dự thống nhất khắc phục tình trạng SIM rác, SIM nặc danh thông qua quá trình kết nối dữ liệu. Việc kết nối, xác thực cần triển khai đồng bộ, bình đẳng giữa các nhà mạng; dữ liệu cần được bảo vệ, không ảnh hưởng đến kinh doanh của nhà mạng hay sự riêng tư của thuê bao. Phó thủ tướng giao Bộ Công an chủ trì, phối hợp với Bộ TT&TT cùng các doanh nghiệp viễn thông thống nhất quy trình thực hiện cấp số thuê bao mới, rà soát cơ sở pháp lý và lựa chọn các giải pháp đối soát, xác thực thông tin thuê bao, đảm bảo không ảnh hưởng đến hoạt động kinh doanh của các doanh nghiệp viễn thông và các ngành, nghề kinh doanh có liên quan sử dụng số điện thoại di động. Bộ TT&TT chỉ đạo doanh nghiệp viễn thông di động bảo đảm hạ tầng công nghệ thông tin, an toàn thông tin thực hiện kết nối cơ sở dữ liệu thông tin thuê bao tập trung của doanh nghiệp với cơ sở dữ liệu quốc gia về dân cư. Phó thủ tướng cũng đề nghị các doanh nghiệp viễn thông di động phối hợp cơ quan liên quan để kết nối thông tin thuê bao (trừ thông tin mật) với cơ sở dữ liệu quốc gia về dân cư. Đồng thời, tiến hành đối soát dữ liệu SIM đang hoạt động, đảm bảo xác thực khớp đúng giữa 3 thành phần gồm thông tin của thuê bao đăng ký tại các doanh nghiệp viễn thông; thông tin cá nhân của thuê bao trong CSDL quốc gia về dân cư và thông tin người đang sử dụng/sở hữu/nắm giữ SIM thực tế. Theo kế hoạch, trước 30/9, các doanh nghiệp viễn thông di động phải xây dựng kế hoạch, triển khai đối soát, cập nhật thông tin đối với số thuê bao đã được cơ sở dữ liệu quốc gia về dân cư xác định có thông tin chưa chính xác theo quy định.","answer":"Người dân phải nhận hơn 74 triệu cuộc gọi rác nửa đầu năm"},{"question":"Isi tempat kosong dengan jawapan yang paling sesuai. Hujan yang turun __ tidak menghalang mereka untuk terus bermain bola sepak di padang. Pilihan:  A) jarang-jarangB) putus-putusC) renyai-renyai D) halus-halus","answer":"Jawapan yang betul ialah C) renyai-renyai "},{"question":"Completa il seguente paragrafo:\\"Nel 2004-05 la Juventus si piazzò al primo posto (titolo che le verrà tuttavia revocato nel 2006) davanti al Milan, in un'annata che vide le due rivali battagliare sino alla fine per il tricolore. Le sfide si conclusero con uno 0-0 a Torino e un 1-0 a Milano per i bianconeri: proprio nello scontro diretto dell'8 maggio 2005, una Juventus corsara vinse di misura grazie a Trezeguet. Nel 2005-06 ...\\"","answer":"\\"... Juventus e Milan finirono si piazzarono nuovamente al primo e secondo posto, tuttavia entrambi subirono le decisioni della giustizia sportiva a seguito di \\"Calciopoli\\": i piemontesi vennero declassati all'ultimo posto e retrocessi in serie cadetta, mentre i lombardi furono penalizzati di 30 punti, sanzione che precluse loro la possibilità di fregiarsi di un titolo finito all'Inter terza classificata. In quella stagione i rossoneri s'imposero in casa per 3-1, mentre a Torino la gara si risolse a reti bianche. Nel 2008-09 i bianconeri si classificarono secondi, davanti al Milan terzo. Entrambe le squadre conclusero a quota 74 punti, ma la Juventus trasse vantaggio dai risultati maturati negli scontri diretti: vittoria 4-2 a Torino, e pareggio 1-1 a Milano.\\""},{"question":"నగరంలో మొక్కల పెంపకం ఆవశ్యకత గురించి పత్రికా సంపాదకునికి లేఖ.","answer":"హైదరాబాదు,X X X X X.ఈనాడు పత్రికా సంపాదకులకు,ఆర్యా,మన హైదరాబాదు నగరం వివిధ కాలుష్యాలకు లోనవుతూ ప్రజాజీవనం చాలా దుర్భరంగా తయారయింది. పట్టణాభివృద్ధి, పారిశ్రామికాభివృద్ధి, జనాభా పెరుగుదల అనేక కారణాలు ప్రకృతిని కాలుష్యానికి గురిచేస్తున్నాయి. మంచిగాలి, మంచి వాతావరణం రోజురోజుకూ కరువైపోతున్నాయి. ప్రకృతిలోని పచ్చనిచెట్లు మనిషికి స్వచ్ఛమైన గాలిని ప్రసాదించి ఆరోగ్యాన్ని కాపాడుతాయి. ఈ విషయాన్ని గ్రహించి అందరు తమ ఇండ్లలోను, పరిసర ప్రాంతాలలోను, రోడ్ల ప్రక్కన మొక్కలను పెంచి నగర కాలుష్యం నుండి బయటపడునట్లు సహకరించవలసిందిగా మీ పత్రికా ముఖమున కోరుతున్నాము.ఇట్లు,తమ విధేయుడు,పి. శ్రీనివాస్.చిరునామా:పత్రికా సంపాదకుడు,ఈనాడు దినపత్రిక,సోమాజిగూడ, హైదరాబాద్."},{"question":"වැඩ රැස්වීම් වඩාත් කාර්යක්ෂම කරන්නේ කෙසේද?","answer":"ඔබේ රැස්වීම් වර්ගය සඳහා ඔබට නිවැරදි තාක්ෂණික ක්‍රම සොයා ගැනීමට සිදු වනු ඇත, නමුත් ඔබට උත්සාහ කළ හැකි ප්‍රයෝජනවත් සාමාන්‍ය ශිල්පීය ක්‍රම කිහිපයක් තිබේ. කාලය නරඹන්න: රැස්වීම හැකි තරම් කෙටි කරන්න; එක් එක් සාකච්ඡාව කාල පෙට්ටිය; සහ එක් එක් පුද්ගලයාට කතා කිරීමට හැකි බවට වග බලා ගන්න. අරමුණු සහිත වන්න: පැහැදිලි න්‍යාය පත්‍රයක් කලින් සකසන්න; සම්බන්ධ වන ලෙස වැදගත් පාර්ශවකරුවන්ගෙන් පමණක් ඉල්ලා සිටින්න; සහ අවසානයේ දී ගැනීම් සහ ක්‍රියා අයිතම නිර්වචනය කරන්න. කලින් සූදානම් වන්න: රැස්වීමට පෙර, වැදගත් සාකච්ඡා සඳහා රැස්වීම් කාලය ඉතිරි කර ගැනීම සඳහා, මිනිසුන්ට කියවීමට හෝ අදහස් දැක්වීමට අවශ්‍ය පරිදි ද්‍රව්‍ය බෙදා ගන්න. රැස්වීම සරලව ප්රයෝජනවත් නොවේ නම්, ඔබ එය ඉවත් කළ යුතුය."},{"question":"Kíni olú ìlú Uganda?","answer":"Kampala ni."},{"question":"Trả lời câu hỏi sau bằng cách chọn câu trả lời phù hợp trong các câu dưới đây.Câu hỏi:  Sa mạc lớn nhất châu Á thuộc lãnh thổ nước nào?A. Trung Quốc và Mông CổB. Trung Quốc và NepalC. Mông Cổ và Kazakhstan","answer":"A. Trung Quốc và Mông CổSa mạc lớn nhất châu Á là Gobi. Với diện tích gần 1,3 triệu km2, đây cũng là sa mạc lớn thứ năm thế giới. Gobi bao phủ một phần khu vực phía bắc của Trung Quốc và phía nam của Mông Cổ.Trong tiếng Mông Cổ, tên gọi của sa mạc này có nghĩa là \\"nơi khô hạn\\", theo thông tin từ trang Gobi Desert. Còn AFP ví sa mạc lớn nhất châu Á này như \\"vùng đất trên sao Hoả\\"."},{"question":"Iza no nanoratra ny Lehilahy Thin in 1934 ? ","answer":"I Dashiell Hammett no nanoratra ny Lehilahy Thin in 1934. "},{"question":"Um mundo de animais antropomórficos enfrenta questões de preconceito e inclusão. Qual é o filme? Dica: É da Disney.","answer":"O filme é Zootopia. O filme é conhecido como \\"Zootrópolis\\" em Portugal e \\"Zootopia - Essa Cidade É o Bicho\\" no Brasil. É um filme de animação computadorizada, dos géneros aventura e comédia, produzido pela Walt Disney Animation Studios. O filme situa-se num mundo povoado por mamíferos antropomórficos, e conta a história de Judy Hopps, uma coelha com o sonho de se tornar policial na cidade de Zootopia, e da raposa sagaz Nick Wilde, que ganha a vida na base da trapaça. Juntos terão de superar suas diferenças para desvendar um caso relevante em Zootopia."},{"question":"නවීන ස්ටේප්ලර් නිපැයුම්කරු ලෙස සැලකෙන්නේ කවුද, සහ මෙම සොයා ගැනීම සිදු වූයේ කවදාද?","answer":"Henry R. Heyl"},{"question":"Ngày đăng tải bài Hồ Chí Minh và Tuyên ngôn Độc lập (Bùi Đình Phong)?","answer":"Ngày đăng tải bài viết: Thứ Bảy, 1-9-2018 – trước một ngày kỉ niệm 73 năm Ngày Quốc khánh nước Cộng hòa Xã hội Chủ nghĩa Việt Nam (2/9/1945 - 2/9/2018)"},{"question":"鹿児島県にある、「砂ぶろ」で有名な温泉はどこでしょう？","answer":"指宿（いぶすき）"},{"question":"Tamin’ny taona firy no nampiraisan’ny Fanjakana Merina ho fanjakana foibe tokana i Madagasikara?1) 16002) 17943) 1817","answer":"Valiny: 3) 1817 - Ny Mpanjaka Radama I ao amin’ny Fanjakana Merina dia nahomby tamin’ny fampiraisana an’i Madagasikara ho fanjakana foibe tamin’ny taona 1817."},{"question":"Hãy tiếp tục đoạn văn sau: Trên con đường thực hiện quyết tâm của mình, không ít người mắc phải một số sai lầm khiến họ bị rời xa mục tiêu giảm cân của mình. Những sai lầm này là gì? Chuyên gia dinh dưỡng nổi tiếng Rujuta Diwekar chia sẻ trên Instagram những lỗi giảm cân cần tránh, như sau: 1. Đừng chỉ nói về cân nặng của bạn Có nghĩa là một người muốn giảm cân không chỉ nên tập trung vào mỗi việc giảm cân. Thay vào đó, họ nên chọn những điều tốt cho sức khỏe, tập trung vào tỷ lệ eo và hông, và đảm bảo eo nhỏ hơn hông khoảng 25,4 cm. 2. Đừng so sánh thời gian giảm cân hiện tại với kinh nghiệm trong quá khứ Kinh nghiệm trong quá khứ và kinh nghiệm của người khác không quan trọng; tận hưởng quá trình giảm cân của bạn trong thời điểm này. Đảm bảo giảm cân toàn diện và lành mạnh. 3. Đừng đổ lỗi cho bản thân khi thiếu kết quả Không có kỷ luật bản thân nào có thể bù đắp cho một kế hoạch ăn kiêng được thiết kế kém và việc tự trách bản thân khi bạn không thấy kết quả chẳng có ích gì, chuyên gia Diwekar khẳng định. 4. Đừng vội vàng giảm cân Hãy nhớ rằng cơ thể mất khoảng 12 tuần để thích nghi với bất cứ điều gì mới, chẳng hạn như thay đổi kế hoạch ăn kiêng, tập thể dục,… Vì vậy, hãy cho phép bản thân có chừng ấy thời","answer":"gian. Hãy biết rằng số cân bạn tăng lên không phải chỉ trong một sớm một chiều, vì vậy việc giảm cân cũng sẽ mất nhiều thời gian. 5. Đừng tập thể dục quá sức hoặc sử dụng nó như một hình phạt Điều quan trọng là duy trì hoạt động nhưng không quá sức. Khoảng 20-30 phút tập thể dục chuyên dụng mỗi ngày là đủ, ngay cả khi bạn không thể đi bộ 10.000 bước. Đừng bao giờ sử dụng tập thể dục như một cách để trừng phạt bản thân, vì điều đó có thể gây hại cho sức khỏe của bạn hoặc bạn có thể bị thương. 6. Không đánh giá thấp tầm quan trọng của giấc ngủ Hầu hết mọi người không nhận ra giá trị của giấc ngủ trong hành trình giảm cân của họ. Hãy nhớ ưu tiên giấc ngủ nếu bạn đang muốn thấy cơ thể mình bị mất đi vài cm. 7. Không chạy theo xu hướng ăn kiêng/những người có ảnh hưởng trên mạng xã hội Thay vào đó, hãy làm theo các mẹo truyền thống đã được kiểm nghiệm qua thời gian, được nhiều thế hệ làm theo. 8. Không cố định kích thước khẩu phần ăn Cảm giác thèm ăn là một thực thể chuyển động, hãy tôn trọng điều đó. Điều này có nghĩa là sự thèm ăn phụ thuộc vào cảm giác của bạn hàng ngày. Không cần thiết phải hạn chế khẩu phần mỗi ngày, vì điều đó có thể gây hại nhiều hơn lợi và khiến bạn thèm ăn những món không lành mạnh. Hãy tuân thủ nguyên tắc: 'ngồi và ăn', 'ăn từ từ', theo 'giác quan' của bạn và lưu tâm trong khi ăn. 9. Đừng trông đợi sự nhận ra của người khác về tiến bộ giảm cân của bạn Những thay đổi bạn nhận thấy ở bản thân, chẳng hạn như kinh nguyệt đều đặn, da sáng, tóc khỏe, giảm số cm cơ thể, vẫn tiến triển ngay cả khi không ai để ý đến chúng. "},{"question":"(Uyagquma, uyahlina, ubambe isandla usezinhlungwini)(Ngomoya ophansi) Ungethuki mfowethu ukuvakashelwa yilomuntu oyimina ongasondelene neze naye futhi ongamejwayele.NginguMbhebhezeli Mdluli mina nginomuzi elokishini lase Dark CityeMandeni.(Usesimweni esidabukisayo) Yebo-ke ngiyathokoza ukwazananawe Mdluli.Ngithi angizozwa ngesimo sempilo ndoda yamadoda kwazise phelabese ngiwutholile umbiko ngawe komunye woSomatekisiwaseMandeni onetekisi elithuthela eThekwini.(Uyahlina, usezinhlungwini, usikhuluma ubukwerekwere isiZulu)Eish! Kunjengoba ubona nje ntanga yamashinga, akukabi bikhobungcono. Khona ngike ngawuthola umjovo wokudambisaiminjunju kanye namaphilisi okuthoba izinhlungu kodwa umehlukokube ngokwesikhashana nje. Eqinisweni lilonke ekwemukelwenikwami lapha esibhedlela bekungathi isitapamunwana esingiphethengaze ngazinika ithemba lokuthi kuzosheshe kushabalale. Okubikakhulu manje ukuthi isandla siya ngokudlebeleka nokubolaesikhundleni sokukhombisa ubungcono.(Udangele) Wewu! Ngikhalisana kanye nawe mfanakithi kulobubuhlungu okubo1. Beka ngokufingqiwe izenzo zikaMbhebhezeli ezibonisa ukuthi ungumlingiswaongathembekile. Bhekisa impendulo yakho kulo mdlalo.","answer":"UMbhebhezeli uthi engumngani kaMdaluli avakashele uChivenga esibhedlelaamtshele ukuthi bewumphakathi bazowa bevuka naye nakuba bekunguyeuMbhebhezeli obegqugquzela uMdaluli ukuthi athakathe uChivenga.Uphinde atshele uChivenga nokuthi lesisi sifo esimphethe senziwe ngabantufuthi uyamazi umuntu omthakathile"},{"question":"Зээригүү деген сөздү кандай түшүнөсүз?","answer":"-  Зээригип жатам.- Зээригүү – аңкоонун, жалкоонун иши. Бир аз башың иштегенде зээрикмек эмессиң."},{"question":"أي من التالي يعد مخلوق حي وليس له خصائص المخلوقات الحية؟(أ) الفيروس(ب) البكتيريا(ج) الفطريات (د) الطلائعيات","answer":"الإجابة الصحيحة هي: (أ) الفيروس "},{"question":"TAMBAYA: Shin yaya za a rubuta goma sha-biyar a matsayin lamba?","answer":"Amsa: 15"},{"question":"Responde la siguiente pregunta : ¿Qué película fue dirigida por Quentin Tarantino y protagonizada por Michael Fassbender?","answer":"La película se llama Bastardos sin gloria, es una película de guerra y acción qué se dasarrolla durante la Segunda Guerra Mundial, recibió aclamación de la crítica y fue un éxito en taquilla. "},{"question":"Euskal herri musikak hainbat sormen eta estilo musikal ditu. Zer inportantzia duen euskal herri musikak euskal gizartearen eta bere historia sinesgaitzaren barnean, eta nola erabil daitezke musikaren garapenak gizartearen aldaketak ulertzeko?","answer":"Euskal herri musika euskal kulturaren erakusle nagusietariko bat da. Historian zehar, euskal herri musikak gizartearen gora-beherak, festak, eta konfliktoak islatzen ditu. Musikaren bidez, euskal gizartea bere sentimenduak, aspirazioak, eta kezkak adierazi ditu. Hainbat musikari eta taldek, hala nola, Mikel Laboa edo Oskorri, euskal gizartearen aldaketa eta borrokak islatu dituzte euren abestietan. Hori dela eta, euskal herri musikaren garapenak gizartearen aldaketak ulertzeko giltzarri gisa erabil daitezke."},{"question":"प्रश्न का उत्तर दें:प्रश्न: सचिन तेंदुलकर भारतीय क्रिकेट की किस टूर्नामेंट में अपना पहला शतक बनाया था?","answer":"उत्तर: सचिन तेंदुलकर ने एकदिवसीय इंटरनेशनल क्रिकेट में अपना पहला शतक पाकिस्तान के खिलाफ 1990 में बनाया था।"},{"question":"Кибербуллинг деген сөздү кандай түшүнөсүз?","answer":"Интернет аркылуу чабуул жасаган инсандар!!!📌Шылдыңдоо — көп учурда социалдык тармактардагы шылдыңдаган\\rкомментарийлер түрүндө кездешет.\\r📌 Асылуу — социалдык тармактардагы түздөн-түз максаттуу чабуул.\\r📌Ушак-айың таркатуу — жабырлануучунун репутациясын атайлап \\rбулгоо.\\r📌Жалган ысым пайдалануу — өзүн башка адам катары көрсөтүү же \\rбашкаларды манипуляция кылуу үчүн жабырлануучунун аккаунтун \\rпайдалануу.\\r📌Жеке маалыматтарды ачыкка чыгаруу — интимге байланыштуу \\rсүрөттөрдү, кат жазышууларды, жеке маалыматтарды жабырлануучуну \\rбасынтуу үчүн жарыялап жиберүү.\\r📌 Социалык изоляция — жабырлануучу менен суйлөшүүдөн баш \\rтартуу, таптакыр көңүл бурбоо.\\r📌Ачык коркутуулар же асылуу.Башка бирөөнүн кызыкчылыгы үчүн жабырлануучу болуп калууга жол бербеңиз.\\r"},{"question":"ما هي السورة الملقبة بقلب القرآن؟\\t","answer":"\\tيس"},{"question":"క్రింద ఇచ్చిన అంశం మీద శీర్షిక రాయండి: కనీసం ఐదు పేరాలు వచ్చేలాగా రాయండి ఇదెక్కడి చోద్యం?","answer":"మధ్యాహ్నం మృష్టాన్న భోజనం చేసి బ్రేవ్ మని త్రేన్చుతూ కూర్చున్నారు జంఘాల శాస్త్రి గారు. భార్య గేనపెసూనాంబగారు ఇంకా వంటిట్లో పని చేస్తున్నారు.  జంఘాల శాస్త్రి గారు ఆలస్యం తట్టుకోలేక ఒసేయ్ ‘భోజనానంతరం తాంబూల చర్వణం అన్నారు’ విపిస్తున్నాదా కాలభైరవ పట్టి అని అరిచేడు.  ఆవిడ లోపలినుంచి వస్తున్నానండి అని తాంబూలానికి తమలపాకులు, సున్నం, వక్కలు  వగైరా పట్టుకుని వచ్చి ఇంకా మెయ్యండి  వానర పుత్ర అని అందించింది. నెమ్మదిగా   వాళ్ళు మాటల్లో పడ్డారు.  ఏమాటకామాటే చెప్పుకోవాలి కానీ గేనపెసూన ఒకరి మొహం చూస్తే పెట్ట బుద్ధవుతుంది. ఒకరి మొహం చూస్తే కొట్టబుద్ధవుతుంది అంటారు. ఎదో తండ్రిచాటు బిడ్డని, భర్తచాటు భార్యని, లోకజ్ఞానం తెలీనిదాన్నిఅదేంటో గానీ ఎన్నితప్పులు చేసినా దేవతలను పొగుడుతాం ఎన్ని ఒప్పులు చేసినా రాక్షసుల్ని తిడతాం.  దేవుళ్లకో రూలు. రాక్షసులకోరూలు.  అన్న శ్రీరాముణ్ని గుడ్డిగా అనుసరించిన లక్ష్మణుణ్ని ఆదర్శప్రాయుడైన తమ్ముడని చెప్పుకుంటాం! రాక్షసుడు కాకపోతేనేం, పాపం దుశ్శాసనుడు చేసింది కూడా తన అన్న చెప్పిన పనేగా. కానీ ద్రౌపది వస్త్రాపహరణం చేశాడని వాణ్ని నోటికొచ్చినట్లు తిడుతున్నాము.  రాక్షసుడు అంటే అసలు అర్థం దేవతలు చేసే యజ్ఞాల బారి నుంచి జంతువులను రక్షించేవాడు అని   కదండీ  అలాంటి రక్షకులను తక్షకుల్లాగా చూస్తే ఎలా? త్రేతాయుగంలోనూ ఇదే పరిస్థితి కదా! విభీషణుడు స్వధర్మాన్ని పాటించకుండా అన్న రావణాసురుడికి ఎదురు తిరిగి, రాముడి పంచన చేరి, ఆయనకు బేషరతు మద్దతునివ్వడం ఏం న్యాయం? ఇది వెన్నుపోటు రాజకీయం కాదంటారా ఎదో లోకజ్ఞానం తెలీని దాన్ని.అంతేకాదండి ఈ దేవతల రాజకీయాలకి అంతు… పొంతూ   లేదండి. రాక్షసులకు వరాలు ఇచ్చినట్టే ఇచ్చి వారిని నిలువునా ముంచేశారు. పిచ్చమొహాలైన రాక్షసులు దేవతలను  నమ్మి నష్టపోయారు. రాక్షసులు నానా కష్టాలు పడి తపసు చేయడం, దేవతలు వాళ్లకు ప్రత్యక్షం కావడం, తమకు చావు రాకూడదంటూ వాళ్లు కోరడం, దేవుళ్లూ ఒప్పుకుని వరాలు ఇవ్వడం.. అంతా బాగుంటుంది కానీ, చివరకు ‘సాంకేతిక కారణాలతో’ ఆ వరాలు ఉపయోగంలోకి రాకుండా చేశారు దేవతలు దేవతలు రాక్షసులు అక్కచెల్లెళ్ల పిల్లలే కదా కొంచెం కూడా బంధుప్రీతి లేకుండా, జాలీ దయా కరుణా అనేవే లేకుండా రాక్షసుల్ని సంహరించారు దేవతలు. రాక్షసులకు శివుడు వరాలు ఇవ్వడం ఎందుకు? ఆ వరాల్ని ఉపయోగించుకున్న పాపానికే రాక్షసుల్ని విష్ణుమూర్తి వచ్చి మట్టుపెట్టడం ఎందుకు? భస్మాసురుడులాంటి వాళ్లు బలిపశువులు అయిపోలేదా? దేవతలది దొంగభక్తి అయితే రాక్షసులదే అసలు సిసలు భక్తి. ఏం చేసినా వాళ్లు త్రికరణ శుద్ధిగా చేస్తారు. మాటలకు చేతలకు తేడా ఉండదు. కానీ దేవతలకు అలా కాదు. ‘మూతిదారి మూతిదే. చేతిదారి చేతిదే’. దేవతల మాటలకు, చేతలకు పొంతన ఉండదు. రాక్షసులకు ఉన్న సద్గుణాలు దేవతలకు ఎక్కడ ఏడ్చాయి? ఏ తప్పూ చేయనివాళ్లని ‘నిప్పు’తో పోల్చుతారు కానీ, రుషిపత్నులతో అగ్నిదేవుడు ఎలా ప్రవర్తించాడసలు? ఈయన నిర్వాకంతో పోల్చితే ‘మనసు పడ్డాను మహాప్రభో’ అన్న పాపానికే ముక్కూచెవులూ పోగొట్టుకున్న శూర్పణఖ మంచితనం ఎవరికీ తెలీదు లోక జ్ఞానంతెలీని దాన్ని నేను చెప్పింది కరెక్ట్ కదా!            ఎక్కువ మంది భార్యలు ఉండడం తప్పు అనీ, పరస్త్రీ వ్యామోహం తప్పు అనీ శాస్త్రాలన్నీ ఘోషిస్తున్నాయి. ఇదే నిజమైతే ఒక్క  శ్రీరామచంద్రుడు తప్ప ఆయన పేరులో చంద్రుడితో సహా దేవతలు ఈ ఆరోపణల నుంచి తప్పించుకోలేరు! ఫలానా దేవుడి రెండో భార్య ఎవరు అంటే ఎవరైనా చెబుతారు. కానీ రాక్షసులకు ఆ అపప్రథ లేదు. హిరణ్యకశిపుడి రెండో భార్య ఎవరు? రావణాసురుడి ద్వితీయ కళత్రం ఎవరు? అంటే ఎవరూ చెప్పలేరు. వారికి లేరు కాబట్టి. ఇలాంటి విషయాలు ఎన్నింటినో తులనాత్మక పరిశీలన చేస్తే, చంద్రుడికైనా మచ్చ ఉంది గానీ రాక్షసులకు అలాంటిది కనిపించదు గాక కనిపించదు. ఇక దేవతలకు ఉన్న వివాహేతర సంబంధాలు కోకొల్లలు. ఎందెందు వెదకి చూసిన అందందే కనబడతాయి. దేవతలకు రాజు, స్వర్గాధిపతి ఇంద్రుడికి వెయ్యి కళ్ల సంగతేమిటి? తెలుసుకుంటే చాలు విషయం ‘కళ్లకు’ కట్టినట్టు అర్థమైపోతుంది.  రాక్షసులకు అన్నింటిలోనూ అన్యాయమే జరిగింది. దేవతలతో సమానంగా కష్టపడ్డా ప్రయోజనం లేకుండా పోయింది. క్షీరసాగర మథనంలో పుట్టినవన్నీ దేవతలే కొట్టేశారు. చివరకు విషాన్ని కూడా ఆ శివుడే తీసుకున్నాడు. రాక్షసులకు శ్రమదోపిడీ మాత్రమే మిగిలింది. దీనికి ఏ లేబరు కోర్టులోనూ న్యాయం జరగలేదు.            గొప్పవాళ్లను ఇంద్రుడు చంద్రుడు అంటారే! అదే నిజమైతే తారాశశాంకం ఏం చెబుతోంది? దాన్ని ‘సీరియస్‌’గా తీసుకుంటే బృహస్పతి తాతల్లాంటి గురువైనా ఏ ‘శిష్యచంద్రుణ్నయినా’ చేరదీస్తాడా? ఇక సూర్యుడు, కుంతి సంగతేమిటి? అన్నింటికీ మించి రాక్షసులకున్న దానగుణం దేవతలకు ఎక్కడుంది? ఉదాహరణకు బలిచక్రవర్తికి ఉన్న దానగుణంలో సహస్రాంశం అయినా దేవతలకు ఉందా? లేనేలేదు. ‘వచ్చినవాడు విష్ణువు… తనను చంపడానికే వచ్చాడు’ అని బలిచక్రవర్తికి తెలిసినా భయపడలేదు వెనక్కుతగ్గలేదు. ప్రాణత్యాగానికైనా సిద్ధపడ్డాడు.ఆదిన్‌ శ్రీసతి కొప్పుపై తనువుపై అంసోత్తరీయంబుపైపాదాబ్జమ్ములపై గపోలతటిపై బాలిండ్లపై నూత్న మర్యాదం జెందు కరంబు క్రిందగుట మీదై నా కరంబుంట మేల్గాదె రాజ్యము గీజ్యమున్‌ సతతమున్‌ కాయంబు నాపాయమే      అని బలిచక్రవర్తిని కళ్లారా చూసినట్టు, చెవులారా విన్నట్టు బమ్మెర పోతన భాగవతంలో చెప్పేశాడు. దీనికి అప్పీలు లేదు. ఇలాంటి వాడు దేవతల్లో ఒక్కరైనా దొరుకుతారా?      దేవతలను సురులు అంటారు. అంటే సురను తాగేవాళ్లు అని అర్థం. రాక్షసులను అసురులు అంటారు. అంటే సురాపానం చేయని వాళ్లు. దేవతలు మంచివాళ్లని, రాక్షసులు చెడ్డవాళ్లని భూనభోంతరాలు దద్దరిల్లేట్టు ప్రచారం చేశారు. ఇంతకీ తాగని వాళ్లు మంచివాళ్లా? తాగేవాళ్లు మంచివాళ్లా? తాగేవాళ్లే మంచివాళ్లయితే మందుబాబులను ఎందుకు చిన్నచూపు చూస్తారు? చెడ్డవాళ్లుగా ఎందుకు చిత్రిస్తారు?  ఇదేమి చోద్యమండి?  గేనపెసూనాంబ  గుక్కతిప్పుకోకుండా మాట్లాడిన తీరుకి జంఘాల శాస్త్రికి నోటిమాట….కంటిచూపు పోయి నిశ్చేష్టుడై    కూలపడ్డాడు"},{"question":"Inona ny afolava?","answer":"Ny afolava dia zavamaniry kely mamoa menamena fanao tambavy fa sady mampavitribitrika no ody malemy valahana ary manala ny aretin-kihy; ny ranony mahafaka ny hao raha anasan-doha; mbola azo ampiasaina ho fandiovana ny fivalanandrano sy fampitomboana ny hatsembohana koa ny laingon' ny afolava madinika."},{"question":"Descreva a bandeira de Micronésia.","answer":"A bandeira de Micronésia possui uma faixa azul no canto superior esquerdo e, no restante da bandeira, há quatro estrelas brancas dispostas em um círculo em um campo azul."},{"question":"আকাশের রং নীল দেখায় কেন?","answer":"ধূলিকণা দ্বারা আলো বিচ্ছুরিত হলে বিচ্ছুরণের কারণে আকাশের রঙ নীল দেখায়"},{"question":"إعطني مثالاُ عن سؤال وجواب في مجال الإدارة:","answer":"ما عدد الأقسام الإدارية التي تتشكل منها مدينة نيويورك؟ 5."},{"question":"ప్రశ్న : పశ్చిమ కనుమలలో పుట్టిన నదులు తూర్పుగా ప్రవహిస్తూ బంగాళాఖాతంలో కలుస్తున్నాయి. మీ ఉపాధ్యాయునితో చర్చించండి.","answer":"పశ్చిమ కనుమలలో పుట్టి తూర్పుగా ప్రవహిస్తూ బంగాళాఖాతంలో కలుస్తున్న నదులు :గోదావరి, కృష్ణా, కావేరి, తుంగభద్ర, పెన్నా, ఘటప్రభ, మాలప్రభ, భీమ, వైగై, తాంబ్రపరిణి, పెరియార్ మొదలైనవి."},{"question":"Ndi mafuko ati ku Tete Mozambique?","answer":"Mafuko a m'derali a Sena, Nyanja ndi Nyungue amadziwika kwambiri chifukwa cha magule achikhalidwe omwe amakhala osangalatsa."},{"question":"Sheeg Magacyada Afar Wadan Ee Uu Maro Wabiga Niil","answer":" Waxay Kala Yihiin1- Masar,2- Uganda,3- Sudan,4- Ethiopia."},{"question":"Odpowiedz na pytanie. Jakie są polskie tradycje bożonarodzeniowe?","answer":"Oto wybrane tradycje, które towarzyszą polakom co roku podczas Świąt Bożego Narodzenia: ubieranie choinki, oczekiwanie na pierwszą gwiazdkę, wzajemne przebaczenie win podczas łamania się opłatkiem, przygotowanie 12 potraw wigilijnych czy pozostawienie wolnego miejsca przy stole. Tradycje te, choć związane z jednym z najważniejszych dla chrześcijan wydarzeń, splotły się z prastarymi obrzędami słowiańskimi, a nawet rzymskimi."},{"question":"Năm nay con tôi 12 tuổi cận độ 3, tôi muốn hỏi năm 18 tuổi con tôi có thể mổ mắt được không? Phương pháp này có ưu và khuyết điểm gì? Tôi có nghe một số bác sĩ nói phương pháp mổ mắt không tốt, có đúng không?","answer":"Cháu đang còn nhỏ, việc cần thiết nhất là phải đeo đúng số kính, sử dụng mắt hợp lý thì mới đảm bảo ở tuổi 18 số kính ổn định. Khi số kính ổn định mới nghĩ đến chuyện phẫu thuật. Bất kỳ một biện pháp nào cũng có ưu, nhược điểm. Ví dụ, đeo kính thì đơn giản, rẻ tiền nhưng hạn chế trong vận động, sinh hoạt, đi trời mưa, ảnh hưởng thẩm mỹ…. Kính áp tròng thì giải quyết được nhược điểm của đeo kính nhưng đeo lâu lại dễ bị viêm kết mạc, giác mạc, hoặc làm thiếu oxy trên giác mạc…. Kính áp tròng cứng dùng ban đêm thì hàng ngày phải đặt kính và cũng rất dễ bị viêm nhiễm và làm yếu cấu trúc mắt. Với phẫu thuật, từ phẫu thuật Lasik, Femto – Lasik, Smile thì giải quyết được những khó khăn của đeo kính, nhưng cũng có những tỉ lệ biến chứng nhất định, phụ thuộc vào từng phương pháp. Với phương pháp Smile có thể nói, đây là một phuơng pháp cải biên, giúp tỷ lệ biến chứng gần như giảm tuyệt đối."},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਅਸੰਖ ਗਰੰਥ ਮੁਖਿ ਵੇਦ ਪਾਠ ॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 3 ਤੋਂ ਲਈ ਗਈ ਇੱਕ ਤੁਕ ਦਾ ਵਾਕ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਨਾਨਕ ਦੇਵ ਜੀ ਇਸ ਬਾਣੀ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਹਨ।ਇਸਦਾ ਮਤਲਬ ਇਹ ਹੈ,\\"ਬੇਅੰਤ ਜੀਵ ਵੇਦਾਂ ਅਤੇ ਹੋਰ ਧਾਰਮਿਕ ਪੁਸਤਕਾਂ ਦੇ ਪਾਠ ਮੂੰਹ ਨਾਲ ਕਰ ਰਹੇ ਹਨ। \\""},{"question":"ඔන්චිල්ලා වාරම් කවියක් කියන්න ","answer":"ව ට් ටු සතර හා ලී දඬු වැල් ගෙ නකි ට් ටු නොකර එහි බඳිමින් තැන තැ නඔ ට් ටු කරති සැම දෙන මග යන එ නගැ ට් ටු නැතුව අපි පදිමුව අට දෙ න"},{"question":"Hãy chỉ ra các chi tiết hoang đường, kì ảo trong truyện Thạch Sanh. Những chi tiết này có tác dụng gì trong việc khắc họa nhân vật Thạch Sanh?","answer":"- Các chi tiết hoang đường, kì ảo trong truyện:+ Ngọc Hoàng sai thái tử xuống đầu thai làm con của hai vợ chồng già tốt bụng.+ Người vợ mang thai mấy năm mãi mới sinh được một cậu con trai.+ Ngọc Hoàng sai thiên thần xuống dạy đủ các môn võ nghệ và mọi phép thần thông cho Thạch Sanh.+ Chằn tinh có nhiều phép lạ, thường ăn thịt người.+ Chằn tinh hiện nguyên hình là con trăn khổng lồ, khi chết đi để lại bộ cung tên bằng vàng bên mình.+ Đại bàng là con yêu tinh trên núi, có nhiều phép lạ.+ Thái tử con vua Thủy Tề mời chàng xuống chơi thủy cung.+ Tiếng đàn của Thạch Sanh vang lên trong ngục khiến công chúa cười nói vui vẻ trở lại; khiến quân giặc bủn rủn tay chân, không còn nghĩ gì đến chuyện đánh nhau nữa.+ Niêu cơm của Thạch Sanh bé xíu cứ ăn hết lại đầy.- Những chi tiết này có tác dụng trong việc khắc họa nhân vật Thạch Sanh:+ Khẳng định nguồn gốc cao quý, tài năng phi thường của Thạch Sanh+ Khẳng định sức mạnh chính nghĩa, trừ hại cho dân của Thạch Sanh.+ Tượng trưng cho công lí, cho sức mạnh của chính nghĩa – ước mơ, khát vọng công bằng, sự chiến thắng của cái thiện đối với cái ác."},{"question":"ਸਾਈਮਨ ਕਮਿਸ਼ਨ ਉੱਤੇ ਨੋਟ ਲਿਖੋ ।","answer":"1928 ਈ: ਵਿੱਚ ਸੱਤ ਮੈਂਬਰਾਂ ਦਾ ਇੱਕ ਕਮਿਸ਼ਨ ਭਾਰਤ ਵਿਚ ਆਇਆ । ਇਸ ਦਾ ਪ੍ਰਧਾਨ ਸਰ ਜਾਨ ਸਾਈਮਨ ਸੀ । ਇਸ ਕਮਿਸ਼ਨ ਵਿੱਚ ਇੱਕ ਵੀ ਭਾਰਤੀ ਸ਼ਾਮਲ ਨਹੀਂ ਸੀ । ਇਸ ਲਈ ਭਾਰਤ ਵਿਚ ਇਸ ਕਮਿਸ਼ਨ ਦਾ ਥਾਂ-ਥਾਂ ਵਿਰੋਧ ਕੀਤਾ ਗਿਆ । ਇਹ ਕਮਿਸ਼ਨ ਜਿੱਥੇ ਵੀ ਗਿਆ ਇਸ ਦਾ ਸਵਾਗਤ ਕਾਲੀਆਂ ਝੰਡੀਆਂ ਨਾਲ ਕੀਤਾ ਗਿਆ । ਥਾਂ-ਥਾਂ ਸਾਈਮਨ ਕਮਿਸ਼ਨ ‘ਵਾਪਸ ਜਾਓ’ ਦੇ ਨਾਅਰੇ ਲਗਾਏ ਗਏ ! ਜਨਤਾ ਦੇ ਇਸ ਸ਼ਾਂਤ ਦਿਖਾਵੇ ਨੂੰ ਸਰਕਾਰ ਨੇ ਬੜੀ ਸਖ਼ਤੀ ਨਾਲ ਦਬਾਇਆ ਨੇ ਲਾਹੌਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਇਸ ਕਮਿਸ਼ਨ ਦਾ ਵਿਰੋਧ ਕਰਨ ਦੇ ਕਾਰਨ ਲਾਲਾ ਲਾਜਪਤ ਰਾਏ ਉੱਤੇ ਲਾਠੀਆਂ ਵਰਾਈਆਂ ਗਈਆਂ ਜਿਸ ਨਾਲ ਉਹ ਸ਼ਹੀਦ ਹੋ ਗਏ ।"},{"question":"Rehema Nanfuka","answer":"Rehema Nanfuka (bíi ni ọjọ́ kẹẹ̀dọ́gbọ̀n oṣù karùn-ún ọdún 1986) jẹ́ òṣèré àti adarí lórílẹ̀-èdè Uganda tí ó gbajúmọ̀ fún ipa tí ó kó nínú eré Imani, Veronica's Wish, Imbabazi, Haunted Souls, The Road We Travel, Papi, Tropical Fish, Slay Queen of Africa Queen of Katwe, àti Imperial Blue.Ipa tí ó kó nínú eré Mary nínú eré Imani ni ó jẹ́ kí ó gbajúmọ̀, èyí sì ló jẹ́ kí ó gbà àmì ẹ̀yẹ méjì : Africa Movie Academy Awards for Most Promising Actress ní ọdún 2010 àti òṣèré bìnrin to dára jù lọ láti ọ̀dọ̀ African Film Festival of Cordoba ní ọdún 2010. Rehema kó ipa Suzanna nínú eré Yat Madit ní ọdún 2016, ìyẹn sì ló jẹ́ kí ó gbà àmì ẹ̀yẹ òṣèré bìnrin to dára jù lọ ní Uganda Film Festival ní ọdún 2017. Nanfuka ṣe adarí fún eré Veronica Wish, ó si gba àmì ẹ̀yẹ adarí eré tó dára jù lọ láti ọ̀dọ̀ Uganda Film Festival ní ọdún 2018, òun sì ni obìnrin àkọ́kọ́ tí ó má gba àmì ẹ̀yẹ náà. Ó kó ipa Lady Macbeth nínú eré orí ìtàgé ti Macbeth. Ní ọdún 2010, ó wá lára àwọn tí ó fi ohun ṣe eré fún The Cow Needs a Wife. Ilé iṣẹ́ The Moth ti kọ nípa Ìtàn ayé Rehema. Ó gbé igbá orókè níbi ìdíje Kampala Slam ní ọdún 2013. Ó jẹ́ àmbásẹ́dọ̀ fún ilé iṣẹ́ Airtel Uganda, Airtel Malawi, Milkman Uganda àti Eco Bank Uganda."},{"question":"మీరు ఆడుకొనే ఆటల జాబితా తయారుచేసి, వాటిని ఉపయోగించి ఒక గేయం రాయండి.","answer":"రండి రండి పిల్లలూ – ఆటలాడుదాం, ఆటలాడుదాం ||దాగుడు మూతలూ – కోతి కొమ్మచ్చులూకిరికీ ఆటలూ – కుందెన గుడులూదూదుంపుల్లలూ – కుప్పాతన్నులూవెన్నెల పాటలూ – బిళ్ళా బాధుడూ || రండి రండి పిల్లలూ || ఆటలాడుదాం ||చెడుగుడు ఆటలూ – ఉప్పట్టి కూతలూకొక్కో ఆటలూ – కబడ్డీ ఆటలూబ్యాడ్మింటన్, ఫుట్ బాలూ – వాలీబాలు, క్రికెట్టూలాంగు జంపు, హై జంపు – పోలు జంపు, రన్నింగులునడక పరుగు పోటీలు – రకరకాల ఆటలు || రండి రండి పిల్లలూ || ఆటలాడుదాం ||"},{"question":"තනි පද යනු මොනවාද?","answer":"සිංහල භාෂාවේ භාවිතා කරන දිගු වැකියක් සදහා යොදන කෙටි පදය තනි පද නම් වේ"},{"question":"வினா:குடும்ப விளக்கு நூலில் தலைவி பேச்சில் வெளிப்படும் பெண்கல்விக்கான கருத்துகளை இன்றைய சூழலுடன் ஒப்பிட்டு எழுதுக.","answer":"விடை:முன்னுரை:பாரதிதாசன் இயற்றிய குடும்ப விளக்கு என்னும் நூலில், குடும்பத்தலைவி தன் உள்ளக்கருத்துகளை வெளிப்படுத்தும் போது, பெண்கல்வி குறித்த கருத்துகளையும் வெளிப்படுத்துகிறார். அவ்வாறு தலைவி கூறும், கருத்துகளும், இன்றைய சூழலையும் பார்ப்போம்.தலைவியின் பேச்சு:கல்வி இல்லாத பெண்கள் பண்படாத உவர்நிலம் போன்றவர்கள்; அங்கு பயனற்ற புல் விளைந்திடலாம். அறிவார்ந்த புதல்வர்கள் உருவாவதில்லை. கல்வியறிவு பெற்ற பெண்கள், பண்பட்ட நன்செய் நிலம் போன்றவர்கள். அவர்கள் மூலமே சிறந்த அறிவார்ந்த மக்கள் உருவாகின்றனர்.பெண்கல்வி இல்லாததினால், இன்று உலகம் ஆண்களின் கட்டுப்பாட்டில் நலிந்து போனதால், பெண்களுக்கு விடுதலை பறிபோனது.கல்வியறிவு இல்லாத பெண், மின்னல் போல் ஒளிரும் அழகு பெற்றவளாயினும், அவள் வாழ்வு ஒளிர்வதில்லை .“கல்வி இல்லா மின்னாள்வாழ்வில் என்றும் மின்னாள்”சமைக்கும் பணி, தாய்மார்களுக்கே உரியது எனும் வழக்கத்தினைக் கண் இமைக்கும் நேரத்தில் நீக்க வேண்டுமாயின் பெண்களுக்கு எப்போதும் கல்வி வேண்டும்.இன்றைய சூழல் :கல்வி கற்ற பெண் குடும்பத்தலைவியாய் இருப்பதால், பட்டங்களும், பதவிகளும் பெறும் மக்கட்பேறு இல்லந்தோறும் காணப்படுகிறது.துறைதோறும்:வானூர்தியைச் செலுத்துதல் விண்கலத்தில் செல்லுதல், மருத்துவர், எனப் பல்வேறு துறைகளிலும், உலகை அளத்தல், மாக்கடலை அளத்தல் என அனைத்துத் துறைகளிலும் ஆணுக்கு நிகராக பெண்ணும் இடம்பெறுகிறாள், செயலாற்றும் திறன் உடையவளாய் இருக்கிறாள் என்பதை மறுக்க இயலாது.“வானூர்தி செலுத்தல் வையமாக்கடல் முழுது மளத்தல்ஆனஎச் செயலும் ஆண்பெண்அனைவர்க்கும் பொதுவே” ஆகிவிட்டது.சமையல்பணி :சமைப்பதும், வீட்டு வேலைகளைச் சலிப்பில்லாமல் செய்வதும் பெண்களுக்கு உரியது என்ற நிலை மாறிவருகிறது. ஆண்களும் அதனைத் தாழ்வாக எண்ணாது ஏற்று நடத்தும் காலம் வந்து கொண்டிருக்கிறது எனில் மிகையாகாது.குடும்ப விளக்கு தலைவிபேசும், கால கட்டத்தை விட ‘பெண்கல்வி’ இன்று பல மடங்கு வளர்ந்திருக்கிறது.முடிவுரை:“பட்டங்கள் ஆள்வதும் சட்டங்கள் செய்வதும்பாரினில் பெண்கள் நடத்த வந்தோம்”என்ற பாரதியின் கனவு வரிகள் நனவாகிக் கொண்டு தான் இருக்கின்றது."},{"question":"Toplumsal uyumluluk nedir?","answer":"Sosyal uyum, bireylerin toplum içindeki diğer insanlarla başarılı bir şekilde iletişim kurabilme, ortak değer ve normlara uyabilme ve sosyal becerilerini kullanarak sağlıklı ilişkiler kurabilme yeteneğidir. İnsanların birbirleriyle anlaşarak, saygı göstererek ve iş birliği yaparak ortak hedeflere ulaşmalarını sağlar."},{"question":"Qu'est-ce que la psychologie comportementale et quelles sont ses principales théories ? ","answer":"La psychologie comportementale est une thérapie dite brève. Elle suggère que tout symptôme d'anxiété ou de phobie est la marque d'un comportement inadapté acquis par l'individu au cours de son enfance.  Branche de la psychologie clinique, elle est apparue en parallèle de la psychologie cognitive au milieu du XXème siècle. Si un clivage a longtemps existé entre ces deux branches, il tend aujourd'hui à disparaître, à tel point qu'on les regroupe sous l'appellation TCC (thérapies cognitivo-comportementales)."},{"question":"બીએમડબ્લ્યુ માટે પૂર્ણફોર્મ શું છે?","answer":"બાયરીશે મોટરન વર્ક એજી, બીએમડબ્લ્યુ તરીકે સંક્ષિપ્તમાં, જર્મનીના બાવેરિયાના મ્યુનિકમાં મુખ્ય મથક લક્ઝરી વાહનો અને મોટરસાયકલોના જર્મન મલ્ટિનેશનલ ઉત્પાદક.આ કંપનીની સ્થાપના 1916 માં એરક્રાફ્ટ એન્જિનના ઉત્પાદક તરીકે કરવામાં આવી હતી, જે તે 1917 થી 1918 દરમિયાન અને ફરીથી 1933 થી 1945 સુધી ઉત્પન્ન થયું હતું."},{"question":"Шта означава вештачка интелигенција као појам у ширем смислу?","answer":"Вештачка интелигенција као појам у ширем смислу, означава капацитет једне вјештачке творевине за реализовање функција које су карактеристика људског размишљања. Могућност развоја сличне творевине је будила интересовање људи још од античког доба ; ипак, тек у другој половини XX вијека таква могућност је добила прва оруђа (рачунаре), чиме се отворио пут за тај подухват.Потпомогнута напретком модерне науке, истраживања на пољу вештачке интелигенције се развијају у два основна смера: психолошка и физиолошка истраживања природе људског ума, и технолошки развој све сложенијих рачунарских система."},{"question":"Phù Tang là tên gọi của đất nước nào?","answer":"Phù Tang hay Khổng Tang là tên một loài cây dâu rỗng lòng. Theo một số truyền thuyết cổ phương Đông, khi thần Mặt Trời du hành ngang qua bầu trời từ Đông sang Tây, ngài đã dừng lại dưới gốc cây Phù Tang.Tên gọi Phù Tang cũng được dùng chỉ nơi mặt trời mọc. Nhật Bản nằm ở cực đông châu Á nên sẽ là nơi đón bình minh đầu tiên của châu lục. Thực tế, chữ kanji trong quốc hiệu Nhật Bản nghĩa là \\"gốc của Mặt Trời\\", và người dân quốc gia này từ lâu coi trọng hình tượng mặt trời. Theo tài liệu cổ Nihon Shoki, các Thiên hoàng Nhật Bản còn được coi là hậu duệ của nữ thần Mặt trời Amaterasu.Vì thế, từ lâu Phù Tang được dùng để chỉ xứ sở mặt trời mọc - Nhật Bản."},{"question":"ನಾನು ಸಾಕಷ್ಟು ನೀರು ಕುಡಿಯದಿದ್ದರೆ ಏನಾಗುತ್ತದೆ? ","answer":"ನೀವು ಸಾಕಷ್ಟು ನೀರು ಕುಡಿಯದಿದ್ದರೆ, ನೀವು ನಿರ್ಜಲೀಕರಣವನ್ನು ಅನುಭವಿಸಬಹುದು, ಇದು ವಿವಿಧ ಆರೋಗ್ಯ ಸಮಸ್ಯೆಗಳಿಗೆ ಕಾರಣವಾಗಬಹುದು. ನಿರ್ಜಲೀಕರಣವು ಆಯಾಸ, ತಲೆತಿರುಗುವಿಕೆ, ಒಣ ಚರ್ಮ, ತಲೆನೋವು ಮತ್ತು ತೀವ್ರತರವಾದ ಪ್ರಕರಣಗಳಲ್ಲಿ ಇನ್ನಷ್ಟು ಗಂಭೀರ ತೊಡಕುಗಳನ್ನು ಉಂಟುಮಾಡಬಹುದು. ದೇಹದ ಕಾರ್ಯಗಳು ಮತ್ತು ಒಟ್ಟಾರೆ ಯೋಗಕ್ಷೇಮವನ್ನು ಬೆಂಬಲಿಸಲು ಹೈಡ್ರೀಕರಿಸಿರುವುದು ಮುಖ್ಯ."},{"question":"السؤال: ما هي البحار التي تقع عليها الشواطئ التركية؟","answer":"الإجابة: البحر الأسود، البحر الأبيض المتوسط ، بحر مرمرة ، بحر إيجة"},{"question":"પીનાકીન ઠાકોર ની \\"નૈણા રંગ રૂપાળાં\\" કવિતા લખો.","answer":"નૈણા રંગ રૂપાળાં,કમલ નહીં, નહીં હરિણ વીન સમ,અનુપમ રસરળીયાળા રે.. નૈણા રંગ રૂપાળાં..કાજળનાં નવા આંજ્યા અંજન,તોય કાળજા રંજન રંજન,પલક ગંભીર, પલક શા ચંચળ,પલનીજ પલક નીરાળા રે.. નૈણા રંગ રૂપાળાં..મીટ માંડતા સરતા શમણા,મીચું પોપચાં ઉઘડે નમણા,અધબીડ્યાં ખોલ્યાની મધુરપ,મનમોહે મર્માળા રે.. નૈણા રંગ રૂપાળાં.."},{"question":"حمید سوریان در مسابقات المپیک پکن ۲۰۰۸ چگونه ظاهر شد؟","answer":"سوریان در نخستین المپیک خود در المپیک ۲۰۰۸ که تیم ملی کشتی کشور ایران در بدترین عملکرد المپیکی خود تنها یک مدال برنز را کسب کرد، به ترتیب پس از برد برابر ونلین ونکوف از بلغارستان و الگین الوایس از پالائو در دور سوم مسابقات مغلوب نظیر مانکیف، روسی شد. در ادامه او با پیروزی برابر کریستین فریس از صربستان به دیدار رده‌بندی رسید که با باخت برابر پارک ائون چول کره‌ای به مقام پنجم این رقابت‌ها رسید"},{"question":"Ndeipi tsumo inoyenderana neinotevera:Kupfuura nomuchinanga hugonda neshangu","answer":"Kubata mwana wengwe senga pfuti"},{"question":"Fenoy ity ohabolana ity: \\"Be famangotra toa rambon'osy, ___\\"","answer":"\\"Be famangotra toa rambon'osy, ny lanitra tsy hianjera tohanana fa ny vody kaikerin'ny moka tsy heverina.\\""},{"question":"現在、パ・リーグで唯一の永久欠番保持者である、元近鉄の投手は誰でしょう？","answer":"鈴木啓示です。"},{"question":"次の文章に書かれている内容に基づいて、少なくとも200語の段落を書いてください。： 日本の新しいロケット「H3」　打ち上げに失敗","answer":"JAXAは7日朝、新しいロケット「H3」を打ち上げました。しかし、8分後にロケットの2つ目のエンジンに火がついていないことがわかりました。正しく打ち上げることができなかったため、ロケットを壊して、打ち上げが失敗しました。このロケットは、日本の人工衛星「だいち3号」を宇宙に運ぶ予定でした。「H3」は、JAXAなどが9年前から2000億円以上かけて作った新しいロケットです。計画では2020年度に打ち上げる予定でしたが、新しいエンジンを作るのに時間がかかって、遅くなりました。今年2月17日には、打ち上げの6.3秒前に問題が見つかって、打ち上げを中止しました。JAXAは「失敗した原因を急いで調べます。そして、次の打ち上げをどうするか考えます」と話しています。"},{"question":"Tôi không có thời gian nấu ăn sáng cho bé tại nhà nên hay mua bánh mì, xúc xích ở cổng trường, nhưng lo không an toàn thực phẩm. Nên cho con ăn sáng thế nào?","answer":"Nhiều phụ huynh không thể chuẩn bị bữa sáng đúng nghĩa cho con đến trường, đây là một thực tế. Ngoài ra, cũng không ít người cho rằng bữa sáng là bữa phụ nên ăn qua loa, điều này hoàn toàn sai lầm.Bữa sáng sau khoảng thời gian dài 10-12 giờ kể từ bữa ăn tối, cung cấp dinh dưỡng, năng lượng để bắt đầu ngày học tập và làm việc hiệu quả. Vì vậy bữa sáng được coi là bữa quan trọng nhất trong ngày.Bạn cho con ăn sáng bằng những thực phẩm bán ở cổng trường như bánh mì, bánh ngọt, thịt xiên nướng, xúc xích rán, bánh rán... là hoàn toàn không nên. Những thực phẩm này không đảm bảo vệ sinh, phụ huynh cũng không kiểm soát được liệu con có ăn thật hay không."},{"question":"క్రింది పదాలకు విగ్రహవాక్యాలు రాసి సమాసం పేరు వ్రాయండి. అ) కాకతీయుల కంచుగంటఆ) కళ్యాణ ఘంటలుఇ) బ్రతుకుత్రోవఈ) మహారవముఉ) వికారదంష్ట్రలుఊ) కాంతివార్డులుఋ) తెలంగాణ రాష్ట్రంౠ) మతపిశాచి","answer":"సమాసపదం – విగ్రహవాక్యం – సమాసం పేరుఅ) కాకతీయుల కంచుగంట – కాకతీయుల యొక్క కంచుగంట – షష్ఠీ తత్పురుష సమాసముఆ) కళ్యాణ ఘంటలు – కళ్యాణ ప్రదమైన ఘంటలు – విశేషణ పూర్వపద కర్మధారయంఇ) బ్రతుకుత్రోవ – బ్రతుకు యొక్క త్రోవ – షష్ఠీ తత్పురుష సమాసముఈ) మహారవము – మహాయైన (గొప్పదైన) రవము – విశేషణ పూర్వపద కర్మధారయంఉ) వికారదంష్ట్రలు – వికారమైన దంష్ట్రలు – విశేషణ పూర్వపద కర్మధారయంఊ) కాంతివార్డులు – కాంతి అనెడి వార్థులు – రూపకంఋ) తెలంగాణ రాష్ట్రం – తెలంగాణ అను పేరుగల రాష్ట్రం – సంభావనాపూర్వపద కర్మధారయంౠ) మతపిశాచి – మతమనెడు పిశాచి – రూపక సమాసం"},{"question":"Dia melekatkan setem _________ poskad yang cantik itu _________menggunakan gam.","answer":"pada ... dengan"},{"question":"इंद्रधनुष्य कसे तयार होते?","answer":"इंद्रधनुष्य ही एक हवामानशास्त्रीय घटना आहे जी जेव्हा वातावरणातील पाण्याच्या थेंबांद्वारे सूर्यप्रकाश अपवर्तन, परावर्तित आणि विखुरली जाते तेव्हा उद्भवते. ते कसे तयार होते ते येथे आहे:1. सूर्यप्रकाश: प्रक्रिया सूर्यप्रकाशापासून सुरू होते, जी आपल्याला पांढरी दिसते परंतु प्रत्यक्षात प्रकाशाच्या वेगवेगळ्या रंगांचे संयोजन असते, प्रत्येकाची स्वतःची तरंगलांबी असते.2. पावसाचे थेंब: जेव्हा सूर्यप्रकाश वातावरणात पावसाच्या थेंबांचा सामना करतो तेव्हा इंद्रधनुष्य तयार होतात. हे पावसाचे थेंब लहान प्रिझम्ससारखे कार्य करतात, विखुरणे नावाच्या घटनेमुळे सूर्यप्रकाशाचे विविध रंगांमध्ये विभाजन करतात.3. अपवर्तन: सूर्यप्रकाश पावसाच्या थेंबात प्रवेश करत असताना, तो (हवा ते पाण्यापर्यंत) जात असलेल्या माध्यमात बदल झाल्यामुळे त्याचा वेग कमी होतो आणि दिशा बदलते. प्रकाशाच्या या झुकण्याला अपवर्तन म्हणतात.4. प्रतिबिंब: नंतर प्रकाश थेंबाच्या मागील पृष्ठभागावर आदळत, पावसाच्या थेंबाच्या आतील पृष्ठभागावर परावर्तित होतो.5. पुढील अपवर्तन आणि फैलाव: परावर्तित झाल्यानंतर, प्रकाश पावसाच्या थेंबातून बाहेर पडतो आणि हवेत परत जाताना दुसरे अपवर्तन करतो. या अपवर्तनामुळे प्रकाशाचे वेगवेगळे रंग एकमेकांपासून पुढे पसरतात किंवा विखुरतात.6. दृश्यमान रंग: हे पसरणे पांढर्‍या प्रकाशाला त्याच्या घटक रंगांमध्ये वेगळे करते, रंगांचे परिचित स्पेक्ट्रम तयार करते: लाल, नारंगी, पिवळा, हिरवा, निळा, इंडिगो आणि व्हायलेट. या प्रत्येक रंगाची तरंगलांबी वेगळी असते.7. पाहण्याचा कोन: इंद्रधनुष्य पाहण्यासाठी, निरीक्षकाची दृष्टी सूर्यप्रकाशाच्या विरुद्ध दिशेने निर्देशित केली पाहिजे. याचा अर्थ असा की जेव्हा तुम्ही सूर्यापासून दूर जाता आणि पावसाचे थेंब असलेल्या आकाशाच्या क्षेत्राकडे पाहता तेव्हा तुम्हाला सामान्यत: इंद्रधनुष्य दिसते.8. वर्तुळाकार आकार: इंद्रधनुष्य गोलाकार आकाराचे असतात कारण ते वातावरणात विखुरलेल्या अनेक पावसाच्या थेंबांनी तयार होतात. तथापि, वर्तुळाच्या खालच्या भागामध्ये जमीन अडथळा आणत असल्याने, आपल्याला सहसा आकाशात अर्धवर्तुळाकार कंस दिसतो. तुम्ही उंचावर असल्यास, विमानाप्रमाणे, तुम्हाला पूर्ण वर्तुळाकार इंद्रधनुष्य दिसू शकते.हे लक्षात घेणे महत्त्वाचे आहे की प्राथमिक इंद्रधनुष्य बाह्य काठावरील लाल ते आतील काठावरील व्हायलेट रंगांच्या क्रमाचे अनुसरण करत असताना, दुय्यम इंद्रधनुष्य देखील असू शकतात. हे फिकट आहेत आणि त्यांचे रंग उलटे आहेत, आतील काठावर लाल आणि बाहेरील काठावर वायलेट आहे. दुय्यम इंद्रधनुष्य पावसाच्या थेंबामध्ये दुहेरी प्रतिबिंबाने तयार होतात.लक्षात ठेवा की इंद्रधनुष्य पाहण्याच्या अटी विशिष्ट आहेत, ज्यामध्ये सूर्यप्रकाश, पावसाचे थेंब आणि योग्य दृश्य कोन यांचा समावेश आहे."},{"question":"Поясни значення терміну \\"цитоплазма\\".","answer":"Цитоплазма складає основну масу клітини - це весь її внутрішній вміст, за винятком ядра. Містить 75-85 % води, 15-25 % білків і багато інших речовин, але в менших кількостях. При вивченні клітини за допомогою світлового мікроскопа цитоплазма є гомогенною, безбарвною, прозорою, в'язкою рідиною, проте в електронному мікроскопі можемо побачити складну багатокомпонентну, поліфункціональну, високовпорядковану структуру цитоплазми. Цитоплазма складається із цитозолю (цитоплазматичний матрикс), внутрішньоклітинних органел і включень."},{"question":"Can you summarize the following document?        Water mint is an herbaceous, rhizomatous perennial plant growing to tall. The stems are square in cross section, green or purple, and variably hairy to almost hairless. The rhizomes are wide-spreading, fleshy, and bear fibrous roots. The leaves are ovate to ovate-lanceolate, long and broad, green (sometimes purplish), opposite, toothed, and vary from hairy to nearly hairless. The flowers of the watermint are tiny, densely crowded, purple, tubular, pinkish to lilac in color, and form a terminal hemispherical inflorescence; flowering is from mid- to late-summer. Water mint is visited by many types of insects and can be characterized by a generalized pollination syndrome, but it can also be spread by underground rhizomes. All parts of the plant have a distinctly minty smell. Unbranched, hairless plants with narrower leaves and paler flowers, native to areas of Sweden and Finland near the Baltic Sea, have been called \\"Mentha aquatica\\" var. \\"litoralis\\" \\"Mentha aquatica\\" is a polyploid, with 2\\"n\\" = 8\\"x\\" = 96 chromosomes.\\"Mentha aquatica\\" was first described by Carl Linnaeus in 1753. As with other \\"Mentha\\" species, it was subsequently re-described under a variety of different names; Plants of the World Online listed 87 synonyms, including four forms or varieties that it does not recognize. The cultivated eau de Cologne mint (also known as bergamot mint) is considered to be a variety of this species. It hybridizes with \\"Mentha spicata\\" (spearmint) to produce \\"Mentha\\" × \\"piperita\\" (peppermint), a sterile hybrid; with \\"Mentha suaveolens\\" (apple mint) to produce \\"Mentha\\" × \\"suavis\\"; with \\"Mentha arvensis\\" (corn mint) to produce \\"Mentha\\" × \\"verticillata\\"; and with both \\"M. arvensis\\" and \\"M. spicata\\" to give the tri-species hybrid \\"Mentha\\" × \\"smithiana\\".Water mint is native to much of Europe, northern Africa, and western Asia. It has been introduced to North and South America, Australia, and some Atlantic islands. As the name suggests, water mint occurs in the shallow margins and channels of streams, rivers, pools, dikes, ditches, canals, wet meadows, marshes, and fens. If the plant grows in the water itself, it rises above the surface of the water. It generally occurs on mildly acidic to calcareous (it is common on soft limestone) mineral or peaty soils. \\"M. aquatica\\" can occur in certain fen-meadow habitats, such as the Juncus subnodulosus-Cirsium palustre plant association. It is a component of purple moor grass and rush pastures, a type of Biodiversity ActPlan habitat in the UK.It can be used to make herbal tea. The cultivated variety known as eau de Cologne mint or bergamot mint is used to produce mentha citrata oil, also known as bergamot oil, used in perfumery.","answer":"Mentha aquatica (water mint; syn. \\"Mentha hirsuta\\" Huds.) is a perennial flowering plant in the mint family Lamiaceae. It grows in moist places and is native to much of Europe, northwest Africa, and southwest Asia."},{"question":"¿Joe Biden es demócrata o republicano?","answer":"Joe Biden es demócrata. Es miembro del Partido Demócrata de los Estados Unidos y actualmente ocupa el cargo de Presidente de la nación."},{"question":"Kush e fitoi FIFA Kupën e Botës në vitin 1990?","answer":"FIFA Kupën e Botës në vitin 1990 e fitoi Gjermania."},{"question":"Dame un ejemplo de trivia en está categoría : libros. ","answer":"¿En qué año nació el autor de Heredero del Imperio? Respuesta : En el año 1951. "},{"question":"भारतामध्ये सशस्त्र दलाचे सर्वोच्च सेनापती कोण असतात?उत्तर : ","answer":"भारतामध्ये सशस्त्र दलाचे सर्वोच्च सेनापती राष्ट्रपती असतात."},{"question":"من هم خاصة الله وأهله؟","answer":"أهل القرآن الكريم."},{"question":"ਸਮਾਜ ਵਿਗਿਆਨ ਬਾਕੀ ਸਮਾਜਿਕ ਵਿਗਿਆਨਾਂ ਨਾਲ ਸੰਬੰਧਿਤ ਹੈ ।","answer":"ਸਾਰੇ ਸਮਾਜਿਕ ਵਿਗਿਆਨ ਦੇ ਵਿਚ ਵਿਸ਼ੇ-ਖੇਤਰ ਦੀ ਭਿੰਨਤਾ ਨਹੀਂ ਬਲਕਿ ਦ੍ਰਿਸ਼ਟੀਕੋਣ ਵਿਚ ਹੀ ਕੇਵਲ ਭਿੰਨਤਾ ਹੁੰਦੀ ਹੈ ਪਰੰਤੂ ਸਾਰੇ ਹੀ ਸਮਾਜਿਕ ਵਿਗਿਆਨ ਕੇਵਲ ਮਨੁੱਖੀ ਸਮਾਜ ਦਾ ਹੀ ਅਧਿਐਨ ਕਰਦੇ ਹਨ ਜਿਸ ਕਰਕੇ ਅਸੀਂ ਸਮਾਜ ਵਿਗਿਆਨ ਨੂੰ ਇਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਬਾਕੀ ਸਮਾਜਿਕ ਵਿਗਿਆਨਾਂ ਤੋਂ ਵੱਖ ਨਹੀਂ ਕਰ ਸਕਦੇ ਜਿਵੇਂ ਅਰਥ ਵਿਗਿਆਨ ਆਰਥਿਕ ਸਮੱਸਿਆਵਾਂ ਨਾਲ ਭਾਵੇਂ ਸੰਬੰਧਿਤ ਹੈ ਪਰੰਤੂ ਇਹ ਸਮੱਸਿਆਵਾਂ ਸਮਾਜ ਦਾ ਹੀ ਇਕ ਹਿੱਸਾ ਹਨ । ਕਿਸੇ ਵੀ ਸਮੱਸਿਆ ਦਾ ਹੱਲ ਲੱਭਣ ਲਈ ਬਾਕੀ ਵਿਗਿਆਨਾਂ ਦਾ ਵੀ ਸਹਾਰਾ ਲੈਣਾ ਪੈਂਦਾ ਹੈ ।"},{"question":"Кыргызстандын кайсы дарыясы эң узун жана кайсы жерге куят?","answer":"Жооп: Кыргызстандагы эң узун дарыя Нарын дарыясы , ал  акырында Сыр-Дарыяга куят."},{"question":"لاندې پوښتنې ته ځواب ورکړئ. څوک د خپلواکۍ وروسته د نایجریا لومړی ولسمشر دی","answer":"د نایجیریا لومړی ولسمشر چې په ۱۹۶۰ کې د برتانوي استعمار څخه خپلواکي ترلاسه کړه، ډاکټر نومدي بنیامین ایزیوی وو. هغه د نایجیریا د خپلواکۍ په مبارزه کې مهم رول لوبولی او د هیواد د خپلواکۍ وروسته په لومړیو سیاستونو کې یو مهم شخصیت وو. ډاکټر عزیزیو یو معتبر ملتپال او د ځان واکمنۍ مهم مدافع وو.هغه د ۱۹۶۰ کال د اکتوبر په لومړۍ نېټه د نایجیریا د والي په توګه لوړه وکړه او وروسته د ۱۹۶۳ کال د اکتوبر په لومړۍ نېټه د نایجیریا د رسمي ولسمشر په توګه وټاکل شو - د برتانوي استعمار له کلونو وروسته حکومت.ډاکټر ایزیکیوی مشرتابه په یو متنوع ملت کې د څو توکمیزو او سیمه ایزو هویتونو سره د یووالي لپاره د هغه د ژمنې نښه وه. د هغه هڅو د نایجیریا د یو خپلواک او دیموکراتیک ملت په توګه د پرمختګ بنسټ کېښود.\\""},{"question":"Cad é an céatadán? ","answer":"Más cuimhin liom i gceart, sílim go bhféadfadh tú an focal 'céatadán' a úsáid chun cur síos a dhéanamh ar líon na n-uaireanta a tharlaíonn rud éigin i sraith, i gcodarsnacht le méid rud éigin a tharlaíonn. Mar sin mar shampla d'fhéadfadh tú a rá go ndearna 80% de na mic léinn an tástáil matamaitice a rith. Nó d'fhéadfá a rá go bhfuil 20% níos lú uaireanta sa lá ná mar atá sa bhliain."},{"question":"በሶቭየት ኅብረት የቀለም ቴሌቭዥን ስርጭት የተጀመረው መቼ ነው?","answer":"በ1959"},{"question":"Ahitsio ny tsipelina amin'ity fanambarana manaraka ity: \\"Ny sakoroka manolôna ny fitran-drahana volamena teny Soamahamanina natao ny Sinoa no naresaka tato ato.\\"","answer":"Ity ny fanambarana miaraka amin'ny hadisoana voahitsy \\"Ny sakoroka manoloana ny fitrandrahana volamena teny Soamahamanina nataon’ny Sinoa no naresaka tatoato.\\""},{"question":"保有財産の売却や、株などの取引によって得られた利益のことを英語で何というでしょう？","answer":"キャピタルゲインです。"},{"question":"Apakah jawapan untuk teka-teki berikut: Tindakan untuk menggerakkan pintu dan troli.","answer":"Jawapannya ialah tolak"},{"question":"హిమాలయాల్లో కార్చిచ్చులను ఆపి కరెంటు సృష్టిస్తున్నారు.. ఇలా..nఆకాశాన్ని తాకేలా కనిపిస్తున్న పొడుగాటి పైన్ చెట్ల మధ్యలోంచి సూరీడు తొంగిచూస్తున్నాడు. సేంద్రియ రంగులు మాత్రమే వాడి తయారుచేసి చేనేత పట్టు, కాటన్ దుస్తుల కోసం నేను అక్కడకు వెళ్లాను.స్థానిక చేనేత కార్మికులు రూపొందించిన ఆ వస్త్రాలను అవని అనే సంస్థ విక్రయిస్తోంది.అక్కడ నా దృష్టిని మరో విషయం ఆకర్షించింది. అది... ఎండిన పైన్ చెట్ల కొమ్మలు, ఆకుల గుట్టలు. ఓ వ్యక్తి ఆ ఎండిన పైన్ కొమ్మలను ఒక మోటారుకు అమర్చిన పెద్ద సిలిండర్‌లో పెడుతున్నాడు. పైన్ ఆకులతో విద్యుదుత్పత్తి చేస్తున్నారక్కడ.పశ్చిమ హిమాలయ ప్రాంతంలోని ఉత్తరాఖండ్‌‌లో అనేక ఆలయాలు ఉండడంతో ఆ రాష్ట్రాన్ని దేవభూమి అంటారు. ఈ రాష్ట్రానికి టిబెట్, నేపాల్‌తో సరిహద్దులున్నాయి.మంచు పర్వతాలు, నదులు, అనేక వృక్ష, జంతుజాతుజాలాలున్న ఉత్తరాఖండ్‌ది ప్రత్యేకమైన పర్యావరణ వ్యవస్థ.ఉత్తరాఖండ్ అంతటా పైన్ అడవులు విస్తారంగా ఉన్నాయి. సుమారు 10 లక్షల ఎకరాల్లో విస్తరించిన ఉన్న ఈ పైన్ అడవులతో అక్కడ కొన్ని ఇబ్బందులూ ఉన్నాయి. ఎండిన పైన్ ఆకులు నేలరాలి పోగవుతాయి. తేలిగ్గా ఉండే ఇవి ఏమాత్రం అగ్గి రాజుకున్నా అడవిని దహించివేస్తాయి.ఏటా ఒక్క ఉత్తరాఖండ్ రాష్ట్ర అడవుల్లోనే 13 లక్షల టన్నుల పైన్ ఆకులు నేలరాలుతుంటాయని అంచనా. మార్చి, జూన్ నెలల మధ్య ఎక్కువగా ఈ ఆకులు రాలుతాయి. ఇవి కొండవాలులో పరుచుకుంటాయి. ఇవి ఉత్తరాఖండ్‌లో కార్చిచ్చులకు కారణమవుతున్నాయి.బయోమాస్ గ్యాసిఫికేషన్ ప్లాంట్కార్చిచ్చుల కారణంగా నష్టం జరుగుతుందని.. అటవీ సమతుల్యతను అవి దెబ్బతీస్తాయని జీబీ పంత్ నేషనల్ ఇనిస్టిట్యూట్‌ ఆఫ్ హిమాలయన్ ఎన్విరానమెంట్‌లో సెంటర్ ఫర్ సోషియో ఎకనమిక్ హెడ్ జీసీఎస్ నేగి అన్నారు.ఔషధ మూలికలు, ఇతర అవసరాలుగా ఉపయోగించే 1800 రకాల మొక్కలకు ఇక్కడి అటవీ ప్రాంతం ఆలవాలం. కానీ, కార్చిచ్చులు ఈ ప్రాంతాన్ని ఆ మొక్కల మనుగడకు అననుకూలంగా మార్చేస్తున్నాయి.\\"దేశీయ మొక్కలు, చెట్లు పర్యావరణపరంగా, సామాజికంగా ఎంతో విలువైనవి. అవి భూ, జల సంరక్షణలో ఎంతో కీలకం. ఫలితంగా అడవి స్థానికులకు తిండి, ఇతర అటవీ ఉత్పత్తులను అందివ్వడమే కాకుండా జీవివైవిధ్యాన్ని కాపాడుతుంది'' అంటారు నేగి.పైన్ ఆకులతో విద్యుదుత్పత్తి తరువాత మిగిలే వ్యర్థాలలో కార్బన్ ఎక్కువగా ఉంటుంది. దీన్ని బొగ్గులా మలచి వంట చెరకుగా వినియోగిస్తారు.ఉత్తరాఖండ్‌లోని కుమావూ ప్రాంతం బేరినాగ్‌లో అవని సంస్థ ఉంది. సోలార్ ఇరిగేషన్ నేపథ్యం ఉన్న మేనేజ్‌మెంట్ కన్సల్టెంట్ రజనీశ్..ది. ","answer":"చలికాలం ముదురుతున్న నవంబరు నెలలో ఒక ఉదయాన నేను ఉత్తరాఖండ్‌లోని పిత్తోర్‌గఢ్ జిల్లా త్రిపురవేది గ్రామంలోని కొండ మార్గంలో డ్రైవ్ చేసుకుంటూ వెళ్తున్నాను."},{"question":"ඇමරිකා එක්සත් ජනපදයේ විවිධ මාර්ග වර්ග ගැන මට කියන්න.","answer":"ඇමරිකා එක්සත් ජනපදයේ පොදු මාර්ග පද්ධතිය මූලික වශයෙන් අධිවේගී මාර්ග සහ දේශීය මාර්ග වලින් සමන්විත වේ. එක්සත් ජනපද ප්‍රවාහන දෙපාර්තමේන්තුවේ ෆෙඩරල් මහාමාර්ග පරිපාලනය (FWHA) වේග සීමාවන්, මාර්ග දිග සහ පරතරය වැනි ගුණාංග මත පදනම්ව නිර්මාණය කරන ලද කාර්යයන් මත පදනම්ව මාර්ග වර්ගීකරණය කරයි. මාර්ග ක්‍රියාකාරකම් මත පදනම්ව අපට මාර්ග පහත දැක්වෙන වර්ග වලට වර්ග කළ හැක. 1. අන්තර් රාජ්‍ය සහ ධමනි පද්ධතිය 2. අනෙකුත් ධමනි 3. එකතුකරන්නන් 4. ප්‍රදේශය අන්තර් රාජ්‍ය පද්ධතිය මාර්ග ක්‍රියාකාරී වර්ගීකරණ පද්ධතියේ ඉහළින්ම ඇත. ඉහළම වේග සීමාවන් සහිත අධිවේගී මාර්ග සහ නිදහස් මාර්ග ඒවාට ඇතුළත් වන අතර විශාල බාධාවකින් තොරව දුර ගමන් කිරීමට ඉඩ සලසයි. ඒවා නිශ්චිත ප්‍රමිතීන්, සංඥා සහ ආරක්‍ෂාව සැලකිල්ලට ගනිමින් ඉදිකර ඇත. ඇමරිකාවේ කලාප හරහා අත්‍යවශ්‍ය සම්බන්ධතාවයක් සපයන බැවින් ඒවා සමහර විට ධමනි මාර්ග ලෙසද හැඳින්වේ. අන්තර් රාජ්‍ය 95 හෝ I-95 යනු එක්සත් ජනපදයේ නැගෙනහිර වෙරළ තීරයේ ෆ්ලොරිඩා සිට මේන් දක්වා දිවෙන එවැනි එක් අධිවේගී මාර්ගයකට උදාහරණයකි. ප්‍රධාන ධමනි පද්ධතිය එක්සත් ජනපද අධිවේගී මාර්ග වලින් ද සමන්විත වන අතර, ගමනට සහාය වීමට අන්තර් රාජ්‍යයක් නොමැති ප්‍රදේශ හරහා සම්බන්ධතාවය සපයයි. අනෙකුත් ධමනිවල ඉහත විස්තර කර ඇති අන්තර් රාජ්‍ය පද්ධතියට අතිරේකව නිදහස් මාර්ග සහ මහාමාර්ග ද ඇතුළත් වේ. ඒවාට තරමක් අඩු වේග සීමාවක් ඇත. ඔවුන් සාමාන්යයෙන් නගර සහ නාගරික ප්රදේශ සම්බන්ධ කරයි. ඒවා කුඩා අධිවේගී මාර්ග ලෙස සලකන්න. උදාහරණයක් ලෙස, උතුරු කැරොලිනා අධිවේගී මාර්ගය 55 (NC-55) යනු උතුරු කැරොලිනා ප්‍රාන්තයේ ප්‍රාදේශීය සහ නාගරික ප්‍රදේශ කිහිපයක් සම්බන්ධ කරන ප්‍රාථමික රාජ්‍ය මහාමාර්ග ධමනියකි. අදාළ වන විට අන්තර් රාජ්‍ය මහාමාර්ග සමඟ ප්‍රාදේශීය මාර්ග භාවිතා කරමින් නාගරික ජනගහනය සම්බන්ධ කිරීම සඳහා එකතුකරන්නන් ඉතා වැදගත් වේ. ඒවාට වැඩි බාධා ඇති අතර දිග කෙටි වේ. ඒවාට අඩු වේග සීමාවන් ද ඇත (පැයට සැතපුම් 30-35). මේවාට ප්‍රාදේශීය මාර්ග ධමනි මහාමාර්ග සම්බන්ධ කරන රාජ්‍ය මහාමාර්ගවලින් සමන්විත විය හැකිය. අවසාන වශයෙන් ප්‍රාදේශීය මාර්ග ප්‍රජාවන්, ප්‍රදේශ, ගොවිපල සහ අනෙකුත් ප්‍රදේශ අතර සම්බන්ධතාවය සපයයි. ඔවුන් එක්සත් ජනපදයේ මාර්ග පද්ධතියේ සිංහ කොටසයි."},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਸਿਰੀਰਾਗੁ ਮਹਲਾ ੧ ॥ਮਨਮੁਖਿ ਭੁਲੈ ਭੁਲਾਈਐ ਭੂਲੀ ਠਉਰ ਨ ਕਾਇ ॥ਗੁਰ ਬਿਨੁ ਕੋ ਨ ਦਿਖਾਵਈ ਅੰਧੀ ਆਵੈ ਜਾਇ ॥ਗਿਆਨ ਪਦਾਰਥੁ ਖੋਇਆ ਠਗਿਆ ਮੁਠਾ ਜਾਇ ॥੧॥ਬਾਬਾ ਮਾਇਆ ਭਰਮਿ ਭੁਲਾਇ ॥ਭਰਮਿ ਭੁਲੀ ਡੋਹਾਗਣੀ ਨਾ ਪਿਰ ਅੰਕਿ ਸਮਾਇ ॥੧॥ ਰਹਾਉ ॥ਭੂਲੀ ਫਿਰੈ ਦਿਸੰਤਰੀ ਭੂਲੀ ਗ੍ਰਿਹੁ ਤਜਿ ਜਾਇ ॥ਭੂਲੀ ਡੂੰਗਰਿ ਥਲਿ ਚੜੈ ਭਰਮੈ ਮਨੁ ਡੋਲਾਇ ॥ਧੁਰਹੁ ਵਿਛੁੰਨੀ ਕਿਉ ਮਿਲੈ ਗਰਬਿ ਮੁਠੀ ਬਿਲਲਾਇ ॥੨॥ਵਿਛੁੜਿਆ ਗੁਰੁ ਮੇਲਸੀ ਹਰਿ ਰਸਿ ਨਾਮ ਪਿਆਰਿ ॥ਸਾਚਿ ਸਹਜਿ ਸੋਭਾ ਘਣੀ ਹਰਿ ਗੁਣ ਨਾਮ ਅਧਾਰਿ ॥ਜਿਉ ਭਾਵੈ ਤਿਉ ਰਖੁ ਤੂੰ ਮੈ ਤੁਝ ਬਿਨੁ ਕਵਨੁ ਭਤਾਰੁ ॥੩॥ਅਖਰ ਪੜਿ ਪੜਿ ਭੁਲੀਐ ਭੇਖੀ ਬਹੁਤੁ ਅਭਿਮਾਨੁ ॥ਤੀਰਥ ਨਾਤਾ ਕਿਆ ਕਰੇ ਮਨ ਮਹਿ ਮੈਲੁ ਗੁਮਾਨੁ ॥ਗੁਰ ਬਿਨੁ ਕਿਨਿ ਸਮਝਾਈਐ ਮਨੁ ਰਾਜਾ ਸੁਲਤਾਨੁ ॥੪॥ਪ੍ਰੇਮ ਪਦਾਰਥੁ ਪਾਈਐ ਗੁਰਮੁਖਿ ਤਤੁ ਵੀਚਾਰੁ ॥ਸਾ ਧਨ ਆਪੁ ਗਵਾਇਆ ਗੁਰ ਕੈ ਸਬਦਿ ਸੀਗਾਰੁ ॥ਘਰ ਹੀ ਸੋ ਪਿਰੁ ਪਾਇਆ ਗੁਰ ਕੈ ਹੇਤਿ ਅਪਾਰੁ ॥੫॥ਗੁਰ ਕੀ ਸੇਵਾ ਚਾਕਰੀ ਮਨੁ ਨਿਰਮਲੁ ਸੁਖੁ ਹੋਇ ॥ਗੁਰ ਕਾ ਸਬਦੁ ਮਨਿ ਵਸਿਆ ਹਉਮੈ ਵਿਚਹੁ ਖੋਇ ॥ਨਾਮੁ ਪਦਾਰਥੁ ਪਾਇਆ ਲਾਭੁ ਸਦਾ ਮਨਿ ਹੋਇ ॥੬॥ਕਰਮਿ ਮਿਲੈ ਤਾ ਪਾਈਐ ਆਪਿ ਨ ਲਇਆ ਜਾਇ ॥ਗੁਰ ਕੀ ਚਰਣੀ ਲਗਿ ਰਹੁ ਵਿਚਹੁ ਆਪੁ ਗਵਾਇ ॥ਸਚੇ ਸੇਤੀ ਰਤਿਆ ਸਚੋ ਪਲੈ ਪਾਇ ॥੭॥ਭੁਲਣ ਅੰਦਰਿ ਸਭੁ ਕੋ ਅਭੁਲੁ ਗੁਰੂ ਕਰਤਾਰੁ ॥ਗੁਰਮਤਿ ਮਨੁ ਸਮਝਾਇਆ ਲਾਗਾ ਤਿਸੈ ਪਿਆਰੁ ॥ਨਾਨਕ ਸਾਚੁ ਨ ਵੀਸਰੈ ਮੇਲੇ ਸਬਦੁ ਅਪਾਰੁ ॥੮॥੧੨॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 60 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਨਾਨਕ ਦੇਵ ਜੀ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਬਾਣੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਹਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"ਆਪਣੇ ਮਨ ਦੇ ਪਿੱਛੇ ਤੁਰਨ ਵਾਲੀ ਇਸਤ੍ਰੀ (ਜੀਵਨ ਦੇ) ਸਹੀ ਰਸਤੇ ਤੋਂ ਖੁੰਝ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ, ਮਾਇਆ ਉਸ ਨੂੰ ਕੁਰਾਹੇ ਪਾ ਦੇਂਦੀ ਹੈ, ਰਾਹੋਂ ਖੁੰਝੀ ਹੋਈ ਨੂੰ (ਗੁਰੂ ਤੋਂ ਬਿਨਾ) ਕੋਈ (ਐਸਾ) ਥਾਂ ਨਹੀਂ ਲੱਭਦਾ (ਜੇਹੜਾ ਉਸ ਨੂੰ ਰਸਤਾ ਵਿਖਾ ਦੇਵੇ)  ਗੁਰੂ ਤੋਂ ਬਿਨਾ ਹੋਰ ਕੋਈ ਭੀ (ਸਹੀ ਰਸਤਾ) ਵਿਖਾ ਨਹੀਂ ਸਕਦਾ । (ਮਾਇਆ ਦੇ ਵਿਚ) ਅੰਨ੍ਹੀ ਹੋਈ ਜੀਵ-ਇਸਤ੍ਰੀ ਭਟਕਦੀ ਫਿਰਦੀ ਹੈਜਿਸ ਭੀ ਜੀਵ ਨੇ (ਮਾਇਆ ਦੇ ਢਹੇ ਚੜ੍ਹ ਕੇ) ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਨਾਲ ਡੂੰਘੀ ਸਾਂਝ ਪੈਦਾ ਕਰਨ ਵਾਲਾ ਨਾਮ-ਧਨ ਗਵਾ ਲਿਆ ਹੈ, ਉਹ ਠੱਗਿਆ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ, ਉਹ (ਆਤਮਕ ਜੀਵਨ ਵਲੋਂ) ਲੁੱਟਿਆ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ ।੧।ਹੇ ਭਾਈ ! ਮਾਇਆ (ਜੀਵਾਂ ਨੂੰ) ਭੁਲੇਖੇ ਵਿਚ ਪਾ ਕੇ ਕੁਰਾਹੇ ਪਾ ਦੇਂਦੀ ਹੈ ਜੇਹੜੀ ਭਾਗ ਹੀਣ ਜੀਵ-ਇਸਤ੍ਰੀ ਭੁਲੇਖੇ ਵਿਚ ਪੈ ਕੇ ਕੁਰਾਹੇ ਪੈਂਦੀ ਹੈ, ਉਹ (ਕਦੇ ਭੀ) ਪ੍ਰਭੂ-ਪਤੀ ਦੇ ਚਰਨਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਲੀਨ ਨਹੀਂ ਹੋ ਸਕਦੀ ।੧।ਰਹਾਉ।ਜੀਵਨ ਦੇ ਰਾਹ ਤੋਂ ਖੁੰਝੀ ਹੋਈ ਜੀਵ-ਇਸਤ੍ਰੀ ਹੀ ਗ੍ਰਿਹਸਤ ਤਿਆਗ ਕੇ ਦੇਸ ਦੇਸਾਂਤਰਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਫਿਰਦੀ ਹੈਖੁੰਝੀ ਹੋਈ ਹੀ ਕਦੇ ਕਿਸੇ ਪਹਾੜ (ਦੀ ਗੁਫ਼ਾ) ਵਿਚ ਬੈਠਦੀ ਹੈ ਕਦੇ ਕਿਸੇ ਟਿੱਲੇ ਉੱਤੇ ਚੜ੍ਹ ਬੈਠਦੀ ਹੈ, ਭਟਕਦੀ ਫਿਰਦੀ ਹੈ, ਉਸਦਾ ਮਨ (ਮਾਇਆ ਦੇ ਅਸਰ ਹੇਠ) ਡੋਲਦਾ ਹੈ (ਆਪਣੇ ਕੀਤੇ ਕਰਮਾਂ ਦੇ ਕਾਰਨ) ਧੁਰੋਂ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੇ ਹੁਕਮ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿੱਛੁੜੀ ਹੋਈ (ਪ੍ਰਭੂ-ਚਰਨਾਂ ਵਿਚ) ਜੁੜ ਨਹੀਂ ਸਕਦੀ, ਉਹ ਤਾਂ (ਤਿਆਗ ਆਦਿਕ ਦੇ) ਅਹੰਕਾਰ ਵਿਚ ਲੁੱਟੀ ਜਾ ਰਹੀ ਹੈ, ਤੇ (ਵਿਛੋੜੇ ਵਿਚ) ਕਲਪਦੀ ਹੈ ।੨।ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਤੋਂ ਵਿੱਛੁੜਿਆਂ ਨੂੰ ਗੁਰੂ ਹਰਿ-ਨਾਮ ਦੇ ਆਨੰਦ ਵਿਚ ਜੋੜ ਕੇ, ਨਾਮ ਦੇ ਪਿਆਰ ਵਿਚ ਜੋੜ ਕੇ (ਮੁੜ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਨਾਲ) ਮਿਲਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ ਹਰੀ ਦੇ ਗੁਣਾਂ ਦੀ ਬਰਕਤਿ ਨਾਲ ਹਰੀ-ਨਾਮ ਦੇ ਆਸਰੇ ਨਾਲ ਸਦਾ-ਥਿਰ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਵਿਚ (ਜੁੜਿਆਂ) ਅਡੋਲ ਅਵਸਥਾ ਵਿਚ (ਟਿਕਿਆਂ) ਬੜੀ ਸੋਭਾ (ਭੀ ਮਿਲਦੀ ਹੈ) (ਮੈਂ ਤੇਰਾ ਦਾਸ ਬੇਨਤੀ ਕਰਦਾ ਹਾਂ—ਹੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ !) ਜਿਵੇਂ ਤੇਰੀ ਰਜ਼ਾ ਹੋ ਸਕੇ, ਮੈਨੂੰ ਆਪਣੇ ਚਰਨਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਰੱਖ । ਤੈਥੋਂ ਬਿਨਾ ਮੇਰਾ ਖਸਮ-ਸਾਈਂ ਹੋਰ ਕੋਈ ਨਹੀਂ ।੩।ਵਿੱਦਿਆ ਪੜ੍ਹ ਪੜ੍ਹ ਕੇ (ਭੀ ਵਿੱਦਿਆ ਦੇ ਅਹੰਕਾਰ ਕਾਰਨ) ਕੁਰਾਹੇ ਹੀ ਪਈਦਾ ਹੈ, (ਗ੍ਰਿਹਸਤ-ਤਿਆਗੀਆਂ ਦੇ) ਭੇਖਾਂ ਨਾਲ ਭੀ (ਮਨ ਵਿਚ) ਬੜਾ ਮਾਣ ਪੈਦਾ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈਤੀਰਥਾਂ ਉੱਤੇ ਇਸ਼ਨਾਨ ਕਰਨ ਨਾਲ ਭੀ ਜੀਵ ਕੁਝ ਨਹੀਂ ਸੰਵਾਰ ਸਕਦਾ, ਕਿਉਂਕਿ ਮਨ ਵਿਚ (ਇਸ) ਅਹੰਕਾਰ ਦੀ ਮੈਲ ਟਿਕੀ ਰਹਿੰਦੀ ਹੈ (ਕਿ ਮੈਂ ਤੀਰਥ ਇਸ਼ਨਾਨੀ ਹਾਂ) (ਹਰੇਕ ਖੁੰਝੇ ਹੋਏ ਰਸਤੇ ਵਿਚ) ਮਨ (ਇਸ ਸਰੀਰ-ਨਗਰੀ ਦਾ) ਰਾਜਾ ਬਣਿਆ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ, ਸੁਲਤਾਨ ਬਣਿਆ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ । ਗੁਰੂ ਤੋਂ ਬਿਨਾ ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਕਿਸੇ ਹੋਰ ਨੇ ਕਦੇ ਮਤਿ ਨਹੀਂ ਦਿੱਤੀ (ਕੋਈ ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਸਮਝਾ ਨਹੀਂ ਸਕਿਆ) ।੪।(ਹੇ ਬਾਬਾ !) ਗੁਰੂ ਦੀ ਸਰਨ ਪੈ ਕੇ ਆਪਣੇ ਮੂਲ-ਪ੍ਰਭੂ (ਦੇ ਗੁਣਾਂ) ਨੂੰ ਵਿਚਾਰ । ਗੁਰੂ ਦੀ ਸਰਨ ਪਿਆਂ ਹੀ (ਪ੍ਰਭੂ-ਚਰਨਾਂ ਨਾਲ) ਪ੍ਰੇਮ ਪੈਦਾ ਕਰਨ ਵਾਲਾ ਨਾਮ-ਧਨ ਮਿਲਦਾ ਹਜਿਸ ਜੀਵ-ਇਸਤ੍ਰੀ ਨੇ ਆਪਾ-ਭਾਵ ਦੂਰ ਕੀਤਾ ਹੈ, ਗੁਰੂ ਦੇ ਸ਼ਬਦ ਵਿਚ (ਜੁੜ ਕੇ ਆਤਮਕ ਜੀਵਨ ਨੂੰ ਆਪਾ-ਭਾਵ ਦੂਰ ਕਰਨ ਦਾ) ਸਿੰਗਾਰ ਕੀਤਾ ਹੈਉਸ ਨੇ ਗੁਰੂ ਦੇ ਬਖ਼ਸ਼ੇ ਪ੍ਰੇਮ ਦੀ ਰਾਹੀਂ ਆਪਣੇ ਹਿਰਦੇ ਘਰ ਵਿਚ ਉਸ ਬੇਅੰਤ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਪਤੀ ਨੂੰ ਲੱਭ ਲਿਆ ਹੈ ।੫।ਗੁਰੂ ਦੀ ਦੱਸੀ ਹੋਈ ਸੇਵਾ ਕੀਤਿਆਂ ਚਾਕਰੀ ਕੀਤਿਆਂ ਮਨ ਪਵਿਤ੍ਰ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ, ਆਤਮਕ ਆਨੰਦ ਮਿਲਦਾ ਹੈਜਿਸ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਦੇ ਮਨ ਵਿਚ ਗੁਰੂ ਦਾ ਸ਼ਬਦ (ਉਪਦੇਸ਼) ਵੱਸ ਪੈਂਦਾ ਹੈ, ਉਹ ਆਪਣੇ ਅੰਦਰੋਂ ਹਉਮੈ ਦੂਰ ਕਰ ਲੈਂਦਾ ਹੈਜਿਸ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਨੇ (ਗੁਰੂ ਦੀ ਸਰਨ ਪੈ ਕੇ) ਨਾਮ-ਧਨ ਹਾਸਲ ਕਰ ਲਿਆ ਹੈ, ਉਸ ਦੇ ਮਨ ਵਿਚ ਸਦਾ ਲਾਭ ਹੰੁਦਾ ਹੈ (ਉਸ ਦੇ ਮਨ ਵਿਚ ਆਤਮਕ ਗੁਣਾਂ ਦਾ ਸਦਾ ਵਾਧਾ ਹੀ ਵਾਧਾ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ) ।੬।ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਮਿਲਦਾ ਹੈ ਤਾਂ ਆਪਣੀ ਮਿਹਰ ਨਾਲ ਹੀ ਮਿਲਦਾ ਹੈ, ਮਨੁੱਖ ਦੇ ਆਪਣੇ ਉਦਮ ਨਾਲ ਨਹੀਂ ਲਿਆ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ(ਇਸ ਵਾਸਤੇ, ਹੇ ਭਾਈ !) ਆਪਣੇ ਅੰਦਰੋਂ ਆਪਾ-ਭਾਵ ਦੂਰ ਕਰ ਕੇ ਗੁਰੂ ਦੇ ਚਰਨਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਟਿਕਿਆ ਰਹੁ (ਗੁਰ-ਸਰਨ ਦੀ ਬਰਕਤਿ ਨਾਲ ਜੇ) ਸਦਾ ਕਾਇਮ ਰਹਿਣ ਵਾਲੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੇ ਰੰਗ ਵਿਚ ਰੰਗੇ ਰਹੀਏ, ਤਾਂ ਉਹ ਸਦਾ-ਥਿਰ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਮਿਲ ਪੈਂਦਾ ਹੈ ।੭।(ਹੇ ਬਾਬਾ ! ਮਾਇਆ ਐਸੀ ਪ੍ਰਬਲ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਇਸ ਦੇ ਢਹੇ ਚੜ੍ਹ ਕੇ) ਹਰੇਕ ਜੀਵ ਗ਼ਲਤੀ ਖਾ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ, ਸਿਰਫ਼ ਗੁਰੂ ਹੈ ਤੇ ਕਰਤਾਰ ਹੈ ਜੋ (ਨਾਹ ਮਾਇਆ ਦੇ ਅਸਰ ਹੇਠ ਆਉਂਦਾ ਹੈ, ਤੇ) ਨਾਹ ਗ਼ਲਤੀ ਖਾਂਦਾ ਹੈਜਿਸ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਨੇ ਗੁਰੂ ਦੀ ਮਤਿ ਉੱਤੇ ਤੁਰ ਕੇ ਆਪਣੇ ਮਨ ਨੂੰ ਸਮਝ ਲਿਆ ਹੈ, ਉਸਦੇ ਅੰਦਰ (ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ) ਪ੍ਰੇਮ ਬਣ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ  ਹੇ ਨਾਨਕ ! ਜਿਸ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਨੂੰ ਗੁਰੂ ਦਾ ਸ਼ਬਦ ਅਪਾਰ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਮਿਲਾ ਦੇਂਦਾ ਹੈ ਉਸ ਨੂੰ ਉਹ ਸਦਾ-ਥਿਰ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਕਦੇ ਭੁੱਲਦਾ ਨਹੀਂ ।੮।੧੨।\\""},{"question":"Immsaa kujirta qur‘aanka kalimada barzakh? ama barzakhan oo alif ku taagan? mana badna ee la socdo.","answer":"3 jeer ayay ku jirtaa qur’aanka waxeyna ku kala jirtaa suuradahan so socda:    Suuratul Al-Raxmaan,    Suuratul Al-Mu’minuun,    Suuratul Al-Furqaan."},{"question":"एक ऐसी कहानी लिखें जिसमें एक बच्चा एक जादुई पेड़ की खोज में निकलता है और उसे अनदेखी सभी ख़ुशियाँ मिलती हैं।","answer":"रोहन को वह पेड़ बहुत ही खास लगा, जो रोज़ नई-नई ख़ुशियों का स्रोत था। जब उसने उसके नीचे बैठकर बिताये दिनों को अंदर देखा, तो वह जीवन की सच्ची मूलियों को समझने लगा।"},{"question":"لدينا السؤال التالي: من هو زعيم الغابة ؟ ، أجب عليه بطريقة مختصرة.","answer":"حسناً، الإجابة هي الأسد.الأسد حيوان من الثدييات من فصيلة السنوريات وأحد السنوريات الأربعة الكبيرة المنتمية لجنس النمور (باللاتينية: Panthera)، وهو يُعد ثاني أكبر السنوريات في العالم بعد الببر، حيث تفوق كتلة الذكور الكبيرة منه 250 كيلوغراما (550 رطلًا)."},{"question":"Complete a seguinte frase:  A bandeira da RSS Da Bielorrússia foi adotada em 25 de dezembro de 1951. Antes disso, a bandeira estava vermelha com os caracteres cirílicos BССР (BSSR) em ouro no canto superior esquerdo, cercado por uma borda de ouro. Entre 1937 e a adoção da bandeira acima na década de 1940, a bandeira era a mesma, mas com um martelo de ouro e uma foice acima dos caracteres cirílicos e nenhuma borda. Entre 1919 e 1937, a bandeira era vermelha, com os caracteres cirílicos ССРБ (SSRB) no canto superior esquerdo. No início de 1919, uma bandeira vermelha simples foi usada. A bandeira final foi usada até o","answer":"colapso da União Soviética em 1991"},{"question":"Isikan tempat kosong dengan jawapan yang sesuai. \\"Kalau ________ izinkan sekarang juga patik akan melaksanakan tugas itu,\\"sembah ahli nujum kepada sultan.","answer":"Jawapannya ialah tuanku."},{"question":"Iza ilay mpanakanto Meksikana malaza amin'ny sary hosodoko mampiseho ny tantara sy ny kolontsaina Meksikana?","answer":"Diego Rivera no Meksikana mpanakanto malaza amin'ny sary hosodoko."},{"question":"ශ්‍රී ලංකාවේ මුදල් නෝට්ටු මුද්‍රණය කරන සමාගම","answer":"De La Rue"},{"question":"Inona no dikan'ny hoe miasa ivelan'ny ora mahazatra?1-Miasa alina2-Miova asa3-Manao asa vonjimaika","answer":"Valiny: 2. Miova asa"},{"question":"化学式CaCO3で表される、真珠の主成分となっている物質は何でしょう？","answer":"炭酸カルシウムです。"},{"question":"次のパラグラフを続ける： 気象庁によると、とても暑い日がしばらく続きそうです。熱中症にならないように、水を飲んだり部屋を涼しくしたりして、気をつけてください。","answer":"気象庁は25日、8月から10月までの天気予報を発表しました。地球温暖化などのため、日本に暖かい空気が入りやすくなります。 8月から10月までの気温は、北日本と東日本ではいつもの年と同じか、高くなりそうです。西日本と沖縄・奄美ではいつもの年より高くなりそうです。 8月から10月までの雨は、西日本と東日本と北日本ではいつもの年と同じか、多くなりそうです。沖縄・奄美ではいつもの年と同じぐらいになりそうです。 気象庁は「暑い日が10月まで続きそうなので、体の具合に気をつけてください」と話しています。"},{"question":"السؤال: ما هو النصاب الشرعي لإخراج الزكاة من المال؟","answer":"الجواب: أن يبلغ المال 85 غرامًا من الذهب، وأن يحول عليه الحول."},{"question":"Fenoy ny banga: \\"_ dia tandindona kristiana fahiny maneho an'i Kristy sy ny mpianany.\\"","answer":"Valiny: Ny trondro dia tandindona kristiana fahiny maneho an'i Kristy sy ny mpianany."},{"question":"विश्वको जनसंख्या ७ अर्ब कहिले पुग्यो ?","answer":"बिश्वको जनसंख्या ७ अर्ब सन् २०११ अक्टोबर ११ मा पुग्यो ।"},{"question":"ਸੀਰੀਅਲ 'ਬਾਲਿਕਾ ਵਧੂ' ਅਤੇ ਅਦਾਕਾਰਾ ਆਨੰਦੀ ਬਾਰੇ ਦਸੋ।","answer":"ਪਿਛਲੇ ਸਾਲ ਦੌਰਾਨ ਛੋਟੇ ਪਰਦੇ ‘ਤੇ ਅਣਗਿਣਤ ਸੀਰੀਅਲ ਆਏ ਤੇ ਚਲੇ ਗਏ ਪਰ ਕਲਰਜ਼ ਚੈਨਲ ਦੀ ਸ਼ੁਰੂਆਤ ਨਾਲ ਸ਼ੁਰੂ ਹੋਏ ਸੀਰੀਅਲ 'ਬਾਲਿਕਾ ਵਧੂ' ਨੇ ਹਰ ਰੋਜ਼ ਨਵਾਂ ਮੁਕਾਮ ਹਾਸਲ ਕਰਦੇ 1000 ਐਪੀਸੋਡ ਪੂਰੇ ਕਰ ਲਏ। ਇਸ ਦੇ ਨਾਲ ਹੁਣ ਆਨੰਦੀ ਦੀ ਜ਼ਿੰਦਗੀ ਦਾ ਵੀ ਨਵਾਂ ਸਫ਼ਰ ਸ਼ੁਰੂ ਹੋਣ ਜਾ ਰਿਹਾ ਹੈ। ਆਨੰਦੀ ਦੀ ਜ਼ਿੰਦਗੀ ‘ਚ ਨਵਾਂ ਇਨਸਾਨ ਕਲੈਕਟਰ ਸ਼ਿਵਰਾਜ ਸ਼ੇਖਰ (ਸਿਧਾਰਥ ਸ਼ੁਕਲਾ) ਦਾ ਆਗਮਨ ਹੋਇਆ ਹੈ। ਇਸ ਦੇ ਨਾਲ ਹੀ ਜੈਤਸਰ ਜ਼ਿਲ੍ਹਾ ਬਣ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ।ਇਸ ਸੀਰੀਅਲ ਨੇ ਬਾਲ ਵਿਆਹ ਵਰਗੀ ਸਮਾਜਿਕ ਬੁਰਾਈ ਦੇ ਨਾਲ ਔਰਤਾਂ ਲਈ ਸਿੱਖਿਆ, ਵਿਧਵਾਵਾਂ ਦੇ ਪੁਨਰ ਵਿਆਹ ਜਿਹੇ ਬਹੁਤ ਹੀ ਸੰਜੀਦਾ ਅਤੇ ਗੰਭੀਰ ਵਿਸ਼ਿਆਂ ‘ਤੇ ਲੋਕਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਸੋਚਣ ਲਈ ਮਜਬੂਰ ਕੀਤਾ ਹੈ।ਜਦੋਂ ਜੈਤਸਰ ‘ਚ ਹੋ ਰਹੇ ਸਮਾਰੋਹ ਦੌਰਾਨ ਬੱਚੇ ਆਨੰਦੀ ਤੇ ਸ਼ਿਵ ਨੂੰ ਨਾਲ ਨੱਚਣ ਲਾ ਲੈਂਦੇ ਹਨ ਤਾਂ ਦਾਦੀ ਸੋਚਦੀ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਕਾਸ਼! ਇਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਦੀ ਜੋੜੀ ਬਣ ਜਾਵੇ। ਹੁਣ ਸਵਾਲ ਇਹ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਕੀ ਆਨੰਦੀ ਇਹ ਸਵੀਕਾਰ ਕਰੂਗੀ।ਆਨੰਦੀ ਨੇ ਆਪਣੇ ਹੁਣ ਤਕ ਦੇ ਸਫ਼ਰ ਦੌਰਾਨ ਅਨੇਕਾਂ ਚੁਣੌਤੀਆਂ ਦਾ ਸਾਹਮਣਾ ਕੀਤਾ ਹੈ ਤੇ ਹਰ ਚੁਣੌਤੀ ਤੋਂ ਬਾਅਦ ਉਹ ਹੋਰ ਮਜ਼ਬੂਤ ਬਣੀ ਹੈ। ਇਹ ਸੀਰੀਅਲ ਜ਼ਿੰਦਗੀ ਤੋਂ ਕਦੇ ਨਾ ਹਾਰਨ ਤੇ ਮੁਸ਼ਕਲਾਂ ਦਾ ਸਾਹਮਣਾ ਕਰਨ ਦੀ ਸਿੱਖਿਆ ਦਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ।ਓਧਰ ਇਸ ਸੀਰੀਅਲ ‘ਚ ਨਵੇਂ ਦਾਖਲ ਹੋਏ ਸਿਧਾਰਤ ਵੀ ਕਾਫ਼ੀ ਉਤਸੁਕ ਹਨ। ਉਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਦਾ ਕਹਿਣਾ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਭਾਵੇਂ ਮੈਂ ਇਸ ਸੀਰੀਅਲ ਨਾਲ ਬਹੁਤ ਦੇਰ ਬਾਅਦ ਜੁੜਿਆ ਹਾਂ ਪਰ ਆਪਣੇ ਕਿਰਦਾਰ ਨਾਲ ਨਿਆਂ ਕਰਨ ਦੀ ਪੂਰੀ ਕੋਸ਼ਿਸ਼ ਕਰਾਂਗਾ ਅਤੇ ਲੋਕ ਆਨੰਦੀ ਦੇ ਨਵੇਂ ਹਮਸਫ਼ਰ ਤੋਂ ਜੋ ਆਸ ਕਰਦੇ ਹਨ, ਮੈਂ ਉਨ੍ਹਾਂ ‘ਤੇ ਖਰਾ ਉਤਰਨ ਦੀ ਪੂਰੀ ਕੋਸ਼ਿਸ਼ ਕਰਾਂਗਾ।"},{"question":"Шта је потребно да се спакује за камповање?","answer":"У зависности од квалитета услуга и понуде кампа за који се пакујете највероватније ће вам бити потребни неки од следећих објеката: шатор, швајцарски нож, врећа за спавање, ћебе, јастук на надувавање, храна, пиће, лампа и компас."},{"question":"નક્ષત્ર એટલે શુ ?","answer":"નક્ષત્ર આકાશમાં તારાઓ નું કાલ્પનિક જુથ છે. ત્રણ પરીમાણમાં આવેલા આ તારાઓ વચ્ચે કોઇ સબંધ નથી પરંતુ, રાત્રીના અવકાશમાં તે એકમેક સાથે જુથમાં જોવા મળે છે. માનવી હંમેશા ઐતીહાસીક રીતે આવા કાલ્પનિક જુથની કલ્પનાઓ કરતો આવ્યો છે. આવા કાલ્પનિક જુથોને ખગોળ શાસ્ત્રીઓ  માન્યતા આપતા નથી. ખગોળ શાસ્ત્રને આધારે નક્ષત્રોના તારાઓ વચ્ચે પરસ્પર કોઈ સંબંધ નથી કેમકે, આ તારાઓ એક બીજાથી લાખો પ્રકાશવર્ષ દૂર હોય છે.જુદીજુદી સંસ્કૃતિઓમાં નક્ષત્રોના નામ તથા આકારો અલગ-અલગ હોય છે પણ કેટલાંક પ્રખ્યાત નક્ષત્રો જેમકે મૃગશીર્ષ નક્ષત્ર તથા વૃશ્ચીક નક્ષત્ર મોટાભાગની સંસ્કૃતિઓમાં ઓળખાયેલ છે."},{"question":"ऐतिहासिक काळात भारतावर पहिले आक्रमण कोणी केले ?","answer":"ऐतिहासिक काळात भारतावर पहिले आक्रमण राजा दारियसने केले."},{"question":"Lyle Lakay","answer":"Lyle Lakay (ti a bi ni ọjọ ketadinlogun oṣu Kẹjo ọdun 1991) jẹ agbabọọlu afẹsẹgba orilẹ-ede South Africa ti oun gba bọọlu afẹsẹgba fun Mamelodi Sundowns ni Ajumọṣe Bọọlu afẹsẹgba Premier .O jẹ ọmo ti ile-ẹkọ ọdọ SuperSport United, o ni igbega si ẹgbẹ agbabọọlu akọkọ ni 2009 ṣugbọn o lo akoko re ni ọdun 2009–10 pẹlu National First Division fun ẹgbẹ agbabọọlu FC Cape Town . Fun akoko 2010–11 o pada si Supersport United. Lẹhin ọrọ ayalo miiran pẹlu FC Cape Town, Lakay darapọ mọ Bloemfontein Celtic ni ọdun 2012. O nireti lati forukọsilẹ fun ẹgbẹ inawo nla ti Pretoria, Mamelodi Sundowns FC lakoko window gbigbe Oṣu Kini ọdun 2014. Ni ọjọ 14 Oṣu kọkanla ọdun 2013, agbabọọlu naa ti sọ pe, “Bẹẹni, Mo de loni ni Tshwane, ṣugbọn Emi yoo bẹrẹ ikẹkọ pẹlu Sundowns ni ọla (Friday). Mo nireti pe ohun gbogbo yoo dara. ”Ni 2011, wọn pe si ẹgbẹ agbabọọlu to orilẹ-ede South Africa U-20 fun 2011 African Youth Championship ."},{"question":"අපි කතා බහේදි කියන්නෙ \\"මමත් ගන්නව දවසක සුපිරි වන්ඩියක්\\" කියන එකේ වාහනයක් කියන එක අරුත්ගන්වන්න භාවිත කරන \\"වන්ඩිය\\" කියන වචනය සිංහල වචනයක්ද? කොහින් ආපු වචනයක්ද?","answer":"வண்டி (වණ්ඩි) -වාහනය කියන දෙමළ වචනය ඍණීකරණය වීමක් නැතොත් වාග්විද්‍යාවට අනුව ණයට ගැනීමක්.එසේ ආ තව බොහෝ වචන ඇත.සෙරුප්පු,මට්ටු,හෙට්ටු,පොට්ටු,විලක්කු,සමයම්,පාරාට්ටු තව තියෙනවා  ගොඩාක්"},{"question":"वैज्ञानिक विधिको व्याख्या गर्नुहोस्।","answer":"वैज्ञानिक विधि अनुसन्धानको लागि एक व्यवस्थित दृष्टिकोण हो, जसमा अवलोकन, परिकल्पना सूत्रीकरण, प्रयोग, डेटा विश्लेषण, र निष्कर्ष रेखाचित्र समावेश छ।"},{"question":"Sọ fúnmi nípa Yàkúbù Gowon.","answer":"Yàkúbù tí àpèjẹ́ rẹ̀ ń jẹ́ Jack Dan-Yumma Gowon ni wọ́n bí ní ọjọ́ kọkàndínlógún oṣù Ọ̀wàrà, ọdún 1934. Ó jẹ́ ọmọ orílẹ̀-èdè Nàìjíríà láti apá Àríwá. Gowon jẹ́ Ọ̀gágun ní Ilé-iṣẹ́ Ológun ilẹ̀ Nàìjíríà, bẹ́ẹ̀ ni ó sì tún jẹ̀ olórí orílẹ̀-èdè Nàìjíríà láti ọdún 1966 dé 1971. Lásìkò ìjọba rẹ̀ náà ni ilẹ̀ Nàìjíríà ja ogun abẹ́lé láti 1966 sí 1971, lábẹ́ Ọ̀gágun Odumegwu Ojukwu tí ó fẹ́ gba òmìnira lọ́wọ́ ilẹ̀ Nàìjíríà."},{"question":"Inona no loko vokatry ny fampifangaroana mavo sy mena?a) Mavokelyb) volomboasaryd) volomparasye) Maitso","answer":"b) volomboasary no loko vokatry ny fampifangaroana mavo sy mena"},{"question":"નિબંધ - વડાપ્રધાન નરેન્દ્ર મોદી PM - Modi","answer":"આજે જ્યારે રાજનીતિમાં ચારેબાજુ પરિવારવાદની બોલબાલા છે. રાજકારણીય પરિવારમાં વિવાદના સમાચાર સતત ચર્ચામાં છે. આવામાં ગુજરાતમાં રહેનારા પ્રધાનમંત્રી નરેન્દ્ર મોદીના પરિવાર પર એક નજર નાખવી જરૂરી છે. રાજનીતિના વર્તમાન સમયમાં તમને મોદી પરિવારની સ્ટોરી ખૂબ રસપ્રદ લાગશે. તમને એ જાણીને નવાઈ લાગશે કે પ્રધાનમંત્રી મોદીના ભાઈ-ભત્રીજા અને પરિવારના બીજા સભ્ય તેમની ઊંચા મહત્વથી દૂર લગભગ અજાણી જીંદગી જીવી રહ્યા છે.  "},{"question":"ചോദ്യം: കേരളത്തിലെ നെൽകർഷകർ നേരിടുന്ന പ്രധാന വെല്ലുവിളികൾ എന്തൊക്കെയാണ്?","answer":"ഉത്തരം: കേരളത്തിലെ നെൽകർഷകർ തൊഴിലാളികളുടെ ക്ഷാമം, ഉൽപ്പാദനച്ചെലവ് വർദ്ധിക്കുന്നത്, കാലാവസ്ഥാ വ്യതിയാനത്തിന്റെ ആഘാതം, ഇറക്കുമതി ചെയ്ത അരിയിൽ നിന്നുള്ള മത്സരം തുടങ്ങിയ വെല്ലുവിളികൾ നേരിടുന്നു."},{"question":"కింది ప్రశ్నకు సమాధానం ఇవ్వండిఒక కణం సజీవకణంగా పిలువబడడానికి దానిలో ఏ నిర్మాణాత్మక, క్రియాత్మక గుణాలు ఉండాలి?","answer":"1. ‘కణం’ జీవి యొక్క నిర్మాణాత్మక మరియు క్రియాత్మక ప్రమాణం.2. కేంద్రకం కలిగిన కణాన్ని ‘జీవకణం’ అంటారు. కేంద్రకం లేనటువంటి కణాన్ని ‘జీవంలేని’ లేదా చనిపోయిన కణం అంటారు.3. ‘కేంద్రకం’ కణం యొక్క ‘కణమెదడు’. ఇది అన్ని కణాంగాల విధులను నియంత్రిస్తుంది.4. కేంద్రకంలోని క్రోమోసోమ్లు జన్యువులను కలిగి ఉంటాయి. కావున కేంద్రకం అనువంశికతలో పాల్గొంటుంది.5. ‘కేంద్రకం’ ఏకకణ జీవులలో కణవిభజన మరియు ప్రత్యుత్పత్తిలో ముఖ్యపాత్రను పోషిస్తుంది.6. కణం యొక్క ద్రవయుత మాత్రికను కణజీవపదార్ధం అంటారు. జీవకణం యొక్క జీవపదార్ధంలో అనేక జీవక్రియలు జరుగుతాయి.7. కణాలు శక్తినిత్యత్వనియమాలను పాటిస్తాయి. కావున అవి శక్తిని బదిలీ చేస్తాయి.8. కణం స్వయం ప్రతిపత్తిని కలిగిన కేంద్రకామ్లాలను, రైబోసోమ్లను కలిగి ఉంటుంది.9. కణం యొక్క ద్రవాభిసరణత ‘రిక్తికలు మరియు నాళికల ద్వారా’ నియంత్రించబడుతుంది.10. గ్లైకోప్రోటీన్ల ద్వారా కణాలు సమాచారాన్ని చేరవేస్తాయి.11. కణాలు సైక్లోసిస్ ద్వారా యానిమేషన్ ను చూపుతాయి.12. కణాలు పెరిగి, విభజన చెంది, విభేదించబడి చివరికి చనిపోతాయి."},{"question":"Zaza dili mi eski Kürtçe mi?","answer":"Müller çalışmasında Zazaca'yı Farsça'nın bir lehçesi olarak değerlendirmekle birlikte Zazacanın Kürtçe ve Farsçadan daha eski olduğunu ve tarihsel gelişim bakımından Zazacanın Kürtçe ve Farsçadan farklı olduğunu tespit etmiştir."},{"question":"खालील म्हणीचा सोप्या शब्दात अर्थ सांगा  आपलेच दात आपलेच ओठ","answer":"आपल्याच माणसाने चूक केल्यावर अडचणीचे स्थिती निर्माण होणे."},{"question":"மொழிபெயர்ப்பு It is during our darkest moments that we must focus to see the light. ","answer":"நம் இருண்ட தருணங்களிலும் ஒளியைப் பார்ப்பதையே நோக்கமாகக் கொள்ள வேண்டும்"},{"question":"కింది సమాస పదాలకు విగ్రహవాక్యాలు రాసి, సమాసం పేరు రాయండి.ఉదా :సంఘసంస్కర్తలు – సంఘమును సంస్కరించేవారు – ద్వితీయా తత్పురుషంఅ) వరకట్నంఆ) స్త్రీల అభ్యున్నతిఇ) విద్యావిహీనతఈ) విద్యావ్యాప్తిఉ) ధనవ్యయంఊ) శక్తిహీనుడు","answer":"అ) వరకట్నం = వరుని కొరకు కట్నం – చతుర్డీ తత్పురుషంఆ) స్త్రీల అభ్యున్నతి = స్త్రీల యొక్క అభ్యున్నతి – షష్ఠీ తత్పురుషంఇ) విద్యావిహీనత = విద్యచేత విహీనత – తృతీయా తత్పురుషంఈ) విద్యావ్యాప్తి = విద్య యొక్క వ్యాప్తి – షష్ఠీ తత్పురుషంఉ) ధనవ్యయం = ధనము యొక్క వ్యయం – షష్ఠీ తత్పురుషంఊ) శక్తిహీనుడు = శక్తిచేత హీనుడు – తృతీయా తత్పురుషం"},{"question":"Para resumir: ¿El hábito de comer hierba entre nuestras mascotas se debe a problemas de salud?¿Cuántas veces me habrán preguntado por qué comen hierba, a veces para vomitar unos minutos más tarde? Un falso mito dice que lo hacen para purgarse, pero no es así. ¿O acaso sus mascotas siempre vomitan después de comerla? ¿Y por qué no suelen mostrar síntomas de encontrarse mal antes? Simplemente, porque la purga no siempre es una explicación válida.Final de Quizás también te intereseVeamos qué se sabe realmente sobre por qué perros y gatos comen plantas y si es bueno o no permitirlo. Empezaré por los gatos.Un hábito común La mayoría de los dueños de gatos (si es que alguien es verdaderamente capaz de adueñarse de un animal tan independiente) te dirán que si Micifúz zampa un poco de hierba y luego vomita, es que está teniendo problemas estomacales y lo hace para purgarse. Eso no es necesariamente cierto. En realidad, los gatos, esas mascotas tan sigilosas a las que nunca vemos satisfacer sus necesidades fisiológicas, comen hierba todo el tiempo. El hábito de comer hierba entre gatos y perros es extremadamente común, dicen los expertos.Sus dueños solo se dan cuenta de esa práctica cuando encuentran vómitos verduzcos en el suelo.Investigadores de la Facultad de Veterinaria de la Universidad de California en Davis (EE.UU.) prepararon un trabajo de investigación cuyo protocolo consistía en que más de mil dueños de gatos (el único requisito era que los felinos tuvieran acceso a un jardín) pasaran al menos tres horas al día observando el comportamiento de su mascota. Como muchos propietarios de felinos sospechaban, comer hierba es un hábito extremadamente común: el 71% de los animales lo hicieron al menos seis veces en el período de observación y el 61% más de diez veces. Solo un 11% nos mostró prácticas vegetarianas.Mientras que el 39% de los gatos jóvenes (tres años o menos) comía plantas todos los días. ","answer":"Los gatos y los perros comen pasto cuando se sienten mal y así lo vomitan. "},{"question":"Ìjàn Èkìtì","answer":"Ìjàn Èkìtì jẹ́ ìlú ńlá kan tí ó wà ní Ìpínlẹ̀ Èkìtì ní orílẹ̀-èdè Nàìjíríà. Iye àwọn olùgbé ibẹ̀ jẹ́ ọmọ Yorùbá àtàtà tí wọ́n sì yan iṣẹ́ àgbẹ̀ láàyò gẹ́gẹ́ bí iṣẹ́ òòjọ́ wọn tí wọ́n sì ń gbin àwọn ohun ọ̀gbìn bíi: Ìrẹsì ,Ẹ̀gẹ́ , Iṣu , tábà, òwú àti bẹ́ẹ̀ bẹ́ẹ̀ lọ, bá kan náà ni wọ́n yan iṣẹ́ aṣọ híhun láàyò. Gẹ́gẹ́ bí ètò ìkànìyàn ọdún 2004 ṣe fi léde, iye àwọn olùgbé ìlú Ìjàn jẹ́ 46,749 lápapọ̀. Orúkọ adarí tàbí Ọba wọn ní Ìlú ìjàn Èkìtì ni Oníjàn ti Ìjàn Èkìtì."},{"question":"Qual é o processo pelo qual as plantas perdem água na forma de vapor através de pequenos poros em suas folhas?","answer":"Esse processo é chamado de transpiração. A transpiração é uma parte importante do ciclo da água nas plantas."},{"question":"Hoàn thiện đoạn văn sau với nội dung có liên quan tới đoạn văn dưới đây: Tôi và Khánh hẹn hò được hơn 7 tháng thì anh ngỏ lời cầu hôn tôi. Anh là một người hiền lành, tâm lý và đặc biệt rất hiểu tôi. Chuyện tình cảm của chúng tôi đều được gia đình hai bên ủng hộ nên chẳng có lý do gì mà tôi từ chối cả. Những ngày sát cưới, Khánh càng khiến tôi cảm thấy hài lòng, hạnh phúc vì anh rất có trách nhiệm và luôn tôn trọng suy nghĩ của tôi. Vì vậy, tôi cảm thấy bản thân thật may mắn khi lấy được người chồng như anh. Tuy nhiên, trước hôm cưới 3 ngày, chuyện bất ngờ đã xảy ra. Hôm đó, tôi cùng Khánh hẹn nhau tới studio thử váy cưới, nhưng sáng hôm đó Khánh lại bận việc, nói tôi đến trước, anh sẽ tới sau. Tôi tới thử váy cưới được một lúc thì có tin nhắn từ số lạ gửi tới. Tò mò mở ra xem, tôi sững người khi thấy loạt ảnh giường chiếu của Khánh với một cô gái lạ mặt. Cô ta tự xưng là người yêu của Khánh rồi nhắn: \\"Trước khi ở bên chị, anh Khánh đã yêu em thắm thiết như vậy đó. Chị thấy quá khứ của anh Khánh và em có ngọt ngào, cuồng nhiệt không? Dù giờ chị sắp lấy anh Khánh nhưng chắc chắn anh ấy sẽ không bao giờ quên được đoạn quá khứ nồng cháy đó đâu\\". Sau đó, cô ta còn gửi ảnh chồng tương lai của tôi và ả đang ngồi với nhau. \\"Sáng nay chị đi thử váy cưới một mình vì anh Khánh nói bận công việc đúng không? Anh ấy chẳng bận việc gì cả, anh ấy đi hẹn hò với em đấy. Chị thấy không, ngay cả khi 2 người sắp cưới thì anh ấy vẫn không thể quên em được. Vậy mà chị còn cố tình lấy anh ấy thì chị đúng là ngu dốt đấy. Chị lấy anh Khánh về cũng chẳng được anh ấy yêu thương đâu, cả đời này sống dưới cái bóng của em","answer":"thôi chị ạ\\", ả ta nhắn. Tôi tức tới tím tái mặt mày, định gọi điện cho anh Khánh hỏi cho ra nhẽ, nhưng đúng lúc này thì Khánh phi xe tới. Nhìn bộ đồ anh đang mặc, giống hệt với bộ đồ người đàn ông trong bức ảnh, chứng tỏ anh ấy vừa đi gặp tình cũ thật. Tôi liền lao tới chỗ anh, đưa toàn bộ tin nhắn của cô gái kia cho Khánh xem, yêu cầu anh giải thích. Tuy nhiên, anh Khánh lại không hề lúng túng, bảo tôi hạ hỏa ngồi xuống từ từ nghe anh nói: - Cô ta đúng là tình cũ của anh thật, xin lỗi vì anh không nói thật với em ngay từ đầu. Anh cứ nghĩ mình có thể tự giải quyết được nên không muốn nói với em, sợ em nghĩ nhiều, nào ngờ chuyện lại đến mức này. Chẳng là thời gian gần đây cô gái kia liên tục nhắn tin, gọi điện cho anh muốn nối lại tình xưa, nhưng anh không đồng ý. Cô ta bèn mang số ảnh nóng đó ra uy hiếp anh nên anh nghĩ cần gặp nhau lần cuối để giải quyết dứt khoát mọi việc. Cho nên sáng nay anh mới đi gặp cô ta, bảo cô ta thích làm gì với chỗ ảnh kia thì tùy, cũng mong cô ta sau này đừng làm phiền tới cuộc sống của anh và em nữa. Anh giấu em là anh không đúng, nhưng anh mong em có thể hiểu và tin tưởng anh. Qúa khứ đã là quá khứ, anh giờ chỉ cần mình em thôi. Em tin anh được không? Thấy thái độ thành khẩn của Khánh, hơn nữa đúng là thời gian qua anh không hề nhăng nhít bên ngoài, bạn bè, kể cả bạn thân khác giới của anh tôi đều biết hết, nên tôi chọn tin tưởng anh. Vậy là tôi nhắn tin lại cho ả: - Qúa khứ của em và chồng chị rực rỡ quá. Nhưng mà có đẹp đến mấy cũng chỉ là quá khứ, giờ em lôi mấy tấm ảnh cũ rích này ra khoe chị làm gì vậy? Cách hành xử của em cũng làm chị hiểu tại sao năm xưa anh Khánh lại bỏ em rồi. Em trơ trẽn mất phần thiên hạ thế cơ mà. Chị khuyên thật, em cũng đừng nghĩ tới chuyện mang mấy tấm ảnh này \\"bóc phốt\\" trên mạng làm gì, chỉ làm xấu mặt em thôi. Tuy nhiên, tôi cũng quay sang Khánh nói rõ ràng với anh: \\"Em tin anh thì sau này anh đừng phụ lòng tin của em\\". Sau đó, đám cưới của tôi và Khánh đã diễn ra suôn sẻ. Đến giờ đã 5 năm trôi qua, Khánh vẫn là người chồng tốt của tôi. Chúng tôi đã có với nhau một bé gái, mỗi ngày đi làm về anh đều giúp tôi làm việc nhà, chăm sóc con, chẳng nề hà bất cứ việc gì cả. Tôi rất hạnh phúc khi có một người chồng như vậy."},{"question":"Apakah air ampuh?","answer":"Air yang membanjiri sesuatu kawasan"},{"question":"வினா : உலகிலேயே  ஆழமான அகழி எது?","answer":"விடை: மரியானா அகழி.புவிமேலோட்டில் உள்ள மிகத் தாழ்வான பகுதி."},{"question":"Nisy inona teto Madagasikara ny 4 septambra 1996?","answer":"Ny 4 septambra 1996 dia voaongan’ny roa ampahatelon’ny Antenimierampirenena i Zafy Albert, ka ny Praiministra Norbert Lala Ratsirahonana no lasa filoham-panjakana vonjimaika. Nanangana governemanta hikarakara fifidianana izy ka tamin’ny 2 novambra 1996 nonotanterahana ny fifidianana filohan’ny Repoblika; 15 no isan’ny kandidà tamin’izany; i Didier Ratsiraka no nivoaka ho mpandresy. Ho an’ny mpandinika dia anisan’ireo olana namotika ny fitondrana Zafy Albert ny faniriany hametraka ny UNDD ho antoko matanjaka, ny havitsin’ny vokatra azo tamin’ny fanalalahana (libéralisation), ny fitsingevanana (stagnation) ara-toekarena, sns. "},{"question":"Кыргыз накыл кептери англис тилинде жазып бере аласыңбы?","answer":"Curses like chickens come home to roost – Бирөөгө ор казба, өзүң түшөсүң."},{"question":" Sheeg Magaca Qoraalkaay Isticmaalaan Indhoolayaasha","answer":" Waxaa Loo-Yaqaanaa Pareel."},{"question":"إذا تضاعفت كتلة الأرض فإن تسارع الجاذبية:(أ) ينقص للنصف (ب) ينقص للربع(ج) يتضاعف (د) لا يتغير","answer":"الإجابة الصحيحة (ج)"},{"question":"Aiza ny \\"Tour Eiffel\\" ?","answer":"Ny \\"Tour Eiffel\\" Tanànan'i Frantsa."},{"question":"जम्मू काश्मीर मध्ये 370 हे कलम केव्हा हटवले?","answer":"उत्तर : जम्मू काश्मीर मध्ये 370 हे कलम 5-8-2019 हटवले ."},{"question":"Ci ban kembaar la réwum Centre africique nékk","answer":"Réwum Centre afrique mu ngi nékk ci kembaar bi ñuy wax Afrique "},{"question":"Completa la siguiente frase : Di María fue una suplente no utilizada cuando el Real Madrid ganó la... ","answer":"Liga de Campeones de la UEFA 2013-2014. Una semana después, en el partido de ida de la Supercopa de España, jugó los últimos 15 minutos del empate 1-1 en casa contra el Atlético de Madrid en lugar de Luka Modrić, en el cual fue su última aparición como jugador del Real Madrid. El 22 de agosto fue revelado que Di María no fue incluido en la convocatoria para la vuelta de la Supercopa, con el entrenador del equipo, Ancelotti, revelando que el jugador pidió ser vendido durante el verano."},{"question":"Wat voor belangrijke gebeurtenis beschrijft de tekst: De toeren door het Verenigd Koninkrijk der Nederlanden moesten eerder dan gepland worden stilgelegd omdat Anna zwanger was. Schoonvader Willem I had ondertussen Paleis Kneuterdijk gekocht voor het paar, waar ze kort daarna hun intrek namen. In de winter werd besloten om naar het voor hen gebouwde paleis, het huidige Academiënpaleis in Brussel te gaan. Anna verbleef hier het liefst, want Brussel had meer pracht en praal dan het noorden; maar op wens van Willem I wisselden ze hun verblijf af met paleizen in het noorden. Zo verbleven ze 's zomers ook afwisselend op paleis Tervuren en op Paleis Soestdijk, dat Willem ontvangen had als nationaal cadeau voor zijn optreden bij Quatre-Bras en Waterloo in de strijd tegen Napoleon. Tot de afscheiding van de Zuidelijke Nederlanden in 1830 woonde het kroonprinselijk paar voornamelijk afwisselend in 's-Gravenhage en Brussel.","answer":"Het gaat over de afscheiding van de Zuidelijke Nederlanden."},{"question":"Ọlọpaa n wa awọn agbebọn to pa pasitọ sinu igbo l’Ekiti","answer":"Ibẹrubojo ti ba awọn eeyan ipinlẹ Ekiti bayii lori iṣẹlẹ ijinigbe ati ipaniyan to fẹẹ maa di nnkan ojoojumọ bayiii pẹlu bi awọn kan ṣe tun pa Pasitọ Kayọde Ogunlẹyẹ sinu igbo.Oloogbe naa ni ALAROYE gbọ pe wọn deede pa sinu igbo kan to wa lọna Aramọkọ-Ekiti si Ijero-Ekiti, lasiko to lọ soko lati ka ọgẹdẹ.Pasitọ Ogunlẹyẹ to jẹ alufaa nileejọsin All Christian Fellowship la gbọ pe awọn eeyan deede ba ninu igbo naa ti ẹjẹ bo o, bẹẹ ni awọn apa to wa lara ẹ fi han pe wọn yinbọn pa a ni.Eyi lo jẹ kawọn eeyan bẹrẹ si i pariwo pe ọrọ eto aabo ipinlẹ Ekiti ti mẹhẹ nitori iṣẹlẹ naa waye lẹyin ọjọ kan pere tawọn adigunjale kọlu banki kan niluu Iyin-Ekiti, bẹẹ ileeṣẹ ọlọpaa gan-an ti kọkọ kede pe awọn ọdaran kan ti wọ ipinlẹ naa.Pasitọ tawọn agbebọn pa yii tun jẹ oṣiṣẹ ijọba ibilẹ Iwọ-Oorun Ekiti kọlọjọ too de, awọn Fulani darandaran lọpọ awọn to wa lagbegbe naa si gba pe wọn ṣeku pa a.Nigba to n ba wa sọrọ lori iṣẹlẹ naa, Alukoro ọlọpaa Ekiti, ASP Sunday Abutu, sọ pe iwadii ti bẹrẹ lati mọ awọn to ṣiṣẹ laabi ọhun nitori awọn agbofinro gba pe wọn pa a ni."},{"question":"මාළු බිත්තර දමයිද?","answer":"ඔව්. එහෙත් මසුන්ගේ ප්‍රජනන ක්‍රම විවිධ වේ, නමුත් බොහෝ මසුන් කුඩා බිත්තර විශාල ප්‍රමාණයක් දමයි, සංසේචනය කර ශරීරයෙන් පිටත විසිරී ඇත. පෙලැජික් මසුන්ගේ බිත්තර සාමාන්‍යයෙන් විවෘත ජලයේ අත්හිටුවා ඇත. බොහෝ වෙරළ සහ මිරිදිය මත්ස්‍යයන් පතුලේ හෝ ශාක අතර බිත්තර දමයි. සමහරුන්ට මැලියම් බිත්තර ඇත."},{"question":"வினா : தமிழ்த்தாய் சிலை எந்த ஊரில் நிறுவிப்பட உள்ளது?A. தூத்துக்குடிB. திருச்சிC. மதுரைD. தஞ்சாவூர்","answer":"விடை :  C. மதுரை"},{"question":"How does Colombo's public transportation system contribute to its accessibility and connectivity for residents and visitors?","answer":"Colombo's public transportation system is a cornerstone of the city's accessibility and connectivity. The network of buses and trains provides affordable and efficient options for daily commuters, reducing traffic congestion. Investments in infrastructure, like the Colombo Light Rail Transit system, showcase the city's commitment to enhancing transportation, making it more convenient for residents and visitors to navigate the urban landscape."},{"question":"Slutför den här frasen: Organisation for the Maintenance of Supplies (OMS) var en högerrörelse i Storbritannien grundad 1925 för att tillgodo se behovet av bland annat strejkbrytare i händelse av en generalstrejk. Under generalstrejken 1926","answer":"övertogs OMS av den brittiska staten och organisationens resurser användes för att service som bland annat transport och kommunikation skulle fortsätta fungera."},{"question":" \\"Ny fomban-drazana nolalovan'ny taranaka dia mety hahatsapa ho voafetra ihany, kanefa izy ireo koa dia manome fahatsapana fitohizan-dàlana sy lova.\\" inona ny fihetseham-po tamin'ny fanambarana teo aloha?","answer":"Ny andian-teny dia mampifangaro ny fihetseham-po ratsy amin'ny fahatsapana voafetra miaraka amin'ny fihetseham-po tsara amin'ny fitohizan'ny kolontsaina."},{"question":"O kogo chodzi?Urodził się 17 stycznia 1706 w Bostonie jako dziesiąty syn z siedemnaściorga dzieci. Jego ojcem był niezamożny wytwórca świec i mydła Josiah Franklin. Amerykański polityk, drukarz, uczony, filozof i wolnomularz; jeden z ojców założycieli Stanów Zjednoczonych.","answer":"Odpowiedź to: Benjamin Franklin."},{"question":"Kodi mwana wa Mulungu ndani?","answer":"Chiphunzitso cha Utatu chimadziŵikitsa Yesu kukhala Mulungu Mwana, wofanana kwenikweni koma wosiyana ndi munthu ponena za Mulungu Atate ndi Mulungu Mzimu Woyera (Munthu Woyamba ndi Wachitatu wa Utatu)."},{"question":"السؤال: من هو الخليفة الراشدي الذي أمر بجمع القرآن الكريم في نسخة واحدة؟","answer":"الجواب: أبو بكر الصديق."},{"question":"Sheeg Maxaal La Oran Jiray Ninkii Dilay Cali Bin Abii Daalib?","answer":"Waxa La Oran Jiray Ninkii Dilay Cali Bin Abii Daalib C/Raxmaan Bin Muljan"},{"question":"Căn hộ được thiết kế khá hợp lý, giá cả cũng phù hợp với khả năng tài chính của gia đình tôi. Tòa chung cư cao 40 tầng, số lượng căn hộ tương đối lớn, cộng đồng cư dân đông đúc, tiện ích đầy đủ.Tôi thấy ở tầng cao có điểm lợi là được hưởng không khí trong lành, ngắm cảnh đẹp, không bị ảnh hưởng bởi tiếng ồn. Tuy nhiên, người nhà tôi không đồng ý mua và cho rằng căn hộ ở vị trí này sẽ rất nóng vào mùa hè, bất tiện khi chờ thang máy, chưa kể rủi ro khi xảy ra cháy nổ.Sau khi bàn bạc, gia đình tôi vẫn chưa tìm được tiếng nói chung. Mong các chuyên gia và độc giả tư vấn giúp, tôi có nên mua căn hộ và giải pháp khắc phục các nhược điểm kể trên?","answer":"Em và vợ hiện đang ở căn hộ áp mái ở TPHCM (Chung cư em 19 tầng, em ở tầng 19) sau đây là các điểm cộng và trừ em chia sẻ với gia đình anh ạ:*Ưu điểm:- Trần cao hơn các căn hộ cùng mã căn (Cụ thể các căn chung cư em trần 2.8m, riêng căn áp mái của em ở là 3.5m, thiết kế trừ đi 0.4m để làm trần, còn lại 3.1m vẫn rất cao thoáng so với các căn cùng chung cư)- Thiết kế rèm thẩm mĩ hơn, như ở trên đã nói thì anh sẽ thiết kế rèm cửa giấu thanh rèm khá là đẹp, các căn khác thì sẽ lộ thanh kéo rèm do thiết kế trần.- Tầm nhìn thông thoáng: View hướng lên của căn áp mái sẽ thoáng hơn vì không vướn các căn khác- Hạn chế được tiếng ồn hơn: Vì bên trên không có căn hộ khác, độ cao cao hơn nên giảm được tiếng xe cộ di chuyển.*Nhược điểm:- Vì là tầng cao nhất nên đi thang máy sẽ lâu hơn- Nước chảy yếu, áp lực không đủ mạnh, nước chảy yếu hơn so với các căn khác* Tầng em ở không hề nóng, vì thiết kế trần nhà cao hơn và xây dựng trần áp mái cũng rất dày nên không cảm nhận được độ nóng đâu ạ!Thân chúc gia đình anh tìm được tiếng nói chung!"},{"question":"Inona ary izany: ilay boka mitaingin-tseza?","answer":"Ny valiny dia mananasy."},{"question":"« Ataoko mihinana ny tsy fihinana eo ialahy fa ataovy ihany .» Inona no fihetseham-po fonosin’io fanambarana eo ambony io ?","answer":"Io fanambarana io dia maneho fihetseham-po miiba satria hatezerana."},{"question":"Hãy tiếp tục đoạn văn sau: Với sự phát triển ngày càng tăng, AI đang được chính phủ nhiều nước đưa vào tầm kiểm soát. Để đối phó với nhiều tình huống, các công ty AI đã mở mô hình để hacker có thể tấn công. Sự kiện bảo mật Defcon ở Las Vegas tháng trước được xem là cuộc tập trận cho các red team AI. Tám công ty bao gồm OpenAI, ","answer":"Google, Meta, Nvidia, Stability AI và Anthropic đã \\"mở cửa\\" mô hình AI để hơn 2.000 hacker tấn công nhằm tìm ra lỗ hổng bảo mật. Đổi lại, hacker sẽ nhận được một khoản tiền nhất định tùy vào mức độ nghiêm trọng của lỗ hổng. Trong 8 mô hình kể trên, hacker đã tìm thấy khoảng 2.700 sai sót."},{"question":"வினா:  'நீ எவ்வளவு அழகாக இருக்கிறாய்!!' இது எவ்வகை வாக்கியம்?","answer":"விடை :  இது உணர்ச்சி வாக்கியம்.   "},{"question":"महाभारतात किती श्लोक आहेत?उत्तर ","answer":"एक लाख शत सहस्र"},{"question":"Iza no tena anaran'i Dox ?","answer":"Ny tena anaran'i Dox dia Jean Verdi Salomon RAZAKANDRAINA."},{"question":" \\"Ny fandanjalanjana ny habaka manokana sy ny fotoana kalitao miaraka amin'ny sipako dia ahafahantsika mitazona fifandraisana mahasalama sy mahomby.\\" inona ny fihetseham-po tamin'ny fanambarana teo aloha?","answer":"Ny andian-teny dia manondro fihetseham-po tsara amin'ny alàlan'ny fanekena ny maha-zava-dehibe ny fitadiavana fifandanjana eo amin'ny sehatra manokana sy ny fotoana ifampizarana ho an'ny fifandraisana mahasalama."},{"question":"Συμπλήρωσε την πρόταση:  Μέρος του οικιστικού αποθέματος καταστράφηκε και πάλι σχετικά πρόσφατα, με τις","answer":"πυρκαγιές του 2007."},{"question":"Terjemahkanlah penggalan teks Bahasa Inggris yang disadur dari kumpulan cerita anak dunia berikut ke dalam teks Bahasa Indonesia.Bountong has a new hat. He made it himself.Terjemahan:","answer":"Terjemahan dari \\"Bountong has a new hat. He made it himself.\\" dalam Bahasa Indonesia adalah:Bountong mempunyai topi baru. Dia sendiri yang membuat topi tersebut."},{"question":"ਬਿਆਸ ਦੀਆਂ ਸਹਾਇਕ ਨਦੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਨਾਮ ਲਿਖੋ ।","answer":"ਪਾਰਵਤੀ, ਸੁਕੰਤਰੀ, ਮੌਹਾਂ, ਉਗਮਨ ਅਤੇ ਕਾਲੀ ਵੇਈਂ ।"},{"question":"Chidinma ti wọn lo pa baba alaaanu rẹ loun o jẹbi, ile-ẹjọ ti da a pada sẹwọn","answer":"Ile-ẹjọ giga ipinlẹ Eko ti paṣẹ pe ki wọn da afurasi ọdaran akẹkọọ Fasiti Eko, ẹni ọdun mejilelogun nni, Chidinma Ojukwu, ti wọn fẹsun kan pe oun lo ṣekupa Ọga agba ileeṣẹ tẹlifiṣan Super TV, Ọgbẹni Usifo Ataga, lọjọsi, pada satimọle, latari bo ṣe sẹ kanlẹ pe oun o jẹbi ẹsun naa.Ọjọ Iṣẹgun, Tusidee yii, ni wọn wọ Chidinma lọ sile-ẹjọ giga ọhun to wa lagbegbe Tafawa Balewa Square, l’Erekuṣu Eko, nipinlẹ Eko, ẹsun mẹjọ ni wọn ka si i lẹsẹ, lara rẹ da lori iṣikapaniyan, lilu jibiti, ole jija ati igbimọpọ lati huwa ibi.Yatọ si Chidinma, awọn meji mi-in ti wọn jọ kawọ pọyin rojọ niwaju Adajọ Yetunde Adesanya ni kootu ọhun ni aburo Chidinma, Chioma Egbuchu, ti wọn fẹsun kan pe wọn ba ẹru ole lọwọ ẹ, wọn loun ni wọn ka iPhone 7 to jẹ ti oloogbe naa mọ lọwọ, ati Ọgbẹni Quadri Adedapọ, ti wọn loun naa lọwọ ninu ṣiṣekupa Ataga.Chioma ni tiẹ loun o jẹbi ẹsun rira ọja ole, o loun kọ loun n lo iPhone 7 ti wọn n sọrọ rẹ yii, o loun le ṣalaye bọrọ ṣe jẹ gan-an tile-ẹjọ ba gba oun laaye.Abilekọ Ọlayinka Adeyẹmi lati ẹka to n gbọ ẹjọ araalu nipinlẹ Eko lo n ba awọn afurasi ọdaran naa ṣẹjọ, o ṣalaye pe ọjọ kẹrinlelogun, oṣu kẹfa, ọdun yii, ni wọn mu Chidinma lori ẹsun ipaniyan, ati pe afurasi ọdaran naa ti fẹnu ara ẹ jẹwọ ni gbangba pe oun mọ nipa iku ojiji to mu oloogbe naa lọ, o loun fi ọbẹ gun un leralera  ninu yara otẹẹli tawọn jọ sun si lagbegbe Lẹkki, nibi tiṣẹlẹ naa ti waye ni.Ṣugbọn Chidinma tun yi ọrọ pada ninu ifọrọwanilẹnuwo kan to ṣe fawọn oniroyin ninu oṣu keje, ọdun yii, o ni oun o si ninu yara naa nigba ti wọn pa oloogbe yii, o loun ti jade lọọ ran nnkan, oloogbe naa si tilẹkun pa boun ṣe jade, ṣugbọn nigba toun pada de, oun kanlẹkun, ko sẹni to dahun, loun ba ṣakiyesi pe wọn o fi kọkọrọ tilẹkun naa pa, wiwọle toun si wọle, inu agbara ẹjẹ loun ba Ọgbẹni Ataga, o ti ku.O loun tun ṣakiyesi pe gbogbo inu ile naa ti daru, o ti yatọ si boun ṣe fi i si nigba toun n jade lọ, to fihan pe ijakadi waye laarin oloogbe naa atawọn to ṣakọlu si i.O ni idi toun fi ‘purọ mọ ara oun lakọọkọ’ ni pe oun ro pe ko ni i sẹni to maa gba oun gbọ toun ba sọ pe oun o mọ nipa iku rẹ, tori awọn meji pere naa lawọn jọ wa ninu yara ọhun fun ọjọ meji kiṣẹlẹ yii too waye.Bakan naa ni ọkan lara awọn mọlẹbi oloogbe naa sọ fawọn oniroyin lasiko ti wọn n sinku Ataga pe apa to wa lọrun ọwọ oloogbe naa fihan pe niṣe ni wọn de e lokun pinpin ki wọn too pa a, bi ile naa si ṣe daru ati ipo ti oku rẹ wa lasiko tawọn agbofinro de’bẹ fihan pe ki i ṣe Chidinma nikan lo da iṣẹ naa ṣe, o ni lati jẹ pe awọn eeyan mi-in pẹlu lati gbẹmi oloogbe ọhun.Ṣa, Adajọ Yetunde Adesanya ti ni ki wọn da gbogbo wọn pada sọgba ẹwọn Kirikiri, titi ti igbẹjọ to kan yoo fi waye loṣu kọkanla, ọdun yii."},{"question":"Ìlú wo ní ilè Yorùbá ni wọ́n máa ń sun Ẹkún Ìyàwó? ","answer":"Ìlú Ọ̀yọ́ "},{"question":"பண்பாட்டுக் கூறுகளைப் பேணிப் பாதுகாக்க நாம் செய்ய வேண்டிய செயல்களைத் தொகுத்து எழுதுக.","answer":"மனிதன் தோன்றிப் பல்லாயிரம் ஆண்டுகள் கடந்துவிட்டன. இன்றும் பண்பாட்டு அளவில் சிறந்த வாழ்வை வெளிப்படுத்திய தமிழர்களின் வரலாற்றை அறிந்து கொள்ள தமிழகத்தின் தொன்மையான பகுதிகளைக் கொண்டும் மக்கள் பயன்படுத்திய பழமையான கருவிகளைக் கொண்டும் இசைக் கருவிகளைக் கொண்டும் அறிய முடிகிறது. அவற்றைப் பேணிக் காக்க வேண்டும். இது நம் கடமையாகும்.பண்பாட்டுக் கூறு – ஏறுதழுவுதல்:வீரத்திற்கும் விளைச்சலுக்கும் செழிப்பிற்கும் செல்வத்திற்கும் தமிழர்களால் அடையாளப் படுத்தப்படுபவை மாடுகள். முல்லை மற்றும் மருத நிலங்களில் கால் கொண்டு தமிழர் தம் வாழ்வோடு பின்னிப் பிணைந்து பண்பாடாகி உள்ளது ஏறுதழுவுதல். இது தமிழர்களின் நாகரிகத்தை உணர்த்தும் விளையாட்டு. இளைஞர்களின் வீரத்தைப் பெருமிதப்படுத்தும் பண்பாட்டு நிகழ்வு. முன்னோர் வழிநின்று இளந்தலைமுறையினர் கடைப்பிடிக்க வேண்டிய ஒன்று; காதலும் வீரமும் பழந்தமிழரின் பண்பாட்டுத் தடயங்கள். வீரமும் அன்பும் ஏறுதழுவுதலின் விளைநிலங்களாக விளங்குகிறது என்பதை வளரும் தலைமுறையினர்க்கு எடுத்துக்காட்ட ஒரு வாய்ப்பு.பண்பாட்டுக்கூறு – அகழாய்வு:அகழாய்வு என்பது தேர்ந்தெடுக்கப்பட்ட நிலப்பகுதியில் செதுக்கிச் செதுக்கி ஆராய்தல் ஆகும். ஆய்வு என்பது அறிவின் வெளிப்பாடு. நமது முன்னோர்கள் வாழ்ந்து பெற்ற பட்டறிவை வகைப்படுத்தி தொகுத்துப் பார்ப்பதற்குத் தொல்லியல் ஆய்வே பெருங்கல்வியாக அமைகின்றது. பண்பாட்டு எச்சங்களாகத் திகழும் இவ்வகையான ஆய்வுகளைக் கண்டு பயனடையலாம்.பண்பாட்டுக்கூறு – திருவிழாக்கள்:கி.பி. 2 ஆம் நூற்றாண்டோடு தொடர்புடைய புகார்நகரில் கொண்டாடப்பெற்ற இந்திரவிழா சிலப்பதிகாரத்திலும் மணிமேகலையிலும் விவரிக்கப்படுகிறது. கோயில் விழாக்களில் பண்பாட்டுக் கூறுகளாக உள்ள ஒயிலாட்டம், மயிலாட்டம், நாதசுரம், பரதம், பொய்க்கால் குதிரை ஆட்டம் எனப்பல கலைகள் நடந்தேறுகின்றன. விழா நிகழ்ச்சியில் பட்டிமன்றம், தெருக்கூத்து நாடகங்களும் நடைபெறுகின்றன.இத்தகைய பண்பாட்டுக் கூறுகளையும், கலைநிகழ்வுகளையும் பேணிப் பாதுகாத்து இளந்தலைமுறையினருக்கும் இனி வரும் தலைமுறையினருக்கும் காட்டுவது நம் கடமையாகும்."},{"question":" புது எகிப்து இராச்சியம் இதனை எகிப்தியப் பேரரசு என்றும் அழைப்பர்.","answer":"எகிப்தின் இரண்டாம் இடைநிலைக் காலத்திற்குப் பின்னர் பண்டைய எகிப்தை, பதினெட்டாம் வம்சம், பத்தொன்பதாம் வம்சம் மற்றும் இருபதாம் வம்சத்தைச் சேர்ந்த பார்வோன்கள் கிமு 1550 முதல் கிமு 1077 முடிய 473 ஆண்டுகள் ஆட்சி செய்தனர்."},{"question":"Olú Jacobs","answer":"Olúdọ̀tun Jacobs|Olú Jacobs (tí wọ́n bí ní Ọjọ́ kọkànlá oṣù keje ọdún 1942), jẹ́ gbajúmọ̀ ìlúmọ̀ọ́kà òṣèré sinimá àgbéléwò ọmọ Yorùbá láti orílẹ̀ èdè Nàìjíríà. Ó ti kópa nínú ọ̀pọ̀lọpọ̀ fíìmù.Lọ́dún 2007, ó gba àmì ẹ̀yẹ African Movie Academy Award gẹ́gẹ́ bí Òṣèrékùnrin tó dára jùlọ nínú ipò olú-ẹ̀dá-ìtàn.Jacob tí ni ipa nínú iṣẹ́ fíìmù ṣíṣe ní Nàìjíríà. Pẹ̀lú ìrírí rẹ̀ tó ju ogójì ọdún lọ, a lè pè é ní alàgàta láàárín àwọn ọ̀jẹ̀ wẹ́wẹ́ àti àgbà òṣèré. Ní ọdún 2007, ó gba ààmì ẹ̀yẹ ti African Movie Academy Award fún òṣèré tó dára jù lọ."},{"question":"Escreva uma continuação para o parágrafo a seguir - O Apocalipse de Lorvão possui 221 fólios em pergaminho, com as dimensões 345 x 245 mm. O texto apresenta-se regrado, com 29 linhas a duas colunas. A obra distingue-se pelo uso de uma paleta de cores limitada, para além do negro, ao amarelo, laranja e vermelho, e ilustrações românicas","answer":"com influências bizantinas. O texto é em latim, e emprega a escrita gótica da era."},{"question":"ఇచ్చిన పద్యానికి భావం రాయండి:ఉ. ఆయతపక్షతుండహతి నక్కులశైలము లెల్ల నుగ్గుగాఁజేయు మహాబలంబును బ్రసిద్ధియునుం గల నాకు నీపనింబాయక వీఁపునం దవడుఁబాముల మోవను, వారికిం బనుల్సేయను నేమి కారణము సెప్పుము దీనిఁ బయోరుహాననా!","answer":"భావం :పద్మము వంటి ముఖము కల ఓ తల్లీ ! కులపర్వతాలను అన్నింటినీ నా విశాలమైన టెక్కలతోనూ వాడియైన ముక్కుతోనూ దెబ్బతీసి వాటిని పొడిగా చేయగల గొప్పబలమూ, ప్రసిద్ధి నాకు ఉన్నాయి. అటువంటి నాకు మానకుండా దాస్యము చేస్తూ, ఈ నీచమైన పాములను నా వీపుపై మోస్తూ వీటికి సేవలు చేయడానికి గల కారణము ఏమిటో చెప్పు."},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਸਲੋਕੁ ॥ਸਰਬ ਕਲਾ ਭਰਪੂਰ ਪ੍ਰਭ ਬਿਰਥਾ ਜਾਨਨਹਾਰ ॥ਜਾ ਕੈ ਸਿਮਰਨਿ ਉਧਰੀਐ ਨਾਨਕ ਤਿਸੁ ਬਲਿਹਾਰ ॥੧॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 282 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਅਰਜਨ ਦੇਵ ਜੀ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਬਾਣੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਹਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਸਾਰੀਆਂ ਸ਼ਕਤੀਆਂ ਨਾਲ ਪੂਰਨ ਹੈ, (ਸਭ ਜੀਵਾਂ ਦੇ) ਦੁੱਖ-ਦਰਦ ਜਾਣਦਾ ਹੈ । ਹੇ ਨਾਨਕ! ਜਿਸ (ਐਸੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ) ਦੇ ਸਿਮਰਨ ਨਾਲ (ਵਿਕਾਰਾਂ ਤੋਂ) ਬਚ ਸਕੀਦਾ ਹੈ, ਉਸ ਤੋਂ (ਸਦਾ) ਸਦਕੇ ਜਾਈਏ ।੧।\\""},{"question":"پرچم ایران دارای  چند رنگ است؟","answer":"۳ رنگ سبز، سفید و آبی"},{"question":"Ndipe mamwe matipi ekubika yakanakisa bolognese muto.","answer":"\\"Kuti ubike bolognese muto, zvakakosha kushandisa zvigadzirwa zvemhando yepamusoro. Iwe uchada zvinotevera: Italian tomato sauce, hanyanisi, celery, karoti, minced nyama, extra virgin mafuta omuorivhi, munyu, chena kana waini tsvuku uye mukaka.Heano mamwe mazano anobatsira:- Tora nguva yako. Kubika yakakura bolognese muto kunotora angangoita 4 maawa. Isa chitofu chepamusoro pasi.- Tanga nekubika \\"\\"sofritto\\"\\". Uku ndiko kusanganiswa kwehanyanisi dzakachekwa, celery uye karoti. -- Wedzera nyama kune \\"\\"sofritto\\"\\". Iva nechokwadi chekuisa chisimbiso kuti chirege kudonhedza mvura mumuto wako.- Wedzera imwe waini uye uifashaire zvachose.- Kana pasisina mvura, isa muto wematomatisi nemvura, wobika kwemaawa matatu kusvika mashanu. Unogona kuwedzera mamwe mvura panguva yekugadzira kana zvichidikanwa. \\""},{"question":" जालीयनवाला बाग हत्याकांड कोणत्या शहरात घडले ?","answer":" जालीयनवाला बाग हत्याकांड अमृतसर (पंजाब) शहरात घडले. "},{"question":"2023 TikTok Aslan ne kadar?","answer":"Tiktok'da aslan hediyesi gönderen kişi için 2914,24 kuruştur. Kesintiler sonrası hediyeyi alan kişinin hesabına da 1295,04 kuruş yüklenir. Jeton ile hediye almak için ise aslan alınmak istendiğinde 29999 jeton harcamak gerekir. Jeton ile ya da para ile hediye almak ve hesap sahiplerine göndermek mümkündür."},{"question":"Awọn ọmọ ‘Yahoo’ yari n’Ileṣa, wọn ni ki EFCC fi awọn lọrun silẹ","answer":"Lọwọlọwọ bayii, inu ibẹrubojo lawọn olugbe ilu Ileṣa, nipinlẹ Ọṣun, wa pẹlu bi awọn ọmọ ‘Yahoo’ ṣe fọn soju popo nidaaji ojo lsegun, Tusidee, ose yii.A gbọ pe awọn oṣiṣẹ ajọ to n gbogun ti lilu jibiti ori ẹrọ ayelujara, EFCC, ko diẹ lara wọn loru-mọjọ, eleyii si bi wọn ninu.Ariwo ti wọn n pa ni pe wahala awọn EFCC ti pọ ju, wọn ni gbogbo igba ni wọn n mu awọn. Pẹlu igi, okuta, ada ati bẹẹ bẹẹ lọ ni wọn n rin kaakiri.Wọn dana sun taya lawọn ikorita bii Iṣokun Roundabout, Ibala, Oke Omiru ati bẹẹ bẹẹ lọ.Gbogbo igbiyanju wa lati ba Alukoro ileeṣẹ ọlọpaa ipinlẹ Ọṣun, SP Yẹmisi Ọpalọla, sọrọ lo ja si pabo nitori ko gbe foonu rẹ lasiko ti a n koroyin yii jọ."},{"question":"Объясни следующих анекдот:Три логика заходят в бар. Бармен спрашивает: \\"Чай все будут?\\"- Не знаю, - отвечает первый логик. - Не знаю, - говорит второй. - Да! - восклицает третий.","answer":"Этот анекдот основан на игре слов и подразумевает двусмысленность в вопросе бармена. Когда бармен спрашивает: \\"Чай все будут?\\", он фактически спрашивает, хотят ли все трое заказать чай. Первый и второй логики, отвечая \\"Не знаю\\", вероятно, пытаются оценить предпочтения остальных двух логиков, чтобы определить, будут ли они заказывать чай или нет. Третий логик отвечает \\"Да\\", подразумевая, что все три логика будут заказывать чай. Таким образом, анекдот играет с понятием логического мышления и ожиданий, которые могут быть связаны с логикой."},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਪਉੜੀ ॥ਤੂ ਸਚਾ ਸਾਹਿਬੁ ਆਪਿ ਹੈ ਸਚੁ ਸਾਹ ਹਮਾਰੇ ॥ਸਚੁ ਪੂਜੀ ਨਾਮੁ ਦ੍ਰਿੜਾਇ ਪ੍ਰਭ ਵਣਜਾਰੇ ਥਾਰੇ ॥ਸਚੁ ਸੇਵਹਿ ਸਚੁ ਵਣੰਜਿ ਲੈਹਿ ਗੁਣ ਕਥਹ ਨਿਰਾਰੇ ॥ਸੇਵਕ ਭਾਇ ਸੇ ਜਨ ਮਿਲੇ ਗੁਰ ਸਬਦਿ ਸਵਾਰੇ ॥ਤੂ ਸਚਾ ਸਾਹਿਬੁ ਅਲਖੁ ਹੈ ਗੁਰ ਸਬਦਿ ਲਖਾਰੇ ॥੧੪॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 308 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਰਾਮਦਾਸ ਜੀ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਬਾਣੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਸਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"ਹੇ ਸਾਡੇ ਸਦਾ-ਥਿਰ ਰਹਿਣ ਵਾਲੇ ਸ਼ਾਹ! ਤੂੰ ਆਪ ਹੀ ਸੱਚਾ ਮਾਲਕ ਹੈਂ, ਹੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ! ਅਸੀ ਤੇਰੇ ਵਣਜਾਰੇ ਹਾਂ, ਸਾਨੂੰ ਇਹ ਨਿਸਚੇ ਕਰਾ ਕਿ ਨਾਮ ਦੀ ਪੂੰਜੀ ਸਦਾ ਕਾਇਮ ਰਹਿਣ ਵਾਲੀ ਹੈ ਜੋ ਸਦਾ-ਥਿਰ ਨਾਮ ਸਿਮਰਦੇ ਹਨ, ਸੱਚੇ ਨਾਮ ਦਾ ਸਉਦਾ ਖ਼ਰੀਦਦੇ ਹਨ ਤੇ ਨਿਰਾਲੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੇ ਗੁਣ ਉਚਾਰਦੇ ਹਨ ਉਹ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਸਤਿਗੁਰੂ ਦੇ ਸ਼ਬਦ ਦੁਆਰਾ ਸੁਧਰ ਕੇ ਸੇਵਕ ਸੁਭਾਉ ਵਾਲੇ ਹੋ ਕੇ ਉਸ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਨੂੰ ਮਿਲਦੇ ਹਨ ਹੇ ਹਰੀ! ਤੂੰ ਸੱਚਾ ਮਾਲਕ ਹੈਂ, ਤੈਨੂੰ ਕੋਈ ਸਮਝ ਨਹੀਂ ਸਕਦਾ (ਪਰ) ਸਤਿਗੁਰੂ ਦੇ ਸ਼ਬਦ ਦੁਆਰਾ ਤੇਰੀ ਸੂਝ ਪੈਂਦੀ ਹੈ ।੧੪।\\""},{"question":"Hoi, ik wil een sinterklaasgedichtje voor Alice, en het cadeautje is een golf-clubpoetsdoekje","answer":"SInt zat te denkenWat hij Alice zou schenkenMaar het is toch heel gewoonHou je golfclubs toch eens schoon.Groet, Sint"},{"question":"ਓਸਾਮਾ ਬਿਨ ਲਾਦਿਨ ’ਤੇ ਬਣ ਰਹੀ ਫ਼ਿਲਮ ਹੁਣ ਹਾਲੀਵੁੱਡ ਓਸਾਮਾ ਬਿਨ ਲਾਦਿਨ ਨੂੰ ਪਰਦੇ ’ਤੇ ਪੇਸ਼ ਕਰਨ ਜਾ ਰਿਹਾ ਹੈ। ਆਸਕਰ ਐਵਾਰਡ ਜੇਤੂ ਬਰਤਾਨਵੀ ਨਿਰਦੇਸ਼ਕਾ ਕੈਥਰੀਨ ਬਿਗੇਲੋ ਇਸ ਵਿਸ਼ੇ ’ਤੇ  ‘ਜ਼ੀਰੋ ਡਾਰਕ ਥਰਟੀ’ ਨਾਂ ਦੀ ਅੰਗਰੇਜ਼ੀ ਫ਼ਿਲਮ ਬਣਾ ਰਹੀ ਹੈ। ਫ਼ਿਲਮ ਦੀ ਕਹਾਣੀ ਓਸਾਮਾ ਬਿਨ ਲਾਦਿਨ ਅਤੇ ਅਮਰੀਕਾ ਦੀ ਵਿਸ਼ੇਸ਼ ਕਮਾਂਡੋ ਫ਼ੌੌਜ ‘ਸੀਲ ਸਿਕਸ ਟੀਮ’ ਦੀਆਂ ਕਾਰਵਾਈਆਂ  ’ਤੇ ਆਧਾਰਿਤ ਹੈ। ਫ਼ਿਲਮ ਵਿੱਚ ‘ਸੀਲ ਸਿਕਸ ਟੀਮ’ ਦਾ ਮਈ 2012 ਵਿੱਚ ਕੀਤਾ ਵਿਸ਼ੇਸ਼ ਅਪਰੇਸ਼ਨ ਆਕਰਸ਼ਕ ਰੂਪ ਵਿੱਚ ਦਿਖਾਇਆ ਜਾਵੇਗਾ, ਜਿਸ ਤਹਿਤ ਅਮਰੀਕਾ ਵਿੱਚ ਤਬਾਹੀ ਮਚਾਉਣ ਵਾਲੇ ਓਸਾਮਾ ਬਿਨ ਲਾਦਿਨ ਨੂੰ ਲੱਭਣ ਅਤੇ ਐਬਟਾਬਾਦ (ਪਾਕਿਸਤਾਨ) ਵਿੱਚ ਮਾਰਨ ਦੀ ਕਾਰਵਾਈ ਕੀਤੀ ਗਈ ਸੀ। ਅੰਗਰੇਜ਼ੀ ਫ਼ਿਲਮ ‘ਦਿ ਹਾਰਟ ਲਾਕਰ’ ਦਾ ਲੇਖਕ ਮਾਰਕ ਬੋਇਲ ਅਤੇ ਨਿਰਦੇਸ਼ਕਾ ਕੈਥਰੀਨ ਬਿਗੇਲੋ ਲੰਮੇ ਸਮੇਂ ਤੋਂ ‘ਜ਼ੀਰੋ ਡਾਰਕ ਥਰਟੀ’ ਦੀ ਕਹਾਣੀ ’ਤੇ ਕੰਮ ਕਰ ਰਹੇ ਸਨ। ਜਦੋਂ ਬੀਤੇ ਸਾਲ ਮਈ ਵਿੱਚ ਅਮਰੀਕੀ ਫ਼ੌਜ ਵੱਲੋਂ ਓਸਾਮਾ ਨੂੰ ਮਾਰ ਦਿੱਤਾ ਗਿਆ ਤਾਂ ਫ਼ਿਲਮ ਦੀ ਸਕ੍ਰਿਪਟ ਵਿੱਚ ਤਬਦੀਲੀ ਕਰਨੀ ਪਈ। ਸੀਲ ਟੀਮ ਵੱਲੋਂ ਓਸਾਮਾ ਨੂੰ ਮਾਰਨ ਲਈ ਕੀਤੀ ਕਾਰਵਾਈ ਦੀ ਅੰਦਰੂਨੀ ਜਾਣਕਾਰੀ ਅਮਰੀਕੀ ਰੱਖਿਆ ਵਿਭਾਗ ਅਤੇ ਸੀ.ਆਈ.ਏ. ਕੋਲ ਸੀ। ਇਹ ਜਾਣਕਾਰੀ ਲੈਣ ਲਈ ਫ਼ਿਲਮ ਦੇ ਨਿਰਮਾਤਾਵਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਸਖ਼ਤ ਮਿਹਨਤ ਕਰਨੀ ਪਈ ਸੀ। ਫ਼ਿਲਮ ਉਸ ਸਮੇਂ ਵਿਵਾਦਾਂ ਵਿੱਚ ਘਿਰ ਗਈ ਸੀ, ਜਦੋਂ ਅਮਰੀਕੀ ਰੱਖਿਆ ਵਿਭਾਗ ਅਤੇ ਸੀ.ਆਈ.ਏ. ਉੱਤੇ ਇਹ ਦੋਸ਼ ਲੱਗਿਆ ਕਿ ਉਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਨੇ ਓਸਾਮਾ ਸਬੰਧੀ ਸੀਲ ਵੱਲੋਂ ਕੀਤੇ ਅਪਰੇਸ਼ਨ ਦੀ ਗੁਪਤ ਜਾਣਕਾਰੀ ਫ਼ਿਲਮ ਦੇ ਨਿਰਮਾਤਾਵਾਂ ਨਾਲ ਸਾਂਝੀ ਕੀਤੀ ਹੈ। ਇਸ ਫ਼ਿਲਮ ਵਿੱਚ ਹਾਲੀਵੁੱਡ ਸੁਪਰ ਸਟਾਰ ਬ੍ਰੈਡ ਪਿਟ ਅਤੇ ਜੇਸਿਕਾ ਕ੍ਰਿਸਟੀਨ ਵਿਸ਼ੇਸ਼ ਭੂਮਿਕਾਵਾਂ ਨਿਭਾਅ ਰਹੇ ਹਨ। ਮਾਰਕ ਸਟ੍ਰਾਂਗ ਨਾਇਕ ਅਤੇ ਆਇਮਿਨ ਬਲੂ ਨਾਇਕਾ ਦੀ ਭੂਮਿਕਾ ਵਿੱਚ ਹਨ। ਫ਼ਿਲਮ ਦੀ ਸ਼ੂਟਿੰਗ ਅਮਰੀਕਾ ਸਮੇਤ ਭਾਰਤੀ ਪੰਜਾਬ ਵਿੱਚ ਚੰਡੀਗੜ੍ਹ, ਕੁਰਾਲੀ ਅਤੇ ਪਟਿਆਲਾ ਆਦਿ ਥਾਵਾਂ ’ਤੇ ਕੀਤੀ ਜਾ ਰਹੀ ਹੈ। ਫ਼ਿਲਮ ਯੂਨਿਟ ਦੇ ਇੱਕ ਮੈਂਬਰ ਦਾ ਕਹਿਣਾ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਫ਼ਿਲਮ ਭਾਵੇਂ ਪਾਕਿਸਤਾਨ ਨਾਲ ਜੁੜੀ ਹੋਈ ਹੈ ਪਰ ਪਾਕਿਸਤਾਨ ਵਿੱਚ ਫ਼ਿਲਮ ਦੀ ਯੂਨਿਟ ਨੂੰ ਖ਼ਤਰਾ ਸੀ। ਇਸ ਲਈ ਪੰਜਾਬ ਵਿੱਚ ਪਾਕਿਸਤਾਨ ਜਿਹਾ ਮਾਹੌਲ ਬਣਾ ਕੇ ਸ਼ੂਟਿੰਗ ਪੂਰੀ ਕੀਤੀ ਜਾ ਰਹੀ ਹੈ।ਪ੍ਰਸ਼ਨਃ ਫ਼ਿਲਮ ‘ਦਿ ਹਾਰਟ ਲਾਕਰ’ ਦਾ ਲੇਖਕ ਕੌਣ ਹੈ?","answer":"ਉੱਤਰਃ ਫ਼ਿਲਮ ‘ਦਿ ਹਾਰਟ ਲਾਕਰ’ ਦਾ ਲੇਖਕ ਮਾਰਕ ਬੋਇਲ ਹੈ।"},{"question":"Apakah maksud \\"bagai kucing takut akan balur\\"?","answer":"\\"Bagai kucing takut akan balur\\" bermaksud seorang lelaki yang takut perempuan."},{"question":"Quelle est une astuce pour mieux dormir la nuit ?","answer":"Une astuce efficace pour améliorer la qualité de votre sommeil est d'établir une routine régulière avant le coucher. Cela signifie aller vous coucher et vous réveiller à la même heure tous les jours, même les week-ends. Cette régularité aide à réguler votre horloge interne et à stabiliser vos cycles de sommeil. De plus, évitez les stimulants comme la caféine ou la nicotine quelques heures avant d'aller vous coucher. Créez également un environnement propice au sommeil en maintenant votre chambre sombre, calme et à une température confortable."},{"question":"Dựa trên tiêu đề sau, hãy viết một đoạn văn tối đa 500 chữ: Man United ra 'chiêu cuối' để lôi kéo De Jong","answer":"Ở mùa Hè này, Man United đã có 3 tân binh là Christian Eriksen, Lisandro Martinez và Tyrell Malacia nhưng mục tiêu số 1 của HLV Erik Ten Hag là Frenkie De Jong vẫn ở rất xa Old Trafford. Cuộc đàm phán giữa các bên đã bước sang tuần thứ 12 và Quỷ đỏ vừa có một động thái cực kỳ quyết liệt để giải quyết các vướng mắc. Trưởng bộ phận chuyển nhượng Man United sẽ cố gắng gặp gỡ người đại diện của De Jong sau khi Barca trở về từ chuyến du đấu ở Mỹ. Theo Daily Mail, ở cuộc gặp đó, Man United sẽ thông báo việc CLB sẵn sàng trả cho De Jong mức lương 450 ngàn bảng mỗi tuần. Đây là mức thù lao biến De Jong trở thành cầu thủ hưởng lương cao nhất Man Utd. Năm ngoái, Cristiano Ronaldo là người đứng đầu bảng lương của CLB với thu nhập 480 ngàn bảng/tuần. Tuy nhiên, năm nay do Quỷ đỏ không được tham dự Champions League, do đó mức thu nhập của Ronaldo đã bị giảm đi đáng kể, còn 385.000 bảng mỗi tuần. Ngoài ra, tờ Sport của Tây Ban Nha cũng đưa tin, Man United còn \\"thiện chí\\" tới mức sẵn sàng trả giúp Barca khoản tiền 17 triệu bảng mà đối tác đang nợ De Jong. Khoản tiền này Barca đang phải trả chậm ngôi sao người Hà Lan. Mức phí chuyển nhượng vụ De Jong sẽ rơi vào khoảng 74 triệu bảng. Nếu De Jong giữ vững lập trường của mình là ở lại Tây Ban Nha thì anh sẽ phải giảm lương. Việc làm này thật sự khiến các fan khó hiểu bởi bất chấp những khó khăn tài chính, Barca lại mang về được rất nhiều chữ ký chất lượng ở mùa Hè này, bao gồm Robert Lewandowski, Raphinha, Jules Kounde, Franck Kessie và Andreas Christensen. Tổng số tiền họ chi ra ở Hè 2022 lên tới hơn 120 triệu bảng."},{"question":"इस प्रश्न का उत्तर दीजिये। \\"क्या स्मार्टफोन शिक्षा के क्षेत्र में एक सहायक है या एक बाधा?\\" ","answer":"\\"छात्र स्मार्टफोन पर लेक्चर देख सकते हैं, साथ ही अपने प्रश्नों का समाधान भी कर सकते हैं।स्मार्टफोन ने शिक्षा में नए अवसर प्रदान किए हैं, परंतु कुछ लोग इसे शिक्षा के लिए विघटनक मानते हैं क्योंकि यह छात्रों को विचलित कर सकता है।\\""},{"question":"Ijọba ti ko awọn ọlọpaa SWAT ti wọn fi rọpo SARS jade","answer":"Ọga ọlọpaa patapata nilẹ wa, IGP Mohammed Adamu, ti paṣẹ lojọ Aje, Mọnde, pe ki wọn da awọn ikọ ọlọpaa afọgbọn-jagun (Special Weapon and Tactical Team) SWAT, ti wọn ṣẹṣẹ da silẹ jade kaakiri origun mẹrẹẹrin Naijiria sita lẹyẹ-o-sọka.Ninu atẹjade kan ti Adamu kọ si gbogbo awọn Igbakeji Ọga Agba mẹtadinlogun atawọn kọmiṣanna ọlọpaa kaakiri awọn ipinlẹ lorileede yii lo ti paṣẹ naa.O ni kawọn ikọ tuntun naa bẹrẹ iṣẹ ni gbogbo ipinlẹ ati agbegbe ti wọn ba pin wọn si, ki wọn le ro eto aabo lagbara, ki wọn si kun awọn ọlọpaa to wa nilẹ tẹlẹ lọwọ ninu ojuṣe wọn.Tẹ o ba gbagbe, lasiko iwọde gbigbona janjan ta ko ikọ ọlọpaa SARS to waye loṣu kẹwaa, ọdun yii, ni wọn ko ikọ SARS kuro nilẹ, ko si ju ọjọ meji lẹyin naa tijọba fi kede idasilẹ ikọ SWAT tuntun yii, gẹgẹ bii arọpo wọn."},{"question":"Femi Gbajabiamila","answer":"Fẹ́mi Gbàjàbíàmílà tí wọ́n bí ní ọjọ́ kẹẹ̀ẹ́dọ́gbọ̀n oṣù kẹfà ọdún 1962 (June 25, 1962) jẹ́ gbajúmọ̀ òṣèlú, Agbẹjọ́rò àti Agbẹnusọ Ilé-Ìgbìmọ̀ Aṣojú-ṣòfin ẹlẹ́ẹ̀kẹjọ orílẹ̀ èdè Nàìjíríà. Ó jẹ́ ọmọ ẹgbẹ́ òṣèlú, All Progressives Congress tí ó ń ṣojú ìjọba ìbílẹ̀ Sùúrùlérè ni ìpínlẹ̀ Èkó láti ọdun 2019A bí Olufemi \\"Femi\\" Hakeem Gbajabiamila ní 25 June 1962 sí ìdílé Mr àti Mrs Lateef Gbajabiamila àti Olufunke Gbajabiamila ni Ìpínlè Èkó, Nàìjíríà. Ó lọ ilé ìwé àkọ́bẹ̀rẹ̀ ti Mainland fún àkọ́bẹ̀rẹ̀ àti Igbobi College ní ọdún 1973, níbi tí ó ti parí ẹ̀kọ́ girama rẹ̀. Ó tún padà lọ King's William's College ni Isle Of Man, orílè-èdè United Kingdom fún ìwé-ẹ̀rí A-Level rẹ̀. Wọ́n gbà sí Yunifásítì Ìlú Èkó, Nàìjíríà. níbí tí ó ti gba àmì-ẹ̀yẹ nínú ìmò òfin(LL.B) pẹ̀lú ẹ̀yẹ ní ọdún 1983, a sì pé é láti wá ṣiṣẹ́ òfin(call to bar) ní ọdún 1984.Ó kọ́kọ́ ṣiṣẹ́ ni ilé-ìṣẹ́ agbẹjọ́rò Bentley Edu &Co., ní ìpínlè Eko, kí ó tó dá ilé-iṣẹ́ agbẹjọ́rò kan, Femi Gbaja & Co. kalẹ̀.A yan Gbajabiamila sí ilé ìgbìmọ̀ aṣòfin ní ọdún 2003, ó sì ń ṣe aṣojú Surulere I ní ìpínlẹ̀ Èkó.Gbajabiamila máa ń sọ̀rọ̀ lòdì sí bí àwọn ọmọ ilé ìgbìmọ̀ aṣòfin ṣe máa ń yí láti ẹgbẹ́ òṣèlú kan sí òmíràn."},{"question":"අයිෆල් කුළුණ යනු ප්‍රංශයේ පැරිස් නුවර පිහිටි යකඩ දැලිස් කුළුණකි. එය නම් කර ඇත්තේ ඉංජිනේරු ගුස්ටාව් අයිෆල් විසිනි.අයිෆල් කුළුණ පිහිටා ඇත්තේ කොහේද?","answer":"අයිෆල් කුළුණ පිහිටා ඇත්තේ ප්රංශයේ පැරීසිය නුවරෙහිය."},{"question":"ద్రవ్యోల్బణ నిర్వచనాలు గురించి సంక్లిప్తంగా వివరించండి","answer":"సాధారణ పరిభాషలో ద్రవ్యోల్బణమనగా ధరల పెరుగుదల కేవలం ఒకేసారి ధరలు పెరిగినంత మాత్రాన దానిని ద్రవ్యోల్బణం అనకూడదు. నిర్విరామంగా ధరలు పెరుగుతున్నా దీనినే ద్రవ్యోల్బణం అంటారు. భారతదేశంలో ద్రవ్యోల్బణ సమస్య ఉంది.ద్రవ్యోల్బణ నిర్వచనాలు: వివిధ ఆర్థిక శాస్త్రవేత్తలు ద్రవ్యోల్బణం గూర్చి నిర్వచనాలను ఇచ్చారు.హాట్రే అను ఆర్థిక శాస్త్రవేత్త ప్రకారం “కరెన్సీ నోట్లను అధికంగా జారీ చేయటాన్నే ద్రవ్యోల్బణమందురు”.డాల్టన్ అభిప్రాయం ప్రకారం, “ద్రవ్యోల్బణమనగా అధిక ద్రవ్యం తక్కువ వస్తువులను వెంటాడటం”.కిమ్మరర్ అను ఆర్థిక శాస్త్రవేత్త ప్రకారం, “వ్యాపార అవసరాలకు మించి కరెన్సీ ఉంటే దాన్ని ద్రవ్యోల్బణం అందురు”.ఏసి. పిగూ ప్రకారం “వాస్తవిక ఆదాయం కన్నా ద్రవ్య ఆదాయం ఎక్కువగా ఉండటాన్నే ద్రవ్యోల్బణమందురు”.కేదర్ అను ఆర్థిక శాస్త్రవేత్త ప్రకారం, ‘ద్రవ్య విలువ పడిపోవడం అనగా ధరలు పెరగడాన్ని ద్రవ్యోల్బణమని చెప్పవచ్చు”. వస్తువుల సప్లై, డిమాండ్లలో అసమతౌల్యం ఏర్పడడం వల్ల ధరల స్థాయి నిర్విరామంగా పెరుగుదల ఏర్పడినా అటువంటి ధరల పెరుగుదలనే ద్రవ్యోల్బణంగా చెప్పవచ్చు. ప్రతి ధర పెరుగుదలను ద్రవ్యోల్బణంగా చెప్పకూడదు. ధరల పెరుగుదల గణనీయమైందిగా నిర్విరామంగా కొనసాగినపుడే ద్రవ్యోల్బణం ఏర్పడిందని చెప్పాలి”."},{"question":"Hình tròn đỏ trên quốc kỳ của Nhật Bản tượng trưng cho điều gì?","answer":"Quốc kỳ Nhật Bản được tạo thành từ một vòng tròn màu đỏ, tượng trưng cho mặt trời, trên nền trắng. Nó được gọi là hinomaru trong tiếng Nhật, có nghĩa là \\"vòng tròn mặt trời\\". Lá cờ này gợi nhớ tên của Nhật Bản (đất nước Mặt trời mọc). Màu trắng tượng trưng cho sự thuần khiết và chính trực, còn màu đỏ là sự chân thành, tươi sáng và ấm áp."},{"question":"２００８年１１月アメリカ大統領選挙で黒人では史上初のアメリカ大統領に当選した人物とは？","answer":"バラク・オバマです。"},{"question":"Complete a frase: O clássico entre Flamengo e Fluminense é conhecido como...","answer":"O clássico entre Flamengo e Fluminense é conhecido como o \\"Fla-Flu\\"."},{"question":"Ahitsio izay diso fanoratra na diso tsipelina anatin'ity fehezanteny ity:\\"Kay ve, fa izy izany. Tsy nipetra-potsiny akoriny ianao fa nanao zavatra, aza eritreretina izay tsy vita fa ny vokatrin'ny zavatra vitanao androany ve nahafa-po anao.\\"","answer":"Indro ilay fehezanteny rehefa voahitsy ny diso:\\"Kay ve! Efa izy izany. Tsy nipetra-potsiny akory ianao fa nanao zavatra. Aza eritreretina izay tsy vita. Fa ny vokatry ny zavatra vitanao androany ve nahafa-po anao?\\""},{"question":"ఇతర మలస్కా జీవులతో పోలిస్తే సెఫలోపోడ్లు అనేక ప్రత్యేక లేదా పురోగతి చెందిన లక్షణాలను ప్రదర్శిస్తాయి. సంక్షిప్తంగా చర్చించండి.","answer":"సెఫలోపొడా లేదా సైఫనోపొడా:ఈ విభాగంలో కటిల్ చేపలు, స్క్విడ్లు, ఆక్టోపస్లు, నాటిస్లను చేర్చారు. తల స్పష్టంగా ఉండి సుస్పష్టమైన సకశేరుకాలను పోలిన కళ్ళు, ఒక జత కొమ్ము స్వభావం కలిగిన ముక్కులాంటి దవడలు, ఆస్యకుహరంలో రాడ్యులా ఉంటాయి. కొన్నిటిలో అనేక గదులు కలిగిన బాహ్యకర్పరం (నాటిలిస్) లేదా అంతర కర్పరం (సెపియా, లాలిగో) గానీ ఉంటుంది. కొన్నిటిలో కర్పరం ఉండదు (ఆక్టోపస్), సెపియా కర్పరాన్ని సాధారణంగా కటిల్ ఎముక అంటారు. లాలిగోలోని కర్పరాన్ని కలం అంటారు. పాదం రూపాంతరం చెంది నోటి చుట్టూ చూషకాలతో 8 (ఆక్టోపస్) నుంచి 10 (సెపియా, లాలిగో) భుజాలు కలిగి ఉంటుంది. పాదంలోని కొంత భాగం రూపాంతరం చెంది అంకుశనాళంగా మార్పు చెందుతుంది. ఇది ఆకస్మిక కదలికలు కలిగించడానికి ఉపయోగపడుతుంది). కొన్ని జీవులలో సిరా గ్రంథి ఉంటుంది.దీనిలోని సిరను మేఘాల లాగా విడుదల చేసి పరభక్షక జీవి నుంచి తప్పించుకుంటాయి. (రక్షణ అనుకూలత). కంకాభాంగాలు ఏట్రియమ్లు, వృక్కాలు రెండు చొప్పున డైబ్రాంకియేట్లలోనూ (సెపియా) నాలుగు చొప్పున టెట్రాబ్రాంకియేట్లలోనూ (నాటిలస్) ఉంటాయి. ప్రసరణ వ్యవస్థ సంవృత రకం (సెఫలోపొడా విశిష్ఠ లక్షణం), హృదయంలో రెండు నుంచి నాలుగు కర్ణికలు, ఒక జఠరిక ఉంటాయి. నాడీవ్యవస్థ బాగా అభివృద్ధి చెందింది. మెదడు బాగా అభివృద్ధి చెంది మృదులాస్థి నిర్మితమైన కపాలం (మస్తిష్క పేటిక లో ఉంటుంది. ఇవి ఏకలింగ జీవులు. ప్రత్యక్ష అభివృద్ధి జరుగుతుంది.ఉదా : సెపియా (కటిల్ చేప), ఆర్కిట్యూథిస్ (బృహత్ స్క్విడ్ – అతిపెద్ద సజీవ అకశేరుక జీవి), నాటిలస్, ఆక్టోపస్ (దెయ్యపు చేప)."},{"question":"悪い虫がつかないように大事に大事に育てられた娘を何娘という？","answer":"箱入り娘です。"},{"question":"Fantaro raha maneho fifaliana, alahelo, hatezerana, na tahotra ity fanambarana manaraka ity.Fanambarana: \\"Nahazo fanomezana tsy nampoizina avy amin'ny namako akaiky indrindra aho.\\"","answer":"Io fanambarana io dia maneho fifaliana. Faly sy sambatra ilay olona satria tsy nampoiziny ilay fanomezana hazony."},{"question":"\\"Lasa tia ny tanàna aho vao tamin'ny fitsidihana voalohany.\\" Inona ny fihetseham-po raketin'io fanambarana io?","answer":"Ity fanambarana ity dia maneho fihetseham-po tsara. Tena tia an’ilay tanàna ilay olona."},{"question":"शिवाजी महाराजांच्या माता जिजाऊ यांच्या आई व वडीलांचे नाव काय होते ?","answer":"माळसाबाई व लखुजी जाधव"},{"question":"কোন দেশকে উদীয়মান সূর্যের দেশ বলা হয়?","answer":"জাপানকে বলা হয় উদীয়মান সূর্যের দেশ"},{"question":"Mubvunzo wokuti: \\"Pane 12 ounces per troy pound dzinova magiramu 373.242, panzvimbo pe16 ounces per pound inowanikwa muavoirdupois system yakajairika pane magiramu 453.592.\\" ndewei? Nyaya yacho inonzi Troy weight.","answer":"\\"magiramu mangani ari muTroy pound yegoridhe?\\""},{"question":"Apakah soalan untuk ayat berikut: \\"Ada bukti saintifik bahawa peneroka di Jamestown telah beralih ke kanibalisme semasa kebuluran. \\"? Topiknya ialah Waktu Kelaparan.","answer":"\\"Apa yang berlaku semasa kebuluran di Jamestown?\\""},{"question":"في أي قارة تقع إرتيريا؟","answer":"تقع إرتيريا في قارة إفريقيا."},{"question":"Ọọni gba awọn oloṣelu niyanju lati gba alaafia laaye ","answer":"Arole Oduduwa, to tun jẹ Ọọni Ifẹ, Ọba Adeyẹye Ẹnitan Ogunwusi, Ọjaja II, ti ke si gbogbo awọn oloṣelu nipinlẹ Ọṣun ati awọn alatilẹyin wọn lati gba alaafia laaye, ṣaaju, lasiko ati lẹyin eto idibo gomina to n bọ.Ọọni Ogunwusi parọwa yii lasiko ti ọkan lara awọn oludije funpo gomina labẹ asia ẹgbẹ oṣelu PDP, Sẹnetọ Ademọla Adeleke, ṣabẹwo si aafin rẹ ni Ile Oodua, ni Ileefẹ.Kabiesi woye pe ọpọlọpọ wahala to maa n ṣẹlẹ lasiko idibo ti a ti ṣe sẹyin lorileede yii ko ṣẹyin iwa awọn to n tẹle awọn oloṣelu.Gẹgẹ bi Ọba Adeyẹye ṣe sọ, “Ẹyin ololufẹ awọn oloṣelu yii lẹ maa n dari ọkan awọn adari yin. Mo fẹẹ rọ yin lati fi iwa ọmọluabi han nitori abayọri si wahala ati rogbodiyan ki i dara.“Ẹ dẹkun titi awọn adari nitikuti ti awọn yẹn naa aa fi maa ṣeleri asan ti wọn ko ni i le mu ṣẹ. Ẹ ṣe oloootọ ati alaapọn ni gbogbo igba, yoo si dara fun yin”Ṣaaju ninu ọrọ rẹ, Sẹnetọ Adeleke ṣapejuwe Ọọni gẹgẹ bii baba to ṣee mu yangan. O bu ẹnu atẹ lu ipo ti awọn oju-ọna ilu Ileefẹ wa ati bi ko ṣe si awọn nnkan amayedẹrun gbogbo nibẹ.Adeleke sọ pe ti oun ba le lanfaani lati de ipo gomina, oun yoo mu iyipada ba ọpọlọpọ nnkan nitori oun gbagbọ pe ibi ọwọ ni Ileefẹ ati ipo Ọọni jẹ.O sọ siwaju pe pẹlu erongba oun lati da Papakọ ofurufu tipinlẹ Ọṣun silẹ, oun yoo wa jẹẹti aladaani kan (Private Jet) ti yoo maa gbe Ọọni kaakiri ibi gbogbo to ba fẹẹ lọ.Adeleke ṣalaye pe ohun kan pato to mu ifasẹyin ba gbogbo nnkan nipinlẹ Ọṣun ko ṣẹyin bijọba ṣe di ọwọ mọ owo awọn ijọba ibilẹ, ti wọn ko jẹ ki wọn le se ohunkohun, o si ṣeleri pe gbogbo eleyii ni yoo yipada lọdun to n bọ.Ọbalufẹ, Ọba Idowu Adediwura, ninu ọrọ tirẹ, rọ Adeleke lati ṣiṣẹ tọ awọn ileri rẹ lẹyin, ki gbogbo rẹ ma baa jẹ lori irọ lasan gẹgẹ bi awọn oloṣelu kan ṣe ṣe sẹyin.Bakan naa ni Lọwa Adimula ti Ifẹ, Oloye-Agba Adekọla Adeyẹye, pe awọn ọmọ ẹgbẹ oṣelu PDP niluu Ileefẹ nija lati maa beere abọ iṣẹ iriju awọn adari wọn loorekoore nitori awọn araalu n wo wọn."},{"question":"Jawab soalan yang rumit ini: Ahli botani manakah yang menerbitkan buku botani yang paling popular pada zamannya?","answer":"John Gerard ialah ahli botani yang menerbitkan buku botani yang paling popular pada zamannya"},{"question":"Me dê um exemplo de curiosidade nesta categoria: livros","answer":"O que Charlie encontrou para ganhar um passeio pela fábrica de chocolate de Willy Wonka? Um bilhete dourado."},{"question":"Qual artista pintou o famoso quadro O Grito?","answer":"O famoso quadro \\"O Grito\\" foi pintado pelo artista norueguês Edvard Munch. Esta obra icônica, criada em 1893, é conhecida por sua representação emocionalmente carregada e estilisticamente única, capturando uma figura angustiada contra um céu turbulentamente colorido. \\"O Grito\\" é uma das imagens mais conhecidas na arte moderna e tem várias versões criadas por Munch ao longo dos anos, utilizando diferentes técnicas e mídias."},{"question":"「ら抜き言葉」ってダメですか。","answer":"一時期、日本語の乱れの象徴として叩かれましたが、ダメじゃないですね。文化庁の調査でもありましたが、「ら抜き言葉」をつかう人はもはや多数派です。この「ら抜き言葉」、私たち日本語教師の間では「理由のある現象」です。学習者に「ら抜き言葉」で質問されたときはこのように例文を挙げて説明しています。例えば、この３文を見てください。①ネズミがネコに食べられる。②社長が朝食を食べられる。③私はパクチーが食べられる。この「～られる」という言い方は、可能表現と尊敬表現の両方で使われる少々厄介なものなのです。もちろん、助詞で用法の区別もつきますが・・・ちなみに、①は受け身、②は尊敬表現、③は可能表現です。「見られる」、「食べられる」のように「ら」がある動詞では、それが可能表現か、尊敬表現かの区別がつかないので、その区別を付けるために可能のとき「ら」の脱落が起きています。日本語を勉強する外国人にとっては「食べれる」は「ら」がないから可能表現だとなれば、分かりやすいのではないかと思います。"},{"question":"Qual é o papel de um economista?","answer":"Um economista estuda a economia e fornece análises e previsões econômicas."},{"question":"¿Cuál es la respuesta correcta a esta pregunta? ¿La Torre del Reloj Abraj Al-Bait es el edificio más antiguo de Corea del Sur?","answer":"La respuesta correcta para esta pregunta es: No"},{"question":"电风扇的使用注意事项有哪些？","answer":"答：在使用电风扇时，应注意不要让儿童接触到旋转的叶片；不要在湿润的环境下使用；不要让风扇长时间无人看管运行；定期清理灰尘以保持良好的运行效果。"},{"question":"Tungkol saan ang talatang ito? \\"May dalawang seksyion ang mabilisang daanan sa North Luzon Expressway: ang seksyiong bukas (open section) at seksyiong nakasara (closed section). Ang seksyiong bukas (sa loob ng Kalakhang Maynila) ay nagkakarga ng pantay na bayarin batay sa uri ng sasakyan (vehicle class). Ginagamit ang sistemang ito para mabawasan ang dami ng mga tarangkahang pambayad o toll barrier (at ng mga kaugnay nitong balakid pantrapiko) sa loob ng Kamaynilaan. Ang seksyiong nakasara ay nakabatay sa layo (o distansiya), at nagsisingil ito batay sa uri ng sasakyan at nilakbay na layo. Noong minodernisa ang mabilisang daanan, inumpisa ang isang sistemang de-kuryente sa pangongolekta ng mga bayad (electronic toll collection o ETC) para sa mga sasakyang Class 1 upang maipabilis ang mga transaksyon sa mga toll booth. Sa kabilang banda, mga prepaid magnetic card naman ang itinakda para sa mga sasakyang Class 2 at 3. Ang mga ito ay pinalitan na ngayon ng isang pinagsamang sistemang ETC na pinapatakbo ng Easytrip Services Corporation. Magmula noong Oktubre 1, 2011, lahat ng mga bayarin (na pinapakita sa ibaba) ay may kasamang 12% VAT (Value Added Tax).\\"","answer":"Tungkol sa sistema ng pagbabayad ng toll fees sa North Luzon Expressway ang talata. Inilalarawan sa talata kung paano kinakalkula at kung paano babayarin ang toll fee ng bawat sinong gumagamit ng expressway. Inilalarawan din ang mga naging pagbabago sa sistemang ito sa paglipas ng panahon."},{"question":"Andininy voalohany: Nanatrika ny atrikasa momba ny varotra nomerika i Sarah.Andininy faharoa: Nahazo mari-pankasitrahana i Sarah tamin'ny fahavitan'ny atrikasa momba ny varotra nomerika.Mifanaraka ve ireo fehezanteny roa ireo?","answer":" Eny, mifanaraka izy ireo."},{"question":"भारताच्या राष्ट्रध्वजाच्या लांबी आणि रुंदीचे गुणोत्तर किती आहे?","answer":"भारताच्या राष्ट्रध्वजाच्या लांबी आणि रुंदीचे गुणोत्तर ३:२ आहे."},{"question":"නිව් යෝර්ක් ජයන්ට් සහ නිව් යෝර්ක් ජෙට්ස් අතර ඇති වෙනස්කම් මොනවාද?","answer":"නිව් යෝර්ක් ජයන්ට් (New York Giants) සහ නිව් යෝර්ක් ජෙට්ස් (New York Jets) යන දෙකම නිව් යෝර්ක් මෙට්‍රොපොලිටන් ප්‍රදේශයේ ක්‍රීඩා කරන එන්එෆ්එල් හි වෘත්තීය පාපන්දු කණ්ඩායම් වේ. කණ්ඩායම් දෙකම ක්‍රීඩා කරන්නේ NJ හි East Rutherford හි Giants ක්‍රීඩාංගනය ලෙස හැඳින්වූ MetLife ක්‍රීඩාංගනයේ ය. ඔවුන්ගේ රසික පිරිස් මූලික වශයෙන් නිව් ජර්සි සහ නිව් යෝර්ක් හි ජීවත් වෙති. ජෙට් ප්‍රාථමික වර්ණය කොළ වන අතර යෝධයන් නිල් ය."},{"question":"Qual agora famoso chef de TV começou a cozinhar aos oito anos de idade no pub de seus pais, 'The Cricketers, em Clavering, Essex?","answer":"Jamie Oliver é um fenômeno global quando se trata de comida e ativismo. Há mais de dezessete anos, dedica-se a levar cozinha acessível para milhares de pessoas perderem o medo de preparar os próprios alimentos do zero. Jamie começou a cozinhar no pub de seus pais, The Cricketers, em Clavering, Essex, aos oito anos de idade e desde então já trabalhou com alguns dos mais renomados chefs do mundo. Jamie mora em Londres e Essex com sua esposa, Jools, e seus filhos, Poppy, Daisy, Petal, Buddy e River."},{"question":"Wani yare mafi tsufa da dadewa a Najeriya?","answer":"Harshen Hausa shi ne mafi dadewa da aka san rubuce-rubuce a Afirka ta Yamma, tun kafin 1000 C.E."},{"question":"هل يشكل التغير المناخي خطرا علي القطبين المتجمدين ؟","answer":"نعم"},{"question":"قم بالإجابة على السؤال:  من هي أم تاج في فلم عين الجبل ؟من النص التالي: تدور أحداث الفيلم حول الضابط فايز الذي يجد طفل رضيع في الشارع وضعته أمه هناك لتخفيه من أبيه المجرم الذي أراد أن يقتله انتقاما من أمه التي أخذت عليه حكم نفقة وذهبت إلى منزل الضابط فريد لتوصيه أن يعتنى بالولد ثم ماتت وقبض على أبيه ربى فايز وزوجته كريمة الولد مع أولادهما وسمياه تاج ..","answer":"حسناً، بإستخدام النص السابق الإجابة هي: كريمة الولد."},{"question":" मुख्य पुराणे एकूण किती आहेत ?","answer":"एकूण अठरा मुख्य पुराणे आहेत."},{"question":"Mei Shigenobu er mor til den japanske journalist Fusako Shigenobu. Sætning 2: Fusako Shigenobu er mor til den japanske borger Mei Shigenobu, en journalist. Spørgsmål: Har sætning 1 og sætning 2 samme betydning? - Ja eller nej?","answer":"Nej, de to sætninger har ikke samme betydning."},{"question":"కింది అపరిచిత వచన భాగం చదివి, ప్రశ్నకు సరైన జవాబు గుర్తించి, రాయండి.“1940 ప్రాంతంలో తెలంగాణలో స్త్రీల చైతన్యం కొంత వికసించింది. లేడీ హైదరీ క్లబ్, సోదరీ సమాజం, ఆంధ్ర యువతీమండలి, ఆంధ్రమహాసభ మొదలైన సమాజాలు ఏర్పడి, సమావేశాల ద్వారా స్త్రీలను చైతన్యవంతులను చేశాయి. – రత్నదేశాయి తన సాహిత్యం ద్వారా గాంధీ సిద్ధాంతాలను ప్రచారం చేశారు. వితంతువుల కోసం వసతిగృహాలు ఏర్పాటు చేశారు. అనేకమంది రచయితలు, రచయిత్రులు పత్రికల ద్వారా స్త్రీలలో చైతన్యం కలిగించారు. సుమిత్రాదేవి, ఈశ్వరీబాయి, సంగం లక్ష్మీబాయి మొదలైనవాళ్ళు సంఘసంస్కరణకు కృషిచేశారు. అఘోరనాథ ‘ఛటోపాధ్యాయగారి భార్య వసుంధరా దేవి గారు, నాంపల్లిలో బాలికల కోసం ‘పాఠశాలను ప్రారంభించారు. ఈమె సరోజినీ నాయుడు గారి తల్లి.గాంధీ సిద్ధాంతాలను ప్రచారం చేసిన మహిళ ఎవరు?","answer":"గాంధీ సిద్ధాంతాలను ప్రచారం చేసిన మహిళ రత్నదేశాయి."},{"question":"Ẹsan awọn ẹgbọn mi ti wọn pa ni mo fẹẹ gba ti mo fi yinbọn pa ọmọ Mọdakẹkẹ- Ṣina","answer":"Kọmiṣanna ọlọpaa nipinlẹ Ọṣun, Wale Ọlọkọde, ti ṣafihan awọn afurasi mẹrin ti ọwọ tẹ lori wahala iṣekupani to waye lawọn abule kan niluu Mọdakẹkẹ laipẹ yii.A oo ranti pe eeyan meje lo ku iku airotẹlẹ laarin oṣu karun-un si oju kẹjọ, ọdun yii, lagbegbe abule kan ti wọn n pe ni Alapata, awọn eeyan ilu Mọdakẹkẹ ati Ifẹ ni wọn si n da’ko nibẹ.Diẹ lo ku ki iṣẹlẹ yii da ogun abẹle miiran silẹ laarin ilu Mọdakẹkẹ ati Ifẹ, ṣe lawọn ọdọ ilu mejeeji n naka aleebu sira wọn lori iṣẹlẹ naa, kia ni Ọọni Ifẹ, Ọba Adeyẹye Ogunwusi, atijọba ipinlẹ Ọṣun si n pariwo pe ki awọn araalu mejeeji ṣe ṣuuru nitori aṣiri awọn amookunṣika naa yoo tu.L’Ọjọruu, Wẹsidee, ọsẹ yii, ni Kọmiṣanna Ọlọkọde ṣafihan awọn mẹrin ti ọwọ ti tẹ lori iṣẹlẹ naa, to si sọ pe iṣẹ n lọ lọwọ lati mu awọn yooku. Awọn afurasi naa ni Akingbala Ọlakunle, Owoniyi Ṣẹgun, Daramọla Muideen ati Ṣina Adeyẹmi.Nigba ti Ṣina n ba ALAROYE sọrọ, o ṣalaye pe ọmọ bibi agbegbe Okerewe, niluu Ileefẹ, loun, ati pe iṣẹ agbẹ loun yan laayo.O ni ọjọ ti pẹ ti wahala abẹnu ti maa n waye laarin awọn eeyan ilu mejeeji labule naa, ati pe ẹgbọn oun ọkunrin mẹta ati obinrin kan ni wọn ti padanu ẹmi wọn sinu iṣẹlẹ naa latẹyinwa.Ṣina sọ siwaju pe nigba ti awọn eeyan ilu Mọdakẹkẹ tun de lọjọ naa ni inu bi oun pẹlu iku awọn ẹgbọn oun, idi si niyẹn toun fi gbe ibọn sakabula, ti oun si yin in soke, lai mọ pe yoo ba ẹni to ba lọjọ naa, ti iyẹn si ku loju-ẹsẹ.Kọmiṣanna ọlọpaa ti waa ṣeleri pe ni kete ti awọn ba ti pari iwadii lori awọn afurasi naa ni wọn yoo foju bale-ẹjọ lati sọ ohun ti wọn mọ nipa iṣẹlẹ iṣekupani naa."},{"question":"নিচের প্রশ্নের উত্তর দাও:ইউরোপীয় শক্তিগুলি সাধারণত উপনিবেশিক অঞ্চলগুলি নিয়ন্ত্রণ করার জন্য কী করত?","answer":"উপনিবেশিক অঞ্চলগুলি নিয়ন্ত্রণ করার জন্য  পরোক্ষ নিয়ম পছন্দ করেছিল|"},{"question":"السؤال: كم عدد جزر اليابان؟","answer":"الإجابة: أكثر من 4,000 جزيرة صغيرة."},{"question":"வினா: காமன்வெல்த் விளையாட்டுப் போட்டிகள் முதன்முதலில் எப்போது நடைபெற்றது?","answer":"விடை: 1930"},{"question":"வினா: உடலின் வெப்பநிலையைக் கட்டுப்படுத்த யானை எந்தப் பகுதியைப் பயன்படுத்துகிறது?","answer":"விடை: காது"},{"question":"Hãy hoàn thiện đoạn văn sau: Ông Nguyễn Ngọc Hà, Chủ tịch UBND phường Đồng Tâm (TP.Yên Bái, tỉnh Yên Bái) cho biết, người dân vừa phát hiện 1 người đàn ông tử vong trong tư thế treo cổ tại nhà chị gái. Theo đó, khoảng 19 giờ ngày 30/7, người dân phát hiện ông Hoàng Văn H (SN 1969, trú tại phường Yên Thịnh, TP.Yên Bái) tử vong trong tư thế treo cổ tại nhà bà Hoàng Thị B (thuộc tổ 1, đường Trần Quốc Toản, phường Đồng Tâm, TP.Yên Bái). Được biết, nạn nhân là em ruột của bà Hoàng Thị B. Sau khi phát hiện sự việc, người dân đã ngay lập tức","answer":"báo cho cơ quan chức năng. Theo người thân của nạn nhân, bà B sinh sống và làm việc tại miền Nam, thỉnh thoảng mới về nên nhờ ông H trông nhà hộ. 8 giờ sáng 30/7, ông H vẫn gọi điện nói chuyện với chị gái của mình. \\"Việc anh H tử vong có thể là do tự tử vì anh này có tiền sử bị trầm cảm\\", ông Hà cho biết thêm. Hiện, cơ quan Công an đang phối hợp cùng các đơn vị chức năng để điều tra nguyên nhân của vụ việc."},{"question":"வினா : இந்தியாவில் வடகிழக்கில் அமைந்துள்ள மலைத்தொடரின் பெயர்?","answer":" விடை :  பூர்வாச்சல்"},{"question":"ICT යන අකුරු පෙනී සිටින්නේ කුමක් සඳහාද ?","answer":"ICT යන අකුරු පෙනී සිටින්නේ \\"Information and Communication Technologies (තොරතුරු සහ සන්නිවේදන තාක්ෂණය)\\" යන්න සඳහාය."},{"question":"ਪਰਸਰਣ ਕਿਰਿਆ ਕਿੰਨੇ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ ਦੀ ਹੁੰਦੀ ਹੈ?","answer":"ਪਰਸਰਣ ਕਿਰਿਆ ਤਿੰਨ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ ਦੀ ਹੁੰਦੀ ਹੈ-(ਉ) ਅਲਪ ਪਰਸਰਣ-ਜੇ ਕੋਸ਼ਿਕਾ ਨੂੰ ਪਤਲੇ ਘੋਲ ਵਾਲੇ ਮਾਧਿਅਮ ਵਿੱਚ ਰੱਖਿਆ ਜਾਵੇ ਤਾਂ ਪਾਣੀ ਪਰਸਰਣ ਵਿਧੀ ਨਾਲ ਕੋਸ਼ਿਕਾ ਵਿੱਚ ਚਲਿਆ ਜਾਵੇਗਾ | ਪਤਲੇ ਘੋਲ ਵਿੱਚ ਨਮਕ ਜਾਂ ਚੀਨੀ ਜਾਂ ਕਿਸੇ ਹੋਰ ਲੂਣ ਦੀ ਮਾਤਰਾ ਘੱਟ ਅਤੇ ਪਾਣੀ ਦੀ ਮਾਤਰਾ ਵਧੇਰੇ ਹੁੰਦੀ ਹੈ । ਪਾਣੀ ਦੇ ਅਣੂ ਕੋਸ਼ਿਕਾ ਤਿੱਲੀ ਦੇ ਦੋਵੇਂ ਪਾਸੇ ਆਉਣ ਜਾਣ ਲਈ ਮੁਕਤ ਹੁੰਦੇ ਹਨ । ਪਰ ਕੋਸ਼ਿਕਾ ਦੇ ਅੰਦਰ ਜਾਣ ਵਾਲੇ ਪਾਣੀ ਦੀ ਮਾਤਰਾ ਕੋਸ਼ਿਕਾ ਤੋਂ ਬਾਹਰ ਆਉਣ ਵਾਲੇ ਪਾਣੀ ਦੀ ਮਾਤਰਾ ਤੋਂ ਵੱਧ ਹੋਵੇਗੀ । ਸਿੱਟੇ ਵਜੋਂ ਕੋਸ਼ਿਕਾ ਫੁੱਲਣ ਲੱਗੇਗੀ | ਪਾਣੀ ਵਿੱਚ ਡੁੱਬੀ ਸੌਗੀ ਜਾਂ ਖੁਬਾਨੀ ਇਸੇ ਕਾਰਨ ਫੁੱਲ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ ।(ਅ) ਸਮਪਰਸਰਣ-ਜੇ ਕੋਸ਼ਿਕਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਅਜਿਹੇ ਘੋਲ ਮਾਧਿਅਮ ਵਿੱਚ ਰੱਖਿਆ ਜਾਵੇ ਜਿਸ ਵਿੱਚ ਬਾਹਰਲੀ ਅਤੇ ਕੋਸ਼ਿਕਾ ਵਿੱਚਲੀ ਸੰਘਣਤਾ ਬਿਲਕੁਲ ਬਰਾਬਰ ਹੋਵੇ ਤਾਂ ਕੋਸ਼ਿਕਾ ਤਿੱਲੀ ਵਿੱਚੋਂ ਪਾਣੀ ਦੀ ਕੋਈ ਸ਼ੁੱਧ ਗਤੀ ਨਹੀਂ ਹੋਵੇਗੀ । ਜਲ ਕੋਸ਼ਿਕਾ ਵਿੱਚ ਆਉਂਦਾ-ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ ਪਰ ਜਿੰਨੀ ਮਾਤਰਾ ਅੰਦਰ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ ਓਨੀ ਹੀ ਬਾਹਰ ਆ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ ।(ੲ) ਅਤੀਪਰਸਰਣ-ਜਦੋਂ ਕੋਸ਼ਿਕਾ ਦੇ ਬਾਹਰ ਵਾਲਾ ਘੋਲ ਕੋਸ਼ਿਕਾ ਦੇ ਅੰਦਰਲੇ ਘੋਲ ਨਾਲੋਂ ਗਾੜ੍ਹਾ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ ਤਾਂ ਪਾਣੀ ਪਰਸਰਣ ਦੁਆਰਾ ਕੋਸ਼ਿਕਾਂ ਵਿੱਚੋਂ ਬਾਹਰ ਆ ਜਾਵੇਗਾ । ਇਸ ਸਥਿਤੀ ਵਿੱਚ ਕੋਸ਼ਿਕਾ ਵਿੱਚੋਂ ਵਧੇਰੇ ਪਾਣੀ ਬਾਹਰ ਆ ਜਾਵੇਗਾ ਅਤੇ ਘੱਟ ਪਾਣੀ ਅੰਦਰ ਜਾਵੇਗਾ ।"},{"question":"Como é feito o ácido sulfúrico?","answer":"O ácido sulfúrico é um importante produto industrial, e é produzido a partir do enxofre, oxigênio e água, por meio do processo de contato tradicional, pelo processo úmido, pelo processo de câmara de chumbo, além de outros métodos menos comuns. "},{"question":"Ичек-боору катуу","answer":"Аябай көзүнөн жаш чыкканча күлүү, күлкүсүн токтото албай ыкшуу.Куудулдардын сахнадагы оюнунан көрүүчүлөр ичек–боору катканча күлүштү."},{"question":"Ọwọ tẹ ayederu ọlọpaa ati sifu difẹnsi kan n’Ibogun","answer":"Nitori wọn pe ara wọn ni ọlọpaa lai jẹ pe agbofinro ni wọn loootọ, awọn ọlọpaa ipinlẹ Ogun ti ko awọn ọkunrin meji yii, Tajudeen Bankọle ati Fawọyi Rotimi, satimọle, bẹẹ naa ni wọn si ju Oduọla Abiọla toun naa n wọṣọ sifu difẹnsi kiri lai ki i ṣe ara awọn oṣiṣẹ ajọ naa si gbaga.Ọjọ kẹtalelogun, oṣu kẹfa, lọwọ ba awọn meji to pe ara wọn lọlọpa, Ibogun, nijọba ibilẹ Ifọ, ni wọn ti mu wọn lẹyin tawọn mejeeji lọọ halẹ mọ ọkunrin olotẹẹli kan, Ibikunle Idowu, pe bi ko ba fawọn lowo tawọn n beere lọwọ rẹ, awọn yoo gbe e wọ mọto tawọn gbe wa, o pari fun un niyẹn.Ọkunrin olotẹẹli naa ko fẹẹ fun wọn lowo kankan, wọn ko si yee dunkooko mọ ọn pe awọn yoo fagidi gbe e lọ, niyẹn ba pe DPO teṣan ọlọpaa Ibogun, CSP Samuel Ọladele, lawọn ọlọpaa ba de otẹẹli naa, wọn si ba awọn ayederu ọlọpaa naa nibẹ, ni wọn ba ko wọn.Nigba tawọn ọlọpaa fọrọ wa wọn lẹnu wo, ọkan ninu wọn ṣalaye pe ọlọpaa loun tẹlẹ ki wọn too le oun danu nitori aṣemaṣe toun ṣe. Ẹni keji sọ pe oun maa n ta ọlọpaa lolobo lori iṣelẹ ni.Wọn ṣalaye siwaju pe awọn n kọja lọ lagbegbe otẹẹli naa lawọn ri i pe epo ti tan ninu ọkọ awọn, ko si sowo tawọn yoo fi repo lawọn ṣe fẹẹ dọgbọn gbowo lọwọ olotẹẹli yii, to fi waa di wahala sawọn lọrun bayii.Iwe aṣẹ iyẹlewo meji to jẹ tọlọpaa ni wọn ba lọwọ awọn ayederu ọlọpaa meji yii.Ni ti ayederu Sifu Difẹnsi, Oduọla Abiọla, ẹni ọdun mokanlelogbon, foonu kan ti wọn ji lawọn ọlọpaa tọpinpin ẹ de ọdọ ọkunrin yii, n’Ibara, l’Abẹokuta.Nigba ti wọn mu un, aṣọ iṣẹ awọn Sifu lo wọ, bẹ́ẹ̀ ki i ṣe ara wọn. Bi ẹsun tiẹ ṣe di meji nìyẹn.Oduọla ṣalaye ibi to ti ri yunifọọmu aawọn sifu, o loun ji i lọdọ oṣiṣẹ ajọ naa kan ni.Gbogbo awọn tọwọ ba yii ni wọn ti wa nibi ti wọn ti n sọ tẹnu wọn fọlọpaa, ti wọn yoo si gba ibẹ dele-ẹjọ."},{"question":"¿Cuánto tiempo tarda la sangre en dar una vuelta completa al cuerpo?","answer":"La sangre tarda aproximadamente 20 a 30 segundos en dar una vuelta completa al cuerpo humano. Esto depende de la frecuencia cardíaca y del estado de salud del individuo."},{"question":"文中の主な言葉を見つけて、その内容を説明しなさい。 アメリカで、日本語を勉強している高校生たちが出るクイズの大会がありました。24の高校から集まった160人ぐらいが、日本の文化や歴史についての問題に答えました。14日の決勝では、ことわざを使って文章を考える問題が出ました。高校生は「『聞くはいっときの恥、聞かぬは一生の恥』というように、質問があったら早く先生に聞いたほうがいいです」と上手な日本語で答えました。留学生について調べる団体によると、2018年度にアメリカから日本に留学した人は9000人ぐらいでした。しかし新型コロナウイルスの問題で少なくなって、2020年度は100人ぐらいでした。17歳の高校生は「将来、日本の文化を翻訳する仕事がしたいです」と話していました。","answer":"文にある主な言葉とその内容はこちらです。- クイズ: 1）質問を出して、相手に答えさせる遊び。- 大会: 1）多くの人が集まる会。2）ある組織の全員が集まる会。- 決勝: 1）最後の勝ち負けを決めること。2）第一位のものを決めること。- ことわざ: 1）昔から言い伝えられている、ためになる短い言葉。「急がば回れ」「まかぬ種は生えぬ」など。- 聞くはいっときの恥、聞かぬは一生の恥: 1）知らないことを聞くのは、そのとき恥ずかしいが、聞かないで知らないままだと一生恥ずかしい思いをする。- 団体: 1）大勢の人の集まり。2）同じ目的を持った人々の集まり。- 年度: 1）仕事の都合で決めた一年の期間。ふつう四月一日に始まり、翌年の三月三十一日に終わる。- 留学: 1）外国に行って、勉強すること。"},{"question":"بناء: تشييد. لديهما علاقة معينة. اختر كلمتين لهما علاقة مشابهة:(أ) إعدام: قتل(ب)إصلاح: تعليم(ج) موز: فاكهة(د) تذكر: فهم","answer":"الإجابة (ب) إصلاح: تعليم، حيث إن التشييد يحتاج بناء، والتعليم يحتاج إصلاح."},{"question":"Aşağıdaki ifadeyi tamamlayın:Madison Hubbell (d. 24 Şubat, 1991) Amerikalı buz patenci. Kardeşi Keiffer Hubbell ile birlikte buz dansında yarışmaktadır. Çift 2006-2007 Junior Grand Prix Finali şampiyonu ve","answer":"2009 ABD dördüncüsüdür."},{"question":"Trong tuyển tập \\"Thi nhân Việt Nam\\", nhà thơ Tản Đà được trích đăng các bài thơ nào?","answer":"nhà thơ có hai bài 'Thề non nước' và 'Tống biệt'Trong các tuyển tập thơ ca, phê bình văn học, Tản Đà là tác giả chiếm vị trí quan trọng. Trong văn đàn công khai của văn học Việt Nam hơn ba thập niên đầu của thế kỷ 20, Tản Đà nổi lên như một hiện tượng vừa đột xuất, vừa độc đáp, vừa dồi dào năng lực sáng tạo.Trong tuyển tập Thi nhân Việt Nam (1932-1941), trang sách đầu tiên, tác giả Hoài Thanh - Hoài Chân viết về Tản Đà với bài Cung chiêu anh hồn Tản Đà. Bài viết có đoạn: \\"Tiên sinh còn giữ được của thời trước cái phong thái vững vàng, cái cốt cách ung dung. Tiên sinh đã đi qua giữa cái hỗn độn của xã hội Việt Nam đầu thế kỷ 20 với tấm lòng bình thản một người thời trước\\".Hoài Thanh đã dành cho Tản Đà những lời khen tặng danh giá nhất, gọi ông là \\"con người của hai thế kỷ\\". Với tâm hồn lãng mạn, ý tưởng \\"ngông nghênh, đậm cá tính\\", ông được đánh giá là người chuẩn bị cho sự ra đời của thơ mới trong nền văn học Việt Nam, là \\"gạch nối giữa hai thời kỳ văn học cổ điển và hiện đại\\".Ngoài bài thơ Thề non nước, tác giả Thi nhân Việt Nam trích đăng bài thơ Tống biệt của Tản Đà:Lá đào rơi rắc lối Thiên Thai,Suối tiễn, oanh đưa, những ngậm ngùi!Nửa năm tiên cảnh,Một bước trần ai,Ước cũ duyên thừa có thế thôi.Đá mòn, rêu nhạt,Nước chảy, huê trôi,Cái hạc bay lên vút tận trời!Trời đất từ đây xa cách mãi.Cửa động,Đầu non,Đường lối cũ,Ngàn năm thơ thẩn bóng trăng chơi.Theo GS Lê Trí Viễn trong sách Đến với thơ hay (Nhà xuất bản Giáo dục, 2005), bài thơ nằm trong vở ca kịch Thiên Thai (1917-1917), sau rút ra in vào tập Khối tình con (quyển thứ hai) như một bài thơ độc lập.Bài Tống biệt là lời hai nàng tiên hát tiễn đưa hai chàng Lưu Thần, Nguyễn Triệu ở núi Thiên Thai (tỉnh Chiết Giang, Trung Quốc) xuống núi từ biệt cõi tiên, đi về cõi trần. Lời bài thơ viết theo điệu Hoa phong lạc trong từ khúc của Trung Quốc."},{"question":"වර්තමානයේ ලෝකයේ ප්‍රධානතම කහ නිෂ්පාදකයා වන්නේ කුමන රට ද?","answer":"වර්තමානයේ ලෝකයේ ප්‍රධානතම කහ නිෂ්පාදනය කරන රට ඉන්දියාව යි."},{"question":"आयुर्वेदात कर्करोगावर औषध आहे का ?","answer":"आयुर्वेदात कर्करोग नावाच्या आजाराचे वर्णन केले नसले तरी, या आजाराचा संबंध आयुर्वेदात सांगितलेल्या गाठी, ग्रंथींशी करता येऊ शकतो. आज ज्याला कॅन्सर समजले जाते त्या वर्गात यापैकी कशाचाही समावेश केला जाऊ शकत नाही असे आम्हाला व्यक्तीशः वाटते, त्यामुळे या आजाराचे नाव ठरवताना योग्य ती काळजी घेतली पाहिजे.या आजारावर यशस्वी उपचार करण्यासाठी त्याचे नाव निश्चित करणे आवश्यक नाही. यावर आयुर्वेदाचा पूर्णत: विश्वास आहे.आयुर्वेदात रोगाचे मूळ कारण समजून घेणे आणि त्याचे निदान करून उपचार सुरू करणे याला महत्त्व दिले जाते.कर्करोगाच्या रुग्णांना वैद्यकीय उपचार देताना आपण याच पद्धतीचे अनुसरण गेल्या अनेक वर्षांपासून करत आहोत आणि त्याचे परिणामही आशादायक आहेत. आयुर्वेदाच्या तत्त्वांनुसार, आपण दोष, धातु, मल, उपधातु आणि ओजांचे परीक्षण करतो आणि त्यात होणारे बदल  पूर्णतः समजून घेऊन सर्व प्रकारच्या कर्करोगाच्या रुग्णांवर आपण यशस्वीरीत्या वैद्यकीय उपचार  करण्याचे योग्य प्रकारे नियोजन करतो. तुमच्या प्रश्नाचे थोडक्यात उत्तर द्यायचे झाले तर आपण असे म्हणू शकतो की आयुर्वेदात कर्करोगावर औषधे आहेत. आयुर्वेदात कर्करोगाच्या रुग्णांवर उपचार करण्याची पद्धत पारंपारीक पद्धतीच्या उपचारांपेक्षा  वेगळी आहे. एकाच प्रकारच्या कर्करोगाने ग्रस्त असलेल्या सर्व रुग्णांसाठी, आयुर्वेद पारंपारिक शास्त्रांप्रमाणे उपचार पद्धती वापरत नाही. प्रत्येक रुग्णाच्या आजाराच्या उपचारात सामाविष्ट असलेल्या सर्व घटकांची चाचणी घेतली जाते आणि त्यांनतर थेरपीची/ उपचाराची पद्धत ठरवली जाते. आयुर्वेदामध्ये उपचारापूर्वी रुग्णाला असलेल्या रोगाची कारणे तपासली जातात.  रुग्णाच्या शरीरातील दोष आणि  धातू यांच्यात झालेला बदल व त्यांची नैसर्गिक रचना तसेच इतर घटकांचा विचार केला जातो.म्हणूनच या थेरपीला वैयक्तिक उपचार पद्धती/औषध म्हणतात. याच कारणास्तव या उपचार पद्धतीला वैयक्तीक वैद्यकीय शास्त्र पद्धत म्हणून ओळखले जाते."},{"question":"How do Sri Lankan traditional dances contribute to cultural identity?","answer":"Sri Lankan traditional dances are integral to the island's cultural identity, contributing in several ways:Expressing Heritage: Traditional dances showcase the rich cultural heritage, reflecting stories, rituals, and myths.Preserving Traditions: Dances like Kandyan and Sabaragamuwa contribute to the preservation of regional traditions.Symbolic Meaning: Movements, costumes, and gestures in traditional dances carry symbolic meanings, connecting to cultural narratives.Ceremonial Significance: Dances are often performed during ceremonies, festivals, and religious events, reinforcing cultural practices.Community Bonding: Participation in traditional dances fosters a sense of community and shared identity, emphasizing the diversity within Sri Lanka's cultural tapestry."},{"question":"Apakah maksud 'beralih akal' ? Nyatakan satu contoh ayat bagi peribahasa tersebut.","answer":"Ia bermaksud berubah fikiran atau pendapat. Contoh ayat: Semalam dia bersetuju dengan cadangan saya, tetapi hari ini dia beralih akal pula."},{"question":"\\"Niandry adiny iray aho vao nahita ahy ny dokotera, nahakivy.\\" Inona ny fihetseham-po raketin'io fanambarana io?","answer":"Ity fanambarana ity dia maneho fihetseham-po ratsy. Sorena ilay olona noho ny fotoana niandrasany."},{"question":"Qual é a capital de Comores?","answer":"Moroni."},{"question":"Given the following context “Yes, I thought I was going to lose the baby.” “I was scared too,” he stated, sincerity flooding his eyes. “Youwere ?” “Yes, of course. Why do you even ask?” “This baby wasn’t exactly planned for.” and the Target sentence: “Do you honestly think that I would want you to have a _ ?” predict the target word","answer":"Target word: miscarriage"},{"question":"ਵਾਰਾਂ ਭਾਈ ਗੁਰਦਾਸ : ਵਾਰ ੧ ਪਉੜੀ ੨੫ ਪੰ. ੧ਤੀਰਥਾਂ ਪਰ ਪ੍ਰੇਮ ਦੀ ਸੁੰਞਬਾਬਾ ਆਇਆ ਤੀਰਥੈ ਤੀਰਥ ਪੁਰਬ ਸਭੇ ਫਿਰਿ ਦੇਖੈ।ਪੂਰਬ ਧਰਮ ਬਹੁ ਕਰਮ ਕਰਿ ਭਾਉ ਭਗਤਿ ਬਿਨੁ ਕਿਤੇ ਨ ਲੇਖੈ।ਭਾਉ ਨ ਬ੍ਰਹਮੈ ਲਿਖਿਆ ਚਾਰਿ ਬੇਦਿ ਸਿੰਮ੍ਰਿਤ ਪੜ੍ਹਿ ਪੇਖੈ।ਢੂੰਡੀ ਸਗਲੀ ਪ੍ਰਿਥਵੀ ਸਤਿਜੁਗਿ ਆਦਿ ਦੁਆਪਰਿ ਤ੍ਰੇਤੈ।ਕਲਿਜੁਗਿ ਧੰਧੂਕਾਰ ਹੈ ਭਰਮਿ ਭੁਲਾਈ ਬਹੁ ਬਿਧਿ ਭੇਖੈ।ਭੇਖੀ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਨ ਪਾਈਐ ਆਪੁ ਗਵਾਏ ਰੂਪ ਨ ਰੇਖੈ।ਗੁਰਮੁਖਿ ਵਰਨੁ ਅਵਰਨ ਹੋਇ ਨਿਵ ਚਲਣਾ ਗੁਰ ਸਿਖਿ ਵਿਸੇਖੈ।ਤਾ ਕਛੁ ਘਾਲਿ ਪਵੈ ਦਰਿ ਲੇਖੈ ॥੨੫॥","answer":"ਬਾਬਾ (ਨਾਨਕ) ਤੀਰਥ ਸਥਾਨਾਂ 'ਤੇ ਆਏ ਅਤੇ ਉਥੇ ਸਮਾਗਮਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਹਿੱਸਾ ਲੈ ਕੇ ਉਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਦਾ ਧਿਆਨ ਨਾਲ ਦੇਖਿਆ।ਲੋਕ ਰਸਮਾਂ ਨਿਭਾਉਣ ਵਿੱਚ ਰੁੱਝੇ ਹੋਏ ਸਨ ਪਰ ਪ੍ਰੇਮ ਭਗਤੀ ਤੋਂ ਸੱਖਣੇ ਹੋਣ ਕਾਰਨ ਉਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਦਾ ਕੋਈ ਲਾਭ ਨਹੀਂ ਹੋਇਆ।ਵੇਦਾਂ ਅਤੇ ਸਿਮ੍ਰਿਤੀਆਂ ਨੂੰ ਪੜ੍ਹ ਕੇ ਪਤਾ ਲੱਗਦਾ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਬ੍ਰਹਮਾ ਨੇ ਵੀ ਪਿਆਰ ਦੀ ਭਾਵਨਾ ਬਾਰੇ ਕਿਤੇ ਨਹੀਂ ਲਿਖਿਆ।ਇਹੀ ਪਤਾ ਲਗਾਉਣ ਲਈ ਸਤਿਯੁਗ, ਤ੍ਰੇਤਾ ਦਵਾਪਰ ਆਦਿ ਦਾ ਪਰਦਾਫਾਸ਼ ਕੀਤਾ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ।ਕਲਿਯੁਗ ਵਿਚ ਘੁੱਪ ਹਨੇਰਾ ਪਸਰਿਆ ਹੋਇਆ ਹੈ ਜਿਸ ਵਿਚ ਕਈ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ ਦੇ ਪਾਖੰਡੀ ਤਰੀਕੇ ਸ਼ੁਰੂ ਹੋ ਗਏ ਹਨ।ਪਹਿਰਾਵੇ ਅਤੇ ਭੇਖ ਦੁਆਰਾ ਬੰਦਾ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਤੱਕ ਨਹੀਂ ਪਹੁੰਚ ਸਕਦਾ। ਉਸ ਤੱਕ ਸਵੈ-ਮੁਕਤੀ ਰਾਹੀਂ ਪਹੁੰਚਿਆ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ।ਗੁਰੂ ਦੇ ਸਿੱਖ ਦੀ ਵਿਸ਼ੇਸ਼ਤਾ ਇਹ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਉਹ ਜਾਤ-ਪਾਤ ਦੇ ਘੇਰੇ ਤੋਂ ਪਰੇ ਹੋ ਕੇ ਨਿਮਰਤਾ ਨਾਲ ਅੱਗੇ ਵਧਦਾ ਹੈ।ਤਦੋਂ ਉਸ ਦੀ ਮਿਹਨਤ (ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੇ) ਦਰ ਤੇ ਕਬੂਲ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ।"},{"question":"O que é a Ilha de Fernando de Noronha?","answer":"A Ilha de Fernando de Noronha é um parque marinho nacional brasileiro e uma reserva no Atlântico Sul Equatorial."},{"question":"In welchem Monat beginn traditionell das Oktoberfest?","answer":"September"},{"question":"Mwanamke mzuri anasifa gani?","answer":"Mwanamke mzuri anasifa zifuatazo, tabia ya kuvutia, sura yenye mvuto, maumbile mazuri na mwonekano mzuri katika jamii"},{"question":"Lẹyin ọpọlọpọ miliọnu, awọn Fulani ti tu alaga ijọba ibilẹ Iganna ti wọn gbe silẹ","answer":"Awọn Fulani ti tu alaga ijọba ibile Onidagbasoke Iganna, Ọgbẹni Jacob Ọlayiwọla Adeleke, silẹ lẹyin ti wọn gbowo, ti wọn tun fiya nla jẹ ẹỌjọ Abamẹta, Satide,  lawọn Fulani ajinigbe tu alaga ọhun ati dẹrẹba ẹ ti wọn ji gbe silẹ, lẹyin ti wọn ti lo ọjọ marun-un lọdọ wọn.Ilu Ibadan ni Adeleke n lọ ki wọn too ji awọn mejeeji gbe lọjọ Aiku, Sannde, to kọja yii.ALAROYE gbọ pe, deede aago mẹfa irọlẹ ana ni wọn ri alaga kansu ọhun ati dẹrẹba ẹ ti wọn pe ni Mufu gba pada, lẹyin tawọn Fulani yii ti bii miliọnu marun-un aabọ lọwọ awọn eeyan wọn.Ọkan ninu awọn eeyan agbegbe ọhun to ba wa sọrọ, ṣugbọn to kọ lati darukọ ara ẹ sọ pe awọn Fulani ni wọn ji ọkunrin oloṣelu naa gbe, ati pe ori oke kan ni wọn gbe wọn lọ lagbegbe Ado-Awaye mọ Iṣẹyin. O ni awọn janduku ọhun ko duro soju kan, niṣe ni wọn n rin kiri, ti wọn si fiya jẹ alaga yii pẹlu ẹni keji ẹ.Alaga kansu Iwajọwa, Ọnarebu Akeem Adedibu, ni wọn sọ pe o lọọ gbe alaga ọhun wa ni kete ti wọn tu u silẹ. Bakan naa la gbọ pe awọn ajinigbe yii to meje.Wọn ni ọkunrin oloṣelu yii ti pinnu lati lọọ gba itọju lọsibitu, ki ara ẹ le bọ sipo lẹyin idaamu tawọn Fulani ajinigbe ko ba a.Tẹ o ba gbagbe, igba miliọnu naira lawọn ajinigbe ọhun lawọn fẹẹ gba nigba ti wọn kọkọ ba awọn eeyan Ogbẹni Jacob Ọlayiwọla Adeleke sọrọ lẹyin ti wọn ji i.Ilu Ilua, ni wọn ti kọ lu oun ati dẹrẹba ẹ laarin Ado-Awaye si Okeho. Wọn ni gbogbo igba nirufẹ iṣẹlẹ bẹẹ maa n waye laarin Ado-Awaye, Iganna, Okeho atawọn ibomi-in to sun mọ ọn"},{"question":"別名「花キャベツ」とも言われる野菜は何？","answer":"カリフラワーです。"},{"question":"Берилген суйлөмдү толукта :- \\"Аны көп ... бербе. Өзүңдү ...\\"a) айаай, айааб) аяй, аяв) айай, айаг) аяай, аяа","answer":"Туура жооп  б)Аны көп аяй бербе. Өзүңдү ая."},{"question":"قم بالإجابة على السؤال متى اكتشف الزيت في حقل بقي ؟ من النص التالي: اكتشف الزيت بكميات تجارية في حقل بقيق في نوفمبر 1940م. أغلق الحقل فيما بعد، بسبب ركود في الأعمال أثناء الحرب العالمية الثانية. ثم استؤنف الحفر في عام 1944م ووصل نشاط الأعمال إلى حد دعا في عام 1948م، إلى إقامة مرافق سكنية وصناعية في بقيق، لمساندة برنامج الحفر الكبير. وحتى عام 1950 كان حقل بقيق أحد ثلاثة حقول تضم جميع انتاج شركة أرامكو. عام 1981 تمت توسعة معامل بقيق لتصبح المركز الرئيس في أرامكو لمعالجة الزيت الخام العربي الخفيف والخفيف جدا..","answer":"حسناً بإستخدام النص السابق, اكتشف الزيت في نوفمبر 1940."},{"question":" متحد المال مکتوب څه ته وایې؟","answer":"ځواب: متحد المال مکتوب د هغه مکتوب څخه عبارت دي چې د لوړو مقاماتو لخوا د یو مشترک موضوع په اړه طرحه شوې وي اوټیټو مقاماتو ته ابالغ کیږي."},{"question":"নিম্নলিখিত অনুচ্ছেদের জন্য একটি শিরোনাম তৈরি করুন |ঢাকার একটি হাসপাতালের চিত্র (ফাইল ফটো)সরকারের পক্ষ থেকে আজ জানানো হয়েছে যে দেশের ৬৪টি জেলার মধ্যে ৫৫টি জেলাতেই কোভিড-১৯ রোগী শনাক্ত হয়েছে। স্বাস্থ্য অধিদপ্তরের অতিরিক্ত মহাপরিচালক নাসিমা সুলতানা এক সংবাদ সম্মেলনে বলেছেন, আক্রান্তদের মধ্যে বেশিরভাগই, অর্থাৎ মোট আক্রান্তের ৭৩ শতাংশ, ঢাকা বিভাগের বাসিন্দা। ঢাকা শহরের পরেই বেশি রোগী রয়েছে নারায়ণগঞ্জ জেলায়। এই জেলায় মোট আক্রান্ত ব্যক্তির সংখ্যা ৪৯২ জন। এর মধ্যে নারায়ণগঞ্জ সিটি কর্পোরেশন এলাকায় আছেন ৩৬৪ জন। এখানে মারা গেছেন ৩৫ জন আর সুস্থ হয়েছেন ১৬ জন। এরপরে সংখ্যার দিক থেকে রয়েছে গাজীপুর, কিশোরগঞ্জ এবং নরসিংদীর অবস্থান। ঢাকা বিভাগের ১৩টি জেলায় এখন পর্যন্ত করোনাভাইরাসে আক্রান্ত রোগী শনাক্ত হয়েছে।বাংলাদেশে সুস্থ হওয়ার হার এতো কম কেন?বাংলাদেশে যে হারে করোনাভাইরাস আক্রান্ত রোগী শনাক্ত হচ্ছেন, সেই তুলনায় সুস্থ হওয়ার হার অনেক কম বলে সরকারি পরিসংখ্যানে দেখা যাচ্ছে। বিশ্বের বিভিন্ন দেশে সুস্থ রোগীদের সংখ্যা বৃদ্ধি পেতে শুরু করলেও বাংলাদেশে আক্রান্ত ও মৃত্যুর তুলনায় এখনো তা অনেক কম বলে বিশেষজ্ঞরা মনে করছেন। বুধবার পর্যন্ত বাংলাদেশে কোভিড-১৯ রোগে আক্রান্ত হয়েছেন ৩,৭৭২ জন। তাদের মধ্যে মৃত্যু হয়েছে ১২০ জনের, আর সুস্থ হয়েছেন ৯২ জন। স্বাস্থ্য বিভাগ জানাচ্ছে, গত ২৪ ঘণ্টায় ৩,০৯৬টি নমুনা পরীক্ষা করে ৩৯০ জন আক্রান্তকে শনাক্ত করা হয়েছে, যা পরীক্ষা করা নমুনার প্রায় ১০ শতাংশ।বিষয়টি ব্যাখ্যা করে স্বাস্থ্য অধিদপ্তরের অতিরিক্ত মহাপরিচালক নাসিমা সুলতানা প্রেস ব্রিফিংয়ে বলেন, আসলে যারা কোভিড-১৯ রোগে আক্রান্ত হচ্ছেন, তাদের সুস্থ হতে দীর্ঘ সময় লেগে যায়। ''অনেক সময় উপসর্গ ও লক্ষণ নিয়েই তারা ১৪/১৫ দিন পর্যন্ত থাকেন। তারপরে তাদের এই লক্ষণ বা উপসর্গ কমতে শুরু করে এবং প্রায় মাসখানেক সময় লেগে যায় সম্পূর্ণ সুস্থ হতে।''''একজন ব্যক্তিকে আমরা তখনই সম্পূর্ণ সুস্থ বলবো, যখন পরপর দুইটি পরীক্ষার ফলাফল নেগেটিভ আসবে।''বেশিরভাগ মৃত্যু ঢাকায়স্বাস্থ্য বিভাগের এই উর্ধতন কর্মকর্তা জানান, গত ২৪ ঘণ্টায় যে ১০ জন মারা গেছেন, তাদের মধ্যে সাত জন পুরুষ, আর তিন জন নারী। এদের মধ্যে সাতজন ঢাকার বাসিন্দা। আর বাকি তিনজন ময়মনসিংহ, নারায়ণগঞ্জ এবং টাঙ্গাইলের বাসিন্দা। ","answer":"করোনাভাইরাস: বাংলাদেশের ৬৪ জেলার মধ্যে ৫৫টি জেলাতেই ছড়িয়ে পড়েছে করোনাভাইরাস |"},{"question":"heeg xubinta jirka bini’aadamka ee adeegsata 40% Oksijiinta dhiigga?","answer":"Waa Maskaxda."},{"question":" Sheeg Kumuu ahaa Madaxweynihii ugu horeyey ee afrikan ah Kursiga Madaxtinimada Si xur ah Kaga Dago?","answer":"Wuxu ahaa Aadan Cabdule Cusmaan (Aadan Cadde) kana ahaa dalka soomaaliga."},{"question":"О каком историческом событии рассказывает этот текст: В Великую Отечественную войну, 25 июля 1942 года, город был оккупирован немцами. После освобождения Новочеркасска в 1943 году, военнопленные немцы несколько лет участвовали в восстановительных работах, в том числе на обустройстве спуска Герцена. Был уменьшен уклон его проезжей части, ниже к реке сделали насыпь, которая вывела спуск на уровень новых мостов через Тузлов и железную дорогу. Несмотря на уменьшение наклона, спуск остался достаточно крутым для автомобильного транспорта. Параллельно части спуска проходит трамвайная линия разнонаправленных которая через тузловский мост следует в соцгород. В послевоенные годы спуск Герцена стал связующим звеном между промышленным районом и старой частью Новочеркасска. В советское время, в майские и ноябрьские праздники, колонны трудящихся предприятий из соцгорода поднимались по спуску и вливались в общегородскую демонстрацию. По этому же спуску забастовавшие рабочих НЭВЗа и других заводов, преодолев заслон военных на мосту через Тузлов, направились вверх к центру города, где произошёл расстрел демонстрации.","answer":"Текст повествует о расстреле демонстрации в Новочеркасске"},{"question":"Hãy tiếp tục đoạn văn sau: Tờ Sud Ouest cho rằng thầy trò Didier Tholot đã tạo ra một bản sao tệ hơn trận đầu trên sân khách mùa trước. Khi đó, Pau thua chủ nhà Rodez 0-1, còn lần này họ thua tới 0-4. Cả mùa trước, không có trận nào họ thua đậm như thế. \\"Pau đã khởi đầu theo cách tệ nhất. Thấy trò Tholot thể hiện rõ sự bất lực khi kết thúc trận đấu\\", ký giả Matheo Girard viết. Cùng quan điểm này, ký giả Laurent Vignasse trên tờ La Rep cho rằng Guingamp đã áp đảo mọi khía cạnh trận này. \\"Pau chơi mờ nhạt, mất hút trên thảm cỏ xanh Roudourou\\", tác giả viết. \\"Công thức của Pau là chiến thắng hoặc mỉm cười. Nhưng sau hiệu còi mãn cuộc, gương mặt của các cầu thủ Pau hoàn toàn trái ngược\\". Trong trận ra quân tối 30/7 ở Guingamp, Pau thủng lưới ba bàn chỉ sau 34 phút. Trong đó, hai bàn tới","answer":"từ sai lầm cá nhân thủ môn Alex Olliero và trung vệ Antoine Batisse. Guingamp ấn định tỷ số đầu hiệp hai, trước khi Quang Hải được đưa vào sân ở phút 60. Màn trình diễn của Quang Hải giúp anh nhận điểm cao thứ hai Pau, chỉ sau tiền đạo Mons Bassouamina. Nhưng Pau vẫn nhận thất bại đậm nhất lịch sử họ trong ba mùa ở Ligue 2. Dù vậy, Sud Ouest cho rằng chưa có gì đáng báo động với Pau bởi đây mới là trận mở màn. Nguyễn Quang Hải và đồng đội sẽ trở về Pau để tiếp Dijon ở vòng hai tối 6/8. Do chơi trận đầu tiên trên sân nhà, Pau thuê sân Hameau với sức chứa hơn 18.000 chỗ ngồi để thi đấu. Ở chiều ngược lại, Guingamp đã có khởi đầu như mơ. Họ kiểm soát bóng 62%, tung 11 cú dứt điểm và bảy trong số đó đúng hướng khung thành. Theo HLV Stephane Dumont, chiến thắng dành cho đội bóng của ông là hoàn toàn xứng đáng. \\"Chúng tôi không cho Pau thời gian để thở\\", ông nói. \\"Chúng tôi đã chơi tuyệt vời ở hiệp đầu tiên, vượt quá kỳ vọng của toàn đội. Nhưng đây mới là trận đầu, và thắng đậm cũng chỉ đồng nghĩa với ba điểm\\". Xuân Bình"},{"question":"Eyi ni bi awọn Sifu Difẹnsi ṣe ba oyun oṣu mẹta jẹ mọ Funmilayọ lara n’Ibadan","answer":"Nitori bi awọn oṣiṣẹ ajọ alaabo ilu, iyẹn Nigeria Security and Civil Defence Corps (NSCDC), ta a mọ si Sifu Difẹnsi ṣe lu oun atọkọ ẹ nilukulu nigboro Ibadan, oyun oṣu mẹta ti bajẹ mọ obinrin naa, Funmilọla Adekọya, lara.Ọkọ obinrin naa, Ọgbẹni Francise Adekọya, lo kọkọ riya he nigba ti meji ninu awọn eeyan yii ti a ko mọ orukọ wọn, pẹlu ọkunrin kan ti wọn jọ pera wọn ni oṣiṣẹ to n gbowo ori fun ijọba ipinlẹ Ọyọ, lọọ ka oun atiyawo ẹ mọ ṣọọbu wọn to wa nileetaja igbalode kan ti wọn n pe ni Gbangbalọlọunwa Complex, lagbegbe ka Idi-Ọpẹ, ni Imalefalaafia, Oke-Ado, n’Ibadan, lọjọ kọkandinlọgbọn, oṣu kẹsan-an, ọdun 2020 yii, ti i ṣe ọjọ Iṣẹgun, Tusidee, to kọja.Owo ti tọkọ-tiyawo yii ko ri san lo mu ki wọn fiya jẹ Ọgbẹni Francise. Bi ara ṣe ta iyawo ẹ (Funmilọla), to ni ki wọn fi ọkọ oun silẹ ni wọn ki oun paapaa mọlẹ, ti wọn si bẹrẹ si i rọjo iya le e lori.Loju ẹsẹ lobinrin ọlọmọ kan to loyun ekeji sinu yii dákú, ko too di pe awọn dokita fidi ẹ mulẹ pe oyun oṣu mẹta to ni ti bajẹ mọ ọn lara lẹyin ti awọn araadugbo ti sare gbe e digbadigba lọ sileewosan aladaani kan lagbegbe naa.Diẹ lo ku ki oju ọkọ paapaa fọ nibi ti awọn ọdaju eeyan ti wọn pera wọn laṣoju ijọba yii fiya jẹ ẹ de.Nigba to n royin bi iṣẹlẹ ọhun ṣe waye, Ọgbẹni Francise ṣalaye pe “Awọn eeyan yẹn ko ṣafihan nnkan kan to le jẹ ka mọ pe loootọ ni wọn jẹ aṣoju to n gba owo-ori fun ijọba. Ṣadeede ni wọn kan de, ti wọn ni ka maa san ẹgbẹrun meji naira (N2,000) gẹgẹ bii owo-ori ta a ni lati san sapo ijọba ipinlẹ Ọyọ.“Mo dahun pe mi o lowo lọwọ bayii nitori awa naa ko ti i pawo kankan laaarọ ọjọ yẹn, ati pe ẹ ko sọ fun wa ti tẹlẹ pe ẹ n bọ, a ba ti mura yin silẹ. Bi wọn ṣe da a ságídí niyẹn. wọn ni awọn maa ti ṣọọbu mi ti mi o ba rowo san.“Wọn ti wọ mi jade ninu ṣọọbu mi. Nibi ti wọn ti fẹẹ fagídí ti ṣọọbu mi ni mo ti yari mọ wọn lọwọ. Bi wọn ṣe bẹrẹ si i lu mi niyẹn.“Kinni ina kan bayii ti wọn mu lọwọ ni wọn kọkọ tẹ si mi lara. Niṣe niyẹn gbe mi bii igba ti ina ilẹtiriki ba ṣọ́ọ̀kì eeyan. Lẹyin naa ni wọn fin gaasi tajútajú si mi loju, ti mi o si rina ri nnkan kan laarin iṣẹju marun-un.”“Nibi ti iyawo mi ti n da wọn lẹkun ni wọn ti fi kinni ina yẹn gbe oun naa, to si ṣubu lulẹ, to daku gbọnrangandan. Ọpẹlọpẹ awọn araadugbo ti wọn sare ba mi gbe e lọ sọsibitu.“Awọn dokita sọ pe Ọlọrun lo doola ẹmi iyawo mi nitori oyun oṣu mẹta to wa lara ẹ ti bajẹ. O ṣi wa lọsibitu to ti n gbàtọ́jú di bi mo ṣe n sọrọ yii.”Gẹgẹ b’ALAROYE ṣe gbọ, agọ ọlọpaa to wa ni Iyaganku, n’Ibadan  lọkunrin to pera ẹ lẹnjinnia kọ̀ǹpútà yii kọḳọ fẹjọ sun. Ohun ti awọn ọlọpaa si sọ ni pe awọn ko le mu awọn Sifu Difẹnsi naa nitori pe oṣiṣẹ ijọba apapọ lawọn jọ jẹ, iṣẹ agbofinro kan naa lawọn si jọ n ṣe.Ọkunrin ti wọn fiya jẹ pẹlu iyawo ẹ yii ti waa rọ ijọba ipinlẹ Ọyọ, labẹ akoso Gomina Ṣeyi Makinde, lati ṣewadii iṣẹlẹ yii, ki wọn si gbe igbesẹ to ba yẹ lori rẹ.Alukoro ajọ NSCDC nipinlẹ Ọyọ, Ọgbẹni Oluwọle Oluṣẹgun, fidi iṣẹlẹ yii mulẹ, o ni nitori pe Ọgbẹni Fracise atiyawo ẹ lu awọn oṣiṣẹ ajọ naa lawọn naa ṣe fọwọ ba wọn lati le gba ara wọn silẹ lọwọ iya àjẹkú dórógbó.O fi kun un pe oṣiṣẹ awọn ti wọn lu yii naa wa nileewosan to n gbatọju lọwọ bo tilẹ jẹ pe ko darukọ ileewosan naa.Agbẹnusọ fun Gomina Makinde, Ọgbẹni Taiwo Adisa, ti sọrọ lori iṣẹlẹ yii, o lo ya oun lẹnu pe ẹnikẹni le ṣe bẹẹ lo agbofinro lati jẹ ọmọ ipinlẹ yii niya lọna aitọ.O sọ gbangba pe ijọba ko ran ẹnikẹni niṣẹ lati fipa gbowo ori lọwọ araalu nitori ni kete ti gomina yii ti dori aleefa lo ti gbe iṣẹ owo-ori gbigba le ileeṣẹ aladaani kan lọwọ, ati pe ọna to bofin mu lawọn eeyan naa fi n ṣiṣẹ ti ijọba gbe le wọn lọwọ ọhun."},{"question":"¿Cuál es la capital de Australia?","answer":"Canberra, la capital de Australia, es una ciudad inmersa en la naturaleza, rodeada por los pintorescos bosques australianos. Canberra es el hogar de importantes instituciones nacionales como el Parlamento australiano y el Memorial de Guerra Australiano, combina importancia cultural con un entorno sereno, ofreciendo un equilibrio único entre la vida urbana y la belleza natural."},{"question":"ما هو اسم أبو جهل ؟\\t","answer":"عمرو بن هشام بن المغيرة المخزومي"},{"question":"Sheeg Magaca qoraaga buugga “Taariikhdii hore ee Muqdisho iyo haatan”","answer":" Waxaa qoray Aw Jaamac Cumar Ciise"},{"question":"송전선이 정말 인체에 영향을 주나요?","answer":"송전선에서 발생하는 전자파의 인체영향에 대한 문제는 현재 가장 큰 이슈입니다. 하지만 실제로 사람이 접근할 수 있는 위치에서 송전선으로부터 발생하는 전자파를 측정한 결과에 따르면, 우리나라의 60 ㎐ 자기장 노출 규제치인 83.3 μT(833 mG) 보다 상당히 낮은 수준입니다. 일부 역학 연구자들은 연구를 통하여 어린이들이 0.4 μT 이상의 자기장에 지속적으로 노출되면 어린이백혈병에 걸릴 가능성이 두 배가 된다고 보고했지만, 생물학적 연구는 그러한 영향에 대한 메커니즘을 발견하지 못하였고 세포 실험이나 동물 실험에서도 증명이 되지 못하였습니다. 이러한 결과들에 따라 WHO Fact Sheet No. 322(극저주파에 대한 노출)에서는 ‘어린이 백혈병과 관련있다는 증거는 인과관계가 고려될 만큼 충분하지 않으며, 극저주파 자기장 노출로 인하여 건강을 해롭게 할 수 있는 연관성에 대해 연구를 해 왔지만, 아직까지도 과학적인 증거는 없다’는 결론을 내렸습니다.WHO에 따르면, 아직까지 송전선에서 발생하는 전자파가 백혈병이나 암을 유발한다는 근거를 과학적으로 입증하지 못하였습니다."},{"question":"文章からキーワードを選び、その解釈を述べなさい。 広島で19日から21日まで、7つの国などのトップが集まる「G7サミット」があります。このため、警備を厳しくしていて、広島空港や広島駅などでは今、コインロッカーを使うことができません。広島以外でも、新幹線の東京駅や名古屋駅、京都駅などでは19日から21日までコインロッカーとごみ箱を使うことができません。JRや東京メトロの上野駅や新宿駅、渋谷駅などでも21日まで使うことができません。京都駅では、使うことができないコインロッカーが少し前から増えています。駅の案内所は「コインロッカーのほかにも荷物を預けることができる所はありますが、たくさんの人が並んで待っています」と言っています。21日まで厳しい警備が続くため、出かける人は行く場所の情報をよく調べてください。","answer":"この文章に含まれるキーワードとその解釈は以下です。- トップ: 1）先頭。真っ先。一番。2）会社や団体・組織などの、いちばん上の人。3）新聞などのページでいちばん目立つところ。- 警備: 1）悪いことが起こらないように、気をつけて守ること。- コインロッカー: 1）（駅などに備えてある）コインを入れて使用するロッカー。- 所: 1）ところ。2）こと。もの。- 預ける: 1）自分の物を、そこに置いてもらう。2）ものごとの収め方を任せる。- 情報: 1）出来事やものごとのようすについての知らせ。"},{"question":"मद्रास प्रांतात होमरूल लिगची स्थापना कोणी केली ?","answer":"डॉ. ऍनी बेझंटने"},{"question":"Wọn yinbọn pa sọrọsọrọ ori redio kan n’Ibadan","answer":"Awọn agbebọn kan ti awọn eeyan fura si pe o ṣee ṣe ko jẹ ayakila ti yinbọn pa gbajumọ sọrọsọrọ ori redio kan niluu Ibadan, Titus Badejọ, ti gbogbo eeyan mọ si Ejanla lọjọ Abamẹta, Satide, opin ọsẹ to kọja yii.ALAROYE gbọ pe lasiko to fẹẹ kuro ni ileegbafẹ kan to ti n ṣe faaji ni adugbo Oluyọle ni wọn ṣina ibọn fun un laarin awọn ti wọn jọ wa nibẹ, ti wọn si ri i pe o ku ki wọn too kuro nibẹ.A gbọ pe lati nnkan bii aago mẹsan-an alẹ lo ti wa ni kilọọbu kan to wa ni Oluyọle Estate, nibi to ti n ṣe faaji pẹlu awọn eeyan kan. Ni nnkan bii aago mọkanla kọja ni wọn lo fi kilọọbu naa silẹ to n lọ sile.Lojiji ni awọn agbebọn yii yọ si wọn, ti wọn si ni ki gbogbo awọn to wa nibẹ dojubolẹ. Ṣugbọn oun nikan ni awọn apani-jaye yii kọju ibọn si, ti wọn si ri i pe ẹmi bọ lara rẹ ki wọn too kuro nibẹ. Ohun to jẹ ki awọn eeyan fura pe o ṣee ṣe ko jẹ ayakila ni pe wọn ko gba nnkan kan lọwọ ọkunrin naa, bẹẹ ni wọn ko mu ohunkohun kuro lara rẹ. Bi wọn ṣe pa a tan ni wọn ta le ọkada to gbe wọn wa, ti wọn si sa lọ.Badejọ ti wọn pa yii ti figba kan ṣiṣẹ ni Space FM ati Naija FM, ti mejeeji wa niluu Ibadan. Bẹẹ lo tun maa n ba wọn kopa ninu sinima agbelewo."},{"question":"Menurut zodiak Cina, apakah sifat baik and buruk untuk harimau? ","answer":"Sifat baik: Sukar diduga, suka melawan, berwarna-warni, sangat berkuasa, berkobar-kobar, berani, mengikut gerak hati, penuh bersemangat, merangsang, ikhlas, pengasih, berperikemanusiaan, murah hati Sifat buruk: Mudah gelisah, semberono, tidak sabar, cepat berang, degil, mementingkan diri "},{"question":"Inona no volana faharoa amin'ny teny gasy?","answer":"Ny volana faharoa amin'ny teny gasy dia Febroary."},{"question":"ಒಗಟು ಬಿಡಿಸಿ : ಬಿಳಿ ಹುಡುಗನಿಗೆ ಕರಿಟೋಪಿ .ಏನಿದು ?","answer":"ಈ ಒಗಟಿನ ಉತ್ತರ ಬೆಂಕಿ ಕಡ್ಡಿ"},{"question":"Inona no fihetseham-pon'ity fanambarana manaraka ity?\\"Ny vaovao momba ny dian'ny fianakavianay tany Italia tamin'ny fahavaratra manaraka dia nanatanjaka ahy tanteraka. Tsy andriko ny hahatongavan'ity fitsangatsanganana ity.\\"","answer":"Tsara ny fahatsapana, noho ny fahatsinjovana ny handeha any Italia."},{"question":"میٹھے مشروبات پینے سے صحت کے کیا مسائل ہو سکتے ہیں؟","answer":"بار بار چینی والے میٹھے مشروبات پینے کا تعلق وزن میں اضافہ، موٹاپا، ٹائپ 2 ذیابیطس، دل کی بیماری، گردے کی بیماریاں، غیر الکوحل جگر کی بیماری، دانتوں کی خرابی اور گٹھیا اور گاؤٹ، گٹھیا کی ایک قسم سے ہے۔ 1-4 میٹھے مشروبات کے استعمال کو محدود کرنا افراد کو صحت مند وزن برقرار رکھنے اور صحت مند غذائی پیٹرن رکھنے میں مدد مل سکتی ہے۔"},{"question":"ఇచ్చిన గద్యానికి కొనసాగింపుగా ఒక పేరా రాయండి:రష్యాకు చెందిన పన్నెండేళ్ల అన్నాసిన కోవ రాసిన ‘అనారోగ్యం గురించి ఆలోచించకు’ కవితకూడా వారిని అబ్బురపరచింది. ఏమైనా ముఖ్యమైన పనులు చేపట్టినప్పుడు సమస్యలు తప్పనిసరిగా వస్తూ ఉంటాయి. కాని ఆ సమస్యలు శాసించకూడదని అబ్దుల్ కలాం నమ్ముతారు. దానినే మీరు సమస్యలు అధిగమించండి విజయం సాధించండి అని యువతీయువకులకు చెప్తారు.","answer":"ఇటువంటి భావాలే అన్నాసిన్యకోవ కవితలో కూడా ప్రతిధ్వనించాయి. ఆరోగ్యవంతమైన జీవితాల్ని నిలబెట్టుకోవటం కోసం ఎటువంటి వ్యాధినైనా, అనారోగ్యాన్నైనా ఎదుర్కొనే ధైర్యం ఉండాలనే బలమైన సందేశం ఆమె కవితలో కలాంకు కనబడింది."},{"question":"اقرأ النص التالي ثم استخرج إجابة السؤال الذي يليه: تصف قوانين كبلر مدارات الأجرام السماوية حول الشمس. وفقًا لقانون كبلر ، تدور الأجرام السماوية حول الشمس على طول مداراتها الإهليلجية ، والشمس في إحدى النقاط المحورية. كلما اقترب الجرم السماوي من الشمس (كلما كان المحور شبه الرئيسي أقصر) ، زادت السرعة المدارية بسبب الجاذبية الأكبر للشمس. في المدار الإهليلجي ، ستتغير المسافة بين الجسم السماوي والشمس باستمرار مع سنة الثورة (الفترة). تسمى النقطة في مدارها الأقرب إلى الشمس الحضيض ، وتسمى النقطة الأبعد عن الشمس الأوج. تكون مدارات الكواكب دائرية تقريبًا ، لكن العديد من المذنبات والكويكبات وأجسام حزام كايبر تدور حول مدارات إهليلجية للغاية. يمكن التنبؤ بمواضع هذه الأشياء باستخدام المحاكاة العددية. ما الذي تركز عليه كل الأجرام وفقًا لقوانين كبلر؟","answer":"وفقًا لقوانين كبلر تتركز كل الأجرام على الشمس."},{"question":"கேள்வி:அடிபிறழாமல் எழுதுக.(அ) “மாற்றம் எனது மானிடத் தத்துவம்” எனத் தொடங்கும் காலக்கணிதம்’ பாடலை எழுதுக.(ஆ) “செம்பொனடிச் சிறு கிங்கிணியோடு ” எனத் தொடங்கும் முத்துக்குமாரசாமிபிள்ளைத்தமிழ்’ பாடலை எழுதுக.","answer":"பதில்:(அ) “மாற்றம் எனது மானிடத் தத்துவம்” எனத் தொடங்கும் காலக்கணிதம்’ பாடல்:மாற்றம் எனது மானிடத் தத்துவம்; மாறும்உலகின் மகத்துவம் அறிவேன்!எவ்வெவை தீமை எவ்வெவை நன்மைஎன்ப தறிந்து ஏகுமென் சாலை!தலைவர் மாறுவர்; தர்பார் மாறும்;தத்துவம் மட்டுமே அட்சய பாத்திரம்!கொள்வோர் கொள்க; குரைப்போர் குரைக்க!உள்வாய் வார்த்தை உடம்பு தொடாது;நானே தொடக்கம்; நானே முடிவு;நானுரைப் பதுதான் நாட்டின் சட்டம்! (- கண்ணதாசன்)(ஆ) “செம்பொனடிச் சிறு கிங்கிணியோடு ” எனத் தொடங்கும் முத்துக்குமாரசாமி பிள்ளைத்தமிழ்’ பாடல்:செம்பொ னடிச்சிறு கிங் கிணியோடு சிலம்பு கலந்தாடத்திருவரை யரைஞா ணரைமணி யொடு மொளி திகழரை வடமாடப் பைம்பொ னசும்பிய தொந்தி யொடுஞ்சிறு பண்டி சரிந்தாடப்பட்ட நுதற்பொலி பொட்டொடு வட்டச் சுட்டி பதிந்தாடக்கம்பி விதம்பொதி குண்டல முங்குழை காது மசைந்தாடக்கட்டிய சூழியு முச்சியு முச்சிக் கதிர்முத் தொடுமாடவம்பவ ளத்திரு மேனியு மாடிட ஆடுக செங்கீரை .ஆதி வயித்திய நாத புரிக்குக னாடுக செங்கீரை (- குமரகுருபரர்)"},{"question":"ਵਰਗਾਕਾਰ ਢੰਗ ਤੋਂ ਤੁਹਾਡਾ ਕੀ ਭਾਵ ਹੈ ?","answer":"ਇਹ ਬਾਗ਼ ਲਾਉਣ ਦਾ ਇੱਕ ਢੰਗ ਹੈ ਜਿਸ ਵਿੱਚ ਬੁਟਿਆਂ ਅਤੇ ਕਤਾਰਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਫ਼ਾਸਲਾ ਬਰਾਬਰ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ । ਇਸ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ ਆਮਣੇ-ਸਾਹਮਣੇ ਲਗਾਏ ਚਾਰ ਬੂਟੇ ਇੱਕ ਵਰਗਾਕਾਰ ਬਣਾਉਂਦੇ ਹਨ ।"},{"question":"Кичинеңизде асманда учак учуп баратса жердеги балдардын абалы кандай болгон?","answer":"Абдан кубанчубуз колубузду жайып🧍самалётко окшош анан дагы чуркап ырдачу элек.Самолёт самолёт ✈️Кайда учуп барасыңЧөнтөгүңө салат кетКапитандын баласын. Балалык доор кайра кайтып келсе."},{"question":"Su’aal: Sheeg Qoomkii Lagu Halaagay Isu Galmoodka Ragga?","answer":"Jawaab: Waa Qoomkii Nebi Luud CS."},{"question":"ചോദ്യം: മാർക്കിന് 50 ബലൂണുകൾ ഉണ്ടായിരുന്നു. അവൻ 10 പോപ്പ് ചെയ്തു 8 കൊടുത്തു. ഇപ്പോൾ അവന്റെ പക്കൽ എത്ര ബലൂണുകൾ ഉണ്ട്?","answer":"ഉത്തരം: മാർക്കിന് ഇപ്പോൾ 32 ബലൂണുകൾ ഉണ്ട്."},{"question":"కింది సామాన్య వాక్యాలను సంయుక్త వాక్యాలుగా మార్చి రాయండి.‘పద్మ గ్రంథాలయమునకు వెళ్ళింది. పద్మ పుస్తకము చదివింది.","answer":"పద్మ గ్రంథాలయమునకు వెళ్ళి పుస్తకము చదివింది. "},{"question":"“தமிழே மிகவும் பண்பட்ட மொழி” என்று பாராட்டியவர் யார்?(1) கமில்சுவலபில்(2) மாக்சு முல்லர்(3) முனைவர் எமினோ(4) வில்லியம் ஜோன்ஸ்","answer":"(2) மாக்சு முல்லர்."},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਪਉੜੀ ॥ਲੂਣ ਹਰਾਮੀ ਗੁਨਹਗਾਰ ਬੇਗਾਨਾ ਅਲਪ ਮਤਿ ॥ਜੀਉ ਪਿੰਡੁ ਜਿਨਿ ਸੁਖ ਦੀਏ ਤਾਹਿ ਨ ਜਾਨਤ ਤਤ ॥ਲਾਹਾ ਮਾਇਆ ਕਾਰਨੇ ਦਹ ਦਿਸਿ ਢੂਢਨ ਜਾਇ ॥ਦੇਵਨਹਾਰ ਦਾਤਾਰ ਪ੍ਰਭ ਨਿਮਖ ਨ ਮਨਹਿ ਬਸਾਇ ॥ਲਾਲਚ ਝੂਠ ਬਿਕਾਰ ਮੋਹ ਇਆ ਸੰਪੈ ਮਨ ਮਾਹਿ ॥ਲੰਪਟ ਚੋਰ ਨਿੰਦਕ ਮਹਾ ਤਿਨਹੂ ਸੰਗਿ ਬਿਹਾਇ ॥ਤੁਧੁ ਭਾਵੈ ਤਾ ਬਖਸਿ ਲੈਹਿ ਖੋਟੇ ਸੰਗਿ ਖਰੇ ॥ਨਾਨਕ ਭਾਵੈ ਪਾਰਬ੍ਰਹਮ ਪਾਹਨ ਨੀਰਿ ਤਰੇ ॥੫੨॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 261 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਅਰਜਨ ਦੇਵ ਜੀ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਬਾਣੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਹਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"ਮਨੁੱਖ ਨਾ-ਸ਼ੁਕਰਾ ਹੈ, ਗੁਨਹਗਾਰ ਹੈ, ਹੋਛੀ ਮਤ ਵਾਲਾ ਹੈ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਨਾਲੋਂ ਓਪਰਾ ਹੀ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ, ਜਿਸ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਨੇ ਇਹ ਜਿੰਦ ਤੇ ਸਰੀਰ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਹਨ, ਉਸ ਅਸਲੇ ਨੂੰ ਪਛਾਣਦਾ ਹੀ ਨਹੀਂ । ਮਾਇਆ ਖੱਟਣ ਦੀ ਖ਼ਾਤਰ ਦਸੀਂ ਪਾਸੀਂ ਭਾਲ ਕਰਨ ਤੁਰਿਆ ਫਿਰਦਾ ਹੈ, ਪਰ ਜੇਹੜਾ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦਾਤਾਰ ਸਭ ਕੁਝ ਦੇਣ ਜੋਗਾ ਹੈ, ਉਸ ਨੂੰ ਅੱਖ ਦੇ ਫੋਰ ਜਿਤਨੇ ਸਮੇ ਲਈ ਭੀ ਆਪਣੇ ਮਨ ਵਿਚ ਨਹੀਂ ਵਸਾਂਦਾ ।ਲਾਲਚ, ਝੂਠ, ਵਿਕਾਰ ਤੇ ਮਾਇਆ ਦਾ ਮੋਹ—ਬੱਸ! ਇਹੀ ਧਨ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਆਪਣੇ ਮਨ ਵਿਚ ਸਾਂਭੀ ਬੈਠਾ ਹੈ । ਜੋ ਵਿਸ਼ਈ ਹਨ, ਚੋਰ ਹਨ, ਮਹਾ ਨਿੰਦਕ ਹਨ, ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੇ ਸਾਥ ਵਿਚ ਇਸ ਦੀ ਉਮਰ ਬੀਤਦੀ ਹੈ । (ਪਰ, ਹੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ!) ਜੇ ਤੈਨੂੰ ਚੰਗਾ ਲੱਗੇ ਤਾਂ ਤੂੰ ਆਪ ਹੀ ਖੋਟਿਆਂ ਨੂੰ ਖਰਿਆਂ ਦੀ ਸੰਗਤਿ ਵਿਚ ਰੱਖ ਕੇ ਬਖ਼ਸ਼ ਲੈਂਦਾ ਹੈਂ ।ਹੇ ਨਾਨਕ! ਜੇ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਨੂੰ ਚੰਗਾ ਲੱਗੇ ਤਾਂ ਉਹ (ਵਿਚਾਰਾਂ ਵਿਚ) ਪੱਥਰ-ਦਿਲ ਹੋ ਚੁੱਕੇ ਬੰਦਿਆਂ ਨੂੰ ਨਾਮ-ਅੰਮ੍ਰਿਤ ਦੀ ਦਾਤਿ ਦੇ ਕੇ (ਵਿਕਾਰਾਂ ਦੀਆਂ ਲਹਿਰਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਡੁਬਣੋਂ) ਬਚਾ ਲੈਂਦਾ ਹੈ ।੫੨।\\""},{"question":"Write a continuation for this paragraph - ต่อมาดาเมียตตาก็เป็นเป้าของสงครามครูเสดครั้งที่ 7","answer":"ที่นำโดยพระเจ้าหลุยส์ที่ 9 แห่งฝรั่งเศส กองเรือของพระองค์มาถึงในปี ค.ศ. 1249 และสามารถยึดเมืองได้อย่างรวดเร็ว แต่พระองค์ไม่ทรงยอมยกให้กษัตริย์ของเยรูซาเลมตามที่ได้สัญญากันไว้ตั้งแต่สงครามครูเสดครั้งที่ 5 ต่อมาพระเจ้าหลุยส์เองก็ทรงถูกจับและพ่ายแพ้และทรงถูกบังคับให้ยกเลิกการยึดดาเมียตตา"},{"question":"Tohizo izao ohabolana izao : \\"Tsy mandrombaka ny an-tanan'ny olona fa ...................... \\"","answer":"\\"Tsy mandrombaka ny an-tanan'ny olona fa mitaombato manangana manda sy fiandrianana vaovao. \\""},{"question":"Hãy viết một đoạn văn ít nhất 200 chữ dựa trên nội dung được nói tới trong câu sau: Indonesia bóng gió thừa nhận bố trí sân xấu tại giải U16 Đông Nam Á để 'trả đũa' Việt Nam","answer":"Ở giải U16 Đông Nam Á 2022, Việt Nam sẽ thi đấu các trận tại sân vận động Sultan Agung, một trong những địa điểm từng tổ chức AFF Cup 2018. Nhưng theo ghi nhận, cỏ ở đây mọc không đều, khá lồi lõm, gây trở ngại cho các cầu thủ. Trang chủ VFF nhận xét: \\"Theo đánh giá từ các trợ lý của U16 Việt Nam, mặt sân Sultan Agung không đều. Cỏ được trồng tới 3-4 loại khác nhau với chiều cao chỗ thấp, chỗ cao. Ngoài ra, vì các loại cỏ khác nhau nên có khu vực mặt sân cứng nhưng có chỗ mặt sân lại mềm. Nhiều chỗ lõm, mấp mô, gồ ghề. Điều này ảnh hưởng trực tiếp đến việc di chuyển, chạy chỗ của các cầu thủ U16 Việt Nam. Bởi nó sẽ ảnh hưởng đến việc trụ chân ở từng khu vực (mềm, cứng). Thậm chí, các cầu thủ có thể bị lật cổ chân khi thi đấu trên mặt sân này. Theo đánh giá, chất lượng mặt sân Sultan Agung không bằng so với sân tập mà U16 Việt Nam đã rèn luyện tại trường quốc tế Jorgiakarta những ngày qua\\". Ngay lập tức, chủ tịch PSSI, Mochamad Iriawan đã lên tiếng về nhận xét của Việt Nam. Ông cho rằng phản ứng từ phía Việt Nam là bình thường: \\"À, phía Việt Nam chỉ phàn nàn, cũng bình thường thôi mà\\". Nhưng ông Iriawan không quên gợi lại việc Indonesia cũng từng than vãn chuyện sân bãi khi dự SEA Games 31 tại Phú Thọ. \\"Ở đó chúng tôi cũng nhận được điều đó (chất lượng sân bãi). Vì vậy, cũng bình thường thôi. Hãy cứ ra sân và thi đấu vui vẻ\\", ông Iriawan nói khi tham dự trận khai mạc giải U16 Đông Nam Á tại sân Maguwoharjo tối Chủ nhật (31/7)."},{"question":"问题：阿里巴巴的未来发展前景如何？","answer":"答案：阿里巴巴作为全球领先的技术公司，未来发展前景广阔。在电子商务领域，它将继续深化创新，提升用户体验。同时，也将在云计算、人工智能、物联网等新兴领域寻求新的增长点。"},{"question":"问题：朝鲜的传统舞剧有哪些著名作品？","answer":"答案：朝鲜的传统舞剧有《红舞鞋》、《白头山》和《江南》等。"},{"question":"\\"આવો રે.. આવો રે..\\" કવિતા  લખો.","answer":"આવો રે.. આવો રે..ઓ ચિત્તડું ચોરી જાનારા,મને મોતનાં વાગે ભણકારા..આવો રે.. આવો રે..મને યાદ છે વચનો સૌ તારાં,ઓ દિલડું લૂંટી લેનારા..આવો રે.. આવો રે..એક રાત તણી મુલાકાત મહીં,શા કીધાં હતાં તમે વાયદા..એક ઝુરવું ને મરવું બીજું,છે પ્રિતડી કેરાં કાયદા..ભવ ભવ હું ને તું બળનારા..આવો રે.. આવો રે..સારસ પંખીની જોડી કદી,જગમાં ના રે જુદી પડે..જુદી પડે તો માથું પટકી,બીજું ત્યાં તરફડી મરે..હવે ઘડીયું ગણે નૈનો મારાં..આવો રે.. આવો રે.."},{"question":"Waa maxay aarbe ? ","answer":"Aarbe  waa Odeyga qoyska 1aad."},{"question":"எந்த வைட்டமின் குறைபாட்டால் இரவு குருட்டுத்தன்மை ஏற்படுகிறது?","answer":"வைட்டமின் ஏ குறைபாடு காரணமாக இரவு குருட்டுத்தன்மை ஏற்படுகிறது. ரெட்டினோல் என்பது இரத்தம் மற்றும் பிளாஸ்மாவில் வைட்டமின் ஏ இன் முக்கிய சுழற்சி வடிவமாகும். சக்கரைவள்ளிக் கிழங்கு  கேரட், கீரை, கோஸ் மற்றும் பெரும்பாலான இலை கீரைகள், பால் மற்றும் சீஸ் போன்ற பால் பொருட்கள், ப்ரோக்கோலி, முட்டைகள். போன்றவை வைட்டமின் ஏ  சத்து நிறைந்தவை. இவைகளை உணவுகளில் சேர்ப்பதன் மூலம் இக்குறைபாட்டை தவிர்க்கலாம்."},{"question":"Ở Đà Nẵng muốn tiêm kháng thể đơn dòng thì phải làm sao ạ? Nhờ bệnh viện tư vấn giúp mình!","answer":"Đây là loại kháng thể đơn dòng ngừa Covid-19 được Bộ Y tế chỉ định tiêm tại bệnh viện và hiện chỉ có tại Hệ thống BVĐK Tâm Anh (cơ sở Hà Nội và TP HCM). Do đó, nếu có nhu cầu tiêm kháng thể đơn dòng ngừa Covid-19 này bạn có thể đăng ký tại website, hotline và chờ nhận tin nhắn mời đến tiêm từ hệ thống BVĐK Tâm Anh."},{"question":"ప్రతీకాత్మక చిత్రంవరంగల్‌ నగరం నడిబొడ్డున ఆసుపత్రి నిర్వహిస్తున్న ఈ మెడికల్‌ రిప్రజెంటేటివ్‌, అనుమతి, అర్హత లేకుండా అబార్షన్లు చేస్తున్నారని తెలియడంతో వైద్య ఆరోగ్యశాఖ అధికారులు బుధవారం అర్ధరాత్రి దాడి చేసి పట్టుకున్నారు. వరంగల్‌ రూరల్‌ జిల్లా చెన్నారావుపేటకు చెందిన అండ్రు ఇంద్రారెడ్డి నెల రోజుల కిందట హన్మకొండలోని ఏకశిలా పార్కు ఎదురుగా సిటీ హాస్పిటల్‌ పేరుతో ఆసుపత్రి ప్రారంభించారు. రెండోసారి ఆడపిల్లలు వద్దనుకునే మహిళలను ఆర్‌ఎంపీలు, పీఎంపీల ద్వారా గుర్తించి వారికి అబార్షన్లు చేస్తున్నారు. నర్సింగ్‌లో శిక్షణ పొందినవారితో కలిసి , యూట్యూబ్‌ చూస్తూ ఈ అబార్షన్లు ప్రక్రియను కొనసాగిస్తున్నారు. దీనిపై సమాచారం అందడంతో బుధవారం అర్ధరాత్రి రెవెన్యూ అధికారులు, జిల్లా వైద్య ఆరోగ్యశాఖ అధికారులు ఆసుపత్రిపై దాడి చేశారు. ఆ సమయంలో మహారాష్ట్ర నుంచి వచ్చిన మహిళలకు ఆసుపత్రిలో చికిత్స జరుగుతోంది. అధికారులను చూసి వైద్య సిబ్బంది గోడదూకి పారిపోయారు. థియేటర్‌లో ఉన్న మహిళను బాత్రూంలో దాచారు. పోలీసుల సాయంతో ఆమెను బయటకు తీసుకొచ్చి అధికారులు ప్రశ్నించారు. రక్తస్రావం అవుతుండటంతో హన్మకొండ జీఎంహెచ్‌కు తరలించారు.ఇంద్రారెడ్డి మూడేళ్ల కిందట వరంగల్‌ రూరల్‌ జిల్లా నర్సంపేటలోనూ ఇలాగే ఓ ఆసుపత్రి ఏర్పాటు చేయగా అధికారులు దాన్ని సీజ్‌ చేశారు. డీఎంహెచ్‌వో ఫిర్యాదు మేరకు నకిలీ వైద్యుడిపై పోలీసులు క్రిమినల్‌ కేసు నమోదు చేసి, ఆసుపత్రిని సీజ్‌ చేశారు. నిందితుడు ప్రస్తుతం పోలీసుల అదుపులో ఉన్నట్లు ఈనాడు కథనం పేర్కొంది. రూ.20 లక్షలు స్టవ్‌ మీద కాల్చేసిన తహసీల్దార్‌అవినీతికి పాల్పడి, ఆ వ్యవహారంలో ఎక్కడ దొరికి పోతానో అన్న భయంతో ఓ అధికారి పెద్ద ఎత్తున కరెన్సీ నోట్లను తగలబెట్టినట్లు ఆంధ్రజ్యోతి పత్రిక ఒక కథనం ఇచ్చింది. ఈ ఘటన రాజస్థాన్‌లోని సిరోహి జిల్లాలో బుధవారం నాడు జరిగింది. ఓ వ్యక్తికి కాంట్రాక్టు అప్పగించడానికి అతని నుంచి తహసీల్దార్‌ కల్పేశ్‌ కుమార్‌ జైన్‌ తరఫున రూ.లక్ష లంచం తీసుకునేందుకు రెవెన్యూ ఇన్‌స్పెక్టర్‌ పర్వత్‌ సింగ్‌ సిద్ధమయ్యారు. లంచం పుచ్చుకుంటున్న సమయంలో ఏసీబీ అధికారులు ప్రత్యక్షమై అతన్ని పట్టుకున్నారు. అయితే ఈ తతంగంలో తన ప్రమేయం ఏమీ లేదని, తహశీల్దార్‌ కల్పేశ్‌ కుమార్‌ జైన్‌ తరఫున తాను డబ్బు తీసుకుంటున్నానని రెవిన్యూ ఇన్‌స్పెక్టర్‌ ఏసీబీ అధికారులకు తెలిపారు. ","answer":"వరంగల్: యూట్యూబ్ వీడియోలు చూస్తూ అబార్షన్లు చేస్తున్న నకిలీ డాక్టర్ - ప్రెస్ రివ్యూ"},{"question":"Apakah maksud 'bunga bukan sekuntum'?","answer":"Ia bermaksud laki-laki atau perempuan itu tidak seorang sahaja di dunia ini"},{"question":"வினா:தமிழ்நாட்டில் உள்ள பறவைகள் சரணாலயங்களின் எண்ணிக்கை?","answer":"விடை:தமிழ்நாட்டில் 15 பறவைகள் சரணாலயங்கள் உள்ளன ."},{"question":"شكون مول كتاب(عيون الأخبار)؟","answer":"ابن قتيبة"},{"question":"Sheeg magaca saddexan ee halgame Xalane, meesha uu ku geeriyooday iyo            sanadkii  uu geeriyooday? ","answer":"  Waa Max’ed Cabdulle Xalane waxa uu ku geeriyooday Tog Wajaale sanadkii 1964."},{"question":"Alfanaan Ikraan Carale","answer":"ma’ogtahay sidii baangeesigaan jeclaainuu guulle igu simogacmo kor u hayaayema’ogtahay sidii baangoor iyo ayaanguriguu ku nool yahayisu gacan salaamaayeebal inuu garwaaqsadosiduu caashagq ii galaygasinkiina iga jarayuga go’ay hurdadaha guddoonsadeedeeqsigaan jeclaa gaarsiiyayegaarsiiya idinkunagaarsiiya idinkuna"},{"question":"\\" ઢોલાજી વીંઝણો લ્યો \\" લોકગીત લખો.","answer":"ઢોલાજી હાલ્યો ચાકરી રે                                                 ઢોલાજી વીંઝણો લ્યોકે મુને હારે તેડતા જાવ                                                  ઢોલાજી વીંઝણો લ્યોલવિંગ સરીખી ઢોલા તીખડી રે                                         ઢોલાજી વીંઝણો લ્યોતારે મુખડામાં રમતી આવું રાજ                                        ઢોલાજી વીંઝણો લ્યોતલવાર સરીખી ઢોલા ઊજળી રે                                       ઢોલાજી વીંઝણો લ્યોતારી કેડે ઝૂલતી આવું રાજ                                             ઢોલાજી વીંઝણો લ્યોરૂમાલ સરીખી ઢોલા રેશમી રે                                          ઢોલાજી વીંઝણો લ્યોકે તારા હાથમાં રમતી આવું રાજ                                       ઢોલાજી વીંઝણો લ્યોસૂડી સરીખી ઢોલા વાંકડી રે                                            ઢોલાજી વીંઝણો લ્યોકે તારા ગુંજામાં રમતી આવું રાજ                                      ઢોલાજી વીંઝણો લ્યોપાન સરીખી ઢોલા પાતળી રે                                           ઢોલાજી વીંઝણો લ્યોકે તારા હોઠે રમતી આવું રાજ                                          ઢોલાજી વીંઝણો લ્યોઢોલાજી હાલ્યો ચાકરી રે                                                ઢોલાજી વીંઝણો લ્યોકે મુને હારે તેડતા જાવ                                                 ઢોલાજી વીંઝણો લ્યો"},{"question":"الجملة الأولى: الصناعات الأولى في هيوزفيل بنيت لتخدم المزارعين ومواطني مقاطعة لايكومينغ الشرقية. الجملة التانية: الصناعات الأولى في مقاطعة لايكومينج اتبنت لتخدم المزارعين ومواطني شرق هيوزفيل. سؤال: الجملة 1 والجملة 2 بتعبر عن نفس المعنى؟ نعم ولا لا؟","answer":"لأ، الجملتين مش بيعبروا عن نفس المعنى"},{"question":"Inis dom faoi Theodore Roosevelt. ","answer":"Ba é Theodore \\"Teddy\\" Roosevelt (27 Deireadh Fómhair 1858 – 6 Eanáir 1919) an 26ú uachtarán Stáit Aontaithe Mheiriceá (1901-1909). Státaire, polaiteoir, caomhantóir, nádúraí agus scríbhneoir a bhí ann.Is eisean duine den cheathrar uachtarán gearrtha ar Shliabh Rushmore, taobh le George Washington, Thomas Jefferson, agus Abraham Lincoln. Buachaill easláinteach a bhí ann ina óige agus an plúchadh ag cur go mór isteach air. Sin ráite, bhí sé an-tógtha le saol crua iargúlta an iarthair agus chuaigh sé leis an bhfánaíocht agus an fheirmeoireacht i nDakota ón bhliain 1883 i leith."}]`),I={name:"App",components:{PoemCard:S},data(){return{searchQuery:"",visibleCount:6,poemsData:C,isLoading:!1}},computed:{filteredPoems(){return this.searchQuery.trim()?this.poemsData.filter(e=>{const a=this.searchQuery.toLowerCase();return e.question.toLowerCase().includes(a)||e.answer.toLowerCase().includes(a)}).slice(0,this.visibleCount):this.poemsData.slice(0,this.visibleCount)},hasMorePoems(){return this.visibleCount<this.poemsData.length}},methods:{async loadMore(){this.isLoading=!0,await new Promise(e=>setTimeout(e,1e3)),this.visibleCount+=6,this.isLoading=!1}}},O={class:"search-container"},B={class:"card-container"},x=["disabled"],P={key:0},K={key:1};function D(e,a,u,m,t,r){const k=b("PoemCard");return i(),o("section",null,[a[3]||(a[3]=n("div",{class:"top-banner"},[n("div",{class:"top-banner-title"},[n("div",{class:"top-banner-title-text"},"🤔 AI effective tips collection 🧠")])],-1)),n("div",O,[a[2]||(a[2]=n("span",{class:"search-icon"},null,-1)),y(n("input",{type:"text",class:"search-input","onUpdate:modelValue":a[0]||(a[0]=s=>t.searchQuery=s),placeholder:"Search..."},null,512),[[w,t.searchQuery]])]),n("div",B,[(i(!0),o(c,null,p(r.filteredPoems,(s,d)=>(i(),j(k,{key:d,poem:s},null,8,["poem"]))),128))]),r.hasMorePoems?(i(),o("button",{key:0,class:"load-more-button",disabled:t.isLoading,onClick:a[1]||(a[1]=(...s)=>r.loadMore&&r.loadMore(...s))},[t.isLoading?(i(),o("span",K,"Loading...")):(i(),o("span",P,"See more"))],8,x)):f("",!0)])}const E=g(I,[["render",D],["__scopeId","data-v-50561879"]]),H=JSON.parse('{"title":"","description":"","frontmatter":{"page":true},"headers":[],"relativePath":"deepseek/5.md","filePath":"deepseek/5.md"}'),F={name:"deepseek/5.md"},G=Object.assign(F,{setup(e){return(a,u)=>(i(),o("div",null,[v(E)]))}});export{H as __pageData,G as default};
